<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:27:12Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:1895889" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:1895889</identifier><datestamp>2007-07-04</datestamp><setSpec>plosone</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC1895889</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1895889</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">1895889</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17611626</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17611626</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PONE-RA-00968R1</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
          <subject>Oncology</subject>
          <subject>Oncology/Oncology Agents</subject>
          <subject>Oncology/Skin Cancers</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Comprehensive Expression Profiling of Tumor Cell Lines Identifies Molecular Signatures of Melanoma Progression</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Molecular Melanoma Signatures</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ryu</surname>
            <given-names>Byungwoo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n101">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Dave S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>DeLuca</surname>
            <given-names>Amena M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alani</surname>
            <given-names>Rhoda M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n101">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>The Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins, Department of Oncology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Najbauer</surname>
            <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Academic Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">City of Hope Medical Center, United States of America</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="n101">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>bryu1@jhmi.edu</email> (BR); <email>ralani@jhmi.edu</email> (RMA)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RA BR. Performed the experiments: BR DK AD. Analyzed the data: RA BR DK AD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BR. Wrote the paper: RA BR.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <elocation-id>e594</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Ryu et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Gene expression profiling has revolutionized our ability to molecularly classify primary human tumors and significantly enhanced the development of novel tumor markers and therapies; however, progress in the diagnosis and treatment of melanoma over the past 3 decades has been limited, and there is currently no approved therapy that significantly extends lifespan in patients with advanced disease. Profiling studies of melanoma to date have been inconsistent due to the heterogeneous nature of this malignancy and the limited availability of informative tissue specimens from early stages of disease.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methodology/Principle Findings</title>
          <p>In order to gain an improved understanding of the molecular basis of melanoma progression, we have compared gene expression profiles from a series of melanoma cell lines representing discrete stages of malignant progression that recapitulate critical characteristics of the primary lesions from which they were derived. Here we describe the unsupervised hierarchical clustering of profiling data from melanoma cell lines and melanocytes. This clustering identifies two distinctive molecular subclasses of melanoma segregating aggressive metastatic tumor cell lines from less-aggressive primary tumor cell lines. Further analysis of expression signatures associated with melanoma progression using functional annotations categorized these transcripts into three classes of genes: 1) Upregulation of activators of cell cycle progression, DNA replication and repair (<italic>CDCA2, NCAPH, NCAPG, NCAPG2, PBK, NUSAP1, BIRC5, ESCO2, HELLS, MELK, GINS1, GINS4, RAD54L, TYMS</italic>, and <italic>DHFR</italic>), 2) Loss of genes associated with cellular adhesion and melanocyte differentiation (<italic>CDH3, CDH1, c-KIT, PAX3, CITED1/MSG-1, TYR, MELANA, MC1R,</italic> and <italic>OCA2)</italic>, 3) Upregulation of genes associated with resistance to apoptosis (BIRC5/survivin). While these broad classes of transcripts have previously been implicated in the progression of melanoma and other malignancies, the specific genes identified within each class of transcripts are novel. In addition, the transcription factor NF-KB was specifically identified as being a potential “master regulator” of melanoma invasion since NF-KB binding sites were identified as consistent consensus sequences within promoters of progression-associated genes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
          <p>We conclude that tumor cell lines are a valuable resource for the early identification of gene signatures associated with malignant progression in tumors with significant heterogeneity like melanoma. We further conclude that the development of novel data reduction algorithms for analysis of microarray studies is critical to allow for optimized mining of important, clinically-relevant datasets. It is expected that subsequent validation studies in primary human tissues using such an approach will lead to more rapid translation of such studies to the identification of novel tumor biomarkers and therapeutic targets.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The incidence of melanoma is increasing at one of the highest rates for any form of cancer in the United States <xref rid="pone.0000594-Jemal1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. At present, there are no systemic agents available that significantly extend the lifespan of patients with advanced disease, and the key to improved survival in all affected individuals remains early diagnosis and treatment. While early stage disease may result in occasional deaths, there are no available tests to predict which early stage tumors have a high likelihood of progression and therefore a worse prognosis. Thus, an urgent need exists for the identification of molecular signatures of melanoma progression which can be used to develop accurate prognostic markers and effective targeted therapies. High-throughput gene expression profiling technologies offer an opportunity to uncover critical molecular events in the development and progression of human melanoma and can be used to design improved prognostic testing and effective treatment strategies. Previous transcriptome analyses in other malignancies have provided valuable information for the assessment of patient group classifications such as subgroups of patients that are likely to respond to a particular therapy <xref rid="pone.0000594-Quackenbush1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Expression profiling of metastatic melanomas was able to identify previously unrecognized subtypes of disease and predict phenotypic characteristics which may be of importance to melanoma progression <xref rid="pone.0000594-Bittner1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Further studies using serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE) and cDNA arrays have yielded the identification of additional novel molecules and pathways which may be involved in melanoma development<xref rid="pone.0000594-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Hoek1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Such studies have been limited in utility due to the lack of concordance from one study to the next suggesting tumor heterogeneity <xref rid="pone.0000594-Gyorffy1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In addition, the limited availability of primary tissue from early stages of disease has hindered the ability to identify serial molecular events that lead to melanoma onset. This shortcoming of tissue availability has largely restricted gene expression profiling studies in melanoma to the use of small numbers of established tumor cell lines and cases of metastatic disease.</p>
      <p>Previous studies of primary human melanomas have identified gene signatures associated with tumor progression <xref rid="pone.0000594-Haqq1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Jaeger1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. These signatures included upregulation of cell cycle regulatory proteins, mitotic checkpoint genes, genes involved in DNA replication and repair, and cellular stress response genes in addition to loss of genes promoting apoptosis; however, few of the genes identified in these studies were concordant suggesting limitations due to tumor variability. Since better knowledge of gene expression signatures associated with melanoma progression may identify improved screening tools and therapeutic strategies, we used high density cDNA microarrays for gene expression profiling of genetically well-defined melanoma cell lines isolated from distinctive stages of tumor progression. Novel data reduction algorithms were used to identify gene signatures associated with tumor invasion and metastasis. Here we report unique sets of gene expression signatures that are associated with melanoma progression. Many of these pathways have previously been implicated in melanoma progression; however, the specific signature genes identified are novel. These particular progression-associated genes may reflect the underlying molecular mechanisms of the various phases in the known tumor progression pathways of melanoma. As such, the pathways and molecules identified in this study have the potential to be utilized as therapeutic targets for melanoma as well as novel molecular markers for melanoma progression. Moreover, these studies support the use of renewable sources of tumor cells, such as informative tumor cell lines, for the early identification of genes associated with malignant progression which can be subsequently validated using more precious primary tissue specimens.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>In order to define gene expression patterns during the course of melanoma development and progression, we evaluated a series of primary and metastatic melanoma cells derived from lesions of discrete phases of melanoma progression as well as pools of primary human melanocytes. Tumor cell lines derived from three radial growth phase (RGP) melanomas (WM35, SBC12, and WM1552C), four vertical growth phase (VGP) melanomas (WM902B, WM278, WM983A, and WM793), and three metastatic melanomas (WM852, WM983B, 1205Lu) were evaluated. These cell lines possess a notable ability to recapitulate the clinical stages of disease from which they were derived <xref rid="pone.0000594-HsuMY1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000594-Satyamoorthy1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and have been characterized with respect to tumorigenicity and metastasis <xref rid="pone.0000594-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-ValyiNagy1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>; cellular growth characteristics including life span, growth factor dependency, anchorage-independent growth <xref rid="pone.0000594-HsuMY1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>; and pigmentation and morphology <xref rid="pone.0000594-Herlyn2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. In addition, cytogenetic analyses in these cell lines including non-random abnormalities such as deletions, translocations, and amplifications have been well-documented and suggest high relevance to the primary tumor of origin (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0000594-HsuMY1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>).</p>
      <p>Global gene expression patterns were obtained using Affymetrix gene chips and comparison of gene expression profiles was performed using hierarchical clustering analysis. This clustering analysis identified two distinct groups of melanoma cell lines based on the similarity of their expression patterns, separating radial growth phase (RGP) and metastatic melanomas (MM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1</xref>); however, vertical growth phase (VGP) melanomas failed to form a distinctive cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). The first group, which we characterized as “less-aggressive” primary melanomas (designated as Group1), included all three RGP melanomas (WM35, Sbcl2, and WM1552C) and two VGP melanomas (WM902B and WM278). The second group, which we characterized as “more-aggressive” melanomas (designated as Group2), included all three metastatic melanomas (WM853, WM983B, and 1205Lu) and two VGP melanomas (WM983B and WM793). Additional cluster analyses with different linkage matrices produced similar results (data not shown). Of note, only 2 of the 10 cell lines (Sbcl2 and WM853) were found to be wildtype for BRAF kinase and this genotype failed to demonstrate a notable cluster in our hierarchical analyses.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0000594-g001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.g001</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evaluation of gene expression profiles from melanoma cells lines of varying stages of progression identifies a signature for aggressive melanomas.</title>
          <p>A) Unsupervised hierarchical clustering of melanoma cells indicates the existence of two distinct groups of melanoma cells based on global gene expression patterns (Group 1: RGP2, RGP3, RGP1, VGP1, and VGP2; Group 2: VGP3, MM2, MM1, VGP4, and MM3). B) SAM plot sheet illustrating a signature for differentially expressed genes in aggressive melanomas. Gene expression profiles from the two groups of melanomas were compared (Group1 vs. Group 2) and a differentially expressed gene signature was identified by SAM. Red and green dots represent gene probesets upregulated and downregulated respectively in Group 2. C) The melanoma gene signature was visualized using Java TreeView. Genes over four-fold differentially expressed are indicated on the right side of the image. D) Validation of select differentially expressed genes by real-time RT-PCR. Three genes upregulated in aggressive melanomas (Group 2) were selected for analysis and their differential expression was verified. 3.0 µg of total RNA was subjected to cDNA synthesis reaction as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">materials and methods</xref>. 1.0 µl of the final cDNA samples (100 µl) were used for real-time Q-PCR reaction. For the measurement of gene transcript level, standard curves were generated for each gene using known amount of PCR amplified product from the corresponding genes. Error bars are SD of three independent experiments.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0000594.g001"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In order to identify a cohort of genes differentially expressed between our defined groups of melanomas, the gene expression array dataset was subjected to the microarray data analysis program Significance Analysis of Microarray (SAM) <xref rid="pone.0000594-Tusher1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. This analysis resulted in 142 differentially expressed probesets with a 3.5 % false discovery rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1B and C</xref>). In total, 89 probe sets representing 65 well-defined genes were found to be upregulated in more-aggressive (group 2) versus less-aggressive (group 1) melanomas and 53 probe sets representing 37 well-defined genes were found to be downregulated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0000594.s003">Table S1</xref>). When more stringent criteria were applied (well-characterized genes which are differentially expressed greater than 4-fold) to this signature, we identified 21 upregulated and 5 downregulated genes in the more-aggressive melanoma cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Of note, the set of genes highly expressed in more-aggressive melanomas includes many novel genes with reported functional roles in cell cycle regulation and proliferation such as <italic>ZWINT, CDCA2, NCAPH, NCAPG, NCAPG2, PBK, NUSAP1, BIRC5, ESCO2, HELLS, MELK, and CDKN2C</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0000594-Obuse1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Zindy1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> as well as genes that are involved DNA replication and repair processes including <italic>GINS1, GINS4, RAD54L, TYMS</italic>, and <italic>DHFR</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0000594-Ueno1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Banerjee1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000594-t001">Table 1</xref>). Differential expression of these genes was validated by quantitative real-time RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1D</xref>).</p>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0000594-t001" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.t001</object-id>
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Genes with altered expression in aggressive melanoma cells are involved in cell cycle control, cell proliferation, DNA repair and replication<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref>.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0000594-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0000594.t001"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe Set ID</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Title</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Symbol</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227350_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Helicase, lymphoid-specific</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HELLS<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell proliferation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202589_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thymidylate synthetase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TYMS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA replication, DNA repair</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204558_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAD54-like (S. cerevisiae)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAD54L</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair, response to DNA damage</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204825_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">maternal embryonic leucine zipper kinase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MELK</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitosis, protein phosphorylation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204159_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 2C (p18)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDKN2C</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212949_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">barren homolog 1 (Drosophila)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCAPH</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle, chromosome condensation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219588_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">leucine zipper protein 5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCAPG2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle, chromosome condensation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218663_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome condensation protein G</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCAPG1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle, chromosome condensation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211767_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GINS complex subunit 4 (Sld5 homolog)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GINS4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA replication, cell proliferation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206102_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GINS complex subunit 1 (Psf1 homolog)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GINS1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA replication, cell proliferation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202095_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">baculoviral IAP repeat-containing 5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIRC5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2/M transition cell cycle</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219148_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDZ binding kinase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PBK</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitosis, protein phosphorylation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235178_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">establishment of cohesion 1 homolog 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESCO2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226661_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell division cycle associated 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDCA2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204026_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZW10 interactor</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZWINT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle, spindle organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202534_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dihydrofolate reductase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHFR</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA replication, nucleotide metab olism</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218039_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleolar and spindle associated protein 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NUSAP1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell cycle, chromosome condensation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1555788_a_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tribbles homolog 3 (Drosophila)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRIB3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">anti-proliferation, apoptosis</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt101">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Genes with greater than four-fold differential expression are shown.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt102">
            <label>b</label>
            <p>Fold represents average expression ratio of group 2 over Group1.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt103">
            <label>c</label>
            <p>Genes with multiple probesets are shown with data from a single representative probeset.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Since we were interested in defining melanoma progression signatures, and all melanomas are initiated in primary human melanocytes, we evaluated our expression profiling data in the context of cultured neonatal primary human melanocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Surprisingly, when two pools of short-term cultured primary human melanocytes (HPM1 and HPM2) were included in the previously employed hierarchical clustering protocol, the global gene expression pattern of the normal melanocytes was found to be more similar to that of the more-aggressive melanomas (Group 2) than the less-aggressive melanomas (Group 1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Since early cultures of primary human melanocytes derived from neonatal foreskins divide rapidly yet possess a normal differentiation program, we reasoned that the similarities of these cells to more aggressive tumors was likely due to their proliferative potential. In order to test this hypothesis we compared gene expression profiles of more-aggressive melanoma cells (Group 2) to those of short-term cultured primary human melanocytes. Expression profiles were subjected to SAM analysis which identified a cohort of differentially expressed genes with a 0.85% false discovery rate. Remarkably, all differentially expressed genes were found to be down-regulated genes in aggressive melanoma cells versus primary human melanocytes suggesting that loss of specific gene signatures may be a key event in the development of advanced melanomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Further assessment of all melanoma expression profiles using TreeView revealed that the majority of these melanoma-associated genes are also down-regulated in the less-aggressive primary melanomas (Group1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). This gene signature is comprised of critical mediators of cellular adhesion and melanocyte development and differentiation and includes: <italic>CDH3, CDH1, c-KIT, PAX3, CITED1/MSG-1, TYR, MELANA, MC1R,</italic> and <italic>OCA2</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0000594-Nishimura1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Suzuki1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000594-t002">Table 2</xref>). While such a loss of cellular adhesion by E-cadherin and P-cadherin has been extensively documented in melanoma (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0000594-Bonitsis1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>), and the loss of differentiation-associated genes is not wholly surprising, this signature does notably identify specific defects in the intrinsic melanocyte development program that may contribute to melanoma development. In addition, genes with tumor suppressor and metastasis suppressor functions (DPP4, SYK) are included in this melanoma signature <xref rid="pone.0000594-Wesley1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000594-Coopman1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Significant down-regulation of these genes in the aggressive metastatic melanoma cells was validated using semi-quantitative duplex RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). Furthermore, this differentially expressed “melanoma signature” contains many genes whose functional roles in melanoma progression have not been well characterized and may provide novel insights into the early development of melanoma from primary melanocytes.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0000594-g002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.g002</object-id>
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Evaluation of differential gene expression from aggressive melanomas (Group 2) vs. primary human melanocytes identifies a signature characterized by loss of differentiation-associated genes.</title>
          <p>A) Java TreeView analysis of melanoma cell lines and primary human melanocytes clusters two pools of human primary melanocytes (HPM1 and HPM2) with the Group 2 melanomas. B) SAM plot sheet illustrating a signature of down-regulated genes in group 2 melanomas compared to HPMs. Gene expression profiles of two pools of human primary melanocytes (HPM1 and HPM2) were compared to those of aggressive melanomas (Group 2) and a differentially expressed gene signature was identified by SAM. C) The melanoma gene signature was visualized using Java TreeView. Genes over five-fold downregulated are indicated on the right. D) Validation of differential expression for selected genes by semi-quantitative duplex RT-PCR. Four genes (CDH3, KIT, DPP4, SYK) downregulated in the aggressive melanoma cells (Group 2) were selected for analysis and their differential expression was verified.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0000594.g002"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0000594-t002" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.t002</object-id>
        <label>Table 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Differential expression of genes that are downregulated in aggressive melanoma cells (Group2) compared to primary human melanocytes. Genes with greater than five-fold differential expression are shown <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref>.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0000594-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0000594.t002"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe Set ID</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Title</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Symbol</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203256_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cadherin 3, type 1, P-cadherin (placental)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDH3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−161.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201131_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cadherin 1, type 1, E-cadherin (epithelial)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDH1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−35.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205051_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">v-kit viral oncogenehomolog</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−94.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1565162_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">microsomal glutathione S-transferase 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MGST1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−92.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203716_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dipeptidyl-peptidase 4 (CD26)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPP4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−74.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">proteolysis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206039_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAB33A, member RAS oncogene family</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAB33A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−70.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226311_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDNA clone IMAGE: 30924414</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−64.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236901_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADAM metallopeptidase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADAMTS2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−62.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">proteolysis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229095_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to LIM</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC440895</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−54.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227705_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcription elongation factor A (SII)-like 7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCEAL7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−49.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1556698_a_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein LOC285513</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC285513</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−35.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213924_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">metallophosphoesterase 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPPE1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−33.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209569_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA segment on chromosome 4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D4S234E<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−31.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dopamine receptor signaling</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202283_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">serpin peptidase inhibitor, clade F, member 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SERPINF1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−29.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">development/proliferation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204570_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome c oxidase subunit VIIa polypeptide 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COX7A1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−28.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">electron transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202546_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vesicle-associated membrane protein 8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VAMP8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vesicle-mediated transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208017_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCF.2 cell line derived transforming sequence</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCF2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intracellular signaling cascade</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217248_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">solute carrier family 7, member 8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLC7A8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">amino acid transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206479_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transient receptor potential cation channel</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRPM1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cation transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205114_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220813_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cysteinyl leukotriene receptor 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYSLTR2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−25.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206355_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G protein, alpha activating activity polypeptide</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GNAL<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237472_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOX1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−23.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of transcription</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203815_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glutathione S-transferase theta 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSTT1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">response to stress</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212599_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">autism susceptibility candidate 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUTS2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206426_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">melan-A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLANA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−20.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225407_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myelin basic protein</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MBP<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−19.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNS development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219436_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">endomucin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMCN</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−19.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1556427_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to hypothetical protein</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC221091</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201425_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aldehyde dehydrogenase 2 family (mitochondrial)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALDH2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">carbohydrate metabolism</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207144_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cbp/p300-interacting transactivator 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CITED1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of transcription</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212338_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myosin ID</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYO1D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219315_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome 16 open reading frame 30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C16orf30</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−17.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227532_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">leucine rich repeat containing 39</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LRRC39</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−16.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206569_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 24</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL24</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−16.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">apoptosis/immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226068_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">spleen tyrosine kinase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYK<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213122_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSPY-like 5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TSPYL5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−15.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleosome assembly</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204187_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">guanosine monophosphate reductase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMPR</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleic acid metabolism</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204880_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O-6-methylguanine-DNA methyltransferase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MGMT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204777_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mal, T-cell differentiation protein</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAL</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−14.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell differentiation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1555505_a_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tyrosinase (oculocutaneous albinism IA)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TYR</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">melanin biosynthesis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226778_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome 8 open reading frame 42</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C8orf42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−13.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225792_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hook homolog 1 (Drosophila)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HOOK1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−12.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytoskeleton organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209924_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211427_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">potassium inwardly-rectifying channel,</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KCNJ13</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ion transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213556_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">similar to R28379-1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC390940</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240173_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcribed locus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206498_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oculocutaneous albinism II</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OCA2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eye pigment biosynthesis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241600_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcribed locus</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−11.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205297_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD79b molecule, immunoglobulin-associated</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD79B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228256_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">erythrocyte membrane protein band 4.1 like 4A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPB41L4A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223693_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein FLJ10324</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLJ10324</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243727_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">copine VIII</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPNE8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232687_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDNA FLJ33091 fis, clone TRACH2000660</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232443_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical gene supported by AF131741</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC441052</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236377_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane protein 132D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMEM132D</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211748_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prostaglandin D2 synthase 21kDa (brain)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTGDS</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lipid biosynthesis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204112_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">histamine N-methyltransferase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HNMT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">respiratory gaseous exchange</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228057_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-damage-inducible transcript 4-like</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DDIT4L</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51158_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical gene</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC400451</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209550_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">necdin homolog (mouse)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDN</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of cell cycle</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214255_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATPase, Class V, type 10A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP10A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cation transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1553485_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein LOC151278</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLJ32447</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204273_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">endothelin receptor type B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDNRB</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein signaling</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235758_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">paraneoplastic antigen like 6A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNMA6A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213816_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">met proto-oncogene</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MET</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell proliferation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227704_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">full-length cDNA clone CS0CAP008YI07</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224566_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">trophoblast-derived noncoding RNA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TncRNA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207610_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF-like module containing, mucin-like</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232504_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein LOC285628</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC285628</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241966_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">myosin VA (heavy polypeptide 12, myoxin)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MYO5A<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">actin-based movement</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229925_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">solute carrier family 6, member 17</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLC6A17</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neurotransmitter transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229251_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">two pore segment channel 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCN2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cation transport</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216059_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">paired box gene 3 (Waardenburg syndrome 1)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAX3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227949_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphatase and actin regulator 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHACTR3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209685_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein kinase C, beta 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRKCB1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intracellular signaling cascade</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204995_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cyclin-dependent kinase 5, regulatory subunit 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDK5R1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neuron differentiation</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206020_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">suppressor of cytokine signaling 6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOCS6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of cell growth</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221036_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">anterior pharynx defective 1 homolog B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APH1B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notch signaling pathway</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205458_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">melanocortin 1 receptor</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MC1R</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G-protein signaling</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt104">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Genes with greater than five-fold differential expression are shown.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt105">
            <label>b</label>
            <p>Fold represents average expression ratio of aggressive metastatic melanoma samples (group2) over normal primary human melanocyte samples.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt106">
            <label>c</label>
            <p>Gene with multiple probesets are shown with a representative probeset.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>A current melanoma progression model suggests the sequential evolution of primary <italic>in situ</italic> tumors and minimally invasive tumors which are termed “radial growth phase”, followed by a subsequent conversion to a more aggressive “vertical growth phase”, in which tumor cells are programmed to cross the epidermal basement membrane and invade vertically into the dermis. It has been postulated that the VGP is the critical stage in which a tumor gains metastatic capacity. We therefore compared the gene expression profiles of RGP and VGP melanomas using a uniquely designed data reduction algorithm in order to identify genes that are likely to be relevant to this critical invasive phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Our melanoma invasion-specific signature is notably characterized by the inclusion of several genes involved in chemotaxis and the inflammatory response (<italic>CXCL1, CXCL2, IL8,</italic> and <italic>IL6</italic>), cell adhesion (<italic>HNT, ITGA4, ITGB8, CSPG2, ZP4,</italic> and <italic>FLRT3</italic>), and extracellular matrix organization (<italic>MMP1, COL4A1, COL4A2,</italic> and <italic>COL5A2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000594-t003">Table 3</xref>). These genes and their relative expression profiles are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3B</xref>. These cellular processes have previously been implicated in tumor progression for a wide variety of malignancies including melanoma and are felt to be essential components of tumor invasion and metastasis. In addition, many of these invasion-specific signature genes are also upregulated in metastatic melanomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). The differential expressions were validated on the selected genes using semi-quantitative duplex-PCR analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3C</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="pone-0000594-g003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.g003</object-id>
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Identification of an invasion-specific gene signature for melanoma.</title>
          <p>A) The three-step data reduction algorithm used for identification of a melanoma invasion-specific signature. (see detailed description in Data Extraction and Statistical Analysis section of <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>). B) Relative expression levels of melanoma invasion-specific signature genes in all cells analyzed including human primary melanocytes (HPM1, HPM2). C) Validation of differential expression for selected genes by semi-quantitative duplex RT-PCR. Four genes (IL-8, IGFBP3, CXCL1, CXCL2) that are upregulated in invasive melanomas were selected and their differential expression was verified. D) Promoter analysis of selected genes from the melanoma invasion-specific signature identifies putative NF-κB binding <italic>cis</italic> elements. E) Immunofluorescence staining of NF-κB in invasive (WM902B) vs. non-invasive (WM1552C) melanoma cells demonstrates constitutive activation and nuclear trafficking of NF-κB in invasive melanomas.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0000594.g003"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="pone-0000594-t003" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.t003</object-id>
        <label>Table 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Melanoma invasion-specific signature genes that are upregulated in VGP compared to RGP melanoma cells <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>.</title>
        </caption>
        <alternatives>
          <graphic id="pone-0000594-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0000594.t003"/>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <colgroup span="1">
              <col align="left" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
              <col align="center" span="1"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe Set ID</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Title</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Symbol</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fold <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological Process</td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204470_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCL1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1555471_a_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">formin 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FMN2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204475_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">matrix metallopeptidase 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMP1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">proteolysis/ECM organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202196_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dickkopf homolog 3 (Xenopus laevis)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DKK3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wnt receptor signaling</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208894_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">major histocompatibility complex, class II, DRα</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-DRA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211506_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212730_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">desmuslin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMN</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210095_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">insulin-like growth factor binding protein 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IGFBP3<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of cell growth</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206640_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G antigens</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGEs</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellular defense response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">227566_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neurotrimin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HNT</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212327_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein DKFZP686A01247<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">actomyosin structure</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211776_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">erythrocyte membrane protein band 4.1-like 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPB41L3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytoskeleton organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221729_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">collagen, type V, alpha 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL5A2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECM organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226189_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">integrin, beta 8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITGB8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell-matrix adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226847_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">follistatin</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FST<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222450_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane, prostate androgen induced RNA</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMEPAI<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">androgen receptor signaling</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212942_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIAA1199</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIAA1199</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensory perception of sound</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205207_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">interleukin 6 (interferon, beta 2)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209619_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD74 molecule, major histocompatibility complex</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD74</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211571_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chondroitin sulfate proteoglycan 2 (versican)</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSPG2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion/development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223614_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome 8 open reading frame 57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C8orf57</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207030_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cysteine and glycine-rich protein 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSRP2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">muscle development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229800_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doublecortin and CaM kinase-like 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DCAMKL1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nervous system development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211538_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">heat shock 70kDa protein 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSPA2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein folding</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223638_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neuroblastoma breakpoint family, member 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NBPF3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209312_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">major histocompatibility complex, class II, DR β1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-DRB1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1561691_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein LOC285735</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC285735</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209774_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCL2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemotaxis/inflammatory</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209392_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pyrophosphatase/phosphodiesterase 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENPP2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell motility/chemotaxis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231756_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">zona pellucida glycoprotein 4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fertilization/cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209309_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">alpha-2-glycoprotein 1, zinc</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AZGP1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241803_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204469_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein tyrosine phosphatase, receptor-type, Z</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTPRZ1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nervous system development</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205885_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">integrin, alpha 4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITGA4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesions</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228293_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEP domain containing 7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DEPDC7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of transcription</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213075_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">olfactomedin-like 2A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLFML2A</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219230_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane protein 100</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMEM100</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204681_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rap guanine nucleotide exchange factor 5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RAPGEF5</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211980_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">collagen, type IV, alpha 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL4A1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECM organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211991_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">major histocompatibility complex, class II, DP α1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-DPA1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">immune response</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216959_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neuronal cell adhesion molecule</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRCAM</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neuron cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209967_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cAMP responsive element modulator</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CREM</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222162_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADAM metallopeptidase</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADAMTS1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">proteolysis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233903_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Src domain-containing guanine exchange factor</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGEF<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">c</xref>
</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rho protein signaling</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207034_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLI-Kruppel family member GLI2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLI2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">morphogenesis</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222853_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fibronectin leucine rich transmembrane protein 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FLRT3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell adhesion</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226436_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras association (RalGDS/AF-6) domain family 4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASSF4</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219872_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chromosome 4 open reading frame 18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C4orf18</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211966_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">collagen, type IV, alpha 2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL4A2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECM organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209859_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tripartite motif-containing 9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRIM9</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214023_x_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tubulin, beta 2B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TUBB2B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">microtubule-based movement</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204702_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFE2L3</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">regulation of transcription</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205599_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF receptor-associated factor 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAF1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212325_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hypothetical protein, DKFZP686A01247</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">actomyosin organization</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1554474_a_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">monooxygenase, DBH-like 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MOXD1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catecholamine metabolism</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235116_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF receptor-associated factor 1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRAF1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210139_s_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peripheral myelin protein 22</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMP22</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peripheral nervous develop</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203680_at</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein kinase, cAMP-dependent, type II, beta</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRKAR2B</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal transduction</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </alternatives>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="nt107">
            <label>a</label>
            <p>Genes with greater than five-fold upregulation are shown.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt108">
            <label>b</label>
            <p>Fold represents average expression ratio of VGP melanoma cells over RGP melanoma cells.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn id="nt109">
            <label>c</label>
            <p>Gene with multiple probesets are shown with a representative probeset.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>Since the melanoma invasion-specific signature was associated with common functions of matrix invasion/inflammation/cell migration we sought to determine whether a common upstream regulatory pathway might link these signature genes. The eight most highly up-regulated genes from our melanoma invasion-specific signature were selected for further evaluation and gene promoter sequences were analyzed to identify transcription factor binding <italic>cis</italic> elements. This promoter analysis yielded a profile of transcription factors with common sequence elements in the signature genes. The most ubiquitous <italic>cis</italic> elements among the gene promoters evaluated were E12, E47, GCN4, GR, HES-1, IL-6, MEF-2, NF-κB, N-Oct-3, PU.1, RAR-alpha1, SRF, and the basal gene transcriptional complex components of TFIID, TBP, and TBF1. We notably identified the NF-κB binding sequence in 7 out of 8 of the most upregulated invasion-specific signature genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). We were particularly interested in the NF-κB pathway as a mediator of melanoma invasion since our most highly upregulated invasion-specific genes, <italic>CXCL-1</italic> and <italic>IL-8</italic>, have previously been reported to be activated by NF-κB and had previously been implicated in melanoma progression (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0000594-Ueda1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>). Given the consequences of NF-κB activation in a cell, NF-κB function is highly regulated by specific cytosolic inhibitory activities which prevent inappropriate NF-κB activation and shuttling to the nucleus. Thus, only nuclear NF-κB is considered to be functionally activated. In order to evaluate NF-κB function in our tumor cell lines, we used NF-κB cellular localization as a surrogate marker for NF-κB activity. We find that invasive (VGP) melanomas posses both cytosolic (inactive) and nuclear (active) localization of NF-κB, while non-invasive (RGP) melanomas possess NF-κB confined to the cytosolic compartment suggesting specific activation of NF-κB during melanoma progression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3E</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Molecular profiling studies of melanoma to date have been variably successful and often inconsistent. Much of this inconsistency has been attributed to the heterogeneous nature of this malignancy and the lack of significant sources of meaningful archived tissue specimens for analysis. In addition, variable sample preparation techniques are also likely to lead to disparate results between investigators. Here we have used a series of well-defined melanoma cell lines from varying stages of malignant progression to assess molecular signatures associated with disease progression. These cell lines have undergone extensive characterization of their tumorigenic potential and invasion capacity <xref rid="pone.0000594-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0000594-Hsu1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, and have been shown to possess a remarkable ability to recapitulate the clinical stages of disease from which they were derived. We show that unsupervised hierarchical clustering of global gene expression profiles of melanoma cell lines allows for the classification of tumor cells into 2 groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) that we have defined as less-aggressive (Group 1) and more-aggressive (Group 2) melanomas. While all radial growth phase melanomas clustered in Group 1, and all metastatic melanomas clustered in Group 2, vertical growth phase melanomas failed to form a distinctive cluster suggesting that vertical growth phase melanomas may be considered to be a transient or transition phase within the current melanoma progression model <xref rid="pone.0000594-Clark1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Aggressive (Group 2) melanomas were characterized by upregulation of genes associated with cell cycle progression, DNA replication and repair, and altered expression of apoptosis-related genes including upregulation of the antiapoptotic gene BIRC5/survivin <xref rid="pone.0000594-Grossman1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> and downregulation of the novel stress-associated apoptosis inducer TRIB3 <xref rid="pone.0000594-Ohoka1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000594-t001">Table 1</xref>). These signature genes for melanoma progression are remarkably similar to those obtained from recent large-scale studies using primary human melanomas and suggest high correlation with alterations seen in primary tumor specimens <xref rid="pone.0000594-Winnepenninckx1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Notably, we did not identify a dominant signature associated with BRAF kinase mutations which may be reflective of the relative infrequency of wildtype BRAF in these cell lines. As a whole, this gene signature suggests a series of molecular alterations occur in aggressive melanomas that promote melanoma cell growth, survival and apoptotic resistance which contribute to the unresponsiveness of melanomas to traditional chemotherapeutic agents <xref rid="pone.0000594-Atkins1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>.</p>
      <p>While gene signatures associated with aggressive melanomas provide insights into molecular pathways important for tumor progression, further analysis of these tumor cell lines in conjunction with expression profiles from primary human melanocytes using SAM analysis revealed a striking signature characterized exclusively by gene loss in melanomas and primarily by loss of cellular adhesion and melanocyte differentiation-associated genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g002">Figures 2B, 2C</xref>). We suggest that this melanoma-associated signature defines critical molecular mechanisms involved in melanocyte development and differentiation which distinguish these tumor cells from their primary cell of origin. In fact, the identification of several genes in this signature with established functional roles in melanocyte differentiation and melanin biosynthesis such as <italic>CDH3, CDH1, c-KIT, PAX3, CITED1/MSG-1, TYR, MELANA, MC1R,</italic> and <italic>OCA2</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0000594-Nishimura1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Suzuki1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, supports this notion. Moreover, this signature has identified two tumor suppressor genes, DPP4 and SYK, whose downregulation has previously been implicated in melanoma development <xref rid="pone.0000594-Houghton1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>–<xref rid="pone.0000594-Muthusamy1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Finally, evaluation of an invasion-specific signature for melanoma identified dominant gene activation by the transcription factor, NF-κB. Constitutive activation of NF-κB and an inflammatory response is an emerging hallmark of various tumor types <xref rid="pone.0000594-Karin1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. In addition, NF-κB has specifically been implicated in the development of invasive aggressive melanomas through autocrine and paracrine mechanisms (reviewed in <xref rid="pone.0000594-Ueda1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>). Our melanoma invasion signature is associated with upregulation of critical NF-κB effectors including CXCL1, FMN2, MMP1, IL-8, IGFBP3 which have been implicated in the regulation of tumor cell proliferation, motility, migration, and/or invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). In addition, the putative NF-κB target gene GAGE7B which we identified in our melanoma invasion-specific signature, has been associated with apoptotic resistance and worse prognosis in other tumors <xref rid="pone.0000594-Cilensek1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. In addition, several of our invasion-specific signature genes are chemokines including CXCL1, CXCL2, and IL-8 which have been implicated in the promotion of tumor-associated angiogenesis, a critical feature of invasive tumors <xref rid="pone.0000594-Rofstad1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In summary, our gene expression profiling studies of melanoma cell lines from varying stages of malignant progression and primary human melanocytes have identified several important melanoma signatures including: 1) Aggressive melanomas are characterized by upregulation of genes associated with cell cycle progression, DNA replication and repair and apoptotic resistance as well as loss of genes associated with apoptotic susceptibility, 2) Melanomas notably differ from their cell of origin, primary human melanocytes, due to a loss of cellular adhesion and differentiation-associated genes, and 3) Invasive melanomas are characterized by a signature indicative of global activation of NF-κB and downstream effector genes associated with tumor cell migration, invasion, chemotaxis, and proliferation. Since pathways associated with tumor progression may have clinical utility as prognostic tumor markers and therapeutic targets, we expect novel melanoma signature genes identified in this study will be further developed for such translational endpoints. Moreover, the important information regarding melanoma biology gleaned from these studies on renewable cell resources cannot be understated. A major roadblock to advances in melanoma therapy has been the relative paucity of informative tissue specimens available for analysis in profiling studies as well as the notoriously heterogeneous nature of this malignancy. The use of surrogate tissue resources including tumor cell lines for the early discovery phases in melanoma, as used in this study, will undoubtedly allow for the conservation of precious tissue specimens for use in more advanced validation studies. It is expected that the novel melanoma progression-associated genes identified in this study will provide new insights into the molecular defects associated with this malignancy and ultimately pave the way for the development of new melanoma biomarkers and novel targeted therapies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Cells</title>
        <p>Ten melanoma cell lines (WM35, SBC12, and WM1552C, WM902B, WM278, WM983A, and WM793, WM852, WM983B, 1205Lu) were obtained from M. Herlyn (The Wistar Institute, Philadelphia, PA). These cell lines were maintained in modified complete melanocyte growth medium (Cell Application Inc., San Diego, CA) which lacked 12-<italic>O</italic> -tetradecanoyl phorbol-13-acetate and was supplemented with 2 % fetal bovine serum. Normal human primary melanocytes were isolated from neonatal foreskins and grown in complete melanocyte growth medium (Cell Applications, Cat. No., 135–500). The complete melanocyte growth medium is consisted of the melanocyte basal medium (Cell Applications, Cat. No. 134-500) and growth supplement cocktails containing hydrocortisone (0.5 µg/ml), insulin (5 µg/ml), 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate (10 ng/ml), bovine pituitary extract (21 µg/ml), bFGF (1 ng/ml), heparin (1 µg/ml), FBS (0.5 %), gentamycin sulfate (50 µg/ml), amphotericin B (5 ng/ml), and NaCl (45 mM).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Gene Expression Profiling</title>
        <p>Total RNA was isolated from exponentially growing melanoma cell lines using RNeasy column purification per manufacturer's protocol (Qiagen). Two sets of short-term cultured (2 to 3 passage numbers) normal human melanocytes were prepared from neonatal foreskins. In order to minimize genetic variability melanocytes from 4–5 individuals were pooled for each culture. Total RNA from normal melanocytes was extracted and purified by a combination of phase extraction and chromatography using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies Inc.) and RNeasy columns (Qiagen) in order to remove melanin. In brief, exponentially growing melanocytes were lysed with TRIzol reagent and lysate was incubated at 65°C for 2 minutes to inactivate melanin. Lysate was then subjected to phase extraction and RNeasy column purification. RNA quality checks, double strand complementary DNA synthesis, hybridization with Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 Array Chips (Affymetrix Inc. Santa Clara, CA), and initial data extraction were performed at The Gene Array Core Facility in the Malaria Research Institute (JHMRI) at The Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://malaria.jhsph.edu/jhmri/resources_education/gene_array_core">http://malaria.jhsph.edu/jhmri/resources_education/gene_array_core</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>Data Extraction and Statistical Analysis</title>
        <p>SAM <xref rid="pone.0000594-Tusher1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, Gene Cluster 3.0 <xref rid="pone.0000594-deHoon1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref> and TreeView (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bonsai.ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~mdehoon/software/cluster/index.html">http://bonsai.ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp/∼mdehoon/software/cluster/index.html</ext-link>), Access, and Excel (Microsoft, Seattle, WA) programs were used. For all of the statistical analysis beyond the initial description of datasets, microarray data were normalized (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0000594.s001">Dataset S1</xref>) and a subset of the 12 microarray data (10 from melanoma cell lines and 2 from normal human melanocytes) was obtained by filtering to require each gene probe to have at least one observation in the expression intensity resulting in a ‘present’ call from all 12 samples. This produced a subset of data containing a total of 32,632 affymetrix gene probes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0000594.s002">Dataset S2</xref>). This filtered subset of data was used for all of the additional analysis. <italic>Cluster Analysis.</italic> Unsupervised hierarchical clustering analysis was performed on the subset of data (without log transformation) with Gene Cluster 3.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bonsai.ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~mdehoon/software/cluster/index.html">http://bonsai.ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp/∼mdehoon/software/cluster/index.html</ext-link>) by using the correlation (uncentered) similarity metric and centeroid linkage clustering method. The resulting tree-images were visualized using Java TreeView. <italic>Statistical Analysis of Microarray (SAM).</italic> SAM was performed on the subset of array data without log transformation using SAM software package. Groups are defined based on the hierarchical clustering; for example, group 1  =  less-aggressive primary melanomas (RGP melanomas: WM35, Sbcl2, WM1552C and VGP melanomas: WM902B and WM278), and group 2  =  aggressive metastatic melanomas (Metastatic melanomas: WM852, WM983B, and 1205Lu; and VGP melanomas: WM983A and WM793) as seen <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000594-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Delta was chosen to limit the output gene list so that minimum predicted false-positives would be included. <italic>Three-step Data Reduction Algorithm.</italic> In order to identify melanoma invasion-specific gene signature, uniquely designed three-step data reduction algorithm was applied to the subset of expression data. First step is that the proveset should be called as ‘present’ in three samples out of four VGP melanoma cells and two samples out of three RGP melanoma cells. Second step is that the candidate proveset should be expressed five folds or more in VGP melanoma cell lines than RGP melanoma cell lines. The last step is that the gene probesets were retained only when the expression level is greater than three folds in VGP melanoma cell lines compared to that of primary human melanocytes. The last step is implemented because the candidate gene expression level should be higher if the gene products have certain degree of functional roles in the invasion processes of malignant melanoma. The probesets, those that pass through three-step filtration criteria are subjected to probeset to gene mapping using NetAffx, a web interface program from Affymetrix Inc. Gene annotation for the gene mane, gene symbol, and GO Biological Procession Analysis also performed by the NetAffx.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Quantitative Real-time PCR</title>
        <p>cDNA was generated by using the SuperScript™ First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR according to manufacturers instructions (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). Quantitative real-time PCR was performed with an Applied Biosystems Prism 7900 HT Sequence Detection System using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). The thermal cycling conditions for quantitative real-time RT-PCR analysis to validate gene expression changes were as follows: hold for 10 minutes at 95°C, followed by three-step PCR for 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 seconds, 55°C to 60°C for 25 seconds, and 72°C for 30 seconds. Optimal annealing temperatures were predetermined to ensure single amplified product. All samples were performed in triplicate. Amplification data were analyzed with an Applied Biosystems Prism Sequencer Detection Software Version 2.3 (Applied Biosystems, Forster City, CA). Human <italic>GAPDH</italic> gene was used as endogenous control. To normalize the relative expression of the genes of interest to the <italic>GAPDH</italic> control, standard curves were prepared for each gene and <italic>GAPDH</italic> in each experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Semi-quantitative Duplex PCR</title>
        <p>Semi-quantitative duplex RT-PCR was performed by an MJ Research Programmable Thermal Controller (PTC-100, Inc., Watertown, MA) and the amplified products were separated on an agarose gel. Our duplex PCR utilized 20 bp oligonucleotides to amplify regions of 300–400 bp from the genes of interest. Intitial optimization experiments were conducted to establish the most favorable primer concentrations between the genes of interest and internal control GAPDH, yielding 0.8 µM and 0.04 µM, respectively. The PCR was carried out in a total volume of 25 µL, containing 2.5 µL of 10X PCR Buffer (containing 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), 0.2 mM dNTPs, and 0.3 ul AmpliTaq Gold DNA Polymerase (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Thirty to thirty-five amplification cycles were performed by an MJ Research Programmable Thermal Controller (PTC-100, Inc., Watertown, MA), using a denaturing temperature of 95°C for 25 seconds, an annealing temperature varying between 55°C−60°C (depending on gene) for 30 seconds, and primer extension at 72°C for 30 seconds. Each amplification experiment also included two negative PCR controls, a no-RNA control from reverse transcription procedures and a no-cDNA water control. Following amplification, 25 µL of the samples were separated via electrophoresis on a 3% agarose gel. The primer sequences were designed by using Primer3, primer analysis software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi">http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi</ext-link>), yielded only one amplified product and had the following sequences:<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000594-t004"/>
</p>
        <table-wrap id="pone-0000594-t004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000594.t004</object-id>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic id="pone-0000594-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0000594.t004"/>
            <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
              <colgroup span="1">
                <col align="left" span="1"/>
                <col align="center" span="1"/>
              </colgroup>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MELK</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-TGGCTCTCTCCCAGTAGCAT-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-TAGCACTGGCTTGTCCACAG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GINS4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-CAGAGAGTTCATGGCGAACA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-CTCCCAAAGTGCTGGGATTA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCAPG</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-TATTGGTGTGCCCTTTGTGA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-CAGGGATATTGGGATTGTGG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDH3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-ACGACACCCTCTTGGTGTTC-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-GTCAAACTGCCCACATTCCT-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KIT</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-TGACTTACGACAGGCTCGTG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-AAGGAGTGAACAGGGTGTGG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPP4</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-CAAATTGAAGCAGCCAGACA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-CAGGGCTTTGGAGATCTGAG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYR</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-GAAGCCATATCGAGGGATGA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-TGACAAGTTGTGGGCATGTT-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCL1</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-TGTTTGAGCATCGCTTAGGA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-GATCTCATTGGCCATTTGCT-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCL2</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-TTGCGCCTAATGTGTTTGAG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-ATACATTTCCCTGCCGTCAC-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL8</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-AGGGTTGCCAGATGCAATAC-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-AGCAGACTAGGGTTGCCAGA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IGFBP3</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-GCTACAGCATGCAGAGCAAG-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-AACATGTGGTGAGCATTCCA-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAPDH</td>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: 5′-GATCATCAGCAATGCCTCCT-3′</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                  <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: 5′-TTCAGCTCAGGGATGACCTT-3′</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Immunofluorescence Labeling</title>
        <p>RGP and VGP Cells were plated on glass slides and cultured in melanocyte growth media overnight without any stimulation. Cells were fixed at room temperature for 15 minutes using 3.5% para-formaldehyde solution. Cells were washed briefly with PBS and then permeabilized with either 0.5% Triton X-100 for 10 minutes or −20°C cooled methanol for 15 minutes. Slides were blocked with 16% normal goat serum (Santa Cruz Biotech., Santa Cruz, CA) for 1 hour and then incubated with rabbit polyclonal IgG p65 antibody (Santa Cruz Biotech., Santa Cruz, CA) at 1:100 dilution. Subsequent to overnight incubation at 4°C, the slides were washed with PBS and incubated with goat anti-rabbit IgG-Alexa 594 (Molecular Probes Eugene, OR) at 1:200 dilution at room temperature for 1 hour. Stained slides were washed with PBS and viewed under a fluorescence microscope (Eclipse TS100, Nikon, Tokyo, Japan).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Gene Transcription Promoter Analysis</title>
        <p>Transcription factor binding <italic>cis</italic> element sequence profiling in the selected gene promoter was performed by using a web tool known as TESS (Transcription Element Search System, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/tess">http://www.cbil.upenn.edu/tess</ext-link>). Each genes promoter sequences from the transcription start site up to 2.0 kb of upstream of the genes were subjected to the TESS and screened by TRANSFAC database to identify matched consensus sequences of known DNA binding transcription factors.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000594.s001">
        <label>Dataset S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A combined and normalized raw dataset from the 12 sets of microarray data (two sets of primary human melanocytes and ten melanoma cell lines).</p>
          <p>(18.02 MB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0000594.s001.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000594.s002">
        <label>Dataset S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>A subset of the 12 microarray data (10 from melanoma cell lines and 2 from human primary melanocytes) was obtained by filtering to require each Affymetrix probe to have at least one observation in the expression intensity resulting in a present call from all 12 samples.</p>
          <p>(4.50 MB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0000594.s002.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000594.s003">
        <label>Table S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Results of SAM analysis between Group 1 and Group 2 melanoma cells. The results include the SAM Output showing the list of Affymetrix probesets and associated gene symbols that are differentially expressed in the two groups of melanoma cell lines.</p>
          <p>(3.20 MB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0000594.s003.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0000594.s004">
        <label>Table S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Results of SAM analysis between HPMs and Group 2 melanoma cells. The results include the SAM Output showing the list of Affymetrix probesets and associated gene symbols that are downregulated in Group 2 melanoma cell lines.</p>
          <p>(3.05 MB DOC)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0000594.s004.doc">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank M. Herlyn (Wistar Institute) for generously providing melanoma cell lines used in these studies. We thank G. Parmigiani (Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine) for his statistical support and members of the Alani Lab for their careful review of this manuscript and helpful comments.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>Funding: </bold>National Institutes of Health Grants CA107017 (RA) and CA113779 (BR), American Skin Association (R.A., A.D.), Flight Attendant Medical Research Institute (R.A.), The Murren Family Foundation (R.A.), and The Henry and Elaine Kaufman Foundation (R.A.).</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Jemal1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Cancer statistics, 2006.</article-title>
<source>CA Cancer J Clin</source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>106</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16514137</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Quackenbush1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quackenbush</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Microarray analysis and tumor classification.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>354</volume>
<fpage>2463</fpage>
<lpage>2472</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760446</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Bittner1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bittner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seftor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Molecular classification of cutaneous malignant melanoma by gene expression profiling.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>406</volume>
<fpage>536</fpage>
<lpage>540</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10952317</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Smith1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weeraratna</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>SAGE identification and fluorescence imaging analysis of genes and transcripts in melanomas and precursor lesions.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>104</fpage>
<lpage>109</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14726694</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Weeraratna1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weeraratna</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Duray</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Generation and analysis of melanoma SAGE libraries: SAGE advice on the melanoma transcriptome.</article-title>
<source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2264</fpage>
<lpage>2274</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14755246</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Rumpler1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rumpler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Identification of differentially expressed genes in models of melanoma progression by cDNA array analysis: SPARC, MIF and a novel cathepsin protease characterize aggressive phenotypes.</article-title>
<source>Exp Dermatol</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>761</fpage>
<lpage>771</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14714555</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Hoek1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimm</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Expression profiling reveals novel pathways in the transformation of melanocytes to melanomas.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>5270</fpage>
<lpage>5282</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289333</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Gyorffy1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gyorffy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A Web-based data warehouse on gene expression in human malignant melanoma.</article-title>
<source>J Invest Dermatol</source>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>394</fpage>
<lpage>399</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16946712</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Haqq1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haqq</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nosrati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudilovsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crothers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khodabakhsh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The gene expression signatures of melanoma progression.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>6092</fpage>
<lpage>6097</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15833814</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Winnepenninckx1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winnepenninckx</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Gene expression profiling of primary cutaneous melanoma and clinical outcome.</article-title>
<source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>472</fpage>
<lpage>482</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595783</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Jaeger1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koczan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiesen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Gene expression signatures for tumor progression, tumor subtype, and tumor thickness in laser-microdissected melanoma tissues.</article-title>
<source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>806</fpage>
<lpage>815</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17289871</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-HsuMY1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu M-Y</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The Wistar (WM) melanoma cell lines;</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Palsson</surname></name><name><surname>Masters</surname></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Kluwer Acad. Publ.</publisher-name>
<fpage>259</fpage>
<lpage>274</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Satyamoorthy1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satyamoorthy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>DeJesus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Linnenbach</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraj</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornreich</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Melanoma cell lines from different stages of progression and their biological and molecular analyses.</article-title>
<source>Melanoma Res</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue>
<fpage>S35</fpage>
<lpage>42</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9578415</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Meier1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesbit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Belle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Human melanoma progression in skin reconstructs : biological significance of bFGF.</article-title>
<source>Am J Pathol</source>
<volume>156</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10623667</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Mancianti1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancianti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Tumor progression in melanoma: the biology of epidermal melanocyte in vitro;</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>CJea</surname><given-names>Conti</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>
<fpage>369</fpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Herlyn1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koprowski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Experimental model of human melanoma metastasis.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Treat Res</source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1673854</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-ValyiNagy1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valyi-Nagy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodeck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancianti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>The human melanocyte system as a model for studies on tumor progression.</article-title>
<source>Basic Life Sci</source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1814292</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Herlyn2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaban</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennicelli</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlyn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>Characteristics of cultured human melanocytes isolated from different stages of tumor progression.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>5670</fpage>
<lpage>5676</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4053039</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Tusher1">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tusher</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Significance analysis of microarrays applied to the ionizing radiation response.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>5116</fpage>
<lpage>5121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11309499</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Obuse1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obuse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyomitsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goshima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A conserved Mis12 centromere complex is linked to heterochromatic HP1 and outer kinetochore protein Zwint-1.</article-title>
<source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>1135</fpage>
<lpage>1141</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502821</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-TrinkleMulcahy1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trinkle-Mulcahy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorhead</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Repo-Man recruits PP1 gamma to chromatin and is essential for cell viability.</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<volume>172</volume>
<fpage>679</fpage>
<lpage>692</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16492807</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Hirano1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Condensins, chromosome condensation protein complexes containing XCAP-C, XCAP-E and a Xenopus homolog of the Drosophila Barren protein.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>521</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9160743</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Kimura1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuvier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Chromosome condensation by a human condensin complex in Xenopus egg extracts.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>5417</fpage>
<lpage>5420</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136719</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Ono1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Losada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuwald</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Differential contributions of condensin I and condensin II to mitotic chromosome architecture in vertebrate cells.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>115</volume>
<fpage>109</fpage>
<lpage>121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532007</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-SimonsEvelyn1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons-Evelyn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey-Dell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Toretsky</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>PBK/TOPK is a novel mitotic kinase which is upregulated in Burkitt's lymphoma and other highly proliferative malignant cells.</article-title>
<source>Blood Cells Mol Dis</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>825</fpage>
<lpage>829</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11783945</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Raemaekers1">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raemaekers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribbeck</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaudouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Annaert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Camp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>NuSAP, a novel microtubule-associated protein involved in mitotic spindle organization.</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biol</source>
<volume>162</volume>
<fpage>1017</fpage>
<lpage>1029</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963707</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Li1">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambrosini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Plescia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tognin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Control of apoptosis and mitotic spindle checkpoint by survivin.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>396</volume>
<fpage>580</fpage>
<lpage>584</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9859993</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Vega1">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Waisfisz</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagihara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Roberts syndrome is caused by mutations in ESCO2, a human homolog of yeast ECO1 that is essential for the establishment of sister chromatid cohesion.</article-title>
<source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>468</fpage>
<lpage>470</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15821733</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Sun1">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Raabe</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Growth retardation and premature aging phenotypes in mice with disruption of the SNF2-like gene, PASG.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>1035</fpage>
<lpage>1046</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105378</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Beullens1">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beullens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vancauwenbergh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrice</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Derua</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceulemans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Substrate specificity and activity regulation of protein kinase MELK.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>280</volume>
<fpage>40003</fpage>
<lpage>40011</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16216881</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Zindy1">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zindy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherr</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Expression of INK4 inhibitors of cyclin D-dependent kinases during mouse brain development.</article-title>
<source>Cell Growth Differ</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1139</fpage>
<lpage>1150</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9372237</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Ueno1">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>PSF1 is essential for early embryogenesis in mice.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>10528</fpage>
<lpage>10532</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16287864</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Kong1">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takakura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of mouse PSF1-binding protein, SLD5.</article-title>
<source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>339</volume>
<fpage>1204</fpage>
<lpage>1207</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16338220</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Banerjee1">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer-Kuckuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Capiaux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Budak-Alpdogan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorlick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Novel aspects of resistance to drugs targeted to dihydrofolate reductase and thymidylate synthase.</article-title>
<source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1587</volume>
<fpage>164</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12084458</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Nishimura1">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunisada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Regulation of E- and P-cadherin expression correlated with melanocyte migration and diversification.</article-title>
<source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>215</volume>
<fpage>155</fpage>
<lpage>166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545227</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Pla1">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morali</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Grille</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Cadherins in neural crest cell development and transformation.</article-title>
<source>J Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>189</volume>
<fpage>121</fpage>
<lpage>132</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11598897</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Mackenzie1">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Activation of the receptor tyrosine kinase Kit is required for the proliferation of melanoblasts in the mouse embryo.</article-title>
<source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>192</volume>
<fpage>99</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9405100</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Hornyak1">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hornyak</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziff</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Transcription factors in melanocyte development: distinct roles for Pax-3 and Mitf.</article-title>
<source>Mech Dev</source>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<lpage>59</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11231058</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Vachtenheim1">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vachtenheim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Expression of genes for microphthalmia isoforms, Pax3 and MSG1, in human melanomas.</article-title>
<source>Cell Mol Biol (Noisy-le-grand)</source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>1075</fpage>
<lpage>1082</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644012</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Spritz1">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spritz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Molecular genetics of oculocutaneous albinism.</article-title>
<source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
<volume>3 Spec No</volume>
<fpage>1469</fpage>
<lpage>1475</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7849740</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Du1">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Widlund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Horstmann</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>MLANA/MART1 and SILV/PMEL17/GP100 are transcriptionally regulated by MITF in melanocytes and melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Am J Pathol</source>
<volume>163</volume>
<fpage>333</fpage>
<lpage>343</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12819038</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Suzuki1">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cone</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordlund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Malek</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Binding of melanotropic hormones to the melanocortin receptor MC1R on human melanocytes stimulates proliferation and melanogenesis.</article-title>
<source>Endocrinology</source>
<volume>137</volume>
<fpage>1627</fpage>
<lpage>1633</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612494</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Bonitsis1">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonitsis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Batistatou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karantima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Charalabopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The role of cadherin/catenin complex in malignant melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Exp Oncol</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>187</fpage>
<lpage>193</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17080010</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Wesley1">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wesley</surname><given-names>UV</given-names></name><name><surname>McGroarty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Homoyouni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Dipeptidyl peptidase inhibits malignant phenotype of prostate cancer cells by blocking basic fibroblast growth factor signaling pathway.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>1325</fpage>
<lpage>1334</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735018</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Coopman1">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coopman</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The Syk tyrosine kinase: A new negative regulator in tumor growth and progression.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Lett</source>
<volume>241</volume>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>173</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16442709</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Ueda1">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>NF-kappaB activation in melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Pigment Cell Res</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>112</fpage>
<lpage>124</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16524427</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Hsu1">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Belle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Adenoviral gene transfer of beta3 integrin subunit induces conversion from radial to vertical growth phase in primary human melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Am J Pathol</source>
<volume>153</volume>
<fpage>1435</fpage>
<lpage>1442</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811334</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Clark1">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerry</surname><given-names>Dt</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>A study of tumor progression: the precursor lesions of superficial spreading and nodular melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Hum Pathol</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>1147</fpage>
<lpage>1165</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6500548</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Grossman1">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Altieri</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Drug resistance in melanoma: mechanisms, apoptosis, and new potential therapeutic targets.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11831644</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Ohoka1">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohoka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Onozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>TRB3, a novel ER stress-inducible gene, is induced via ATF4-CHOP pathway and is involved in cell death.</article-title>
<source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>1243</fpage>
<lpage>1255</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15775988</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Atkins1">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkins</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The treatment of metastatic melanoma with chemotherapy and biologics.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Oncol</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>213</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9161801</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Houghton1">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Albino</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordon-Cardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Cell surface antigens of human melanocytes and melanoma. Expression of adenosine deaminase binding protein is extinguished with melanocyte transformation.</article-title>
<source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>167</volume>
<fpage>197</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2891780</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Roesch1">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittschier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Landthaler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Loss of dipeptidyl peptidase IV immunostaining discriminates malignant melanomas from deep penetrating nevi.</article-title>
<source>Mod Pathol</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1378</fpage>
<lpage>1385</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829852</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Muthusamy1">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthusamy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Duraisamy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Curley</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Epigenetic silencing of novel tumor suppressors in malignant melanoma.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>11187</fpage>
<lpage>11193</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17145863</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Karin1">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Nuclear factor-kappaB in cancer development and progression.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>441</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>
<lpage>436</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16724054</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Cilensek1">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cilensek</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yehiely</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kular</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Deiss</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>A member of the GAGE family of tumor antigens is an anti-apoptotic gene that confers resistance to Fas/CD95/APO-1, Interferon-gamma, taxol and gamma-irradiation.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>380</fpage>
<lpage>387</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432251</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-Rofstad1">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rofstad</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Halsor</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor, interleukin 8, platelet-derived endothelial cell growth factor, and basic fibroblast growth factor promote angiogenesis and metastasis in human melanoma xenografts.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>4932</fpage>
<lpage>4938</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10987309</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0000594-deHoon1">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Hoon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Imoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Open source clustering software.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>1453</fpage>
<lpage>1454</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14871861</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>