<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:26:40Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:1635329" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:1635329</identifier><datestamp>2006-12-26</datestamp><setSpec>nar</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC1635329</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1635329</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">1635329</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17071714</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl765</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17071714</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identification of human tRNA:m<sup>5</sup>C methyltransferase catalysing intron-dependent m<sup>5</sup>C formation in the first position of the anticodon of the <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brzezicha</surname>
            <given-names>Bartosz</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
            <given-names>Marcin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="au1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Makałowska</surname>
            <given-names>Izabela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="au2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jarmołowski</surname>
            <given-names>Artur</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pieńkowska</surname>
            <given-names>Joanna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="au3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Szweykowska-Kulińska</surname>
            <given-names>Zofia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff>
          <institution>Department of Gene Expression, Institute of Molecular Biology and Biotechnology, Adam Mickiewicz University</institution>
          <addr-line>Międzychodzka 5, 60-371 Poznań, Poland</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au1">
          <sup>1</sup>
          <institution>Department of Biotechnology and Food Microbiology, August Cieszkowski University of Agriculture</institution>
          <addr-line>Wojska Polskiego 48, 60-627 Poznań, Poland</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au2">
          <sup>2</sup>
          <institution>Center for Computational Genomics, The Huck Institutes of the Life Sciences, The Pennsylvania State University, State College</institution>
          <addr-line>PA 16802, USA</addr-line>
        </aff>
        <aff id="au3">
          <sup>3</sup>
          <institution>Department of Cell Biology, Institute of Experimental Biology, Adam Mickiewicz University</institution>
          <addr-line>Umultowska 89, 61-614 Poznań, Poland</addr-line>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><sup>*</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +61 829 27 28; Fax: + 61 829 27 30; Email: <email>zofszwey@amu.edu.pl</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <!--For NAR: both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck-->
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>34</volume>
      <issue>20</issue>
      <fpage>6034</fpage>
      <lpage>6043</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <copyright-statement>© 2006 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="openaccess">
        <p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p>
      </license>
      <abstract>
        <p>We identified a human orthologue of tRNA:m<sup>5</sup>C methyltransferase from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, which has been previously shown to catalyse the specific modification of C<sub>34</sub> in the intron-containing yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Using transcripts of intron-less and intron-containing human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes as substrates, we have shown that m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> is introduced only in the intron-containing tRNA precursors when the substrates were incubated in the HeLa extract. m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation depends on the nucleotide sequence surrounding the wobble cytidine and on the structure of the prolongated anticodon stem. Expression of the human Trm4 (hTrm4) cDNA in yeast partially complements the lack of the endogenous Trm4p enzyme. The yeast extract prepared from the strain deprived of the endogenous TRM4 gene and transformed with hTrm4 cDNA exhibits the same activity and substrate specificity toward human pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> transcripts as the HeLa extract. The hTrm4 MTase has a much narrower specificity against the yeast substrates than its yeast orthologue: human enzyme is not able to form m<sup>5</sup>C at positions 48 and 49 of human and yeast tRNA precursors. To our knowledge, this is the first report showing intron-dependent methylation of human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and identification of human gene encoding tRNA methylase responsible for this reaction.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>Maturation of eukaryotic cytoplasmic tRNAs is a multistage process that includes the processing of 5′ and 3′ ends, intron splicing in the case of intron-containing pre-tRNAs, transport from the nucleus to the cytoplasm and numerous nucleoside modifications that take place both in the nucleus and in the cytoplasm. Three classes of intron-containing tRNA genes are present in the human nuclear genome: <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext><mml:mo>Ψ</mml:mo><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Tyr</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (8 genes with intron lengths ranging from 16 to 21 bp), <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>5</mml:mtext></mml:msup><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (5 genes with intron lengths ranging from 22 to 25 bp) and <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>UCU</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Arg</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (1 gene containing a 15 bp intron) (Genomic tRNA database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lowelab.ucsc.edu/GtRNAdb"/>). In all cases, introns are located one nucleotide downstream from the anticodon, which is a typical feature of nuclear intron-containing tRNA genes.</p>
      <p>In the case of <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext><mml:mo>Ψ</mml:mo><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Tyr</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes, it has been shown that the introduction of pseudouridine in the middle position of the anticodon (Ψ<sub>35</sub>) is intron dependent in yeast, plants, animals and humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>). Moreover, it has been demonstrated that the introduction of Ψ<sub>35</sub> strictly depends on the nucleotide sequence surrounding the U<sub>35</sub> to be modified and depends rather on the length of the intron than on its structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>). Transfer <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes contain introns in yeast and vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). However, in plants, there are no introns in these genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>). The first position of the yeast anticodon sequence—cytosine—in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is methylated to 5-methylcytosine (m<sup>5</sup>C)<sub>34</sub>. In yeast, this methylation is intron dependent and its introduction strictly depends on the intron structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>).</p>
      <p>The first functional evidence of the importance of Ψ<sub>35</sub> in tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> came from the Abelson laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). The construction of mutant yeast tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> and tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> genes without introns resulted in the production of mature tRNA molecules without appropriate modified bases. When the suppressor activity of a tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> product derived from intron-containing tRNA (SUP 6 coding for ochre suppressor tRNA) with the ochre suppressor tRNA transcribed from the gene without intron was compared, it turned out that tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> derived from the mutated gene without intron exhibited a strong reduction in the suppressor activity. In an analogous experiment, a mutant, intron-less yeast tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene encoding amber suppressor tRNA (SUP 53) also gave a product with a weak suppressor activity when compared with the intron-containing amber tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> suppressor gene product. In both cases, the decreased suppressor activity correlated with the absence of Ψ<sub>35</sub> and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub>, respectively. Similarly, Ψ<sub>35</sub> is required in the anticodon (GΨA) of cytoplasmic tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> from <italic>Nicotiana rustica</italic> for UAG and UAA suppression in the translation of the tobacco mosaic virus (TMV) RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>). Summarizing the afore-mentioned experiments, it is clear that both Ψ<sub>35</sub> and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> are necessary to stabilize anticodon–codon pairing leading to the correct decoding of mRNA. In this paper, we show that intron in the human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is indispensable for the C5-methylation of cytosine in the first position of the anticodon. We also show that the modification of C<sub>34</sub> depends on the nucleotide sequence surrounding the position to be modified and on the structure of intron-containing prolongated anticodon stem.</p>
      <p>Enzymes that introduce Ψ<sub>35</sub> and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in the intron-containing pre-tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> and pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, respectively, have been identified in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>). However, our knowledge about the corresponding enzymes in multicellular eukaryotes remains obscure. The first human m<sup>5</sup>C methylase Dnmt2 has been reported very recently and is responsible for the modification of C<sub>38</sub> in tRNA<sup>Asp</sup> in mice, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. This MTase was found to be localized in cytoplasm and acts at the level of a mature tRNA molecule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>). Here, we present the characterization of a human gene encoding a methyltransferase (MTase) that is involved in the formation of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The product of the gene, hTrm4, acts at the level of the intron-containing tRNA precursor and is localized in the nucleoplasm and nucleolus. During the preparation of this paper, it was found that this MTase is a novel downstream Myc-target which mediates Myc-induced cell proliferation and growth. Therefore, the characterization of hTrm4 substrate specificity can be essential since this MTase is a potential target for cancer therapies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Enzymes and reagents</title>
        <p>The restriction enzymes, T4 DNA polymerase and T4 DNA ligase were from Roche, Fermentas and Promega. RNase T<sub>2</sub> and SAM (<italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-<sc>l</sc>-methionine) were obtained from Sigma. [α-<sup>32</sup>P]NTPs were from Amersham/Pharmacia Biotech. <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase, T7 RNA polymerase, Calf Intestine Alkaline Phosphatase (CIAP), dNTPs and NTPs were from Fermentas. P1 nuclease was obtained from Roche. Marathon-Ready cDNA library was obtained from the Clontech, TAKARA BIO company. DNA sequencing was carried out using fmol DNA Cycle Sequencing System from Promega and CEQ DTCS Quick Start Kit from Beckman Coulter. Oligonucleotides for amplification and mutagenesis were synthesized by oligo.pl. Cellulose plates for TLC were purchased from Merck. Kits for plasmid isolation and for DNA isolation from agarose were obtained from A&amp;A Biotechnology. The QuickChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit was from Stratagene. All other reagents were from Amersham/Pharmacia Biotech, Fermentas and Sigma.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Bacterial, yeast and HeLa strains and plasmids</title>
        <p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> TG1, CJ236 and JM109 were used as hosts for the propagation of pUC19 plasmid and M13mp19 phage derivatives, respectively. The recombinant plasmids used in this study were: pHLIVS2 carrying the human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gene and pYLIVS carrying the yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gene, respectively. Both tRNA genes were inserted under T7 RNA polymerase promoter and contained the MvaI restriction site to linearize plasmids and terminate the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription. Human HeLa cells were used for nuclear cell-free extract preparations. <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> haploid strain BY4742 (wild type) and its deletion derivative with the open reading frame YBL024w (corresponding to the TRM4 gene) replaced by kanMX4, a kanamycin resistance gene mediating G418 resistance, were obtained from EUROSCARF. Yeast strains were used for transformation and tRNA:m<sup>5</sup>C methyltransferase activity assays. pYES2 (Invitrogen) vector was utilized for protein expression in yeast.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Construction of tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene mutants</title>
        <p>The recombinant plasmid pHLIVS2 harbouring human tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene that contains the 22 bp intron was mutagenized using the Kunkel method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>) or QuickChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit according to the manufacturer's instructions. The introduced mutations were confirmed by DNA sequencing. The mini-helix consisting of the prolongated anticodon stem of <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gene was synthesized according to the Milligan's method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>) with modifications described in ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>) using two DNA oligonucleotides: one (58 nt long) including the 17 nt long sequence of T7 RNA polymerase promoter followed by the coding sequence of prolongated anticodon stem containing 22 nt long intron and the other with the sequence complementary to the T7 RNA promoter.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>T7 RNA transcription of <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gene and its mutants</title>
        <p>Plasmids carrying the yeast tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene and the human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gene or its mutants (with the exception of mutant pHLIVS2 C<sub>35</sub>) were linearized by digestion with MvaI before transcription. Plasmid pHLIVS2 C<sub>35</sub> contains a mutation that introduces a new MvaI restriction site into the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> mutant gene and was linearized with BamHI. <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription was carried out in Fermentas T7 RNA polymerase buffer, 500 μM each of CTP, GTP, UTP, 12 μM ATP, 50 μCi of [α-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP, 1 μg of linearized plasmid and 20 U of T7 RNA polymerase in total volume of 20 μl at 37°C for 1.5 h. Radiolabelled ATP was added in the case of the wild-type gene and all the mutant transcription reactions with the exception of pHLIVS2 C<sub>35</sub>, pHLIVS2 G<sub>35</sub> and pHLIVS2 C<sub>35</sub> where [α-<sup>32</sup>P]CTP, [α-<sup>32</sup>P]GTP or [α-<sup>32</sup>P]UTP were added, respectively. For the visualization of m<sup>5</sup>C localized at position 48/49 in tRNAs plasmids carrying the yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GUC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Asp</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AGA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ser</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes were transcribed using [α-<sup>32</sup>P]GTP. Transcripts were purified on 10% denaturating polyacrylamide gels, identified by autoradiography, excised from the gels and eluted with 0.3 M sodium acetate (pH 5.2), 0.5 M EDTA, 0.1% (w/w) SDS. After phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation, the RNA was resuspended in water. The average amount of the recovered labelled tRNA transcripts varied between 1 and 2 pmol per reaction. The transcription of mini-helix was performed as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>In vitro</italic> 5-methylcytosine formation assays in HeLa and yeast extract</title>
        <p>A nuclear cell-free extract was prepared from HeLa cells according to Dignam <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>). Yeast cells used for protein extract preparations were grown as follows: single yeast colony was picked from YPD agar plate and inoculated into 15 ml SD-U synthetic medium containing 0.67% nitrogen base, 2% glucose, amino acids and no uracil. The culture was grown overnight at 30°C with shaking. The OD<sub>600</sub> of the overnight culture was determined and the amount of culture necessary to obtain an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.4 in 50 ml of induction medium was calculated and taken for further experiments. Cells were pelleted at 1500 <italic>g</italic> for 5 min at 4°C, resuspended in 2 ml of induction medium (SD-U medium containing 2% galactose instead of 2% glucose), inoculated into 50 ml of the induction medium and grown overnight at 30°C with shaking. Yeast S-10 extract was prepared by the following procedure: 5 ml of cell suspension were centrifuged, collected, washed twice in 500 μl of distilled water and resuspended in twice their volume of lysis buffer [50 mM Tris–HCl, pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 0.1 mM EDTA, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10% glycerol, 2% Protease Inhibitor Cocktail for yeast (Sigma)]. One volume of glass beads was added. The mixture was frozen in liquid nitrogen and thawed at room temperature. The suspension was vigorously vortexed 5–7 times for 1 min with 5 min pause between each vortexing when the suspension was kept on ice. The resulting homogenate was centrifuged at 12 000 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min to remove cell debris. The resulting supernatant was aliquoted, quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept frozen at −70°C for later use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Quantification of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
        <p>About 3000 c.p.m. of <sup>32</sup>P-labelled RNAs, obtained as described above, were digested with 0.5 U of RNase T<sub>2</sub> for 5 h at 37°C in 10 μl of 5 mM ammonium acetate, pH 4.6. The labelled nucleotides were identified by a two-dimensional (2D) chromatographic analysis on cellulose TLC plates as described by Grosjean <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>). The efficiency of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation was measured by cutting out the labelled spots from the TLC plates and counting the radioactivity by the liquid scintillation technique. Otherwise, radioactivity in the spots was evaluated by ImageQuant 5.1 software after exposure to a PhosphorImager screen (Typhoon, Molecular Dynamics, USA) and scanning. Taking into account the amount of label in each of the nucleotide spots (AMP, UMP, GMP, CMP and/or m<sup>5</sup>CMP) and knowing the relative number of labelled nucleotides per RNA substrate, the number of moles of m<sup>5</sup>C per mole of pre-tRNA was easily calculated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cloning of yeast and human TRM4 cDNA</title>
        <p>Yeast Trm4 protein was used as a query in searching for sequences of homologous proteins in the human expressed sequence tags (ESTs) database using tBLASTn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>). For the localization of the gene in human genome and the determination of the chromosomal localization, BLAT software was used.</p>
        <p>hTrm4 cDNA was amplified from the human cDNA library using following primers: 5′-ATGGTGGTCAACCATGATGCCTCCAGCATAC-3′ and 5′-TCACCGGGGTGGATGGACCCCCGCCGG-3′. PCR was performed in two step ‘touchdown’ manner, with the following conditions: 30 s at 96°C, followed by 25 cycles of 5 s at 96°C and 4 min at 72°C. The PCR product of expected size was excised from the agarose gel and eluted. The cDNA product was re-amplified with primers harbouring sequences for XbaI and EcoRI restriction enzymes and cloned into the pUC-19 vector (giving hTRM4/pUC construct) and sequenced. Yeast genomic DNA was isolated using QIAGEN Genomic DNA kit according to manufacturer's instructions. Primers used for the amplification of yeast Trm4p cDNA were: 5′-AAA<bold>GGATCC</bold><italic>ACC<underline>ATG</underline>G</italic>CTAGAAGAAAGAATTTCAA-3′ (Kozak translation initiation sequence is marked in italics, start codon is underlined and the BamHI restriction site is in boldface) and 5′-AAA<bold>GAATTC</bold><underline>TCA</underline>ATTAGCAGCGCTAGGAG-3′ (the stop codon is underlined and EcoRI restriction sequence is in boldface). After amplification, a product of expected size was excised and eluted from the EtBr/agarose gel. Yeast and human TRM4 cDNA were cloned into pYES2 yeast expression vector (constructs TRM4/pYES2 and hTRM4/pYES2, respectively). After each cloning procedure, the correctness of insert-vector ligation was assessed by sequencing or restriction digestion.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Yeast cells transformation</title>
        <p>Yeast strain ΔYBL024w was made competent by lithium acetate/PEG 3350 treatment according to procedures described in the User Manual for pYES2 vector system (Invitrogen). Competent cells were then transformed by purified pYES2 plasmid or its derivative constructs carrying the sequence corresponding to the yeast TRM4 gene or human TRM4 cDNA, respectively. Transformed yeast cells were grown on a synthetic selective medium as required to maintain plasmids.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Preparation of low-molecular weight RNA from <italic>S.cerevisiae</italic></title>
        <p>Yeast RNA was extracted as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>). RNA products were purified on 8% denaturing polyacrylamide gel. After EtBr staining, bands corresponding to approximate tRNA size (80–110 nt) were eluted from the gel, ethanol precipitated, carefully washed with ethanol/water (70:30), resuspended in DEPC-treated water and kept frozen at −70°C for later use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>HPLC chromatography</title>
        <p>Low-molecular RNA (10–20 μg) was digested by P1 nuclease according to the manufacturer's manual (Roche). Nucleotides were dephosphorylated by CIAP phosphatase. The volume of the reaction was reduced to 10 μl by vacuum centrifugation. HPLC separation was performed on the reversed phase SUPELCOSIL™ LC-318 HPLC Column, 25 cm × 4.6 mm (Supelco) attached to ÄKTAexplorer 10S (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech). Chromatographic solvents were as follows: (A) 100 mM ammonium acetate and (B) 100% acetonitrile. HPLC conditions were: 4°C, 1 ml/min flow rate and absorbance measuring at λ = 277 nm. The gradient method consisted of 2 CV (Column Volume) solvent A, a gradient &gt;10 CV to 6% solvent B, held 2 CV solvent B and column re-equilibration. To determine retention times of standards, 10 μl mix of six ribonucleosides (pseudouridine, cytidine, uridine, 5-methylcytidine, guanosine and adenosine), each at the concentration of 1 mM, was separated.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is formed only in intron-containing precursors</title>
        <p>Green <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>) isolated five <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes that slightly differ in intron sequence. Inspection of the Genomic tRNA database revealed that there are five human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes containing introns with nucleotide sequences identical or nearly identical to those published by Green <italic>et al</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>) and Karwowska and Szweykowska-Kulinska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>).</p>
        <p>The only human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> sequence with the identified modified nucleosides is known from HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). Its nucleotide sequence corresponds exactly to the nucleotide sequence of the mature domain of the isolated human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes from HeLa cells with the exception of one additional G nucleotide in the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene extra arm coding sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). However, Harada <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>) was not able to identify the nature of modified cytidine in position 34. Storbel and Abelson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>) have shown that this modification in the yeast tRNA corresponds to m<sup>5</sup>C and that its formation is intron-dependent. Using PCR, we have previously isolated two intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M27"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes from human blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>). One of the isolated human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes was studied further. It contains 22 bp intron. The putative structure of pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> derived from this gene is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1a</xref>. The structure of the prolongated anticodon stem containing intron is proposed according to the model of yeast intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M29"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). The putative model of the extended anticodon stem shows that (i) the second (A<sub>35</sub>) and third (A<sub>36</sub>) anticodon nucleotides and G<sub>37</sub> can be base-paired with the complementary nucleotides of the intron; (ii) the majority of the intron can be arranged in two hairpin-stem and loop structures (arm I and arm II, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>); (iii) the 5′ splice site junction is located at the boundary of the stem–loop of the first arm in the prolongated anticodon stem; (iv) the 3′ splice site junction is located in the unpaired region. To test whether C<sub>34</sub> in human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is modified to m<sup>5</sup>C and whether its introduction depends on the presence of 22 nt long intron, the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene with the intron and a mutant of the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> gene without (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1b</xref>) were transcribed <italic>in vitro</italic> using T7 RNA polymerase and [5′-α<sup>32</sup>P]ATP. Radiolabelled transcripts were then incubated in the presence of nuclear, cell-free HeLa extract which contained the activity necessary for m<sup>5</sup>C synthesis. The modified transcripts were gel-purified and analysed for their m<sup>5</sup>C content after a complete hydrolysis of RNA with RNase T<sub>2</sub>. Since RNase T<sub>2</sub> produces nucleoside-3′-monophosphates, the labelled phosphate is exclusively derived from the nearest adenosine. This ensures that only five cytidine nucleotides will be labelled in the tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> without intron and six in the intron-containing precursor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>), since they have 3′-flanking adenosines. The only m<sup>5</sup>C that was found in the sequenced human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M31"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was C<sub>48</sub>, but this nucleoside is accompanied at the 3′ side by guanosine and thus C<sub>48</sub> is not labelled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). Nucleotides were resolved in a thin-layer two-dimensional chromatographic system that separates modified nucleotides from their unmodified counterparts. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> shows the autoradiograms of T<sub>2</sub> hydrolysates derived from intron-less and intron-containing pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>. Only pre-tRNA containing intron gives rise to 3′-m<sup>5</sup>CMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a and b</xref>). It shows that the only cytosine that can be methylated in the intron-containing pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> is C<sub>34</sub>. Thus, the first cytosine of the anticodon of human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M32"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is methylated in intron-dependent manner.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>The structure of a prolongated anticodon stem and nucleotide sequence that surrounds the position to be modified are crucial for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M33"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
        <p>To learn more about the sequence and structure specificity of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> methylation in tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> precursor, a number of mutants were generated where wild-type nucleotides occupying positions 32, 33, 35, 36 and 37 were exchanged for other nucleotides. Moreover, two mutants were constructed with partially deleted intron sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1c and d</xref>) and four mutants in which either the base-pairing in the prolongated anticodon stem was disrupted or base pairs were reversed. All mutant pre-tRNAs listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> were examined for their capacity to be substrates for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in HeLa cell-free nuclear extract.</p>
        <p>A mini-helix consisting of prolongated anticodon stem was not methylated at the C<sub>34</sub> position. The removal of the intron arm I or II resulted in the complete abolishment of C<sub>34</sub> methylation. Thus, m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation depends on the structure of the intron-containing prolongated anticodon stem. The exchange of C<sub>32</sub> to A or U had no major effect on the efficiency of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation (85% of the wild-type efficiency). However, the exchange of C<sub>32</sub> to G resulted in the inhibition of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> methylation. The transversion of U<sub>33</sub> to A did not significantly influence the formation of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub>. However, the transversion of U<sub>33</sub> to G and transition to C strongly reduced the level of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. All mutations in positions 35, 36 and 37 resulted in m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub>-deficient pre-tRNAs<sup>Leu</sup>. From these experiments, a consensus sequence for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> methylation in pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was established: C/A/U<sub>32</sub>-U/A<sub>33</sub>-C<sub>34</sub>-A<sub>35</sub>-A<sub>36</sub>-G<sub>37</sub>. Careful inspection of the prolongated anticodon stem secondary structure reveals that A<sub>35</sub>, A<sub>36</sub> and G<sub>37</sub> can base pair with intron nucleotides U<sub>i11</sub>U<sub>i10</sub> and C<sub>i9</sub>, respectively. To learn more about the sequence and structure dependence of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> methylation within the prolongated anticodon stem, additional mutations were introduced in which potential base pairs were reversed or base-pairing was disrupted. The reversion of base pair A<sub>35</sub>–U<sub>i11</sub> to U<sub>35</sub>–A<sub>i11</sub> did not promote m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. The reversion of base pair A<sub>36</sub>–U<sub>i10</sub> to G<sub>36</sub>–C<sub>i10</sub> resulted in 85% efficiency of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation, showing that no A<sub>36</sub> <italic>per se</italic> is indispensable for modification but N<sub>36</sub>–N<sub>i10</sub> base-pairing within the moiety of the prolongated anticodon stem is crucial. However, like in the case of the base pair A<sub>35</sub>–U<sub>i11</sub>, the reversion of G<sub>37</sub>–C<sub>i9</sub> to C<sub>37</sub>–G<sub>i9</sub> resulted in a complete abolishment of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. In this case, not the base-pairing but the identity of guanosine in position 37 (and adenosine in the position 35), and possibly their pairing with C<sub>i9</sub> and U<sub>i10</sub>, respectively, is crucial for the modification to occur. Disruption of all three base pairs A<sub>36</sub>–U<sub>i11</sub>, A<sub>37</sub>–U<sub>i10</sub>, and G<sub>37</sub>–C<sub>i9</sub> by the introduction of noncomplementary nucleotides within the intron sequence, i.e. A<sub>i11</sub>, A<sub>i10</sub> and G<sub>i9</sub>, leads to the inhibition of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. Thus, both the sequence and structure of the prolongated anticodon stem are crucial for the introduction of methyl group on C<sub>34</sub> of pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>NSUN2</italic> encodes yeast TRM4 orthologue</title>
        <p>The BLAST similarity search of human UniGene database at NCBI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>) using the yeast Trm4p (enzyme that introduces m<sup>5</sup>C into yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in an intron-dependent manner) as a query enabled us to identify EST sequences of a putative human orthologue. The putative protein sequence encoded by the contig sequence, constructed from identified ESTs using the CAP3 program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>), shows 35% identity to the yeast sequence. A comparison of the contig sequence with the human genome revealed only one gene with an identical putative coding sequence (NCBI accession no. NM_017755), located on the human chromosome 5, with precise position 5p15.31. This gene is called <italic>NSUN</italic> according to HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee and contains 19 exons, and encompasses ∼34 000 nt. Based on the results of the analyses reported in this article, we propose to rename it as <italic>hTRM4</italic>. Bioinformatic analysis of amino acid sequence of putative m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> MTases and the alignment of regions forming the active site in yeast and human Trm4 enzymes were already published by Bujnicki <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). Sequence analysis using the programs predictNLS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>), SignalP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>) and PSORT II (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://psort.hgc.jp"/>) revealed 60–70% probability of nuclear localization of hTrm4. However, we did not find any classical nuclear localization signals (NLS) within the protein sequence.</p>
        <p>Using the cDNA library from HeLa cells, we isolated a 2304 bp cDNA encoding hTrm4 protein. Its nucleotide sequence was confirmed to be identical to the virtually constructed cDNA contig from EST libraries and to exon sequences of the identified human gene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Human Trm4 catalyses the formation of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> in human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M35"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
        <p>Since our efforts to overexpress the hTrm4 protein in different prokaryotic expression systems were unsuccessful (data not shown), we decided to investigate hTrm4 activity in yeast strain BY4742 with the deleted endogenous TRM4 gene. The deletion of this gene has no phenotypic effect on cell growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>). Δtrm4 yeast strain BY4742 was transformed with hTrm4 cDNA that was cloned into yeast pYES2 plasmid. The same yeast strain was also transformed with pYES2 plasmid containing yeast Trm4p cDNA. Low-molecular weight RNA was isolated from both yeast lines, digested with P1 nuclease and digestion products were dephosphorylated. Nucleosides were separated on HPLC chromatography using RPC18 column. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref> presents the chromatographic elution profiles of nucleosides from yeast lines: wild type, Δtrm4, Δtrm4 transformed with plasmid carrying hTrm4 cDNA and Δtrm4 transformed with plasmid carrying yeast Trm4p cDNA. In the elution profile of nucleosides obtained from low-molecular weight RNA from Δtrm4 + yeast Trm4p, the level of m<sup>5</sup>C was restored to that achieved for m<sup>5</sup>C for wild-type yeast strain. In the Δtrm4 yeast strain, m<sup>5</sup>C nucleosides are undetectable. In the case of Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA, we observed only a low level of m<sup>5</sup>C. However, this small peak appeared repeatedly in all consecutive experiments. The low level of m<sup>5</sup>C methylation may be due to several (mutually not exclusive) reasons: (i) hTrm4 protein recognizes a small group of substrates that are normally methylated by the yeast Trm4p enzyme, (ii) the expressed hTrm4 enzyme has only residual activity, e.g. because of non-native folding or post-translational modification or (iii) hTrm4 localization in yeast is not fully correct. To test whether hTrm4 exhibits activity toward human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> containing intron, we prepared total protein extracts from Δtrm4, Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA, Δtrm4 + Trm4p cDNA and wild-type yeast lines, and conducted activity tests similar to those in the HeLa cell-free nuclear extract. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref> shows the m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> analyses of human intron-less and intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M37"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNAs</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the wild-type yeast strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4a</xref>), Δtrm4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4b</xref>), Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4c</xref>) and Δtrm4 + Trm4p cDNA yeast lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4d</xref>). In the case of the wild-type yeast strain, human pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> containing intron is a substrate for endogenous MTase while pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> without intron is not. When the protein extract from Δtrm4 yeast line was used, there was no m<sup>5</sup>C in intron-containing and intron-less pre-tRNAs. However, when we used the protein extract prepared from Δtrm4 + Trm4p cDNA, human intron-containing pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> was methylated at C<sub>34</sub>, demonstrating that in the wild-type yeast strain TRM4 MTase was responsible for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. In the case of Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA, human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was methylated when its precursor contained an intron. Finally, yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M39"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> containing intron is methylated at C<sub>34</sub> in the S-10 yeast extract prepared from the Δtrm4 + hTrm4 strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4e</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref> shows the kinetics of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in human intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the extract prepared from the Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA yeast line. The efficiency of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in yeast pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> in the same yeast line is about the same (∼45%, data not shown). Several mutants of the human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M41"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were tested in yeast extracts containing the human Trm4 enzyme. In all cases, we obtained similar results as in the case of HeLa cell-free nuclear extract (data not shown). These biochemical experiments definitely prove that the human gene identified by us encodes a functional counterpart of the yeast Trm4p enzyme.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Human Trm4 has narrower substrate specificity than its yeast orthologue</title>
        <p>Apart from methylating C<sub>34</sub> in yeast pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> containing intron, yeast Trm4p is required for C<sub>48</sub> and C<sub>49</sub> methylation in different yeast tRNAs. Using total protein extracts from yeast lines described in the preceding chapter, we examined hTrm4 ability to methylate cytosines at positions 48/49. hTrm4 is not able to introduce a methyl group at position C<sub>48</sub> of human tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, both at the level of intron-containing and intron-less precursors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6a</xref>), while the yeast Trm4p methylates human intron-less precursor and does not recognize intron-containing substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6b</xref>). Additionally, we analysed m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>48</sub> and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>49</sub> formation in yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AGA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ser</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M43"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GUC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Asp</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively. We show that neither of them is methylated at C<sub>48</sub> or C<sub>49</sub> by hTrm4 and both are substrates for yeast Trm4p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6c and d</xref>). Control experiments carried out in the Δtrm4 strain show no detection of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>48/49</sub> formation in any tRNA tested (data not shown). Thus, human Trm4 substrate specificity is narrower than in the case of its yeast orthologue.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>In this article, we describe the identification, cloning and enzyme activity of the corresponding gene product encoding human Trm4 enzyme. This is the first report showing intron-dependent methylation of human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M44"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and identification of human gene encoding tRNA methylase responsible for this reaction. The <italic>hTRM4</italic> gene was identified on the basis of its amino acid sequence similarity to a known Trm4p MTase from yeast. Our studies provide experimental validation of the phylogenetic analysis of RNA:m<sup>5</sup>C MTases by Bujnicki <italic>et al</italic>. who predicted the product of the <italic>NSUN2</italic> gene as the closest human homologue of yeast Trm4p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>). <italic>hTRM4</italic> is a single-copy gene, located on the human chromosome 5, with the precise position 5p15.31. The hTrm4 protein is a member of an evolutionarily conserved family, which includes genuine and putative RNA:m<sup>5</sup>C MTases from all three domains of life, such as the human nucleolar proliferation-associated antigen p120 (NOL1) and its homologues. Wu <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>) reported that the yeast Trm4p was found to be localized in the nucleus, including the nucleolus, and was concentrated at the nuclear periphery. Our experiments have shown that its human homologue hTrm4 is always localized in the nucleoplasm and in nucleoli of HeLa cells, and in several cases we also observed a concentration of hTrm4 at the nuclear periphery (data not shown). These data have been recently confirmed by Frye and Watt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>).</p>
      <p>The presence of an intron is required for the m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M45"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as demonstrated in this paper by the maturation of intron-less and intron-containing tRNA precursor in HeLa cell-free nuclear extract. In earlier studies, Harada <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>) showed that this position in the mature human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M46"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is occupied by a hypermodified derivative. The authors suggest that this is a 2′-O-methylated and further hypermodified cytidine derivative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). Very similar results were obtained by Randerath <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>) when leucine tRNAs were isolated and sequenced from rat tumour, Morris hepatoma 5123D cells. Our studies show that the first stage of C<sub>34</sub> modification process in HeLa cells is the m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. However, the final chemical structure of this modification remains to be characterized. In addition to intron-dependent m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation, we have shown that the activity of hTrm4 strictly depends on a specific sequence surrounding the cytosine to be modified and on the intron structure. Similar results were obtained studying the yeast Trm4p enzyme by Storbel and Abelson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>). However, our experiments have shown that minisubstrate composed of the anticodon stem–loop extended by the intron was not methylated at C<sub>34</sub>. In contrast, Motorin and Grosjean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>) presented data that analogous minihelix of yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M47"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was an efficient substrate for tRNA:m<sup>5</sup>C-methyltransferase. These results imply that there are differences in the ability of enzyme–substrate recognition between the human and fungi Trm4 enzymes. The nucleotide sequence that surrounds C<sub>34</sub> in human tRNA precursor is more restrictive for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation than in the case of yeast. The substitution of adenosine from the middle position of the anticodon to uridine did not promote m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in human tRNA precursor while in the case of yeast amber leucine-inserting pre-tRNA containing intron (anticodon CUA), m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> was formed. Additionally, our experiments have shown that the reversion of base pair A<sub>35</sub>–U<sub>i11</sub> to U<sub>35</sub>–A<sub>i11</sub> also resulted in the m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> deficient <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M48"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Moreover, human MTase responsible for the introduction of methyl group at the anticodon wooble cytosine (hTrm4) requires a consensus nucleotide sequence C/A/U<sub>32</sub>-U/A<sub>33</sub>-C<sub>34</sub>-A<sub>35</sub>-A<sub>36</sub>-G<sub>37</sub> as a prerequisite for m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation. Thus, all nucleotides from the anticodon loop that are present upstream from the intron sequence are essential for pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> modification. These results again strengthen the conclusion about the differences in the ability of enzyme–substrate recognition between human and yeast Trm4 enzymes.</p>
      <p>Motorin and Grosjean showed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>) that the yeast Trm4p enzyme catalysed m<sup>5</sup>C formation at four distinct sites in different tRNAs: 34, 40, 48 and 49. m<sup>5</sup>C was found at positions 34 and 40 only in two yeast tRNAs [<inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M49"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CUA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Sup53) and <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Phe</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively], whereas most elongator tRNAs bore either m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>48</sub> or m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>49</sub>, but never both in the same tRNA molecule. Motorin and Grosjean concluded that yeast Trm4p MTase is responsible for cytosine conversion in all yeast tRNAs and pre-tRNAs, while two other identified MTases encoded in <italic>S.cerevisiae</italic> genome are required for proper rRNA m<sup>5</sup>C modification. We transformed yeast strain BY4742 deprived of the <italic>TRM4</italic> gene with yeast Trm4p cDNA and human Trm4 cDNA. In the Δtrm4 + Trm4p cDNA strain, the level of m<sup>5</sup>C in low-molecular RNA molecules was restored to that of the wild-type yeast strain (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). However, in the Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA strain, the level of m<sup>5</sup>C was hardly detectable. It clearly shows that human enzyme is not able to recognize the majority of yeast tRNA substrates. Since our experiments show that yeast and human Trm4 MTases both recognize mammalian <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M51"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> containing intron, the conclusion can be drawn that the yeast enzyme has much broader substrate specificity than the human Trm4. We confirm this statement showing that hTrm4 is not able to introduce m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>48</sub> at the level of intron-containing and intron-less human pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> precursor. Moreover, we show that it does not methylate different yeast tRNA precursors at positions 48 and 49. In the light of these observations, it is interesting to note that Bujnicki <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>) identified two additional human putative orthologues of yeast Trm4p, which have probably originated from duplications and subsequent functional specializations of the original <italic>TRM</italic>4 gene in the animal lineage. One or both of these so-far uncharacterized genes may be responsible for some of the methylations carried out by the yeast Trm4p, but not exhibited by its human counterpart. This speculation can explain a very low level of m<sup>5</sup>C in the Δtrm4 + hTrm4 strain. Summarizing our results concerning the hTrm4 enzyme, it can be concluded that the enzyme acts on intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> precursors, it is more sensitive to the nucleotide sequence that surrounds the position to be modified than its yeast homologue Trm4p and it is equally sensitive to the anticodon prolongated, intron-containing structure. Moreover, its sensitivity to substrate specificity is more constrained than in the case of yeast homologue—Trm4p.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was supported by Badania Statutowe grant of the Faculty of Biology at Adam Mickiewicz University and by the Polish Committee for Scientific Research project no. 6 P04A 02721. We would like to thank Dr Urszula Karwowska for her technical support in <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M53"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mutant genes construction and for carrying out activity tests in HeLa cell extracts, and Dr Janusz Bujnicki for carefully reading the manuscript. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by Badania Statutowe of the Department of Gene Expression and Biology Faculty of Adam Mickiewicz University, Poznań.</p>
      <p><italic>Conflict of interest statement.</italic> None declared.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="b1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>P.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abelson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The yeast tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> gene intron is essential for correct modification of its tRNA product</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>302</volume>
          <fpage>681</fpage>
          <lpage>687</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6339954</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pienkowska</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wrzesinski</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A cell-free yellow lupin extract containing activities of pseudouridine 35 and 55 synthases</article-title>
          <source>Acta Biochim. Polon.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>745</fpage>
          <lpage>754</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9918501</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van Tol</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beier</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>All human tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> genes contain introns as a prerequisite for pseudouridine biosynthesis in the anticodon</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1951</fpage>
          <lpage>1966</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3357766</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Szweykowska-Kulińska</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beier</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence and structure requirements for the biosynthesis of pseudouridine (Ψ<sub>35</sub>) in plant pre-tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup></article-title>
          <source>EMBO J.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>1907</fpage>
          <lpage>1912</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1582418</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Storbel</surname>
              <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abelson</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of intron mutations on processing and function of <italic>Saccharomyces cervisiae SUP53</italic> tRNA <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title>
          <source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>2663</fpage>
          <lpage>2673</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3537724</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karwowska</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New intron-containing human tRNALeu genes</article-title>
          <source>Acta Bichom. Polon.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>791</fpage>
          <lpage>794</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fiedorow</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intergenic sequences of clustered tRNA genes: new type of genetic marker for phylogenetic studies, with application to the taxonomy of liverworts</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1257</fpage>
          <lpage>1261</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9869432</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zerfass</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beier</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pseudouridine in the anticodon GΨA of plant cytoplasmic tRNA(Tyr) is required for UAG and UAA suppression in the TMV-specific context</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>5911</fpage>
          <lpage>5918</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1461724</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Behm-Ansmant</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urban</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>Y-T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Motorin</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Branlant</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> U2 snRNA: pseudouridine-synthase Pus7p is a novel multisite-multisubstrate RNA:Ψ-synthase also acting on tRNAs</article-title>
          <source>RNA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>1371</fpage>
          <lpage>1382</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561887</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Motorin</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grosjean</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multisite-specific tRNA:m5C-methyltransferase (Trm4) in yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: identification of the gene and substrate specificity of the enzyme</article-title>
          <source>RNA</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>1105</fpage>
          <lpage>1118</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10445884</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goll</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirpekar</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maggert</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yoder</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsieh</surname>
              <given-names>C.-L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Golic</surname>
              <given-names>K.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobsen</surname>
              <given-names>S.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bestor</surname>
              <given-names>T.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methylation of tRNA<sup>Asp</sup> by the DNA methyltransferase homolog Dnmt2</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>311</volume>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>398</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424344</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frye</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watt</surname>
              <given-names>F.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The RNA methyltransferase Misu (Nsun2) mediates Myc-induced proliferation and is upregulated in tumors</article-title>
          <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>971</fpage>
          <lpage>981</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713953</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kunkel</surname>
              <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roberts</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zakour</surname>
              <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rapid and efficient site-specific mutagenesis without phenotypic effect</article-title>
          <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>382</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3323813</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Milligan</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uhlenbeck</surname>
              <given-names>O.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synthesis of small RNAs using T7 RNA polymerase</article-title>
          <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2482430</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Szweykowska-Kulinska</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krajewski</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wypijewski</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> pre-tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> affecting pseudouridylation of U<sub>35</sub></article-title>
          <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>1264</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7578262</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dignam</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lebowitz</surname>
              <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roeder</surname>
              <given-names>R.G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accurate transcription initiation by RNA polymerase II in a soluble extract from isolated mammalian nuclei</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>1475</fpage>
          <lpage>1489</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6828386</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grosjean</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Droogmans</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giege</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uhlenbeck</surname>
              <given-names>O.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Guanosine modifications in runoff transcripts of synthetic transfer RNA-Phe genes microinjected into <italic>Xenopus oocytes</italic></article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>1050</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2207154</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altschul</surname>
              <given-names>S. F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gish</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myers</surname>
              <given-names>E.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lipman</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>
          <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>215</volume>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmitt</surname>
              <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trumpower</surname>
              <given-names>B.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A rapid and simple method for preparation of RNA from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>3091</fpage>
          <lpage>3092</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2190191</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>C.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sohel</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vold</surname>
              <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The discovery of new intron-containing human tRNA genes using the polymerase chain reaction</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>265</volume>
          <fpage>12139</fpage>
          <lpage>12142</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2373682</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b21">
        <label>21</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harada</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsubara</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stable tRNA precursors in HeLa cells</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>9263</fpage>
          <lpage>9269</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6514577</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b22">
        <label>22</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wheeler</surname>
              <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barrett</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benson</surname>
              <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bryant</surname>
              <given-names>S.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Canese</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chetvernin</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Church</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DiCuccio</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edgar</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Federhen</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>Database issue</issue>
          <fpage>D173</fpage>
          <lpage>D180</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381840</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b23">
        <label>23</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madan</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CAP3: a DNA sequence assembly program</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>868</fpage>
          <lpage>877</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508846</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b24">
        <label>24</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bujnicki</surname>
              <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feder</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayres</surname>
              <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Redman</surname>
              <given-names>K.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence-structure-function studies of tRNA:m<sup>5</sup>C methyltransferase Trm4p and its relationship to DNA:m<sup>5</sup>C and RNA:m<sup>5</sup>U methyltransferases</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>2453</fpage>
          <lpage>2463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121902</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b25">
        <label>25</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cokol</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nair</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rost</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Finding nuclear localization signals</article-title>
          <source>EMBO Rep.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11258480</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b26">
        <label>26</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bendtsen</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nielsen</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>von Heijne</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brunak</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improved prediction of signal peptides: SignalP 3.0</article-title>
          <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>340</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>795</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15223320</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b27">
        <label>27</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brockenbrough</surname>
              <given-names>J.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paddy</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aris</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>NCL1, a novel gene for non-essential nuclear protein in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>Gene</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>220</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9767141</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b28">
        <label>28</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Randerath</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>R.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>H.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Randerath</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation and sequence analysis of two major leucine transfer ribonucleic acids (anticodon Mm-A-A) from a rat tumor, Morris hepatoma 5123D</article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>3476</fpage>
          <lpage>3483</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6773543</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="display-objects">
      <title>Figures and Tables</title>
      <fig id="fig1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Cloverleaf structure of <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M54"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> precursor containing intron (<bold>a</bold>), mature tRNA (<bold>b</bold>) and two mutants with partially deleted introns (derived from plasmids pHLIVS2 ΔI1, pHLIVS2 ΔI2) (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold>). Anticodon sequence is underlined, arrows point to splice sites.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> content in intron-less (<bold>a</bold>) and intron-containing (<bold>b</bold>) human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M55"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by two-dimensional thin layer chromatography. Pre-tRNAs were incubated in the cell-free nuclear HeLa extract. tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> precursors were synthesized and treated as described in Materials and Methods.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Detection of m<sup>5</sup>C in bulk low-molecular weight RNA extracted from yeast wild-type strain BY4742 (<bold>b</bold>), BY4742 ΔTRM4 (<bold>c</bold>), BY4742 transformed with pYES2 containing yeast Trm4p cDNA (<bold>d</bold>) and BY4742 ΔTRM4 transformed with pYES2 containing hTrm4 cDNA (<bold>e</bold>). Separation of a test nucleoside mixture (Ψ, U, C, m<sup>5</sup>C, G and A) is presented in (<bold>a</bold>). The total RNA fraction was completely hydrolysed by nuclease P1 and the resulting nucleotides dephosphorylated by CIAP. Analysis of nucleosides was performed as described in Materials and Methods.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f3"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> content in human <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> without intron and containing intron by 2-D thin layer chromatography. Pre-tRNAs were incubated in yeast S-10 extract derived from wild-type strain (<bold>a</bold>), BY4742 ΔTRM4 (<bold>b</bold>), BY4742 ΔTRM4 transformed with pYES2-containing hTrm4 cDNA (<bold>c</bold>) and BY4742 ΔTRM4 transformed with pYES2-containing yeast Trm4p cDNA (<bold>d</bold>). (<bold>e</bold>) Incubation of yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M57"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> containing intron in S-10 extract prepared from BY4742 ΔTRM4 transformed with pYES2-containing hTrm4 cDNA. tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> precursors were synthesized and treated as described in Materials and Methods.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f4"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Kinetics of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation in human intron-containing <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>pre-tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CAA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Leu</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <sup>32</sup>P-labelled pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> transcripts were incubated with S-10 yeast extract prepared from BY4742 Δtrm4 + hTrm4 cDNA at 30°C for 10, 20, 40 and 90 min and analyzed for the relative amount of m<sup>5</sup>C residues at position 34. The measurements were taken as described in Materials and Methods.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f5"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Analysis of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>48</sub> (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>) and m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>49</sub> (<bold>d</bold>) content in human and yeast tRNAs using hTrm4 and yeast Trm4p enzymes by 2D TLC. Pre-tRNAs were labelled using [α-<sup>32</sup>P] GTP during T7 RNA polymerase transcription, gel purified and incubated in S-10 extract. (a) BY4742 Δtrm4 + hTrm4 yeast strain and human pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, (b) BY4742 Δtrm4 + yeast Trm4p and human pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup>, (c) BY4742 Δtrm4 + hTrm4 (left) and BY4742 Δtrm4 + Trm4p (right) and yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M59"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AGA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ser</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and (d) BY4742 Δtrm4 + hTrm4 (left), BY4742 Δtrm4 + Trm4p (right) and yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GUC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Asp</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Yeast <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M61"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GUC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Asp</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tRNA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AGA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ser</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> genes do not contain introns.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="gkl765f6"/>
      </fig>
      <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Efficiency of C<sub>34</sub> to m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> conversion in HeLa extract</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutant name</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation site</th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative amount of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> (%)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mini-helix</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> anticodon stem-containing intron</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (undetectable)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 Δ I</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intron deleted</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 Δ I 1</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intron arm I deleted</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 ΔI 2</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intron arm II deleted</td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 A<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>32</sub> → A<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>32</sub> → G<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 U<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>32</sub> → U<sub>32</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 A<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<sub>33</sub> → A<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 C<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<sub>33</sub> → C<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U<sub>33</sub> → G<sub>33</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 C<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>35</sub> → C<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>35</sub> → G<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 U<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>35</sub> → U<sub>35</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 C<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>36</sub> → C<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>36</sub> → G<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 U<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>36</sub> → U<sub>36</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 A<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>37</sub> → A<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 C<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>37</sub> → C<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 U<sub>35</sub>A<sub>11i</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>35</sub> → U<sub>35</sub>, U<sub>11i</sub> → A<sub>11i</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 U<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>37</sub> → U<sub>37</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>36</sub>C<sub>i10</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>36</sub> → G<sub>36</sub>, U<sub>i10</sub> → C<sub>i10</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 C<sub>37</sub>G<sub>i9</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G<sub>37</sub> → C<sub>37</sub>, C<sub>i9</sub> → G<sub>i9</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pHLIVS2 G<sub>i9</sub>A<sub>i10</sub>A<sub>i11</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>i9</sub> → G<sub>i9</sub>, U<sub>i10</sub> → A<sub>i10</sub>, U<sub>i11</sub> → A<sub>i11</sub></td>
              <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p><sup>32</sup>P-labelled pre-tRNAs<sup>Leu</sup> were incubated in cell-free nuclear extract for 20 min at 30°C. The intron-containing pre-tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> and its mutants were analysed for the presence of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> after T<sub>2</sub> digestion by thin layer chromatography as described in Materials and Methods. The efficiency of m<sup>5</sup>C<sub>34</sub> formation was calculated as described in Materials and Methods.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>