<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:31:39Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2290908" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2290908</identifier><datestamp>2008-05-01</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">J. Cell Biol.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2290908</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2290908</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2290908</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253844</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">94075409</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253844</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>440-kD ankyrinB: structure of the major developmentally regulated domain and selective localization in unmyelinated axons</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>1993</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>123</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1463</fpage>
      <lpage>1473</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>440-kD ankyrinB is an alternatively spliced variant of 220-kD ankyrinB, with a predicted 220-kD sequence inserted between the membrane/spectrin binding domains and COOH-terminal domain (Kunimoto, M., E. Otto, and V. Bennett. 1991. J. Cell Biol. 236:1372-1379). This paper presents the sequence of 2085 amino acids comprising the alternatively spliced portion of 440-kD ankyrinB, and provides evidence that much of the inserted sequence has the configuration of an extended random coil. Notable features of the inserted sequence include a hydrophilicity profile that contains few hydrophobic regions, and 220 predicted sites for phosphorylation by protein kinases (casein kinase 2, protein kinase C, and proline-directed protein kinase). Secondary structure and folding of the inserted amino acid residues were deduced from properties of recombinant polypeptides. Frictional ratios of 1.9-2.4 were calculated from Stokes radii and sedimentation coefficients, for polypeptides comprising 70% of the inserted sequence, indicating a highly asymmetric shape. Circular dichroism spectra of these polypeptides indicate a nonglobular structure with negligible alpha- helix or beta sheet folding. These results suggest a ball-and-chain model for 440-kD ankyrinB with a membrane-associated globular head domain and an extended filamentous tail domain encoded by the inserted sequence. Immunofluorescence and immunoblot studies of developing neonatal rat optic nerve indicate that 440-kD ankyrinB is selectively targeted to premyelinated axons, and that 440-kD ankyrinB disappears from these axons coincident with myelination. Hypomyelinated nerve tracts of the myelin-deficient Shiverer mice exhibit elevated levels of 440-kD ankyrinB. 440-kD ankyrinB thus is a specific component of unmyelinated axons and expression of 440-kD ankyrinB may be downregulated as a consequence of myelination.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>