<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:33:44Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2654296" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2654296</identifier><datestamp>2009-07-26</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jcb</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2654296</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2654296</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2654296</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171758</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171758</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200805147</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200805147</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Articles</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Kank attenuates actin remodeling by preventing interaction between
IRSp53 and Rac1</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chandra Roy</surname>
            <given-names>Badal</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kakinuma</surname>
            <given-names>Naoto</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Kiyama</surname>
            <given-names>Ryoiti</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>
          <institution>Neuroscience Research Institute, National Institute of Advanced
Industrial Science and Technology, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8566,
Japan</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence to Ryoiti Kiyama: <email>kiyama.r@aist.go.jp</email></corresp>
        <fn>
          <p>B.C. Roy and N. Kakinuma contributed equally to this paper.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>184</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>253</fpage>
      <lpage>267</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2009 Roy et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an
Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No
Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date
(see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml">http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml</ext-link>). After six months it is
available under a Creative Commons License
(Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported
license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In this study, insulin receptor substrate (IRS) p53 is identified as a binding
partner for Kank, a kidney ankyrin repeat–containing protein that
functions to suppress cell proliferation and regulate the actin cytoskeleton.
Kank specifically inhibits the binding of IRSp53 with active Rac1
(Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>) but not Cdc42 (cdc42<sup>G12V</sup>) and thus inhibits the
IRSp53-dependent development of lamellipodia without affecting the formation of
filopodia. Knockdown (KD) of Kank by RNA interference results in increased
lamellipodial development, whereas KD of both Kank and IRSp53 has little effect.
Moreover, insulin-induced membrane ruffling is inhibited by overexpression of
Kank. Kank also suppresses integrin-dependent cell spreading and IRSp53-induced
neurite outgrowth. Our results demonstrate that Kank negatively regulates the
formation of lamellipodia by inhibiting the interaction between Rac1 and
IRSp53.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The Rho family of small GTPases acts as molecular switches for a variety of
extracellular signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Hall, 1998</xref>). These
signals are transduced through a rapid reorganization of the actin cytoskeleton that
changes the cell shape, leading to cell adhesion and locomotion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">Ridley et al., 1992</xref>). Rho GTPases are also
implicated in many other cellular events and functions such as cell polarity, gene
transcription, cell cycle progression in the G1 phase, microtubule dynamics,
vesicular transport, and enzymatic processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Kozma et al., 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Van Aelst and
D'Souza-Schorey, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aspenström, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Etienne-Manneville and Hall, 2002</xref>). The Rho family proteins such as Rac1
and cdc42 along with proteins like Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein (WASP), neural
WASP, and Scar/WAVE participate in cell migration, neurite extension, and budding in
yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Innocenti et al., 2004</xref>). These
proteins can bind to the globular actin and Arp2/3 complex through their catalytic
domain, which results in filament branching at the membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Takenawa and Miki, 2001</xref>). The regulatory actions of WASP and
neural WASP proteins involve their binding to active cdc42 at their GTPase-binding
domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Higgs and Pollard, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Takenawa and Miki, 2001</xref>). WAVE1 was found to
be inactive in a complex with Nap1, Abi2, PIR121, and HSP300, and a GTP-loaded
active Rac1 dissociated from this complex, relieving active WAVE1-HSP300 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Eden et al., 2002</xref>). In contrast, WAVE2 was
found to bind to active Rac1 indirectly through insulin receptor substrate (IRS) p53
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and Takenawa, 2002</xref>), a
well-characterized adapter protein that connects actin remodeling proteins with the
Rho family of small GTPases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Funato et al.,
2004</xref>). IRSp53 contains several domains: a Rac1-binding domain in the N
terminus, a half cdc42/Rac1 interactive binding (CRIB) motif, a proline-rich domain,
and an Src homology 3 (SH3) domain. It also binds to cdc42 via the CRIB motif and
stimulates the formation of filopodia through Mena (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Krugmann et al., 2001</xref>). IRSp53 is involved in neuronal morphogenesis
through a variety of proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Soltau et al.,
2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Choi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hori et
al., 2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>During a comprehensive analysis of loss of heterozygosity in renal cell carcinoma
patients, Kank, a kidney ankyrin repeat–containing protein, was identified
as a growth suppressor in HEK293 cells and a disruptor of β-actin
distribution in G-402 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Sarkar et al.,
2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Rodley et al., 2003</xref>). The
protein contains a coiled-coil domain in the N-terminal region and an ankyrin repeat
domain in the C-terminal region, both of which are likely to be involved in
protein–protein interactions and thus may play a major role in cellular
events. Interestingly, an orthologue of Kank in <italic>Caenorhabditis
elegans</italic>, VAB-19, was reported to act in epidermal morphogenesis and to play
a significant role in the regulation of the actin cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Ding et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this study, we report that Kank disrupts the function of active Rac1 through
IRSp53. The binding between IRSp53 and Kank inhibits the association of active Rac1
with IRSp53 rather than the association of active cdc42 with IRSp53. Kank inhibits
the formation of lamellipodia and membrane ruffles induced by active Rac1 in NIH3T3
cells. In addition, the depletion of Kank induced lamellipodial membrane protrusions
in NIH3T3 cells. Furthermore, Kank inhibits IRSp53-induced cell spreading and
neurite outgrowth in N1E115 cells.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank interacts with IRSp53 in vivo</title>
        <p>To identify proteins binding to Kank, we screened a human placental cDNA library
using Kank (amino acids 77–977) as bait with the yeast two-hybrid
system. Among &gt;200 clones isolated, two encoded IRSp53, both lacking 49
amino acids from the N terminus. The specificity of interaction was confirmed by
the growth of the yeast clones on plates lacking Leu/Trp/His and by
β-galactosidase activity in the X-gal filter assay (unpublished data).
To verify the result of the screening, reciprocal coimmunoprecipitation
experiments were performed using antibodies against Kank and IRSp53 with
mammalian cell lysates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>).
Immunoprecipitation of Kank resulted in the coprecipitation of IRSp53 as
detected by Western blotting using the anti-IRSp53 antibody, whereas the result
of the control experiment using a preimmune serum was negative. However,
immunoprecipitation of IRSp53 resulted in coprecipitation of Kank as detected
with the anti-Kank antibody, confirming binding in vivo between Kank and IRSp53.
Immunocytochemical characterization of Kank in VMRC-RCW cells, a renal cell
carcinoma cell line, also showed the colocalization of endogenous Kank and
IRSp53 at the cell periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 B</xref>,
arrowheads). To further authenticate our finding, we coimmunostained Kank with
WAVE2, which is known to be localized to areas of ruffling, in VMRC-RCW cells.
Kank and WAVE2 were colocalized at the cell periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 C</xref>, arrowheads). Furthermore, Kank and IRSp53 were
both present in the membrane fraction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1
D</xref>). In the spreading cells, IRSp53 was detected at the tips of both the
lamellipodium and the filopodium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Nakagawa et
al., 2003</xref>) where WAVE2 is also localized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>). Thus, we concluded that Kank is
localized at the leading edge in the VMRC-RCW cells.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank interacts and is partially colocalized with IRSp53 in
vivo.</bold> (A) Coimmunoprecipitation of Kank and IRSp53 in VMRC-RCW
cells. Approximately 600 µg of total protein lysate (shown on
the right) was used for immunoprecipitation (IP) with a preimmune serum
or with a polyclonal antibody against Kank or IRSp53. The proteins in
the immunoprecipitates were detected by Western blotting (WB;
arrowheads). (B) Immunostaining of Kank and IRSp53 in VMRC-RCW cells.
Confocal laser microscopic images were obtained for Kank (green) and
IRSp53 (red) using anti-Kank (monoclonal) and anti-IRSp53 (polyclonal)
antibodies, respectively, and their colocalization at the cell periphery
(arrowheads) is shown in yellow. (C) Immunostaining of Kank and WAVE2 in
VMRC-RCW cells. Confocal laser microscopic images were obtained for Kank
(green) and WAVE2 (red) using anti-Kank (polyclonal) or anti-WAVE2 (goat
polyclonal) antibodies, respectively, and their colocalization at the
cell periphery (arrowheads) is shown in a merged image (yellow). (D)
Fractionation of HeLa cells. The proteins in the membrane and cytosolic
fractions were separated, and those indicated were detected by Western
blotting. EGF receptor is a marker for the membrane, and
β-actin and β-tubulin are markers for the cytosol.
Bars, 10 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig1"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To determine the binding domains of Kank and IRSp53, various mutants were
constructed for IRSp53 (in GFP-tagged forms; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 A</xref>) and Kank (in Flag-tagged forms; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 C</xref>).2 HEK293T cells were transfected with the
indicated constructs along with the wild-type Flag-Kank, and immunoprecipitation
was performed using an anti-Flag antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.
2 B</xref>). Positive GFP signals were observed for the wild-type GFP-IRSp53
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 A</xref>, construct a) and
GFP-IRSp53(N) (N-terminal part containing the IMD/RCB domain and half CRIB
domain; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 A</xref>, construct c). In
contrast, a mutant of IRSp53 having a deletion at the coiled-coil domain (amino
acids 75–153; GFP-IRSp53<sup>Δcoil</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 A</xref>, construct b), a mutant containing
the C-terminal part, including the SH3 domain (amino acids 362–521;
construct d), and the GFP-vector (control; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig.
2 A</xref>, construct v) did not show any signal for GFP in the
immunoprecipitates, indicating that Kank binds to IRSp53 at its coiled-coil
domain. The lanes for lysates showed the expression of the individual
constructs. Similarly, Flag-tagged Kank and its mutants were expressed in
HEK293T cells along with GFP-IRSp53(N) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2
A</xref>, construct c) and were immunoprecipitated with polyclonal anti-GFP
antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 D</xref>). Western blotting
using an anti-Flag antibody showed strong signals for Flag-Kank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 C</xref>, construct e) and
Flag-Kank<sup>ΔAnk</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2
C</xref>, construct g) but no signal for Flag-Kank<sup>Δcoil</sup>
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 C</xref>, construct f). The result
also indicates that Kank binds to IRSp53 at the coiled-coil domain. This result
was further verified by coexpressing Flag-IRSp53(N) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 A</xref>, construct c) and a GFP-tagged coiled-coil region
of Kank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 C</xref>, construct h) in
HEK293T cells and by examining reciprocal immunoprecipitation followed by
Western blotting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 E</xref>). The
specificity of the binding was further examined by using a coiled-coil domain of
kinectin (amino acids 1,116–1,356; GFP-kinectin<sup>coil</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 F</xref>). In this study,
GFP-kinectin<sup>coil</sup> did not bind to Flag-IRSp53(N). Thus, the
results indicate that IRSp53 binds specifically to Kank through its coiled-coil
domain.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank interacts with IRSp53 through their coiled-coil
domains.</bold> (A) GFP-tagged constructs of IRSp53 used in this study
and the results of binding to Kank. (B) Interaction of IRSp53 with Kank
through its coiled-coil domain. The vectors expressing Flag-Kank and
GFP-tagged constructs (constructs a–d in A) of IRSp53 were
transfected in HEK293T cells, and the complex containing Kank was
immunoprecipitated with an anti-Flag antibody and analyzed by Western
blotting using an anti-Kank antibody (top) or an anti-GFP antibody
(indicated by dots; bottom). The GFP expression vector was used as a
control (v), and the lysate lanes show the expression of each plasmid
construct (bottom). (C) Flag-tagged and GFP-tagged Kank constructs used
in this study and the results of binding to IRSp53. (D) Interaction of
Kank with IRSp53 through its coiled-coil domain. The vectors expressing
GFP-IRSp53(N) and Flag-tagged constructs (constructs e–g in C)
of Kank were transfected in HEK293T cells, and the complex containing
IRSp53(N) was immunoprecipitated with an anti-GFP antibody and analyzed
by Western blotting using an anti-GFP antibody (the positions of
GFP-IRSp53(N) are indicated by dots; top) or an anti-Flag antibody
(bottom). The GFP expression vector was used as a control (v), and the
lysate lanes show the expression of each plasmid construct (bottom). (E)
Interaction of the coiled-coil domain of Kank with IRSp53. The lysates
from the cells expressing the GFP-tagged coiled-coil domain of Kank
(Kank<sup>coil</sup>; construct h in C) and Flag-IRSp53(N)
(construct c in A) were immunoprecipitated with preimmune serum or with
an antibody against GFP or Flag. The complex was then analyzed by
Western blotting. (F) The coiled-coil domain of IRSp53 does not interact
with the coiled-coil domain of kinectin. The lysates of the cells
expressing the GFP-tagged coiled-coil domain of kinectin (amino acids
1,116–1,356; GFP-kinectin<sup>coil</sup>) and Flag-IRSp53(N)
(construct c in A) were immunoprecipitated with control IgG or
antibodies against GFP (α-GFP) or Flag (α-Flag). The
complex was then analyzed by Western blotting as indicated. IP,
immunoprecipitation; WB, Western blot.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_GS_Fig2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank regulates the binding between active Rac1 and IRSp53</title>
        <p>As reported, active Rac1 binds to IRSp53 through its N-terminal 229 amino acid
residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and Takenawa, 2002</xref>), which contain
the Kank binding domain, so we tested whether Kank can compete against Rac1 in
vitro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>). Both
His-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and His-cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> bound to GST-IRSp53(N),
whereas GST alone did not, indicating that IRSp53 binds to Rac1 or cdc42 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>, lanes 2 and 3). When this
binding was challenged by maltose-binding protein (MBP; a control) or
MBP-Kank<sup>coil</sup>, MBP-Kank<sup>coil</sup> inhibited the binding of
GST-IRSp53(N) to His-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> in a dose-dependent manner more
efficiently than the binding of GST-IRSp53(N) to His-cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>, lanes 6–8). MBP
alone or MBP-kinectin<sup>coil</sup> (containing a control coiled-coil domain)
did not affect the binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and
B</xref>, lanes 4 and 5). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 B</xref>, we
determined the binding domain of Kank in IRSp53 (amino acids 80–150),
which also overlapped with the coiled-coil domain and was located within the
RCB. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Yamagishi et al. (2004)</xref> reported
that the N-terminal half of IRSp53 contains a filopodium-inducing domain
regulated by Rac1 and cdc42. IRSp53 contains a partial CRIB motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Burbelo et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Krugmann et al., 2001</xref>), a sequence of 16
amino acid residues (amino acids 267–283), which is located far from
the Kank binding domain (amino acids 80–150). Our result showed that
the binding of Kank to IRSp53 partially affected the binding between cdc42 and
IRSp53 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>). We then
examined the effect of knockdown (KD) of Kank using endoribonuclease-prepared
siRNA (esiRNA) on the binding between active Rac1 and IRSp53 in vivo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 C</xref>). For this, we established HEK293
cells stably expressing active Rac1 (Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>). These cells were
transfected with Kank esiRNA along with control esiRNA. After treatment with
esiRNA for 30 h, the cells were subjected to immunoprecipitation using an
anti-IRSp53 antibody that was raised against the C-terminal portion of IRSp53.
The results of Western blot analysis revealed that Kank esiRNA efficiently
decreased the level of Kank protein in the lysates but did not change the level
of IRSp53 or Rac1 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 C</xref>,
compare lanes 3 and 4 with lanes 1 or 2 in the lysate panel). The results of
immunoprecipitation showed that depletion of Kank with Kank esiRNA resulted in
less Kank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 C</xref>, compare lanes 3 and
4 with lane 2 in the top row) and, at the same time, increased the amount of
active Rac1 (Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3
C</xref>, lanes 2–4 in the third row), both of which were
immunoprecipitated with IRSp53. In other words, KD of Kank resulted in increased
binding between IRSp53 and active Rac1. Normal IgG was used as a negative
control, and GST-PAK1<sup>CRIB</sup> was used for the pull down of active Rac1
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 C</xref>, lanes 1 and 5,
respectively). From these results, Kank specifically inhibits the binding of
Rac1 to IRSp53.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank regulates the binding between IRSp53 and active Rac1.</bold>
(A) Inhibition of binding in vitro of Rac1 (for the top Western blots)
or cdc42 (for the bottom Western blots) with IRSp53 by Kank. Binding
between GST-IRSp53(N) (lanes 3–8) or control GST (lane 1) and
His-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> or His-cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> (lanes
2–8) was examined in the presence of MBP-Kank<sup>coil</sup>
(increasing concentrations; lanes 6–8).
His-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> (top) and His-cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> (bottom) used
for the experiments in lanes 2–8 are shown in the last lane
(shown as Input). (B) Quantified data of Rac1 and cdc42 bands. The
intensity of the bands of Rac1 and cdc42 in A was quantified, and the
mean ± SD of three Western blots for each band is shown. Band
intensities are measured in arbitrary units. (C) Increased binding
between IRSp53 and active Rac1 in vivo on KD of Kank. Lysates from
HEK293 cells stably expressing Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> were used for
immunoprecipitation (IP) with normal IgG as a negative control (lane 1)
or with α-IRSp53 (against the C terminus) after transfection
with control esiRNA (lane 2) or with Kank esiRNA (lanes 3 and 4,
duplicated). Pull down with GST-PAK1<sup>CRIB</sup>, a
cdc42/Rac1-binding domain of PAK1 fused to GST, was used for detecting
active Rac1 (lane 5). Western blots of individual proteins are shown.
Immunoprecipitated Rac1 and IRSp53 were quantified, and the relative
amount of coimmunoprecipitated Rac1 was calculated as the ratio of the
intensity of Rac1 to that of corresponding immunoprecipitated IRSp53 and
is shown under the image of anti-Rac1 antibody. Black lines indicate
that intervening lanes have been spliced out. WB, Western blot.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_GS_Fig3"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank inhibits Rac1-induced formation of lamellipodia through IRSp53</title>
        <p>Kank affected the interaction between IRSp53 and Rac1 and partially affected that
between IRSp53 and cdc42 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). This
led us to investigate the effect of Kank expression on the formation of
lamellipodia or filopodia mediated by Rac1 or cdc42 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>).
Initially, IRSp53 was reported to be a downstream target of Rac1 that links Rac1
activity to WAVE/Scar and the Arp2/3 complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Etienne-Manneville and Hall, 2002</xref>). However, others reported that
IRSp53 preferentially binds to active cdc42 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Krugmann et
al., 2001</xref>). Overexpression of Kank severely impaired the development
of lamellipodia and cell spreading induced by a constitutively active form of
Rac1, Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>, lane
4). Overexpression of Kank<sup>S167A</sup>, which lacks the ability to bind to
14-3-3 and has inhibitory effects on active RhoA and cell migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kakinuma et al., 2008</xref>), also impaired the
formation of lamellipodia induced by Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>, lane 5). However,
Kank<sup>Δcoil</sup>, which cannot interact with IRSp53, had no effect
on the Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-induced development of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>, lane 6). To confirm that this
effect of Kank depends on the interaction with IRSp53, we performed coexpression
of Kank with IRSp53 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>).
Coexpression of GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and Kank with IRSp53 resulted in the
disappearance of Kank's inhibitory effect on the
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>, lane 4). However, coexpression of
GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and Kank with IRSp53<sup>R11E/Q23E</sup> or
IRSp53<sup>K143E</sup>, which could not bind to Rac1 and could bind to Kank
(Fig. S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Suetsugu et al., 2006b</xref>), resulted in the
retention of the inhibitory effect on the Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent
development of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>,
lanes 5 and 6). This result implies that Kank inhibits Rac1–IRSp53
signals for the formation of lamellipodia. Moreover, to confirm that this
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent formation depends on IRSp53, we performed KD
of IRSp53 along with GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>). We first examined the KD of mouse IRSp53 (mIRS)
in NIH3T3 cells using various candidate plasmids (Fig. S2). These plasmids
contained an H1 promoter–based expression system for siRNAs in
mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Steffen et al., 2004</xref>).
Based on the results, we used #513 siRNA for the KD of mIRS.
Coexpression of GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and mIRS-KD reduced the
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>, lane 3), whereas on the coexpression of human
IRSp53 with GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and mIRS-KD, GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>
retained its function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>, lane 4).
However, the coexpression of human IRSp53<sup>R11E/Q23E</sup> or
IRSp53<sup>K143E</sup> with GFP-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> and mIRS-KD had little
effect on mIRS-KD's function in the Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent
formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>,
lanes 5 and 6). Therefore, the interaction between IRSp53 and active Rac1 is
important for lamellipodia to form. These results suggest that IRSp53 is one of
the targets of Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> in the Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent
development of lamellipodia. However, overexpression of Kank and
Kank<sup>S167A</sup> had little effect on the formation of filopodia induced by
a constitutively active form of cdc42, cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>, lanes 3 and 4), which may imply
that Kank was not involved in the cdc42<sup>G12V</sup>-mediated formation of
microspikes.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Expression of Kank inhibits lamellipodial development mediated by
active Rac1 through IRSp53.</bold> (A) Effect of the expression of
Kank on active Rac1-induced formation of lamellipodia. NIH3T3 cells were
transfected as indicated, treated as described in Materials and methods,
and stained for GFP (green) and Kank or its mutants (red). The number of
cells spreading with lamellipodia is shown on the right as a percentage
of the total number of transfected cells. *, P &lt; 0.001
compared with lane 3. (B) Overexpression of IRSp53 abolished the effect
of Kank on Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent lamellipodial formation. NIH3T3
cells were transfected as indicated, treated as described in Materials
and methods, and stained for Kank (red) and human IRSp53 or its mutants
(purple). GFP is shown in green. The number of cells spreading with
lamellipodia is shown as in A. *, P &lt; 0.001 compared with
lane 1; **, P &lt; 0.01 compared with lane 1 or 4.
IRS<sup>R,Q/E</sup>, human IRSp53 with arginine replaced by glutamic
acid at position 11 and glutamine replaced by glutamic acid at position
23; IRS<sup>K/E</sup>, human IRSp53 with lysine replaced by glutamic
acid at position 143. (C) KD of mIRS (mIRS-KD) decreased
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>-dependent lamellipodial formation. NIH3T3 cells were
transfected as indicated, treated as described in Materials and methods,
and stained for GFP (green) and mIRS (endogenous) with human IRSp53
(expressing transiently) or its mutants (red). The number of cells
spreading with lamellipodia is shown as in A. *, P &lt;
0.001 compared with lane 2; **, P &lt; 0.01 compared
with lane 2 or 4. LM, phase-contrast light microscopic image. The
results are shown as the mean ± SD for triplicate experiments
in which ∼100 cells per experiment were counted. Bars, 10
µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig4"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank has no effect on active cdc42-dependent filopodial
development.</bold> The effect of Kank expression on active
cdc42-dependent formation of filopodia was examined. NIH3T3 cells were
transfected as indicated, treated as described in Materials and methods,
and stained for GFP (green) and Kank or its mutants (red). The number of
cells spreading with filopodia is shown on the right as a percentage of
the total number of transfected cells. The results are shown as the mean
± SD for triplicate experiments in which ∼100 cells
per experiment were counted. LM, phase-contrast light microscopic image.
Bar, 10 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig5"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Depletion of Kank promotes lamellipodial development</title>
        <p>Based on the finding that Kank bound to IRSp53 and inhibited active Rac1-mediated
lamellipodial development, as well as reports of IRSp53 as a downstream target
of Rac1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and Takenawa, 2002</xref>), we examined the
effect of KD of Kank on the formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>).6 NIH3T3 cells were transfected with a Kank KD
vector that targeted mouse <italic>Kank</italic> transcripts, a control KD
vector, and an mIRS-KD as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig.
6</xref>. Because we used plasmids containing a <italic>neo-gfp</italic> fusion
gene in this assay, transfected cells can be stained with an anti-GFP antibody
against GFP or can be detected with GFP fluorophore. The cells were cultured for
48 h after transfection and fixed and stained with anti-GFP antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 B</xref>; green) or with phalloidin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 B</xref>; red). Transfection of a KD vector
(Kank-KD) effectively suppressed the expression of Kank protein by ∼80%
with respect to control-KD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 A</xref>,
lanes 2 and 3), and mIRS-KD suppressed the expression of mIRS protein by
∼100% with respect to control-KD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6
A</xref>, lanes 3 and 4). A careful observation of cell morphology revealed
that silencing of Kank resulted in the formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 B</xref>, lane 2). However, the silencing
of both Kank and IRSp53 simultaneously had little effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 B</xref>, lane 3). These findings support the idea that
Kank inhibits lamellipodia from forming by interrupting the interaction between
active Rac1 and IRSp53.</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Deletion of Kank significantly increases lamellipodial development
through IRSp53.</bold> (A) Relative expression of Kank and IRSp53 in
NIH3T3 cells expressing RNAi. The levels of expression of Kank and mIRS
relative to the amount of actin in the cell lysates were analyzed by
Western blotting and quantified. (B) Confocal laser microscopic images
of NIH3T3 cells transfected with Kank-KD and/or IRSp53-KD constructs.
pSUPER.neo+gfp constructs were transfected, and the cells were
fixed and stained with anti-GFP antibody (green) and phalloidin (red).
Transfected cells were indicated as GFP-expressing cells, which were
likely to show KD of the protein as indicated.
Kank-KD–dependent lamellipodial extension was magnified in the
bottom panel (lane 2). Quantification of lamellipodia in NIH3T3 cells
expressing Kank-KD and/or IRSp53-KD is summarized in a graph. The
results are shown as the mean ± SD for three independent
experiments in which ∼100 cells were counted in each experiment.
*, P &lt; 0.001 compared with lane 1. Bar, 10
µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig6"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank inhibits insulin-induced membrane ruffling</title>
        <p>Lamellipodia and filopodia are formed at the leading edge in migrating cells in
response to growth factors, chemokines, and extracellular matrix molecules
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Ridley et al., 2003</xref>). Insulin acts
as a growth factor, and insulin-stimulated KB cells, a strain derived from human
epidermoid carcinoma, show membrane ruffling and Rac1 activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Nishiyama et al., 1994</xref>). Overexpression
of Kank inhibited active Rac1-dependent lamellipodial development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>), and KD of Kank enhanced the
formation of lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). We
then investigated whether Kank can inhibit insulin-induced membrane ruffling
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). Whereas serum-starved
NIH3T3 cells without treatment showed little membrane ruffling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>, lane 1), insulin-stimulated cells
exhibited extensive membrane ruffling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.
7</xref>, lane 2). When Kank was overexpressed, the number of cells with
membrane ruffling was significantly decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>, lane 3). However, the effect of overexpression of Kank was
not observed when IRSp53 was coexpressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig.
7</xref>, lane 5). This result suggests that IRSp53 abrogates the inhibitory
effect of Kank on insulin-induced membrane ruffling and, thus, that Kank
inhibits insulin-induced membrane ruffling through IRSp53.</p>
        <fig id="fig7" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank inhibits insulin-induced membrane ruffling.</bold> The effect
of Kank on insulin-induced membrane ruffling in NIH3T3 cells was
examined. The cells were transfected and treated as described in
Materials and methods. The images were obtained by confocal laser
microscopy. The number of cells with membrane ruffling is shown on the
right as a percentage of the total number of transfected cells. The
results are shown as the mean ± SD for triplicate experiments
in which 100 cells per experiment were counted. *, P &lt;
0.001 compared with lane 2. Bar, 10 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig7"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank inhibits integrin-mediated cell spreading through IRSp53</title>
        <p>Integrins are major adhesion receptors in vertebrates and play major roles in
cell adhesion and in a variety of intracellular signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hynes, 2002</xref>). The Rho family of small
GTPases such as Rac1 and cdc42 are involved in integrin-mediated cell spreading
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Clark et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Price et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Katoh and Negishi, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Choi et al., 2005</xref>). As Kank interrupted the interaction between
active Rac1 and IRSp53 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>), we
hypothesized that it might inhibit integrin-mediated cell spreading. To
investigate the role of Kank downstream of integrin signaling, NIH3T3 cells were
transfected, seeded on fibronectin-coated glass substrata, fixed, and stained
with phalloidin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>).8 The cells
adhered rapidly to the substrata and completed spreading in 30 min, showing a
normal shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, lane 1). However,
the expression of the wild-type Kank radically changed cell shape and markedly
inhibited cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, lane
2). Notably, this change was not caused by apoptosis because nuclear staining of
transfected cells with DAPI did not show any sign of apoptosis (unpublished
data) and the cells were viable, as they could spread later (unpublished data).
Kank<sup>Δcoil</sup>, which cannot bind to IRSp53, did not show
any significant changes in cell shape or cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, lane 3). Kank<sup>S167A</sup>, which cannot bind
to 14-3-3, partially inhibited cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, lane 4). We obtained similar results using COS-7 and HeLa
cells (unpublished data). In contrast, a control protein with the coiled-coil
domain, kinectin<sup>coil</sup>, did not affect the spreading of NIH3T3 cells
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, lane 5). From these
results, Kank inhibits cell spreading specifically through its coiled-coil
domain.</p>
        <fig id="fig8" position="float">
          <label>Figure 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank inhibits integrin-dependent cell spreading through
IRSp53</bold>. (A) Effect of Kank expression on cell spreading. NIH3T3
cells were transfected as indicated and treated as described in
Materials and methods. The cells were then stained for GFP (green). The
number of spreading cells is shown on the right as a percentage of the
total number of transfected cells. *, P &lt; 0.001 compared
with lane 1. (B) Overexpression of IRSp53 partially abolished the effect
of Kank on the spreading of NIH3T3 cells. The cells were transfected as
indicated and treated as described in Materials and methods. The cells
were stained for GFP (green) and IRSp53 or its mutants (red). The number
of spreading cells was counted as in A. *, P &lt; 0.001
compared with lane 1; **, P &lt; 0.001 compared with
lane 1 or 2. (C) Integrin-dependent cell spreading was mediated by
IRSp53 in NIH3T3 cells. pSUPER.neo+gfp constructs were
transfected with or without IRSp53 or its mutants as indicated. The
cells were treated as described in Materials and methods and were
stained for GFP (green) and IRSp53 or its mutants (red). The number of
spreading cells was counted as in A. *, P &lt; 0.001
compared with lane 1. mIRS-KD, IRS<sup>R,Q/E</sup>, and
IRS<sup>K/E</sup> are described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig.
4 (B and C)</xref>. LM, phase-contrast light microscopic image. The
results are shown as the mean ± SD for triplicate experiments
in which ∼100 cells per experiment were counted. Bars, 10
µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig8"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To see how Kank inhibits cell spreading and whether this phenomenon depends on
IRSp53, Kank was coexpressed with IRSp53 in NIH3T3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 B</xref>). When Kank was coexpressed with wild-type
IRSp53, cell spreading was enhanced compared with that when only Kank was
expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 B</xref>, compare lane 2 with
lane 3). Integrin activates Rac1 and cdc42 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Price et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Hynes,
2002</xref>). We then examined whether the inhibitory effect of Kank on cell
spreading depends on IRSp53–Rac1 signaling. Kank was coexpressed with
IRSp53<sup>R11E/Q23E</sup> or IRSp53<sup>K143E</sup> in NIH3T3 cells when
the cells were spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 B</xref>, lanes
4 and 5). Surprisingly, the rates of spreading differed little between wild-type
IRSp53, IRSp53<sup>R11E/Q23E</sup>, and IRSp53<sup>K143E</sup> when Kank was
present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 B</xref>, lanes 3–5).
Next, we investigated whether IRSp53 was involved in the spreading of NIH3T3
cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 C</xref>). KD of mIRS resulted in
the inhibition of cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8
C</xref>, compare lane 1 with lane 3). In contrast, KD of mIRS with
overexpression of the wild type or the mutants of human IRSp53 did not affect
the spreading of NIH3T3 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 C</xref>,
lanes 4–6). Furthermore, there was almost no change in cell spreading
with or without KD of IRSp53 when Kank was overexpressed (Fig. S3, available at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>We then investigated the effect of Kank and IRSp53 expression on cell morphology
when NIH3T3 cells were spreading upon stimulation with fibronectin (Fig. S4,
available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1</ext-link>). Cell
shapes were classified according to those in the process of matrix-based cell
spreading (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Applewhite et al., 2007</xref>).
Overexpression of Kank decreased the number of cells with the filopodial
phenotype, whereas overexpression of IRSp53 increased the number of smooth-edged
cells. Notably, coexpression of Kank and IRSp53 decreased the number of cells
with the filopodial phenotype, whereas there was no increase in the number of
the cells with the smooth-edged phenotype. These results suggest that Kank
partially inhibits the spreading of NIH3T3 cells through IRSp53, although this
phenomenon was not part of the Rac1–IRSp53 signaling pathway. The
reason why IRSp53 partially recovers cell spreading inhibited by Kank might be
that Kank inhibits the formation of both filopodial microspikes and
lamellipodial sheets, whereas IRSp53 contributes only to lamellipodial sheets
when the cells are spreading.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Kank inhibits IRSp53-mediated neurite outgrowth in N1E115 cells</title>
        <p>Ectopic expression of IRSp53 in mouse neuroblastoma N1E115 cells induces neurite
outgrowth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and Takenawa, 2002</xref>), with Rac1 and
cdc42 acting as positive regulators and Rho inhibiting the process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Kozma et al., 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Luo,
2000</xref>). To assess whether Kank is also involved in IRSp53-mediated neurite
outgrowth, N1E115 cells were transfected with GFP-tagged IRSp53 to reproduce the
morphological changes described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>). Overexpression of GFP-Kank inhibited neurite
outgrowth under serum starvation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9
A</xref>). The cells transfected with GFP-IRSp53 showed vigorous neuritic
development in the presence or absence of serum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9 B</xref>, second row). There were no round or adherent neurites when
the cells were not transfected in the presence of serum. When Kank was
coexpressed with GFP-IRSp53, the cells showed a phenotype similar to that seen
with GFP alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9 B</xref>, bottom, Serum
[+]). The quantitative analysis showed that Kank significantly reduced
the extent of the IRSp53-induced outgrowth of neurites both in the presence
(from 40 to 14%) and in the absence (from 85 to 25%) of serum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9 B</xref>, graph). These findings
demonstrate that Kank is involved in the IRSp53-mediated formation of neurites.</p>
        <fig id="fig9" position="float">
          <label>Figure 9.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Kank inhibits IRSp53-mediated neurite outgrowth in N1E115
cells.</bold> (A) Suppression of neurite outgrowth by Kank in N1E115
cells. Fluorescence images were obtained for N1E115 cells expressing GFP
alone or GFP-tagged Kank in the presence (left) or absence (right) of
serum. The quantification of different phenotypes of N1E115 cells is
summarized in a graph. *, P &lt; 0.001 compared with
GFP-expressing cells with the same morphology. (B) Suppression of
IRSp53-mediated neurite outgrowth by Kank in N1E115 cells. Fluorescence
images were obtained for N1E115 cells expressing GFP alone, GFP-tagged
IRSp53 (IRSp53), or GFP-IRSp53 with coexpression of Kank (IRSp53
+ Kank). The effect of the transient expression of GFP alone
(top), GFP-IRSp53 (middle), or GFP-IRSp53 with Kank (bottom) in N1E115
cells in the presence (left) or absence (right) of serum. The
quantification of different phenotypes of N1E115 cells is summarized in
a graph. *, P &lt; 0.001; **, P &lt;
0.01; ***, P &lt; 0.05 compared with
GFP-expressing cells with the same morphology. LM, phase-contrast light
microscopic image. The results are shown as the mean ± SD for
three independent experiments in which ∼100 transfected cells
were counted. Bars, 10 µm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200805147_RGB_Fig9"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we demonstrated that Kank plays a major role in the negative
regulation of lamellipodial development in fibroblasts. The regulation is likely to
be mediated by interaction with IRSp53 in ruffled areas of the cell. This binding
seems to be constitutive because it was not affected by stimulation with a growth
factor like PDGF or EGF (unpublished data). IRSp53 is a multidomain scaffolding
protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Govind et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Krugmann et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Soltau et al., 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Funato et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Choi et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Connolly et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Hori
et al., 2005</xref>) and a downstream target of Rac1 and links WAVE2 to Rac1
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and Takenawa, 2002</xref>), which plays an
important role in the reorganization of the actin cytoskeleton.</p>
      <p>Kank contains two important domains, the coiled-coil and ankyrin repeat domains, both
of which have been described in several structural proteins as well as in proteins
involved in an array of cellular functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Sedgwick and Smerdon, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Burkhard et
al., 2001</xref>). We showed in this study that the coiled-coil domain of Kank
is necessary for binding with IRSp53 and the negative regulation of cell spreading
and lamellipodial development induced by constitutively active Rac1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Although active Rac1- or active cdc42-dependent actin polymerization has been
described for the regulation of WASP and WAVE proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Bompard and Caron, 2004</xref>) and the regulation of Rac1 activity
through three major classes of regulators, GTPase-activating proteins, guanine
nucleotide exchange factors, and GDP dissociation inhibitors, has been identified,
albeit with little understanding of the signaling pathways that modulate their
activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Burridge and Wennerberg, 2004</xref>),
Kank does not possess any of these classical regulatory functions in Rac1
activation. This raises the possibility that Kank functions via other proteins also.</p>
      <p>IRSp53 makes a complex with Eps8 and activates Rac1, which is important to cancer
cell motility and invasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Funato et al.,
2004</xref>). Active cdc42 binds to the complex of IRSp53 and Eps8 and controls its
cellular distribution, thereby contributing to the generation of actin bundles and
promoting filopodial protrusions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Disanza et al.,
2006</xref>). Eps8 was shown to form a complex with Abi-1, Sos-1, E3B1, and
PI3-K, which activate Rac1 and transduce signals from Ras to Rac1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Biesova et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Scita et al., 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Innocenti et al., 2003</xref>).
Tiam1, another Rac1 activator, also binds to IRSp53, leading to increased activation
of Rac1 and enhanced binding of IRSp53 to both active Rac1 and WAVE2. Tiam1 promotes
the localization of IRSp53 to Rac1-induced lamellipodia rather than cdc42-induced
filopodia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Connolly et al., 2005</xref>).
Similarly, Kank specifically inhibits the binding between IRSp53 and
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> rather than that between IRSp53 and cdc42<sup>G12V</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, A and B</xref>), which is consistent with the
finding that the coexpression of Kank with active Rac1 or active cdc42 in NIH3T3
cells showed marked differences: the formation of lamellipodia induced by active
Rac1 was inhibited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>), whereas
microspikes or filopodia generated by active cdc42 showed some but not great
alteration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). Because the IMD/RCB
domain of IRSp53 overlaps with the Kank binding domain, Kank might disrupt the
association of active Rac1 to IRSp53. In contrast, the cdc42-binding domain of
IRSp53 is located far from the Kank binding domain. This may be why Kank weakly
inhibits cdc42-IRSp53 association. KD of Kank by RNAi in NIH3T3 cells revealed that
depletion of Kank resulted in an increase in lamellipodia, whereas KD of both Kank
and IRSp53 resulted in normal or unaltered cell shapes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6 B</xref>). Moreover, Kank inhibited insulin-induced membrane
ruffling, and coexpression of Kank with IRSp53 abrogated this inhibitory effect
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). This suggests that Kank
inhibits the IRSp53-dependent formation of lamellipodia. However, Kank inhibited
integrin-dependent cell spreading through IRSp53, but this was not caused by Rac1
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8, B and C</xref>). Kank also inhibited
IRSp53-dependent neurite outgrowth in N1E115 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig.
9</xref>). Kank binds to the IMD/RCB domain of IRSp53, and it has been shown that
this domain binds not only to active Rac1 but also to actin and lipids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Miki et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">Yamagishi et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Millard et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Suetsugu et al.,
2006b</xref>). The IMD/RCB domain was also shown to have actin-bundling activity
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Millard et al., 2005</xref>), although this
activity may only be seen under nonphysiological conditions such as at a low ionic
strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Lee et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Mattila et al., 2007</xref>). Consistent with this,
we also found that actin was present in a complex immunoprecipitated with an
anti-IRSp53 antibody in HEK293 cells (Fig. S5, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1</ext-link>). Expression
of Kank is likely to inhibit the association of IRSp53 with actin, which implies
that Kank negatively regulates the association of IRSp53 with actin. This might be
why Kank inhibits the spreading of NIH3T3 cells and the outgrowth of neurites in
N1E115 cells through the binding of IRSp53.</p>
      <p>Kank regulates RhoA activity through its 14-3-3 binding motif inside the coiled-coil
domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kakinuma et al., 2008</xref>). Kank
inhibited Rac1–IRSp53 signaling, which is mediated by the coiled-coil
domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). However, the formation of
lamellipodia induced by active Rac1 was inhibited by both Kank and
Kank<sup>S167A</sup>, which cannot bind to 14-3-3 and was ineffective against active
RhoA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>, lanes 4 and 5). From this
finding, the effect of Kank on active Rac1-induced lamellipodial development can be
separated from the effect of the binding of 14-3-3 to Kank. In contrast,
overexpression of Kank<sup>S167A</sup> was relatively ineffective compared with the
effect of wild-type Kank on integrin-dependent cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>, compare lane 2 with lane 4). A deletion mutant,
Kank<sup>Δcoil</sup>, was not completely effective against
integrin-dependent cell spreading (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Fig. 8 A</xref>,
lane 3); Kank may affect the integrin-dependent cell spreading mediated by both
IRSp53 and 14-3-3 or more likely through the Kank coiled-coil domain.</p>
      <p>Although there are orthologues of Kank in different species, in which the coiled-coil
domain along with the ankyrin repeat domain are conserved, only VAB-19 of <italic>C.
elegans</italic> has been studied and was shown to be a component of the
epidermal attachment structure and to interact with actin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Ding et al., 2003</xref>). This further strengthens our finding that
Kank functions through the coiled-coil domain in the regulation of actin remodeling.
This function of Kank in the reorganization of the actin cytoskeleton may be
conserved in other orthologues as well. Further studies are needed to explore other
potential roles of Kank or the Kank–IRSp53 complex in response to external
stimuli, which may contribute to our understanding of the cell signaling mechanisms
in renal cell carcinoma.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Expression vectors and antibodies</title>
        <p>Cytomegalovirus-driven Flag-tagged constructs (Agilent Technologies), GFP-tagged
constructs (BD), the vector pcDNA-3.1 (Invitrogen), the
hEF1-α–driven expression vector pEF1/myc-His (Invitrogen),
and a bacterial expression vector for GST, pGEX-5x-1(GE Healthcare), were
generated by recombinant PCR. Full-length human IRSp53 cDNA was obtained by
RT-PCR. Kank mutants and human IRSp53 mutants were made by PCR-mediated
recombination. The coiled-coil domain of kinectin (kinectin<sup>coil</sup>) was
obtained by RT-PCR and used as a control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Vignal et al., 2001</xref>). All of the constructs were verified by
sequencing. Polyclonal and monoclonal antibodies against Kank were described
previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">Sarkar et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Roy et al., 2005</xref>). The polyclonal
antibody against mouse Kank recognizes a peptide spanning amino acids
861–975 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Kakinuma et al.,
2008</xref>). The polyclonal antibody against IRSp53 was a gift from M. Yamada
(National Research Institute for Child Health and Development, Tokyo, Japan;
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">Okamura-Oho et al., 1999</xref>) or was
generated in a rabbit using the C-terminal part of the protein (163 residues
long, amino acids 358–521) fused to GST as an antigen and was prepared
by affinity purification. A monoclonal antibody against autofluorescent proteins
(MP Biomedicals), a rabbit antiserum against GFP (Invitrogen), a polyclonal
antibody against GFP (Clontech Laboratories, Inc.), a monoclonal antibody
against cdc42 protein, a polyclonal antibody against EGF receptor (Santa Cruz
Biotechnology, Inc.), a monoclonal antibody against Rac1 (Transduction
Laboratories), a goat polyclonal antibody against WAVE2 (Santa Cruz
Biotechnology, Inc.), and monoclonal antibodies against Flag, GFP,
β-actin, and β-tubulin (Sigma-Aldrich) were purchased.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cell culture, immunoprecipitation, and immunoblotting</title>
        <p>HEK293 cells stably expressing Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> were constructed with the
pcDNA4/TO expression vector (Invitrogen). NIH3T3, HeLa, N1E115 (a gift from Y.
Kanaho, Tsukuba University, Ibaraki, Japan), HEK293 (a gift from M. Noguchi,
Hokkaido University, Hokkaido, Japan), and HEK293T cells were cultured in DME
supplemented with 10% FBS. VMRC-RCW cells were cultured in MEM with 10% FBS.
Transfection was performed using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) and Effectine
(QIAGEN) according to the manufacturers' instructions. After 30 h,
cells were harvested, washed with ice-cold PBS, and lysed for 15 min on ice in
buffer A (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 140 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 1% Nonidet P-40,
100 mM NaF, 200 mM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM PMSF, 10 µg/ml
leupeptin, 10 µg/ml aprotinin, and 10 µg/ml chymotrypsin).
The cell lysates were clarified by centrifugation, and the proteins were
immunoprecipitated, washed in the lysis buffer, and boiled in an SDS-PAGE
loading buffer. Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to
polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Immobilon; Millipore), and detected with
respective antibodies. Signals were enhanced with secondary antibody against AP
(Sigma-Aldrich) or HRP (GE Healthcare) and developed with nitroblue
tetrazolium/5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl phosphate (Sigma-Aldrich) or ECL (GE
Healthcare). The intensity of the bands was quantified by ImageJ software
(National Institutes of Health).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunocytochemistry</title>
        <p>The cells on coverslips were fixed with 3.7% formaldehyde-PBS for 30 min and
permeabilized with 0.25% Triton X-100–PBS for 10 min. The cells were
subsequently incubated with the primary and secondary antibodies. The secondary
antibodies used were Alexa Fluor 594–conjugated goat
anti–mouse and anti–rabbit IgG (Invitrogen), Alexa Fluor
488–conjugated goat anti–mouse and anti–rabbit IgG
(Invitrogen), RITC-conjugated donkey anti–goat IgG (Santa Cruz
Biotechnology, Inc.), and Cy5-conjugated goat anti–rabbit IgG
(Millipore). Filamentous actin (F-actin) was stained with TRITC-conjugated
phalloidin (Sigma-Aldrich). Images of cells after they were mounted were
acquired at room temperature in 80% (wt/vol) glycerol in PBS using AxioVision
3.1 software (Carl Zeiss, Inc.) and a fluorescence microscope (Axioskop 2 Plus;
Carl Zeiss, Inc.) with a Plan-NEOFLUAR 40× NA 0.75 objective (Carl
Zeiss, Inc.) and a color camera (AxioCam HRc; Carl Zeiss, Inc.). Confocal laser
microscopy was performed using a laser-scanning confocal microscope (Axiovert
200M; Carl Zeiss, Inc.) with LSM510 META software (Carl Zeiss, Inc.). Optical
thickness was set at 1.0 µm in Z height with a Plan-Apochromat
63× NA 1.4 oil immersion objective (Carl Zeiss, Inc.). All images were
prepared with Photoshop 7.0 (Adobe).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Formation of lamellipodia and filopodia</title>
        <p>NIH3T3 cells were transfected as indicated and incubated for 24 h (for
overexpression) or 48 h (for KD). The cells were then trypsinized and seeded on
10 µg/ml fibronectin-coated coverslips. After incubation overnight,
they were subjected to immunostaining as described in Immunocytochemistry. The
cells with lamellipodia were those with broad ruffles, whereas the cells with
filopodia were those with &gt;15 microspikes in phase-contrast images.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Insulin-induced membrane ruffling</title>
        <p>NIH3T3 cells were transfected as indicated. After 4 h, the cells were trypsinized
and seeded onto fibronectin-coated coverslips. When they had adhered to
coverslips completely, the cells were serum starved by culturing them in 0.5%
FBS-DME for 2 d. Then, the cells were treated with 10 µg/ml insulin
for 6 h. The cells with membrane ruffling were counted from phase-contrast
images and the images for F-actin (phalloidin) staining.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cell spreading assay</title>
        <p>Integrin stimulation was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Katoh and Negishi, 2003</xref>). In brief, cells were
transfected as indicated, incubated with trypsin, and suspended in a serum-free
medium containing 1 mg/ml of trypsin inhibitor (from soybeans; Sigma-Aldrich).
After 1 h, the cells were transferred onto fibronectin-coated coverslips and
cultured for 30 min. The number of spreading cells was counted for the cells
that were completely adhered and examined by phase-contrast microscopy. The
classification of spreading cell morphology was performed as described
previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Applewhite et al., 2007</xref>). In
brief, the cells were transfected as indicated and after 24 h were trypsinized
and seeded on fibronectin-coated coverslips. The cells were incubated for
30–40 min to allow them to attach and spread. They were immunostained
as described in Immunocytochemistry. Morphological typing was performed based on
F-actin (phalloidin) staining and phase-contrast images.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Neurite outgrowth in N1E115 cells</title>
        <p>The N1E115 cells were seeded on 10 µg/ml laminin-coated coverslips and
cultured overnight. The next day, they were transfected with the respective
expression vectors in the presence of serum. After 16 h, the cells were serum
starved for another 12 h, immunostained as described in Immunocytochemistry, and
analyzed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Miki and
Takenawa, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Yamazaki et al.,
2002</xref>). In brief, cells with neurites were defined as the cells
possessing at least one neurite two times longer than the diameter of the cell
body from phase-contrast images.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Subcellular fractionation</title>
        <p>HeLa cells suspended in hypotonic buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM
MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 mM NaF, 1 mM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, and a
protease inhibitor cocktail; Sigma-Aldrich) were homogenized by 10 passages
through a 22-gauge needle. The samples were then centrifuged at 4,300
<italic>g</italic> for 10 min, and the supernatants were again centrifuged at
50,000 <italic>g</italic> for 1 h to separate the cytosolic and membrane
fractions. The membrane fraction was washed three times with the hypotonic
buffer and dissolved in buffer A with 1% SDS. The protein in the cytosolic and
membrane fractions was quantified using a DC Protein Assay kit (Bio-Rad
Laboratories). Each fraction was mixed with SDS sample buffer, and aliquots of
the samples containing 30 µg of protein were analyzed by Western
blotting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>siRNA</title>
        <p>An H1 promoter–based mammalian expression vector, pSUPER.neo, or
pSUPER.neo+gfp, which coexpresses siRNA and a <italic>neo-gfp</italic>
fusion gene (OligoEngine), was used for the expression of siRNA in mouse NIH3T3
fibroblasts. A 19-nucleotide sequence corresponding to nucleotides
609–627 (5′-GAGGCGAAAGCCATCTGTG-3′) of the mouse
cDNA clone A530060J16 (available from GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession no.
<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AK041011.1">AK041011.1</ext-link>) was used as the Kank RNAi
(Kank-KD) vector. A control vector was constructed using a 19-nucleotide
sequence (5′-ACTAGACGAAGCGGTACTG-3′) with no significant
homology to any mammalian gene sequences and used as a nonsilencing control
(control #2 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Suetsugu et al.,
2006a</xref>). For KD of mIRS, we searched for candidate KD sequences by Sfold
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sfold.wadsworth.org/">http://sfold.wadsworth.org/</ext-link>), tested their efficiency using NIH3T3
cells (Fig. S2), and selected a 19-nucleotide sequence (#513)
corresponding to nucleotides 513–531
(5′-GTAAGAACCCTCAGAAGTA-3′) of mIRS (available from
GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF390179">AF390179</ext-link>). For transfection, after cells were grown to
80–90% confluency, they were detached with trypsin/EDTA, washed with
PBS, suspended at ∼10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml in PBS, and subjected to
electroporation. Electroporation was performed with 18 µg of plasmid
DNA using a Gene Pulser II System (Bio-Rad Laboratories) at 270 mV and
975-µF capacitance. Under these conditions, we estimated the
transfection efficiency to be around 50–70% by comparing the level of
expression of GFP in a parallel experiment. After electroporation, the cells
were kept on ice for 5 min and transferred to plates with 10 ml of a complete
medium. After 36 h, the cells were lysed in a lysis buffer for checking the
expression of Kank protein. Kank esiRNA was prepared as described previously
(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Yang et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Kittler et al., 2004</xref>). In brief, sense
and antisense RNA was transcribed using a T7 promoter system (for both strands)
supplied in the MEGAscript kit (Applied Biosystems). After annealing the sense
and antisense strands, RNA was treated with ShortCut RNase III (New England
Biolabs, Inc.) and purified with Sepharose Q (GE Healthcare). Kank esiRNA and
control esiRNA containing the <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> elongation factor
gene (from the MEGAscript kit) were transfected with Lipofectamine 2000 in
HEK293 cells stably expressing Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>In vitro binding assay</title>
        <p>1 µg His-Rac1<sup>G12V</sup> or His-cdc42<sup>G12V</sup>, which was
produced in bacteria and purified with an Ni column, was added with 2
µg of control GST or GST-IRSp53(N) and 10 µg MBP or 1, 3, or
10 µg MBP-Kank<sup>coil</sup> as competitor in binding buffer A. After
these mixtures were rotated for 1 h at 4°C,
glutathione–Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare) was added to recover the
protein complexes, and rotation was continued for 1 h at 4°C. The
complexes were washed four times with the binding buffer, boiled for 5 min in an
SDS-PAGE loading buffer, and subjected to 5–20% SDS-PAGE, Coomassie
blue staining, and Western blot analysis using anti-Rac1 or anti-cdc42
antibodies to detect the respective proteins. The intensity of the bands was
quantified by CS Analyzer (ATTO Corp.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Online supplemental material</title>
        <p>Fig. S1 shows IRSp53 mutants that bind to Kank<sup>coil</sup> but not to
Rac1<sup>G12V</sup>. Fig. S2 shows the candidate sequences for IRSp53 KD.
Fig. S3 shows that KD of IRSp53 does not affect fibronectin-stimulated cell
spreading when Kank is overexpressed. Fig. S4 shows that Kank inhibits the
formation of the cells with filopodial- and IRSp53-induced smooth-edged
phenotypes when cells are spreading. Fig. S5 shows that overexpression of Kank
inhibits the association of IRSp53 with actin. Online supplemental material is
available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200805147/DC1</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Professor T. Akiyama (the University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan) for advice and
discussions, Dr. M. Yamada for the anti-IRSp53 serum, Professor M. Noguchi for
HEK293 cells, Professor Y. Kanaho for N1E115 cells, and Professor R. Matsuoka and
Dr. Y. Furutani (Tokyo Women's Medical University, Tokyo, Japan) for
laser-scanning confocal microscopy.</p>
      <p>This work was supported by the Special Coordination Fund for Promoting Science and
Technology by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of
Japan and by a fund for promoting collaboration with small and medium enterprises
from the National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Applewhite</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barzik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svitkina</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gertler</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borisy</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ena/VASP proteins have an anti-capping independent function in
filopodia formation.</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>18</volume><fpage>2579</fpage>–<lpage>2591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475772</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aspenström</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effectors for the Rho GTPases.</article-title><source>Curr. Opin.
Cell Biol.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>11</volume><fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10047515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biesova</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccoli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of e3B1, an eps8 binding protein
that regulates cell growth.</article-title><source>Oncogene.</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>14</volume><fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9010225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bompard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of WASP/WAVE proteins: making a long story
short.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>166</volume><fpage>957</fpage>–<lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burbelo</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drechsel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A conserved binding motif defines numerous candidate target
proteins for both Cdc42 and Rac GTPases.</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>270</volume><fpage>29071</fpage>–<lpage>29074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7493928</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stetefeld</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strelkov</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Coiled coils: a highly versatile protein folding
motif.</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>11</volume><fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11166216</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wennerberg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho and Rac take center stage.</article-title><source>Cell.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>116</volume><fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744429</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Racz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burette</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of dendritic spine morphogenesis by insulin receptor
substrate 53, a downstream effector of Rac1 and Cdc42 small
GTPases.</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>25</volume><fpage>869</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15673667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>W.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>R.O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Integrin-mediated signals regulated by members of the rho family
of GTPases.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>142</volume><fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9679153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feig</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tiam1-IRSp53 complex formation directs specificity of
rac-mediated actin cytoskeleton regulation.</article-title><source>Mol.
Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>25</volume><fpage>4602</fpage>–<lpage>4614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15899863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncharov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>C. elegans</italic> ankyrin repeat protein VAB-19 is a
component of epidermal attachment structures and is essential for epidermal
morphogenesis.</article-title><source>Development.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>130</volume><fpage>5791</fpage>–<lpage>5801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534136</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Disanza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantoani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertzog</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerboth</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frittoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berhoerster</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreienkamp</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milanesi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of cell shape by Cdc42 is mediated by the synergic
actin-bundling activity of the Eps8-IRSp53
complex.</article-title><source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>8</volume><fpage>1337</fpage>–<lpage>1347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115031</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Podtelejnikov</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of regulation of WAVE1-induced actin nucleation by Rac1
and Nck.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>418</volume><fpage>790</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12181570</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etienne-Manneville</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho GTPases in cell biology.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>420</volume><fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12478284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terabayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suenaga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seiki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>IRSp53/Eps8 complex is important for positive regulation of Rac
and cancer cell motility/invasiveness.</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>64</volume><fpage>5237</fpage>–<lpage>5244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289329</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govind</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monfries</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cdc42Hs facilitates cytoskeletal reorganization and neurite
outgrowth by localizing the 58-kD insulin receptor substrate to filamentous
actin.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>152</volume><fpage>579</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho GTPases and the actin
cytoskeleton.</article-title><source>Science.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>279</volume><fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9438836</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Activation by Cdc42 and PIP<sub>2</sub> of Wiskott-Aldrich
Syndrome protein (WASp) stimulates actin nucleation by Arp2/3
complex.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>150</volume><fpage>1311</fpage>–<lpage>1320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10995437</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konno</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsumoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>NMDA receptor-dependent synaptic translocation of insulin
receptor substrate p53 via protein kinase C
signaling.</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>25</volume><fpage>2670</fpage>–<lpage>2681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15758177</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>R.O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Integrins: bidirectional allosteric signaling
machines.</article-title><source>Cell.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>110</volume><fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innocenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frittoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponzanelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falck</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachmann</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scita</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphoinositide 3-kinase activates Rac by entering in a complex
with Eps8, Abi1, and Sos-1.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>160</volume><fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12515821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innocenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zucconi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Disanza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frittoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Areces</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stradal</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scita</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Abi1 is essential for the formation and activation of a WAVE2
signalling complex.</article-title><source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>6</volume><fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15048123</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakinuma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kank regulates RhoA-dependent formation of actin stress fibers
and cell migration via 14-3-3 in PI3K–Akt
signaling.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>181</volume><fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18458160</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negishi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>RhoG activates Rac1 by direct interaction with the
Dock180-binding protein Elmo.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>424</volume><fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12879077</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kittler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Putz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poser</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heninger</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drechsel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konstantinova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Habermann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>An endoribonuclease-prepared siRNA screen in human cells
identifies genes essential for cell division.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>432</volume><fpage>1036</fpage>–<lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15616564</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The Ras related protein Cdc42Hs and bradykinin promote formation
of peripheral actin microspikes and filopodia in Swiss 3T3
fibroblasts.</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>15</volume><fpage>1942</fpage>–<lpage>1952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7891688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The GTPase-activating protein n-chimaerin cooperates with Rac1
and Cdc42Hs to induce the formation of lamellipodia and
filopodia.</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>16</volume><fpage>5069</fpage>–<lpage>5080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756665</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho family GTPases and neuronal growth cone remodelling:
relationship between increased complexity induced by Cdc42Hs, Rac1 and
acetylcholine and collapse induced by RhoA and lysophosphatidic
acid.</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>17</volume><fpage>1201</fpage>–<lpage>1211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9032247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krugmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordens</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gevaert</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Driessens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandekerckhove</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cdc42 induces filopodia by promoting the formation of an
IRSp53:Mena complex.</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>11</volume><fpage>1645</fpage>–<lpage>1655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696321</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerff</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chereau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferron</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for the actin-binding function of
missing-in-metastasis.</article-title><source>Structure.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>15</volume><fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho GTPases in neuronal
morphogenesis.</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>1</volume><fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11257905</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattila</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pykäläinen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarikangas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paavilainen</surname><given-names>V.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vihinen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokitalo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Missing-in-metastasis and IRSp53 deform PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub>-rich
membranes by an inverse BAR domain–like
mechanism.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>176</volume><fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371834</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>WAVE2 serves a functional partner of IRSp53 by regulating its
interaction with Rac.</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>293</volume><fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12054568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suetsugu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>IRSp53 is an essential intermediate between Rac and WAVE in the
regulation of membrane ruffling.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>408</volume><fpage>732</fpage>–<lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11130076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bompard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heung</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafforn</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machesky</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fütterer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis of filopodia formation induced by the IRSp53/MIM
homology domain of human IRSp53.</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>24</volume><fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozumi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Small</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>IRSp53 is colocalised with WAVE2 at the tips of protruding
lamellipodia and filopodia independently of Mena.</article-title><source>J.
Cell Sci.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>116</volume><fpage>2577</fpage>–<lpage>2583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12734400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaishi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaku</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>rac</italic> p21 is involved in insulin-induced membrane
ruffling and <italic>rho</italic> p21 is involved in hepatocyte growth
factor- and 12-<italic>O</italic>-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate
(TPA)-induced membrane ruffling in KB cells.</article-title><source>Mol.
Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>14</volume><fpage>2447</fpage>–<lpage>2456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139548</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib96">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamura-Oho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohmi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dentatorubral-pallidoluysian atrophy protein interacts through a
proline-rich region near polyglutamine with the SH3 domain of an insulin
receptor tyrosine kinase substrate.</article-title><source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>8</volume><fpage>947</fpage>–<lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10332026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Activation of Rac and Cdc42 by integrins mediates cell
spreading.</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>9</volume><fpage>1863</fpage>–<lpage>1871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9658176</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekmann</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The small GTP-binding protein rac regulates growth factor-induced
membrane ruffling.</article-title><source>Cell.</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>70</volume><fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1643658</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burridge</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Firtel</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borisy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cell migration: integrating signals from front to
back.</article-title><source>Science.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>302</volume><fpage>1704</fpage>–<lpage>1709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657486</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A differential genomic cloning for cancer study: an outline and
applications.</article-title><source>Recent Research Developments in
Molecular Biology.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>1</volume><fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwaya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathological characterization of Kank in renal cell
carcinoma.</article-title><source>Exp. Mol. Pathol.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>78</volume><fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15596059</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohji</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A novel ankyrin repeat-containing gene (Kank) located at 9p24 is
a growth suppressor of renal cell carcinoma.</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>277</volume><fpage>36585</fpage>–<lpage>36591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12133830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scita</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordstrom</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenca</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardina</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutkind</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjarnegård</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betsholtz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>EPS8 and E3B1 transduce signals from Ras to
Rac.</article-title><source>Nature.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>401</volume><fpage>290</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scita</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenca</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Areces</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tocchetti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frittoli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardina</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponzanelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Innocenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An effector region in Eps8 is responsible for the activation of
the Rac-specific GEF activity of Sos-1 and for the proper localization of
the Rac-based actin-polymerizing machine.</article-title><source>J. Cell
Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>154</volume><fpage>1031</fpage>–<lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11524436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedgwick</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The ankyrin repeat: a diversity of interactions on a common
structural framework.</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>24</volume><fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10431175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreienkamp</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The insulin receptor substrate IRSp53 links postsynaptic shank1
to the small G-protein cdc42.</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Neurosci.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>21</volume><fpage>575</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12504591</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltau</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berhörster</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreienkamp</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Insulin receptor substrate of 53 kDa links postsynaptic shank to
PSD-95.</article-title><source>J. Neurochem.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>90</volume><fpage>659</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15255944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rottner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehinger</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Innocenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scita</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stradal</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sra-1 and Nap1 link Rac to actin assembly driving lamellipodia
formation.</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>23</volume><fpage>749</fpage>–<lpage>759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765121</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suetsugu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurisu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Optimization of WAVE2 complex–induced actin
polymerization by membrane-bound IRSp53, PIP<sub>3</sub>, and
Rac.</article-title><source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<year>2006a</year>
<volume>173</volume><fpage>571</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16702231</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suetsugu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanawa-Suetsugu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oikawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishima</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirouzu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The RAC binding domain/IRSp53-MIM homology domain of IRSp53
induces RAC-dependent membrane deformation.</article-title><source>J. Biol.
Chem.</source>
<year>2006b</year>
<volume>281</volume><fpage>35347</fpage>–<lpage>35358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17003044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takenawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>WASP and WAVE family proteins: key molecules for rapid
rearrangement of cortical actin filaments and cell
movement.</article-title><source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>114</volume><fpage>1801</fpage>–<lpage>1809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11329366</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Aelst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Souza-Schorey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rho GTPases and signaling networks.</article-title><source>Genes
Dev.</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>11</volume><fpage>2295</fpage>–<lpage>2322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9308960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib54">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vignal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blangy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier-Rouvière</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kinectin is a key effector of RhoG microtubule-dependent cellular
activity.</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>21</volume><fpage>8022</fpage>–<lpage>8034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11689693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib55">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onishi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A novel actin bundling/filopodium-forming domain conserved in
insulin receptor tyrosine kinase substrate p53 and missing in metastasis
protein.</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>279</volume><fpage>14929</fpage>–<lpage>14936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib56">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maehama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frohman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanaho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate 5-kinase is essential for
ROCK-mediated neurite remodeling.</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>277</volume><fpage>17226</fpage>–<lpage>17230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11877391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib57">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodsky</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Short RNA duplexes produced by hydrolysis with
<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RNase III mediate effective RNA
interference in mammalian cells.</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci. USA.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>99</volume><fpage>9942</fpage>–<lpage>9947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12096193</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <notes>
      <p>Abbreviations used in this paper: CRIB, cdc42/Rac1 interactive binding; esiRNA,
endoribonuclease-prepared siRNA; F-actin, filamentous actin; IRS, insulin
receptor substrate; KD, knockdown; MBP, maltose-binding protein; mIRS, mouse
IRSp53; WASP, Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein.</p>
    </notes>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>