<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:34:21Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2699145" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2699145</identifier><datestamp>2009-09-23</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jcb</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2699145</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2699145</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2699145</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307596</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19307596</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200810155</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200810155</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Report</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Reversion-induced LIM interaction with Src reveals a novel Src inactivation cycle</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Yongjun</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tu</surname>
            <given-names>Yizeng</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
            <given-names>Jianping</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Ka</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Chuanyue</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>
        <institution>Department of Pathology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15261</institution>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence to Chuanyue Wu: <email>carywu@pitt.edu</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>184</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>785</fpage>
      <lpage>792</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2009 Zhang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml">http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aberrant Src activation plays prominent roles in cancer progression. However, how Src is activated in cancer cells is largely unknown. Genetic Src-activating mutations are rare and, therefore, are insufficient to account for Src activation commonly found in human cancers. In this study, we show that reversion-induced LIM (RIL), which is frequently lost in colon and other cancers as a result of epigenetic silencing, suppresses Src activation. Mechanistically, RIL suppresses Src activation through interacting with Src and PTPL1, allowing PTPL1-dependent dephosphorylation of Src at the activation loop. Importantly, the binding of RIL to Src is drastically reduced upon Src inactivation. Our results reveal a novel Src inactivation cycle in which RIL preferentially recognizes active Src and facilitates PTPL1-mediated inactivation of Src. Inactivation of Src, in turn, promotes dissociation of RIL from Src, allowing the initiation of a new Src inactivation cycle. Epigenetic silencing of <italic>RIL</italic> breaks this Src inactivation cycle and thereby contributes to aberrant Src activation in human cancers.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Src is an important regulatory protein that functions in several fundamental processes, including cell differentiation, proliferation, migration, and survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Summy and Gallick, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Frame, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Playford and Schaller, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Russello and Shore, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Yeatman, 2004</xref>). Because of its prominent roles in cell signaling, aberrant Src activation, which is frequently found in common human cancers such as colon cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Rosen et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Bolen et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cartwright et al., 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Aligayer et al., 2002</xref>), is considered a key factor in cancer progression. Thus, inhibition of Src represents a promising approach for cancer therapy. Indeed, a large number (&gt;50 at last count) of Src inhibitor–based clinical trials have been initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Kopetz et al., 2007</xref>). However, despite the wealth of information on the structural basis and functional consequences of Src activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Thomas and Brugge, 1997</xref>), how Src is activated in cancer cells remains largely elusive.</p>
      <p>Reversion-induced LIM (RIL) is a ubiquitously expressed protein that was initially identified during a search for genes that are expressed in normal cells but repressed in Harvey ras–transformed derivatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Kiess et al., 1995</xref>). The expression of <italic>RIL</italic> is restored in several independent phenotypic revertants derived from Harvey ras–transformed cells (thus, it was named as reversion-induced LIM). Recent experiments have shown that <italic>RIL</italic> is a target of epigenetic silencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boumber et al., 2007</xref>). Hypermethylation of <italic>RIL</italic> was found in a large number of cancer cell lines and tumors derived from various origins, including the colon, liver, and breast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boumber et al., 2007</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>RIL</italic> transcription is suppressed in multiple types of human cancer cells, including colon cancer cells, and reexpression of RIL inhibited anchorage-independent growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boumber et al., 2007</xref>). These findings strongly suggest that loss of RIL contributes to malignant behavior. However, the underlying molecular mechanism is not known. In this study, we show that RIL mediates a novel Src inactivation cycle and, thus, that loss of RIL promotes Src activation and consequently anchorage-independent growth.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>We first verified that the expression of RIL protein was inhibited in human colon cancer cells. To do this, we generated an mAb specifically recognizing RIL. Western blotting analyses of HCT116 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 2), HT29 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 3), RKO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 4), Caco-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 5), and DLD-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 6) colon cancer cells showed that they all lacked RIL. Additionally, no RIL was detected in several other types of cancer cells, including HeLa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 8) and 293 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lane 9) cells. The lack of signals in the RIL Western blots was not the result of technical issues with the anti-RIL mAb or the samples, as RIL was readily detected in other cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>, lanes 1 and 7) and tubulin was detected in all samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 A</xref>). Thus, consistent with the epigenetic experiments showing hypermethylation of <italic>RIL</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Boumber et al., 2007</xref>), colon cancer cells lack RIL protein.</p>
      <fig id="fig1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>RIL inhibits Src activation and reduces anchorage-independent growth.</bold> (A) Lysates (15 µg/lane) of WI-38 (lane 1), HCT116 (lane 2), HT29 (lane 3), RKO (lane 4), Caco-2 (lane 5), DLD-1 (lane 6), SK-LMS-1 (lane 7), HeLa (lane 8), and 293 (lane 9) cells were analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies recognizing RIL or tubulin (as a loading control). (B) HCT116 cells were transfected with Flag-RIL vector (lane 2) or a vector lacking the RIL sequence as a control (lane 1). The lysates were probed with antibodies recognizing RIL, Src, pY419 Src, or pY530 Src. (C) Src was immunoprecipitated from HCT116 cells transfected with the control (lane 1) or Flag-RIL (lane 2) vector and analyzed by Western blotting with an anti-Src antibody. (D) The kinase activity of Src derived from the Flag-RIL transfectants was compared with that of the control cells. (E) FAK was immunoprecipitated from HCT116 cells transfected with the control (lane 1) or Flag-RIL (lane 2) vector and analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies specific for FAK or pY566/577 FAK. IP, immunoprecipitation. (F) Anchorage-independent growth of HCT116 cells in the presence of PP2 or PP3 was compared with that of HCT116 cells grown in the absence of PP2 and PP3 (control). (G and H) HCT116 cells were transfected with the control vector (G, lane 1), the Flag-RIL vector (G, lane 2), or the Flag-RIL vector and a vector encoding a constitutively active form of chicken Src (Y527F; G, lane 3). (G) The lysates were probed with antibodies recognizing RIL, pY419 Src, or Src. (H) Anchorage-independent growth of the cells expressing Flag-RIL or Flag-RIL and constitutively active Src was compared with that of the control cells. (D, F, and H) Error bars represent mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Mr, molecular mass.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200810155_GS_Fig1"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The finding that RIL expression is suppressed in human colon cancer cells, in which Src is known to be aberrantly activated, prompted us to test whether RIL plays a role in Src inactivation. To do this, we expressed RIL in human HCT116 colon cancer cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 B</xref>, lane 2). Phosphorylation of Y419 (Y416 in chickens) in the activation loop, which is essential for full activation of Src (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Roskoski, 2005</xref>), was markedly reduced (by 48.2 ± 20.1%; mean ± SD; <italic>n</italic> = 6; P &lt; 0.001), whereas the level of Y530 (Y527 in chickens) phosphorylation, which inhibits Src activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Roskoski, 2005</xref>), was slightly increased (by a mean of 7.6 ± 4.4%; mean ± SD; <italic>n</italic> = 3; P = 0.038) in response to RIL expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 B</xref>). The level of total Src was not changed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 B</xref>). To directly test whether RIL inhibits Src activation, we immunoprecipitated Src from RIL-expressing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 C</xref>, lane 2) and RIL-null control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 C</xref>, lane 1) cells. Consistent with the suppression of Y419 phosphorylation, the activity of Src isolated from the RIL-expressing cells was significantly lower than that of RIL-null control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 D</xref>). To further test this, we analyzed Y576/577 phosphorylation of FAK, an in vivo substrate of Src, and found that it was substantially reduced in response to the expression of RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 E</xref>). Collectively, these results suggest that RIL plays an important role in the suppression of Y419 phosphorylation and consequently the inactivation of Src.</p>
      <p>Src is known to play a role in the regulation of anchorage-independent growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Summy and Gallick, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Frame, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Playford and Schaller, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Russello and Shore, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Yeatman, 2004</xref>). Consistent with this, treatment of HCT116 cells with the Src inhibitor PP2 but not with PP3 (a PP2 analogue lacking Src inhibitory activity) reduced anchorage-independent growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 F</xref>). Expression of Flag-RIL, like treatment of cells with PP2, significantly reduced anchorage-independent growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 H</xref>). Importantly, RIL-induced inhibition of anchorage-independent growth was substantially reversed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 H</xref>) in response to expression of a constitutively active Src (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1 G</xref>, lane 3), suggesting that RIL inhibits anchorage-independent growth at least partly through the suppression of Src activation.</p>
      <p>Next, we sought to determine the mechanism by which RIL suppresses Src activation. A fraction of RIL colocalized with Src, particularly in the perinuclear areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A–C</xref>). Consistent with a role of RIL in Src inactivation, RIL was undetectable in areas where high concentrations of phospho-Y419 (pY419) Src (i.e., active Src) were present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, D–F</xref>). The finding that a fraction of Src colocalizes with RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A–C</xref>) prompted us to test whether Src physically interacts with RIL. To do this, we generated a maltose-binding protein (MBP)–tagged Src protein and found that it was coprecipitated with GST-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 G</xref>, lane 3) but not with GST (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 G</xref>, lane 2). Probing the same samples with an anti-pY419 Src antibody revealed that pY419 Src was enriched in the GST-RIL precipitates. To further analyze the binding, we generated GST-tagged Src and MBP-tagged RIL. MBP-RIL was coprecipitated with GST-Src (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 H</xref>, lane 3) but not GST (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 H</xref>, lane 2), confirming the interaction between the two proteins. To identify Src domains that mediate RIL binding, we generated GST fusion proteins containing the SH3 (residues 88–149), SH2 (residues 150–248), or kinase (residues 249–536) domains of Src. MBP-RIL was coprecipitated with GST kinase domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 H</xref>, lane 5) but not with GST-SH3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 H</xref>, lane 7). A smaller amount of MBP-RIL was also coprecipitated with GST-SH2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 H</xref>, lane 9). Thus, the kinase domain and, to a lesser extent, the SH2 domain but not the SH3 domain mediate the interaction with RIL.</p>
      <fig id="fig2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>RIL colocalizes and interacts with Src.</bold> (A–F) WI-38 cells were dually stained with anti-RIL mAb 2A2.11 (A and D) and rabbit anti-Src (B) or anti-pY419 Src (E) antibodies. C and F show merged images. (G) 312.5 ng MBP-Src was incubated with GST or GST-RIL as indicated. The input (lane 1; 10 ng/lane), GST (lane 2), and GST-RIL (lane 3) pull-downs were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining. (H) 250 ng MBP-RIL was incubated with GST or GST fusion protein containing Src SH3, SH2, or kinase domain (KD) as indicated. The input (lane 1; 2 ng/lane) and GST or GST fusion protein pull-downs (lanes 2–10) were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining. (I) 250 µg of lysates of HCT116 cells transfected with Flag-RIL or the control vector were mixed with 20 µl of M2-conjugated agarose beads. Lane 1 was loaded with 5 µg of the control cell lysates (to show the position of Src). The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blotting with anti-Src or anti-Flag antibodies. (J) Anti-RIL immunoprecipitates were prepared by mixing 500 µg WI-38 cell lysates with 5 µg anti-RIL mAb. The lysates (lane 1; 5 µg/lane) and anti-RIL immunoprecipitates (lane 3) were analyzed by Western blotting with anti-Src or anti-RIL antibodies. The sample in lane 2 was prepared as in lane 3 except the lysates were omitted (to show the IgG bands derived from the anti-RIL antibody used in immunoprecipitation). Mr, molecular mass; WB, Western blot; IP, immunoprecipitation. Bar, 15 µm.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200810155_RGB_Fig2"/>
      </fig>
      <p>To test whether RIL forms a complex with Src in cells, we immunoprecipitated Flag-RIL from Flag-RIL–expressing HCT116 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 I</xref>, lane 3). Src was readily coimmunoprecipitated with Flag-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 I</xref>, lane 3). In control experiments, no Src was detected in anti-Flag immunoprecipitates derived from control transfectants lacking Flag-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 I</xref>, lane 2). To further test this, we immunoprecipitated endogenous RIL from WI-38 cells. Again, Src was readily coimmunoprecipitated with RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 J</xref>, lane 3). Thus, consistent with the colocalization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A–C</xref>) and direct binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, G and H</xref>) experiments, RIL forms a complex with Src in cells.</p>
      <p>The finding that RIL binds Src suggested two potential mechanisms by which RIL could suppress Src activation. First, RIL binding could potentially interfere with conformation changes involved in Src activation and thereby suppresses Src activation. Alternatively, RIL could function as an adapter protein for a protein phosphatase and consequently link the phosphatase to Src and promote pY419 dephosphorylation, resulting in Src inactivation. To test the first possibility, we incubated purified Src with GST-RIL and found that it did not reduce the kinase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 A</xref>). Thus, RIL binding alone is insufficient for Src inactivation. To test the second possibility, we immunoprecipitated Flag-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 B</xref>, lane 2) and analyzed associated phosphatase activity. A significantly higher phosphatase activity was detected in Flag-RIL immunoprecipitates compared with that of the control immunoprecipitates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 C</xref>). Deletion of the LIM domain or the second zinc finger within the LIM domain significantly reduced the phosphatase activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 D</xref>).</p>
      <fig id="fig3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>PTPL1 mediates RIL-induced Src inactivation.</bold> (A) The kinase activity of Src in the presence of GST-RIL was compared with that in the presence of the GST control (normalized to 100%; <italic>n</italic> = 2). (B) Anti-Flag immunoprecipitates were prepared from HCT116 cells transfected with the control vector (lane 1) or vectors encoding Flag-RIL (lane 2), Flag-ΔLIM (lane 3), or Flag-ΔZF2 (lane 4) and analyzed by Western blotting with anti-Flag antibody. (C) Phosphatase activities associated with Flag-RIL and control immunoprecipitates were measured as described in Materials and methods (<italic>n</italic> = 4). (D) Phosphatase activities associated with Flag-ΔLIM, Flag-ΔZF2, or control immunoprecipitates were compared with those associated with Flag-RIL (normalized to 100%; <italic>n</italic> = 4). (E) Anti-Flag immunoprecipitates were prepared by mixing 700 µg cell lysates with 20 µl of M2-conjugated agarose beads. The lysates (lanes 1–4; 15 µg/lane) and immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blotting with anti-PTPL1 or anti-Flag antibodies. (F) HCT116 cells were transfected with the control (lane 1), Flag-RIL (lane 2), or Flag-ΔZF2 (lane 3) vector and analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies as indicated. (G and H) HCT116 cells were transfected with the Flag-RIL vector (lanes 2 and 3), the control vector (lanes 1 and 4), control RNA (lanes 1 and 2), and PTPL1 siRNA-1 (G) or -2 (H; lanes 3 and 4) as indicated. The cells were analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies recognizing PTPL1, pY419 Src, Src, Flag, or tubulin. Note that RIL inhibits Y419 phosphorylation in cells that express a normal level of PTPL1 (lane 2) but not in PTPL1 knockdown cells (lane 3). (A, C, and D) Error bars represent mean ± SD. Mr, molecular mass; IP, immunoprecipitate.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200810155_GS_Fig3"/>
      </fig>
      <p>What is the molecular identity of the phosphatase involved in RIL-mediated Src inactivation? Protein Tyr phosphatase (PTP)–BAS-like (BL), a mouse homologue of human PTPL1, was previously found to interact with RIL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Cuppen et al., 1998</xref>), albeit the function of this interaction is unknown. The catalytic sequence of PTPL1 was identified as an Src antagonizer in a functional screen in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Superti-Furga et al., 1996</xref>). In vitro, PTP-BL phosphatase domain can catalyze pY419 dephosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Palmer et al., 2002</xref>). Based on these findings, we hypothesized that RIL promotes dephosphorylation of pY419 through recruitment of PTPL1. Up to now, the interaction of PTP-BL with RIL was demonstrated only with recombinant PTP-BL fusion protein. Thus, we sought to test whether RIL forms a complex with endogenous PTPL1 in mammalian cells. The results showed that endogenous PTPL1 was readily coimmunoprecipitated with Flag-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 E</xref>, lane 6) but not with control precipitates lacking RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 E</xref>, lane 5), confirming the interaction of PTPL1 with Flag-RIL in cells.</p>
      <p>Next, we sought to test whether PTPL1 binding is required for RIL-induced pY419 dephosphorylation. Deletion of LIM (ΔLIM) or the second zinc finger (ΔZF2) eliminated the PTPL1 binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 E</xref>, lanes 7 and 8). Importantly, expression of the PTPL1 binding–defective ΔLIM (not depicted) or ΔZF2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 F</xref>, lane 3) mutant, unlike that of wild-type RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3 F</xref>, lane 2), failed to inhibit Y419 phosphorylation. These results suggest that the interaction with PTPL1 is required for RIL-mediated dephosphorylation of pY419.</p>
      <p>To further test our hypothesis that RIL promotes pY419 dephosphorylation through PTPL1, we depleted PTPL1 by RNAi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, lanes 3 and 4). Flag-RIL was expressed in PTPL1 knockdown cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, lane 3) as well as in control cells expressing a normal level of PTPL1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, lane 2). As expected, expression of Flag-RIL substantially reduced Y419 phosphorylation in control cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, lane 2). By marked contrast, expression of Flag-RIL failed to inhibit Y419 phosphorylation in the absence of PTPL1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, lane 3). Although knockdown of PTPL1 from RIL-expressing cells markedly increased Y419 phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, compare lane 2 with lane 3), the effect of PTPL1 knockdown on Y419 phosphorylation was noticeably diminished in the absence of RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3, G and H</xref>, compare lane 1 with lane 4). Collectively, these results provide strong evidence suggesting that RIL suppresses Src activation by physically linking PTPL1 to Src and consequently promoting pY419 dephosphorylation.</p>
      <p>Next, we tested the effect of Src inactivation on RIL binding. Treatment of Src with PP2, a pyrazolo pyrimidine-type inhibitor that is known to lock Src in an inactive conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Schindler et al., 1999</xref>), abolished the ability of Src to bind RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>, compare lane 5 with lane 6), suggesting that the interaction between Src and RIL is negatively regulated by Src inactivation. This is consistent with the result of our binding experiments showing that pY419 Src was preferentially pulled down by RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2 G</xref>). To directly test this, we substituted Y419 with Phe, which prevents phosphorylation at the activation loop and thereby inhibits full activation of Src (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Kmiecik and Shalloway, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Piwnica-Worms et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Ferracini and Brugge, 1990</xref>). Again, although wild-type Src readily bound to GST-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>, lane 4), substitution of Y419 with Phe eliminated the ability of Src to interact with GST-RIL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>, lane 6). In control experiments, neither Src nor Y419F bound to GST (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 B</xref>, lanes 3 and 5), confirming the specificity of the binding assay. To further test this, we substituted Pro302 and Pro307 (Pro299 and Pro304 in chickens) in the Y419F mutant with Glu, which is known to convert the Y419F mutant into an active kinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Gonfloni et al., 2000</xref>). The kinase-active Pro302E/Pro307E/Y419F mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>, lane 6), unlike the Y419F kinase-defective mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>, lane 8), was coprecipitated with GST-RIL, confirming that RIL preferentially recognizes active Src. In control experiments, neither Pro302E/Pro307E/Y419F nor Y419F was coprecipitated with GST (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>, lanes 5 and 7). Collectively, our findings suggest a model for RIL-mediated inactivation of Src (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref>). In this model, RIL preferentially recognizes active (i.e., pY419) Src. The binding of RIL to pY419 Src brings it to PTPL1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 A</xref>, step 1), which catalyzes pY419 dephosphorylation. Dephosphorylation of Src at Y419 shifts the balance toward an inactive conformation (similar to the PP2-bound autoinhibited form of Src [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Schindler et al., 1999</xref>] or that of the Y419F mutant), which markedly reduces RIL binding and thus helps to release Src from the RIL–PTPL1 complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 A</xref>, step 2). The free RIL–PTPL1 complex can then bind to another pY419 Src and start a new cycle of pY419 dephosphorylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 A</xref>, step 3). This Src-inactivating cycle counterbalances Src-activating cycles and helps to keep the level of active Src in check in normal cells. Thus, in subcellular compartments in which this RIL-mediated Src inactivation cycle operates, Src activation is suppressed, whereas in areas lacking RIL (e.g., focal adhesions), the level of active Src is elevated. This is highly consistent with our subcellular localization experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2, A–F</xref>) in which high levels of active Src were detected in areas lacking RIL (e.g., focal adhesions) but not in areas where RIL was present. Similarly, in cells (e.g., colon cancer cells) in which RIL is lost as a result of epigenetic silencing, this Src inactivation mechanism is broken, resulting in aberrantly high levels of active (i.e., pY419) Src (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 B</xref>) and thereby contributing to malignant behavior (e.g., anchorage-independent growth). Our experiments suggest a mechanism through which epigenetic silencing of <italic>RIL</italic> is linked to increased Src activation in colon cancer. Loss of this RIL–PTPL1-mediated Src inactivation cycle in colon cancer cells may provide an explanation as to why vanadate, a phosphatase inhibitor, can activate Src in normal colon cells but not in colon cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">DeSeau et al., 1987</xref>). Additionally, our finding that PTPL1 is required for RIL-mediated Src inactivation may explain how epigenetic silencing or genetic mutations in <italic>PTPN13</italic> (the PTPL1 gene), which are frequently found in multiple types of human cancers such as colon cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Wang et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Yeh et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Ying et al., 2006</xref>), could contribute to malignant transformation.</p>
      <fig id="fig4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Inactivation of Src inhibits RIL interaction.</bold> (A) 300 ng MBP-Src was pretreated with (lanes 2, 4, and 6) or without (lanes 1, 3, and 5) PP2 and then incubated with GST-RIL or GST. The inputs (lanes 1 and 2; 5 ng/lane), GST precipitates (lanes 3 and 4), or GST-RIL precipitates (lanes 5 and 6) were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining. (B) 250 ng MBP-Src or 250 ng MBP-Y419F was incubated with GST-RIL or GST. The inputs (lanes 1 and 2; 10 ng/lane), GST precipitates (lanes 3 and 5), or GST-RIL precipitates (lanes 4 and 6) were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining. The sample in lane 7 was prepared as that in lane 4 except that MBP-Src was omitted. (C) 312.5 ng MBP-Y419F or 312.5 ng MBP-Pro302E/Pro307E/Y419F was incubated with GST-RIL or GST as indicated. The inputs (lanes 1 and 2; 10 ng/lane), GST (lanes 5 and 7), or GST-RIL (lanes 6 and 8) precipitates were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining. Lanes 3 and 4 were loaded with GST and GST-RIL pull-downs prepared in the absence of MBP-Y419F or MBP-Pro302E/Pro307E/Y419F. Mr, molecular mass; WB, Western blot.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200810155_GS_Fig4"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="fig5" position="float">
        <label>Figure 5.</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>A model of RIL–PTPL1-mediated Src inactivation.</bold> (A and B) Schematic representations of a RIL–PTPL1-mediated Src inactivation cycle (A) and the effect of loss of RIL or PTPL1 on Src activation (B).</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="JCB_200810155_GS_Fig5"/>
      </fig>
      <p>In summary, we have demonstrated that RIL functions as an activation-dependent binding protein of Src and mediates a novel Src inactivation cycle. The experiments present in this study shed light on the molecular mechanism underlying aberrant Src activation that has been frequently observed in colon and other human cancers. Given the prominent role of Src activation in cancer progression, the identification of this RIL-mediated Src inactivation cycle may also help us to develop novel approaches to control cancer progression.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Cells and antibodies</title>
        <p>HCT116 cells were cultured in McCoy's 5A supplemented with L-Gln and 10% FBS. WI-38 cells were cultured with MEM supplemented with 10% FBS and L-Gln. Rabbit polyclonal anti-Src, anti-pY416 Src, anti-pY527 Src, rabbit anti-FAK, and anti-pY566/577-FAK antibodies were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology. A mouse anti-FAK mAb was purchased from BD. Anti-Flag mouse mAb (M2) and M2-conjugated agarose beads were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. FITC-conjugated anti–mouse IgG and Cy3-conjugated anti–rabbit IgG antibodies were purchased from Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories. Alexa Fluor 488–conjugated anti–mouse IgG was purchased from Invitrogen. Mouse mAbs recognizing RIL were prepared using a GST fusion protein containing the N-terminal region of RIL (residues 1–250) as an antigen based on a previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Tu et al., 2003</xref>). Hybridoma supernatants were initially screened for anti-RIL activities by ELISA using recombinant MBP-RIL fusion protein. Clones recognizing MBP-RIL in ELISA were selected and further tested by Western blotting using MBP-RIL and mammalian cells expressing Flag-RIL.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Subcellular localization of RIL and Src</title>
        <p>Subcellular localization of RIL and Src was analyzed by confocal immunofluorescent staining with mouse anti-RIL and rabbit anti-Src antibodies using a previously described method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Gkretsi et al., 2005</xref>). In brief, cells were plated on fibronectin-coated coverslips, fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde, and double stained with mouse anti-RIL and rabbit anti-Src antibodies. The mouse and rabbit antibodies were detected with Cy3-conjugated anti–mouse IgG and Alexa Fluor 488–conjugated anti–rabbit IgG secondary antibodies. The samples were mounted in gelvatol and observed at room temperature under a confocal microscope (FluoView 1000; Olympus) equipped with a 100× NA 1.40 UPLSAPO objective lens. Fluorescence emission was collected with internal photomultiplier tubes and analyzed using FlowView software (Olympus).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>RIL expression vector construction, transfection, and immunoprecipitation</title>
        <p>The formation of the RIL–Src complex in mammalian cells was analyzed by coimmunoprecipitation. DNA fragments encoding human RIL sequences were cloned into the pFlag-CMV-6c vector (Sigma-Aldrich). HCT116 cells were transfected with the Flag-RIL expression vectors using Lipofectamine Plus (Invitrogen). The expression of Flag-tagged proteins in the transfectants was confirmed by Western blotting and immunofluorescent staining (∼70–80% of the transfectants expressed Flag-RIL based on immunofluorescent staining). For immunoprecipitation analyses, the transfectants were lysed with the lysis buffer (1% Triton X-100 in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, containing 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 25 mM NaF, 1.75% octylglucopyranoside, 0.1 mM PMSF, 1 µM pepstatin, 5 µg/ml aprotinin, and 1 µg/ml leupeptin). The cell lysates were mixed with agarose beads conjugated with anti-Flag mAb M2 (Sigma-Aldrich). To immunoprecipitate endogenous RIL from WI-38 cells, the cell lysates were mixed with anti-RIL mAb 2A2.11 and incubated at 4°C for 4 h. The samples were then incubated with UltraLink Immobilized Protein G (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The beads were washed five times, and the immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies as specified. To prepare anti-FAK immunoprecipitates, HCT116 cells were transfected with the Flag-RIL vector or a Flag vector lacking the RIL sequence as a control. The 750-µg cell lysates were incubated with 1.25 µg anti-FAK mAb. Anti-FAK immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blotting with rabbit antibodies specific for FAK or pY566/577 FAK.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>RNAi</title>
        <p>Two previously validated PTPL1 siRNAs (PTPL1 siRNA-1 [Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.] and -2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Dromard et al., 2007</xref>]) were used to knock down PTPL1. HCT116 cells were transfected with PTPL1 siRNA-1, PTPL1 siRNA-2, or an irrelevant 21-nucleotide RNA using Lipofectamine 2000 reagent (Invitrogen). Depletion of PTPL1 in the PTPL1 siRNA transfectants but not the control transfectants was confirmed by Western blotting with anti-PTPL1 antibody H-300 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Direct interaction of RIL with Src</title>
        <p>The direct interaction between RIL and Src was analyzed using affinity-purified recombinant GST- or MBP-tagged RIL and MBP- or GST-tagged Src fusion proteins in a GST fusion protein pull-down assay. DNA fragments encoding RIL or Src sequences as specified in each experiment were prepared by PCR and inserted into the pGEX-5x-1 vector (GE Healthcare) or the pMAL-C2 vector (New England Biolabs, Inc.). Point mutations were introduced into the Src coding sequence using a QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis system (Agilent Technologies). The recombinant vectors were used to transform <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cells. The expression of the GST and MBP fusion proteins was induced with IPTG, and they were purified by affinity chromatography using glutathione–Sepharose 4B and amylose-agarose, respectively, as we previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Tu et al., 2003</xref>). To test the interaction between GST-RIL and MBP-Src proteins, glutathione–Sepharose 4B beads containing GST-RIL or GST were preincubated with PBS containing 1% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 and 1 mg/ml BSA. The beads were then incubated with 1 µg/ml of MBP-tagged wild-type or mutant forms of Src at 4°C for 2 h and washed five times with 1× PBS/1% Triton X-100. To test the interaction between GST-Src and MBP-RIL proteins, glutathione–Sepharose 4B beads containing GST, GST-tagged wild-type, or mutant forms of Src were preincubated with PBS containing 1% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 and 1 mg/ml BSA and were incubated with MBP-RIL. The samples were analyzed by Western blotting and Coomassie blue staining as specified in each experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Anchorage-independent growth</title>
        <p>Anchorage-independent growth was determined using a soft agar colony formation assay as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Kolligs et al., 1999</xref>). In brief, HCT116 cells were transfected with the Flag-RIL vector, the Flag-RIL vector and a vector encoding the constitutively active Y527F mutant of chicken Src, or the Flag vector lacking the RIL sequence as a control. 1 d after the transfection, the cells were trypsinized and resuspended in culture medium. Underlayers of 0.6% agar medium were prepared in 12-well plates at 0.5 ml/well by combining equal volumes of 1.2% SeaPlaque agarose (FMC BioProducts) and McCoy's 5A containing 10% FBS. The cells were washed three times with the culture medium and seeded in 12-well plates at 4,000 cells/well in 0.3% SeaPlaque agarose. After incubation at 37°C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 2 wk, colonies with diameters &gt;0.5 mm were counted. The numbers of colonies in each microscopic field (113 mm<sup>2</sup>/field) were calculated by analyzing at least six microscopic fields. Colony formation from cells expressing Flag-RIL or Flag-RIL and the constitutively active Src was compared with that of the control cells (presented as percentages of the control cells). The effect of PP2 on anchorage-independent growth was analyzed using the aforementioned protocol except that HCT116 cells were grown in the presence of 10 µM PP2, 10 µM PP3 (a PP2 analogue that lacks Src inhibitory activity), or neither PP2 nor PP3 (control). Colony formation from cells grown in the presence of PP2 or PP3 was compared with that of the control cells (presented as percentages of the control cells).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Src phosphorylation</title>
        <p>pY419 or pY530 Src was detected by Western blotting with antibodies specific for the corresponding forms of Src. The densities of pY419 or pY530 Src were quantified by densitometry analysis using the Scion Image program (National Institutes of Health).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Src kinase assays</title>
        <p>The effect of RIL binding on Src kinase activity was analyzed using an HTScan(r) Src Kinase Assay kit (Cell Signaling Technology) according to the manufacturer's protocol. In brief, 2 ng/µl GST-Src was incubated with GST-RIL or GST at room temperature for 30 min. The samples were incubated with the substrate peptide for 30 min and mixed with an equal volume of 50 mM EDTA to stop the reaction. The reaction solutions were transferred into 96-well streptavidin plates (Millipore) at 25 µl/well, diluted with 75 µl H<sub>2</sub>O, and incubated at room temperature for 60 min. At the end of the incubation, the wells were rinsed three times with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS and incubated with anti–phospho-Tyr antibody pY-100 (1:1,000 dilution) for 60 min. After washing three times with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS, the wells were incubated with HRP-conjugated goat anti–mouse IgG antibody (1:1,000 dilution) for 60 min. The wells were rinsed six times with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS, 100 µl of 1 mg/ml TMB (3,3′,5,5′-tetramethylbenzidine dihydrochloride; Electron Microscopy Sciences) was added to each well, and they were incubated for 15 min. The reaction was stopped by adding 100 µl 2N H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> to each well. Absorbance at 450 nm was read using a microplate reader (GENios; Tecan). For Src immunoprecipitation kinase assay, the lysates of HCT116 cells transfected with the control or Flag-RIL vector were incubated with rabbit anti-Src antibody at 4°C for 60 min followed by incubation with protein A/G–agarose beads (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) for 30 min. The kinase activities of Src immunoprecipitates were analyzed as described above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phosphatase assay</title>
        <p>Phosphatase activities associated with RIL were analyzed using <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate as a substrate in an immune complex phosphatase assay as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Pazdrak et al., 1997</xref>). In brief, HCT116 cells were transfected with vectors encoding Flag-tagged wild-type or mutant forms of RIL or Flag vector lacking the RIL sequence as a control. 1 d after the transfection, the cells were lysed in the lysis buffer (1% Triton X-100 in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, containing 150 mM NaCl, 25 mM NaF, 1.75% octylglucopyranoside, 0.1 mM PMSF, 1 µM pepstatin, 5 µg/ml aprotinin, and 1 µg/ml leupeptin) and incubated with 30 µl of anti-Flag antibody (M2)–conjugated beads at 4°C for 3 h. The beads were washed three times with the lysis buffer and three times with the phosphatase buffer (50 mM Hepes, pH 7.2, 60 mM NaCl, 50 mM KCl, 0.1 mM PMSF, 1 µM pepstatin, 5 µg/ml aprotinin, and 1 µg/ml leupeptin). Each sample of the RIL immunoprecipitates or the control immunoprecipitates was incubated with 100 µl of 5 mM <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl phosphate in phosphatase buffer containing 1 mg/ml BSA, 10 mM DTT, and 5 mM EDTA at 30°C. Absorbance at 405 nm was read using a GENios microplate reader.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analysis was performed using the Student's <italic>t</italic> test. A p-value of &lt;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant and is indicated in the figures.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Dr. Donna B. Stolz for assistance in confocal imaging.</p>
      <p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants GM65188 and DK54639 to C. Wu.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>Abbreviations used in this paper: BL, BAS-like; MBP, maltose-binding protein; PTP, protein Tyr phosphatase; RIL, reversion-induced LIM.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aligayer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiss</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curley</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallick</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Activation of Src kinase in primary colorectal carcinoma: an indicator of poor clinical prognosis</article-title>.<source>Cancer.</source>
<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>344</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11900220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veillette</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSeau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Activation of pp60c-src protein kinase activity in human colon carcinoma</article-title>.<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>2251</fpage>–<lpage>2255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2436227</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boumber</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharibyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estey</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kantarjian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Manero</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>RIL, a LIM gene on 5q31, is silenced by methylation in cancer and sensitizes cancer cells to apoptosis</article-title>.<source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1997</fpage>–<lpage>2005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332327</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamps</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisler</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipas</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckhart</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>pp60c-src activation in human colon carcinoma</article-title>.<source>J. Clin. Invest.</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>2025</fpage>–<lpage>2033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2498394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartwright</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisler</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckhart</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Activation of the pp60c-src protein kinase is an early event in colonic carcinogenesis</article-title>.<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2105487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuppen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerrits</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepers</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieringa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>PDZ motifs in PTP-BL and RIL bind to internal protein segments in the LIM domain protein RIL</article-title>.<source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9487134</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeSeau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Analysis of pp60c-src tyrosine kinase activity and phosphotyrosyl phosphatase activity in human colon carcinoma and normal human colon mucosal cells</article-title>.<source>J. Cell. Biochem.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2448318</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dromard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bompard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glondu-Lassis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puech</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalbos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freiss</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The putative tumor suppressor gene PTPN13/PTPL1 induces apoptosis through insulin receptor substrate-1 dephosphorylation</article-title>.<source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>6806</fpage>–<lpage>6813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17638892</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferracini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Analysis of mutant forms of the c-src gene product containing a phenylalanine substitution for tyrosine 416</article-title>.<source>Oncogene Res.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1690870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frame</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Newest findings on the oldest oncogene; how activated src does it</article-title>.<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>117</volume>:<fpage>989</fpage>–<lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14996930</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gkretsi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Physical and functional association of migfilin with cell-cell adhesions</article-title>.<source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonfloni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretzschmar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Superti-Furga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Crosstalk between the catalytic and regulatory domains allows bidirectional regulation of Src</article-title>.<source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiess</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scharm</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguzzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajnal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemenz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarte-Waldhoff</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Expression of ril, a novel LIM domain gene, is down-regulated in Hras-transformed cells and restored in phenotypic revertants</article-title>.<source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7824279</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kmiecik</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalloway</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Activation and suppression of pp60c-src transforming ability by mutation of its primary sites of tyrosine phosphorylation</article-title>.<source>Cell.</source>
<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3103925</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolligs</surname><given-names>F.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>C.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Neoplastic transformation of RK3E by mutant beta-catenin requires deregulation of Tcf/Lef transcription but not activation of c-myc expression</article-title>.<source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>5696</fpage>–<lpage>5706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10409758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopetz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallick</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Src continues aging: current and future clinical directions</article-title>.<source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>7232</fpage>–<lpage>7236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdmann</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eulenburg</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Porthin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heumann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>EphrinB phosphorylation and reverse signaling: regulation by Src kinases and PTP-BL phosphatase</article-title>.<source>Mol. Cell.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11983165</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pazdrak</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Src homology 2 protein tyrosine phosphatase (SHPTP2)/Src homology 2 phosphatase 2 (SHP2) tyrosine phosphatase is a positive regulator of the interleukin 5 receptor signal transduction pathways leading to the prolongation of eosinophil survival</article-title>.<source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254654</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piwnica-Worms</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation regulates the biochemical and biological properties of pp60c-src</article-title>.<source>Cell.</source>
<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3103926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Playford</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The interplay between Src and integrins in normal and tumor biology</article-title>.<source>Oncogene.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>7928</fpage>–<lpage>7946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489911</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolen</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSeau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Analysis of pp60c-src protein kinase activity in human tumor cell lines and tissues</article-title>.<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>261</volume>:<fpage>13754</fpage>–<lpage>13759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3093483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roskoski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Src kinase regulation by phosphorylation and dephosphorylation</article-title>.<source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>331</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russello</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>SRC in human carcinogenesis</article-title>.<source>Front. Biosci.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicheri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pico</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazit</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitzki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuriyan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Crystal structure of Hck in complex with a Src family-selective tyrosine kinase inhibitor</article-title>.<source>Mol. Cell.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10360180</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summy</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallick</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Src family kinases in tumor progression and metastasis</article-title>.<source>Cancer Metastasis Rev.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12884910</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summy</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallick</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Treatment for advanced tumors: Src reclaims center stage</article-title>.<source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1398</fpage>–<lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16533761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Superti-Furga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtneidge</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>A functional screen in yeast for regulators and antagonizers of heterologous protein tyrosine kinases</article-title>.<source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>600</fpage>–<lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugge</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Cellular functions regulated by Src family kinases</article-title>.<source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442882</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Migfilin and mig-2 link focal adhesions to filamin and the actin cytoskeleton and function in cell shape modulation</article-title>.<source>Cell.</source>
<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sager</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ptak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Mutational analysis of the tyrosine phosphatome in colorectal cancers</article-title>.<source>Science.</source>
<volume>304</volume>:<fpage>1164</fpage>–<lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155950</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeatman</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A renaissance for SRC</article-title>.<source>Nat. Rev. Cancer.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15170449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Genetic characterization of fas-associated phosphatase-1 as a putative tumor suppressor gene on chromosome 4q21.3 in hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>.<source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16489062</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Epigenetic disruption of two proapoptotic genes MAPK10/JNK3 and PTPN13/FAP-1 in multiple lymphomas and carcinomas through hypermethylation of a common bidirectional promoter</article-title>.<source>Leukemia.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16572203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>