<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:29:14Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2172036" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2172036</identifier><datestamp>2008-03-05</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2172036</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2172036</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2172036</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096524</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200312118</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200312118</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096524</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Rab13 regulates PKA signaling during tight junction assembly</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Köhler</surname>
            <given-names>Katja</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Louvard</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zahraoui</surname>
            <given-names>Ahmed</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="N0x1ca1990N0x3ffe130">Laboratory of Morphogenesis and Cell Signaling, UMR144 Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Institut Curie, 75248, Paris, Cedex 05, France</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>Address correspondence to Ahmed Zahraoui, Laboratory of Morphogenesis and Cell Signaling, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, UMR144 Institut Curie, 26 rue d'Ulm, 75248, Paris, Cedex 05, France. Tel.: 33-1-42346370. Fax: 33-1-42346377. email: <email>zahraoui@curie.fr</email>
</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>165</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>175</fpage>
      <lpage>180</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2003</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2004, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The GTPase Rab13 regulates the assembly of functional epithelial tight junctions (TJs) through a yet unknown mechanism. Here, we show that expression of the GTP-bound form of Rab13 inhibits PKA-dependent phosphorylation and TJ recruitment of the vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein, an actin remodelling protein. We demonstrate that Rab13GTP directly binds to PKA and inhibits its activity. Interestingly, activation of PKA abrogates the inhibitory effect of Rab13 on the recruitment of vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein, ZO-1, and claudin1 to cell–cell junctions. Rab13 is, therefore, the first GTPase that controls PKA activity and provides an unexpected link between PKA signaling and the dynamics of TJ assembly.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Rab GTPase; phosphorylation; VASP; cell–cell junctions; epithelial cells</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn>
          <p>The online version of this article contains supplemental material.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn>
          <p>Abbreviations used in this paper: aPKCζ, atypical PKCζ; P-VASP, phosphorylated VASP; TJ, tight junction; VASP, vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>During epithelial morphogenesis, the development and organization of cell asymmetry require the assembly of functional tight junctions (TJs). TJs serve as a barrier to the paracellular diffusion and prevent the movement of lipids and membrane proteins between apical and basolateral membranes (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Tsukita et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Matter and Balda, 2003</xref>). They form a network of transmembrane, scaffolding, and signaling molecules that control cell–cell adhesion, cell polarity, proliferation, and differentiation (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Zahraoui et al., 2000</xref>). The TJ transmembrane proteins, claudins, are required for the establishment of TJ gate function (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Tsukita and Furuse, 1999</xref>). Scaffolding proteins such as ZO-1, a PDZ-containing protein, connect transmembrane proteins to the underlying actin cytoskeleton and recruit cytosolic proteins, such as kinases, GTPases, and transcription factors to TJs (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Itoh et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Wittchen et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Balda and Matter, 2000</xref>). The actin cytoskeleton contributes substantially to maintain TJ integrity (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Madara et al., 1992</xref>). In CaCo-2 cells, disruption of actin filaments with cytochalasin D decreases, and stabilization of F-actin increases barrier function (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Madara et al., 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Balda et al., 1993</xref>). Recently, vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein (VASP), a key actin remodelling protein, has been implicated in epithelial TJ biogenesis (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence et al., 2002</xref>). VASP was shown to be a substrate for both PKA and PKG (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Butt et al., 1994</xref>), and phosphorylation of VASP abolishes its interaction with actin and inhibits actin polymerization, assigning VASP a key role in controlling actin dynamics (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Harbeck et al., 2000</xref>). However, the regulatory pathways that link actin cytoskeleton organization to the assembly of TJ still need to be elucidated. Interestingly, activation of the small GTPases, Rho/Rac, induces the reorganization of the perijunctional actin ring and leads to increased paracellular permeability (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Takaishi et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Benais-Pont et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>Another family of small GTPases, Rab proteins, is also involved in regulating TJ dynamics. Rab GTPases seem to regulate specific membrane transport events including vesicle formation, motility via kinesins or myosins, tethering, and fusion (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Pfeffer, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Zerial and McBride, 2001</xref>). We have shown previously that Rab13 is recruited from a cytoplasmic pool to cell–cell contacts at an early stage during TJ assembly (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Zahraoui et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Sheth et al., 2000</xref>). Expression of the active (Rab13Q67L), but not the inactive (Rab13T22N) mutant of Rab13 in epithelial MDCK cells delays the recruitment of TJ proteins, claudin1 and ZO-1, and alters TJ integrity. Interestingly, it does not impair the recruitment of E-cadherin to the lateral membrane (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>). Nevertheless, how Rab13 interferes with TJ structure and function is still unclear. In the present work, we show that the active mutant Rab13Q67L inhibits PKA-mediated phosphorylation of VASP and its recruitment to cell–cell junctions. Moreover, Rab13GTP binds to PKA and inhibits its activity. Our data provide new insights into the molecular mechanisms by which Rab13 regulates TJ assembly in epithelial cells.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Rab13Q67L prevents the recruitment of VASP to TJs</title>
        <p>The effect of GFP-Rab13Q67L on TJ protein recruitment (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>) suggests that Rab13 regulates some aspects of actin cytoskeleton–TJ interactions. Because VASP is involved in the establishment of TJ barrier (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence et al., 2002</xref>), we tested whether Rab13 mutants could affect VASP localization during TJ assembly. We used the Ca<sup>2+</sup> switch protocol, a model system to study TJ assembly. Cells were plated in medium without Ca<sup>2+</sup> for 16 h to dissociate cell–cell junctions, followed by the addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to trigger synchronous junction assembly. The localization of VASP was analyzed by immunofluorescence at 0, 2, and 4 h after induction of cell–cell contacts. In control cells, as well as in cells expressing GFP-Rab13T22N and Q67L mutants, removal of Ca<sup>2+</sup> resulted in the dissociation of cell–cell junctions and redistribution of VASP into the cytoplasm (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Restoration of physiological Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations induced an increased plasma membrane labeling of VASP at sites of cell–cell contacts in cells expressing GFP or GFP-Rab13T22N. In contrast, in GFP-Rab13Q67L cells, within 4 h after the addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, VASP was not detected at cell–cell contacts and was still cytoplasmic (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). This indicated that Rab13Q67L inhibits the recruitment of VASP to sites of cell–cell contacts during junction assembly.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Rab13Q67L inhibits the recruitment of VASP to cell–cell junctions during TJ formation.</bold> MDCK cells expressing GFP, GFP-Rab13T22N, or GFP-Rab13Q67L were incubated for 16 h without Ca<sup>2+</sup>, then Ca<sup>2+</sup> was added back for the time indicated and the cells stained with a monoclonal anti-VASP antibody. Within 2–4 h after the Ca<sup>2+</sup> switch, VASP was detected at cell–cell junctions in cells expressing GFP and GFP-Rab13T22N (arrows), but not in those expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L. Bar, 10 μm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200312118f1"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rab13 controls PKA-dependent phosphorylation of VASP and its subsequent recruitment to cell–cell junctions</title>
        <p>Because phosphorylated VASP (P-VASP) accumulates at cell–cell junctions under conditions that enhance barrier recovery, it was proposed that P-VASP is a component of TJs (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence et al., 2002</xref>). VASP phosphorylation on residue Ser157 results in a conformational change concomitant with a shift in SDS-PAGE mobility from 46 to 50 kD (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Butt et al., 1994</xref>). Thus, we tested whether Rab13Q67L could interfere with VASP phosphorylation. Using a monoclonal anti-VASP antibody that recognizes nonphosphorylated as well as P-VASP, we found that in MDCK cells and cells expressing GFP or GFP-Rab13T22N, both forms of VASP were detected. In contrast, in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L, only the 46-kD band corresponding to the nonphosphorylated form of VASP was detected (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). This indicates that GFP-Rab13Q67L inhibited phosphorylation of VASP at Ser157. To confirm these results, the same cell lysates used in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A were blotted with an anti-VASP antibody that specifically recognizes VASP phosphorylated at Ser157 (P-VASP). This antibody detected the 50-kD band corresponding to P-VASP in cells expressing GFP-Rab13T22N and in control cells, whereas no P-VASP specific band was observed in GFP-Rab13Q67L cell lysate (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B). Thus, the expression of Rab13Q67L specifically inhibits the phosphorylation of VASP at Ser157 in MDCK cells.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>The activated form of Rab13 inhibits phosphorylation of VASP.</bold> (A) Lysates from MDCK or cells expressing GFP, GFP-Rab13T22N, or GFP-Rab13Q67L were blotted with the monoclonal anti-VASP antibody recognizing both the phosphorylated (50 kD) and non phosphorylated (46 kD) form of VASP. In GFP-Rab13Q67L cells, the 50-kD band was not detected. (B) The same lysates as in A were blotted with a specific antibody recognizing VASP phosphorylated at Ser157 (P-VASP). Note that P-VASP was absent in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L. Similar results were obtained from three independent GFP-Rab13T22N and GFP-Rab13Q67L mutants.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200312118f2"/>
        </fig>
        <p>VASP phosphorylation at Ser157 was observed upon stimulation of PKA or PKG (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Burkhardt et al., 2000</xref>). To determine which kinase is responsible for the Rab13-dependent phosphorylation of VASP, we examined the effect of specific kinase inhibitors and activators on VASP phosphorylation. As shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A, incubation with both PKG and PKC inhibitors did not significantly reduce the phosphorylation of VASP in control cells or cells expressing GFP-Rab13T22N. In contrast, incubation with the PKA inhibitor H89 decreased the amount of P-VASP in a dose-dependent manner, indicating that the effect on VASP-phosphorylation is specific. Moreover, treatment of cells expressing Rab13Q67L with 8-Br-cGMP, an activator of PKG, did not induce phosphorylation of VASP in those cells. Conversely, activation of PKA by either 8-Br-cAMP or Forskolin restored VASP phosphorylation in GFP-Rab13Q67L cells as monitored by the presence of the 50-kD band of VASP (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B). These data indicate that Rab13-dependent phosphorylation of VASP in MDCK cells is mediated by PKA, but not PKC or PKG.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Rab13 regulates PKA-mediated VASP phosphorylation, thereby controlling VASP recruitment to cell–cell junctions.</bold> (A) PKA inhibition decreases VASP phosphorylation. MDCK or cells expressing GFP or GFP-Rab13T22N were treated with inhibitors of PKG (KT5823), PKC (Rö-32-0432), or PKA (H89) and the lysates blotted for VASP. (B) Activation of PKA by Forskolin or cAMP, but not that of PKG by cGMP restores VASP phosphorylation in Rab13Q67L cells. Cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L were incubated with Forskolin (Fsk), 8-Br-cAMP or 8-Br-cGMP and VASP was detected by immunoblot. Nontreated cells were blotted as a control. (C) Cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L or GFP-Rab13T22N were treated with Forskolin (Fsk) or the PKA inhibitor (H89), respectively, and analyzed by immunofluorescence with the anti–P-VASP antibody. P-VASP was not detected at cell–cell junctions in Rab13Q67L cells, but relocated to TJ upon PKA activation. Inhibition of PKA removed P-VASP from cell–cell contacts in cells expressing Rab13T22N. P-VASP was found in cell–cell contacts where junctional complexes developed with neighboring cells (arrows), and absent from the edges of cells devoid of junctional complexes (arrowheads). Bar, 10 μm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200312118f3"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To investigate whether VASP phosphorylation is required for its recruitment to cell–cell junctions, MDCK cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L or GFP-Rab13T22N were incubated with Forskolin and H89, respectively, and P-VASP localization was examined by immunofluorescence using the antibody recognizing P-VASP. In the absence of Forskolin, no P-VASP could be detected at cell–cell junctions in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> C). However, activation of PKA by Forskolin restored the recruitment of P-VASP to cell–cell junctions in those cells. In contrast, in cells expressing GFP-Rab13T22N, P-VASP was detected at cell–cell junctions. Treatment of those cells with the specific PKA inhibitor H89 removed P-VASP from cell–cell junctions (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> C). Overall, our results demonstrate that activation of Rab13 inhibits PKA-mediated phosphorylation of VASP and prevents its association with intercellular junctions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Activation of PKA abolishes the inhibitory effect of Rab13Q67L on the recruitment of TJ proteins, ZO-1 and claudin1</title>
        <p>To determine whether the effect of Rab13 on claudin1 and ZO-1 recruitment could be mediated by PKA, we examined the consequences of PKA activation on the recruitment of ZO-1 and claudin1 in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L using the Ca<sup>2+</sup> switch assay. In control cells as well as in cells expressing GFP-Rab13T22N or GFP-Rab13Q67L, removal of Ca<sup>2+</sup> resulted in the dissociation of cell–cell junctions and redistribution of ZO-1 and claudin1 into the cytoplasm (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). By 2 h after addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, ZO-1 immunoreactivity was already detected at cell–cell junctions in cells expressing GFP and GFP-Rab13T22N. In contrast, expression of GFP-Rab13Q67L delayed slightly the recruitment of ZO-1; ZO-1 labeling was discontinuous along the lateral membrane. By 4 h after readdition of calcium, ZO-1 staining was detected at the plasma membrane, but some ZO-1 immunoreactivity was still observed in the cytoplasm in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A). Similarly, plasma membrane recruitment of claudin1 was delayed in cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L. Within 6–12 h after readdition of calcium, most of the claudin1 staining was still cytoplasmic in GFP-Rab13Q67L cells, whereas claudin1 was detected at the plasma membrane in cells expressing GFP or GFP-Rab13T22N (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> B). Significantly, activation of PKA with Forskolin restored the kinetics of both ZO-1 and claudin1 recruitment to the lateral membrane in GFP-Rab13Q67L cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). This indicates that PKA activation abolished the inhibitory effect of Rab13GTP on the recruitment of TJ proteins, leading to their accumulation at cell–cell junctions. Our data establish that the Rab13–PKA signaling complex plays a key role in TJ biogenesis. They further confirm that PKA-dependent phosphorylation is implicated in the dynamics of epithelial TJ.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>PKA activation abolishes the inhibitory effect of Rab13Q67L on the recruitment of ZO-1 and claudin1.</bold> Cells expressing GFP, GFP-Rab13T22N, or GFP-Rab13Q67L were grown without Ca<sup>2+</sup> for 16 h and subsequently incubated in normal medium for the time indicated in the absence or presence of Forskolin (Fsk). The localization of (A) ZO-1 and (B) claudin1 was analyzed by immunofluorescence. In cells expressing Rab13Q67L, the recruitment of ZO-1 and claudin1 to cell–cell junctions was delayed. Forskolin treatment restored ZO-1 and claudin1 recruitment in those cells. Bars, 10 μm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200312118f4"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Rab13GTP binds to the PKA catalytic subunit and inhibits its activity in vitro</title>
        <p>Given that Rab13 interferes with PKA signaling in the regulation of TJ assembly, we wondered whether and how Rab13 interacts with PKA. Thus, we performed a GST pull-down assay from MDCK cell lysates using GST-Rab13 fusion proteins. GST alone or GST-Rab13 were immobilized on glutathione beads, preloaded either with GDP or GTPγS (a poorly hydrolysable GTP analogue), and incubated with MDCK cell lysates. The proteins retained on the beads were separated on SDS-PAGE and blotted with an antibody against the α catalytic subunit of PKA. As shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> A, the α catalytic subunit of PKA, but not atypical PKCζ (aPKCζ), was preferentially recovered with GST-Rab13 loaded with GTPγS, whereas GST alone did not interact with PKA or aPKCζ. To verify whether the Rab13–PKA interaction is direct, GST-Rab13 loaded with GDP, GTPγS, or GST alone were incubated with a purified preparation of PKA catalytic subunit. Blotting with the anti-PKA antibody revealed that PKA preferentially bound to GST-Rab13-GTPγS, but neither to GST alone, nor to GST-Rab6GTPγS (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> B), indicating that Rab13 interacts directly and specifically with the PKA catalytic subunit.</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Rab13GTP interacts in vitro directly with PKA and inhibits its activity.</bold> (A) MDCK cell lysates were incubated with GST or GST-Rab13 fusion proteins preloaded with GDP or GTPγS. The retained proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with antibodies against the α catalytic subunit of PKA or aPKCζ. Equal loading was confirmed by ponceau staining. (B) GST-Rab13 or GST-Rab6 preloaded with GDP, GTPγS, or GST was incubated with the purified catalytic subunit of PKA. Proteins bound to the beads were separated by SDS-PAGE and blotted with the anti-PKA antibody. 48% of the PKA was recovered with GST-Rab13-GTPγS. (C) VASP immunoprecipitate from cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L was incubated in an in vitro kinase assay with the purified catalytic subunit of PKA in the presence of PKI (a peptide inhibitor of PKA), GST-Rab13-GTPγS, or GST. Samples were subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted with the anti-VASP antibody recognizing both phosphorylated and non–P-VASP.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200312118f5"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Because the GTP bound form of Rab13 inhibits PKA-dependent VASP phosphorylation in vivo, we next determined whether Rab13GTP interferes with PKA activity in vitro. VASP was immunoprecipitated from cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L and used as a physiologically relevant substrate for PKA in a kinase assay. PKI, a potent peptide inhibitor of PKA, was used as a positive control in these experiments. Incubation of VASP with the catalytic subunit of PKA induced VASP phosphorylation in vitro, resulting in a shift in SDS-PAGE mobility from 46 to 50 kD (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> C). Similarly to PKI, GST-Rab13-GTPγS caused a strong inhibition of PKA activity, whereas GST alone had no effect. The results in vitro are concordant with those in vivo and demonstrate that Rab13 is able to inhibit PKA activity.</p>
        <p>In this paper, we identified PKA as a new effector for the small GTPase Rab13. Our data demonstrate that the GTP bound form of Rab13 directly binds and negatively controls PKA activity both in vitro and in vivo. This is the first demonstration of a biochemical and functional link between a small Rab GTPase and the PKA catalytic subunit.</p>
        <p>Protein phosphorylation/dephosphorylation events are required for the regulation of TJ dynamics (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Sakakibara et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Matter and Balda, 2003</xref>). In these processes, VASP may play a key role due to its differential actin binding capacities depending on its state of phosphorylation. Phosphorylation of VASP by PKA reduces VASP–actin interactions and promotes the association of P-VASP with cell–cell junctions. Interestingly, VASP is required for the establishment of cell–cell contacts (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Vasioukhin et al., 2000</xref>). Although Rab13 does not affect the recruitment of E-cadherin (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>) and β-catenin to cell–cell junctions (Fig. S1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200312118/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200312118/DC1</ext-link>), we cannot rule out the possibility that Rab13 alters TJ assembly through regulating the recruitment of other adherens junction components. We suggest that Rab13GTP could locally influence actin rearrangement by controlling PKA-dependent VASP phosphorylation and hence inhibit TJ integrity. Our previous data suggested that Rab13, in its GTP-bound form, interacts with an effector that inhibits the recruitment of claudin1 and, to a lesser extent, that of ZO-1 to TJ. Conversely, the inactive form Rab13T22N, unable to bind the effector, favors the establishment of TJ gate and fence functions (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>). The inhibitory effect of the Rab13Q67L mutant on TJ assembly and function could thus be explained by the inhibition of PKA activity. The Rab13–PKA signaling complex may as well regulate vesicle docking near cell–cell junctions. Indeed, PKA activity has been shown to be required for membrane trafficking (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Pimplikar and Simons, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Rodionov et al., 2003</xref>). Therefore, our observations allow us to postulate the existence of a new signaling cascade at the TJ implicating Rab13–PKA in the dynamics of TJ assembly. They also highlight novel insights into the role of Rab proteins in membrane–cytoskeleton interactions.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Antibodies</title>
        <p>Anti-VASP mAb was purchased from BD Transduction Laboratories; monoclonal anti-VASP antibody specific for VASP phosphorylated at Ser157 was purchased from NanoTools; polyclonal anti–ZO-1 and anti–claudin-1 antibodies were purchased from Zymed Laboratories; anti-PKA α cat and anti-PKCζ pAbs were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. Secondary antibodies coupled to Cy2 or Cy5 were purchased from Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cell culture</title>
        <p>MDCK cells (clone II) were cultured in DME supplemented with 10% FCS, 2 mM glutamine, 100 U/ml penicillin, and 10 mg/ml streptomycin. The cells were incubated at 37°C under 10% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere. MDCK cells stably expressing GFP, GFP-Rab13T22N, or GFP-Rab13Q67L were described previously (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Incubation with kinase inhibitors/activators</title>
        <p>500,000 cells were plated onto 3.5-cm diam culture plates overnight and incubated as follows: 1 h at 37°C with 30 μM of PKA inhibitor H-89; 30 min with the PKC and PKG inhibitors Rö-32-0432 (10 μM) or KT5823 (5 μM; Calbiochem); 30 min with 100 μM cAMP or cGMP; or 20 min with 10 μM Forskolin (Sigma-Aldrich). Cells were washed three times in PBS and subjected to either immunofluorescence or immunoblotting procedures. We confirmed that Rö-32-0432 is effective in inhibiting PKC activity under these conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> switch experiments</title>
        <p>MDCK cells expressing GFP or GFP-Rab13T22N and GFP-Rab13Q67L mutants were plated at a density of 10,000,000 cells/cm<sup>2</sup>, and incubated for 16 h in S-MEM medium without Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Cells were rinsed with normal DME, incubated in DME for the indicated time and analyzed by immunofluorescence. When the effect of PKA activation/inhibition was studied, Forskolin and H89 were added to DME after the Ca<sup>2+</sup>depletion.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunofluorescence microscopy</title>
        <p>Immunofluorescence was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Marzesco et al., 2002</xref>). The samples were analyzed with a fluorescence microscope (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging Inc.) and further processed with Adobe Photoshop Software.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting</title>
        <p>500,000 MDCK or cells expressing GFP, GFP-Rab13T22N, or GFP-Rab13T22N were grown on 3.5-cm diam culture plates for 16 h, washed three times with ice-cold PBS, and extracted in 0.5% Triton, 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.6, 120 mM NaCl, 25 mM KCl, 1.8 mM CaCl, 1 mM sodium vanadate, 50 mM NaF, and a mixture of protease inhibitors (Sigma-Aldrich) on a rocker platform for 30 min at 4°C. In the GST pull-down experiments, cells were grown on 10-cm diam culture plates for 3 d, washed in PBS, and extracted in the same buffer containing 1% NP-40 instead of Triton X-100. Solubilized material was recovered by pelleting at 18.000 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4°C. Supernatants were collected and protein concentration determined using the protein assay kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories). For immunoprecipitation, cells expressing GFP-Rab13Q67L were grown for 3 d on 10-cm diam culture plates, washed with PBS, and extracted in IP buffer (50 mM NaCl, 25 mM Tris, pH 8, 1 mM EDTA, 0.25% Triton, 1 mM sodium vanadate, 50 mM NaF, and protease inhibitors). After centrifugation, supernantants were incubated with 5 μg of anti-VASP antibody over night at 4°C. Protein G agarose beads were added for 2 h and the beads washed three times with IP buffer. Equal amount of protein were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred electrophoretically to nitrocellulose filters. Filters were probed with anti-VASP or anti–P-VASP antibodies before ECL detection according to the manufacturer's protocols (Pierce Chemical Co.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>GST pull-down assay</title>
        <p>GST-Rab13 fusion protein was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified according to the manufacturer's protocol (Amersham Biosciences). GST-Rab13 bound to glutathione beads was loaded with 1 mM GDP or GTPγS (a poorly hydrolyzable GTP analogue) for 90 min at RT in incubation buffer (100 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris, 10 mM EDTA, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1 mM DTT, pH 7.6). After washing, beads were incubated overnight with MDCK cell extracts at 4°C. To prove the direct interaction of Rab13 with PKA, 100 μg of purified PKA catalytic subunit from bovine heart (Sigma-Aldrich) was incubated with a 10-fold molar excess of purified GST, GST-Rab13-GDP, or GST-Rab13-GTPγS proteins in the incubation buffer overnight at 4°C. GST-Rab6 (a gift from B. Goud and S. Monier, UMR144 Institut Curie) was used as negative control. After washing, the extent of PKA binding was determined by SDS-PAGE and Western blotting using polyclonal anti-PKA α cat or anti-PKCζ antibodies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>In vitro kinase assay</title>
        <p>10 U of purified PKA catalytic subunit was incubated with VASP immunoprecipitate and either 1 μg of protein kinase inhibitor peptide, PKI (Sigma-Aldrich), and 10 μg of purified GST-Rab13 loaded with GTPγS or GST in kinase buffer (100 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM ATP) for 30 min at 30°C. The reaction was stopped by adding 3× SDS sample buffer, separated on SDS-PAGE, and VASP phosphorylation determined by Western blot using the anti-VASP antibody.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Online supplemental material</title>
        <p>The online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200312118/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200312118/DC1</ext-link>. Fig. S1 shows that Rab13 mutants do neither alter the recruitment of adherens junction proteins such as (A) β-catenin or (B) afadin nor (C) cortical actin in a calcium switch experiment. Anti–β-catenin and anti-afadin antibodies were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich and BD Transduction Laboratories, respectively. Phalloidin was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. Supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.jcb200312118/DC1">http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.jcb200312118/DC1</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We are grateful to Dr. S. Pfeffer for critical reading of the manuscript, and to Drs. B. Goud and S. Monier for the GST-Rab6 fusion protein.</p>
      <p>This work was supported by grants from Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Institut Curie, and the Association pour la Recherche sur le Cancer (ARC 3457) to A. Zahraoui. K. Köhler is a recipient of a fellowship from the Swiss National Science Foundation.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Balda, M.S., L. Gonzalez-Mariscal, K. Matter, M. Cereijido, and J.M. Anderson. <year>1993</year>. Assembly of the tight junction: the role of diacylglycerol. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>–302.
<?supplied-pmid 8408213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8408213</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Balda, M.S., and K. Matter. <year>2000</year>. The tight junction protein ZO-1 and an interacting transcription factor regulate ErbB-2 expression. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2024</fpage>–2033.
<?supplied-pmid 10790369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10790369</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Benais-Pont, G., A. Punn, C. Flores-Maldonado, J. Eckert, G. Raposo, T.P. Fleming, M. Cereijido, M.S. Balda, and K. Matter. <year>2003</year>. Identification of a tight junction–associated guanine nucleotide exchange factor that activates Rho and regulates paracellular permeability. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>–740.
<?supplied-pmid 12604587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604587</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Burkhardt, M., M. Glazova, S. Gambaryan, T. Vollkommer, E. Butt, B. Bader, K. Heermeier, T.M. Lincoln, U. Walter, and A. Palmetshofer. <year>2000</year>. KT5823 inhibits cGMP-dependent protein kinase activity in vitro but not in intact human platelets and rat mesangial cells. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>33536</fpage>–33541.
<?supplied-pmid 10922374?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10922374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Butt, E., K. Abel, M. Krieger, D. Palm, V. Hoppe, J. Hoppe, and U. Walter. <year>1994</year>. cAMP- and cGMP-dependent protein kinase phosphorylation sites of the focal adhesion vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein (VASP) in vitro and in intact human platelets. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>14509</fpage>–14517.
<?supplied-pmid 8182057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8182057</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Harbeck, B., S. Huttelmaier, K. Schluter, B.M. Jockusch, and S. Illenberger. <year>2000</year>. Phosphorylation of the vasodilator-stimulated phosphoprotein regulates its interaction with actin. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>275</volume>:<fpage>30817</fpage>–30825.
<?supplied-pmid 10882740?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Itoh, M., M. Furuse, K. Morita, K. Kubota, M. Saitou, and S. Tsukita. <year>1999</year>. Direct binding of three tight junction-associated MAGUKs, ZO-1, ZO-2, and ZO-3, with the COOH termini of claudins. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>1351</fpage>–1363.
<?supplied-pmid 10601346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lawrence, D.W., K.M. Comerford, and S.P. Colgan. <year>2002</year>. Role of VASP in reestablishment of epithelial tight junction assembly after Ca<sup>2+</sup> switch. <source>Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol.</source>
<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>C1235</fpage>–C1245.
<?supplied-pmid 11997237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997237</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Madara, J.L., D. Barenberg, and S. Carlson. <year>1986</year>. Effects of cytochalasin D on occluding junctions of intestinal absorptive cells: further evidence that the cytoskeleton may influence paracellular permeability and junctional charge selectivity. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>2125</fpage>–2136.
<?supplied-pmid 3711143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3711143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Madara, J.L., C. Parkos, S. Colgan, A. Nusrat, K. Atisook, and P. Kaoutzani. <year>1992</year>. The movement of solutes and cells across tight junctions. <source>Ann. NY Acad. Sci.</source>
<volume>664</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>–60.
<?supplied-pmid 1456668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1456668</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Marzesco, A.M., I. Dunia, R. Pandjaitan, M. Recouvreur, D. Dauzonne, E.L. Benedetti, D. Louvard, and A. Zahraoui. <year>2002</year>. The small GTPase Rab13 regulates assembly of functional tight junctions in epithelial cells. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1819</fpage>–1831.
<?supplied-pmid 12058051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12058051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Matter, K., and M.S. Balda. <year>2003</year>. Signalling to and from tight junctions. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>–236.
<?supplied-pmid 12612641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pfeffer, S.R. <year>2001</year>. Rab GTPases: specifying and deciphering organelle identity and function. <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>–491.
<?supplied-pmid 11719054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719054</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pimplikar, S.W., and K. Simons. <year>1994</year>. Activators of protein kinase A stimulate apical but not basolateral transport in epithelial Madin-Darby canine kidney cells. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>19054</fpage>–19059.
<?supplied-pmid 8034664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8034664</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Rodionov, V., J. Yi, A. Kashina, A. Oladipo, and S.P. Gross. <year>2003</year>. Switching between microtubule- and actin-based transport systems in melanophores is controlled by cAMP levels. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1837</fpage>–1847.
<?supplied-pmid 14588239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14588239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sakakibara, A., M. Furuse, M. Saitou, Y. Ando-Akatsuka, and S. Tsukita. <year>1997</year>. Possible involvement of phosphorylation of occludin in tight junction formation. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>137</volume>:<fpage>1393</fpage>–1401.
<?supplied-pmid 9182670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9182670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sheth, B., J.J. Fontaine, E. Ponza, A. McCallum, A. Page, S. Citi, D. Louvard, A. Zahraoui, and T.P. Fleming. <year>2000</year>. Differentiation of the epithelial apical junctional complex during mouse preimplantation development: a role for rab13 in the early maturation of the tight junction. <source>Mech. Dev.</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>–104.
<?supplied-pmid 11025210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11025210</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Takaishi, K., T. Sasaki, H. Kotani, H. Nishioka, and Y. Takai. <year>1997</year>. Regulation of cell–cell adhesion by rac and rho small G proteins in MDCK cells. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>1047</fpage>–1059.
<?supplied-pmid 9362522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9362522</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tsukita, S., and M. Furuse. <year>1999</year>. Occludin and claudins in tight-junction strands: leading or supporting players? <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>–273.
<?supplied-pmid 10370242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10370242</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tsukita, S., M. Furuse, and M. Itoh. <year>2001</year>. Multifunctional strands in tight junctions. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>–293.
<?supplied-pmid 11283726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283726</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vasioukhin, V., C. Bauer, M. Yin, and E. Fuchs. <year>2000</year>. Directed actin polymerization is the driving force for epithelial cell-cell adhesion. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–219.
<?supplied-pmid 10660044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10660044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wittchen, E.S., J. Haskins, and B.R. Stevenson. <year>1999</year>. Protein interactions at the tight junction. Actin has multiple binding partners, and ZO-1 forms independent complexes with ZO-2 and ZO-3. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>35179</fpage>–35185.
<?supplied-pmid 10575001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10575001</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zahraoui, A., G. Joberty, M. Arpin, J.J. Fontaine, R. Hellio, A. Tavitian, and D. Louvard. <year>1994</year>. A small rab GTPase is distributed in cytoplasmic vesicles in non polarized cells but colocalizes with the tight junction marker ZO-1 in polarized epithelial cells. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>–115.
<?supplied-pmid 8294494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8294494</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zahraoui, A., D. Louvard, and T. Galli. <year>2000</year>. Tight junction, a platform for trafficking and signaling protein complexes. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>F31</fpage>–F36.
<?supplied-pmid 11086016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11086016</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zerial, M., and H. McBride. <year>2001</year>. Rab proteins as membrane organizers. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>–117.
<?supplied-pmid 11252952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11252952</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>