<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:33:18Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2615523" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2615523</identifier><datestamp>2009-01-16</datestamp><setSpec>jbc</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2615523</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2615523</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2615523</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015261</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1772</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M807083200</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Protein Synthesis, Post-Translational Modification, and  Degradation</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Multiple Anaphase-promoting Complex/Cyclosome Degrons Mediate the
 Degradation of Human
 Sgo1<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Karamysheva</surname>
            <given-names>Zemfira</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Diaz-Martinez</surname>
            <given-names>Laura A.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Crow</surname>
            <given-names>Sara E.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Bing</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yu</surname>
            <given-names>Hongtao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="N0x1c6ed90N0x37799b0">Department of Pharmacology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University
 of Texas Southwestern Medical Center at Dallas, Dallas, Texas, 75390</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="cor1">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>
 An Investigator at the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. To whom correspondence
 should be addressed: Dept. of Pharmacology, UT Southwestern Medical Center,
 6001 Forest Park Rd, Dallas, TX 75390-9041. Tel.: 214-645-6161; Fax:
 214-645-6156; E-mail:
 <email>hongtao.yu@utsouthwestern.edu</email>.
 </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the copyright element. -->
      <volume>284</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>1772</fpage>
      <lpage>1780</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2009, The American Society for Biochemistry and
 Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p>
            <italic>Author's Choice</italic>
          </p>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
 Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author
 Choice Articles</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zbc00309001772.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shugoshin 1 (Sgo1) protects centromeric sister-chromatid cohesion in early
 mitosis and, thus, prevents premature sister-chromatid separation. The protein
 level of Sgo1 is regulated during the cell cycle; it peaks in mitosis and is
 down-regulated in G<sub>1</sub>/S. Here we show that Sgo1 is degraded during
 the exit from mitosis, and its degradation depends on the anaphase-promoting
 complex/cyclosome (APC/C). Overexpression of Cdh1 reduces the protein levels
 of ectopically expressed Sgo1 in human cells. Sgo1 is ubiquitinated by APC/C
 bound to Cdh1 (APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>) <italic>in vitro</italic>. We have further
 identified two functional degradation motifs in Sgo1; that is, a KEN
 (Lys-Glu-Asn) box and a destruction box (D box). Although removal of either
 motif is not sufficient to stabilize Sgo1, Sgo1 with both KEN box and D box
 deleted is stable in cells. Surprisingly, mitosis progresses normally in the
 presence of non-degradable Sgo1, indicating that degradation of Sgo1 is not
 required for sister-chromatid separation or mitotic exit. Finally, we show
 that the spindle checkpoint kinase Bub1 contributes to the maintenance of Sgo1
 steady-state protein levels in an APC/C-independent mechanism.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>This work was supported, in whole or in part, by <grant-sponsor>National
 Institutes of Health</grant-sponsor> Grant
 <grant-num>GM76481</grant-num>. This work was also supported by the
 <grant-sponsor>March of Dimes Foundation</grant-sponsor>, the
 <grant-sponsor>Welch Foundation</grant-sponsor>, and the
 <grant-sponsor>Leukemia and Lymphoma Society</grant-sponsor>. The costs of
 publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page
 charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked
 “<italic>advertisement</italic>” in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734
 solely to indicate this fact.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2">
          <label/>
          <p><italic>Author's Choice</italic>—Final version full
 access.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Loss of sister-chromatid cohesion triggers chromosome segregation in
 mitosis and occurs in two steps in vertebrate cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>).
 In prophase, cohesin is phosphorylated by mitotic kinases including Plk1 and
 removed from chromosome arms
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>). Then, cleavage of
 centromeric cohesin by separase takes place at the metaphase-to-anaphase
 transition to allow sister-chromatid separation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>). The shugoshin (Sgo) family
 of proteins plays an important role in the protection of centromeric cohesion
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>). Human cells depleted of
 Sgo1 by RNAi undergo massive chromosome missegregation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>).
 In cells with compromised Sgo1 function, centromeric cohesin is improperly
 phosphorylated and removed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>), resulting in premature
 sister-chromatid separation. It has been shown recently that Sgo1 collaborates
 with PP2A to counteract the action of Plk1 and other mitotic kinases and to
 protect centromeric cohesin from premature removal
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>).
 In addition, Sgo1 has also been shown to promote stable
 kinetochore-microtubule attachment and sense tension across sister
 kinetochores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>). Thus, Sgo1 is crucial for
 mitotic progression and chromosome segregation.</p>
    <p>Orderly progression through mitosis is regulated by the anaphase-promoting
 complex/cyclosome
 (APC/C),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref> a large
 multiprotein ubiquitin ligase that targets key mitotic regulators for
 destruction by the proteasome
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>). APC/C selects substrates
 for ubiquitination by using the Cdc20 or Cdh1 activator proteins to recognize
 specific sequences called APC/C degrons within target proteins
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>). Several APC/C degrons
 have been characterized, including the destruction box (D box) and the
 Lys-Glu-Asn box (KEN box) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>). The D box, with the
 consensus amino acid sequence of R<italic>XX</italic>L<italic>XXX</italic>N(<italic>X</italic>
 indicates any amino acid), are found in many APC/C substrates, including
 mitotic cyclins and are essential for their ubiquitin-mediated destruction.
 The KEN box, which contains a consensus KEN motif, is also found in several
 APC/C substrates and is preferentially but not exclusively recognized by
 APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>. When APC/C is active, it directs progression through and
 exit from mitosis by catalyzing the ubiquitination and timely destruction of
 mitotic regulators, including cyclin A, cyclin B, and the separase inhibitor
 securin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>). The APC/C
 activity needs to be tightly controlled to prevent unscheduled substrate
 degradation. An important mechanism for APC/C regulation is the spindle
 checkpoint, which prevents the activation of APC/C and destruction of its
 substrates in response to kinetochores that have not properly attached to the
 mitotic spindle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>).</p>
    <p>Recent evidence shows that Sgo1 is a substrate of APC/C, and its protein
 levels oscillate during the cell cycle
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). In this article we study
 the degradation of Sgo1 in human cells. We show that Sgo1 is degraded during
 mitotic exit, and this degradation depends on APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>. We further
 show that both KEN and D boxes are required for Sgo1 degradation <italic>in
 vivo</italic> and ubiquitination <italic>in vitro</italic>. Removal of these motifs
 stabilizes Sgo1 <italic>in vivo</italic>. The prolonged presence of stable Sgo1
 protein in human cells does not change the kinetics of chromosome segregation
 and mitotic exit. Therefore, a timely scheduled degradation of Sgo1 takes
 place but is not required for mitotic exit. Finally, we show that Bub1
 regulates Sgo1 protein levels through a mechanism that does not involve
 APC/C-mediated degradation.</p>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title>
      <p><italic>Antibodies and Immunoblotting</italic>—The production of α-Sgo1
 and α-APC2 antibodies was described previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). The following antibodies
 were purchased from commercial sources: CREST (ImmunoVision), α-cyclin
 B1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology), α-HA and α-Myc (Roche Applied
 Science). For immunoblotting, the antibodies were used at 1:2000 dilution for
 crude sera or 1 μg/ml for purified IgG.</p>
      <p><italic>Mammalian Cell Culture, Drug Treatments, and
 Transfection</italic>—HeLa Tet-On (Clontech) cells were grown in Dulbecco's
 modified Eagle's medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum
 and 10 m<sc>m l</sc>-glutamine. To arrest cells at G<sub>1</sub>/S, cells
 were incubated in growth medium containing 2 m<sc>m</sc> thymidine (Sigma)
 for 18 h. To arrest cells in mitosis, cells were treated with 300
 n<sc>m</sc> nocodazole (Sigma) for 16-18 h or as indicated. Cycloheximide
 was added to the medium when needed at a concentration of 50
 μ<sc>m</sc>.</p>
      <p>Plasmid transfection was performed when cells reached 50% confluency using
 the Effectene reagent (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocols. The
 plasmids were derived from pCS2-Myc or pCS2-HA. For RNAi experiments, HeLa
 cells were transfected using Lipofectamine RNAiMax (Invitrogen) according to
 manufacturer's protocols and analyzed 36-48 h after transfection. For RNAi
 experiments, the siRNA were chemically synthesized at Dharmacon. The sequences
 of the siRNAs used in this study are Bub1-targeting siRNA oligonucleotide
 (GAGUGAUCACGAUUUCUAUTT) and Sgo1 siRNA (GAGGGGACCCUUUUACAGATT).</p>
      <p>To establish stable cell lines, HeLa Tet-On cells were transfected with
 pTRE2-Myc based plasmids encoding Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ΔKEN/ΔDB2</sup>, and selection of stable clones was
 performed in the presence of 300 μg/ml hygromycin. The surviving clones
 were screened for the induced expression of corresponding Myc-tagged proteins
 in the absence or presence of 1 μg/ml doxycycline (Clontech).</p>
      <p><italic>Immunofluorescence and Metaphase Chromosome Spreads</italic>—Mitotic
 cells were harvested by shake-off and swelled in a prewarmed hypotonic
 solution containing 55 m<sc>m</sc> KCl for 15 min at 37 °C. Cells were
 spun onto microscope slides at 1500 rpm for 4 min using a Shandon Cytospin
 centrifuge. Chromosomes were fixed and stained as described
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>). Images were acquired and
 processed with the Slidebook software (Intelligent Imaging) and pseudocolored
 in Photoshop. A series of z-stack images were captured at 0.2-0.3-μm
 intervals and deconvolved using the nearest neighbor algorithm. The maximum
 <italic>z</italic>-projection is then created for the deconvolved images. For the
 analysis of chromosome morphology, a Giemsa staining protocol was used as
 described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>).</p>
      <p><italic>In Vitro Translation and Ubiquitination Assays</italic>—The <italic>in
 vitro</italic> transcription and translation system was purchased from Promega,
 and the reactions were performed according to the manufacturer's instructions.
 Briefly, 80 ng of plasmid DNA, nuclease-free water, 0.2 μl of
 [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine (10 μCi/μl), and 4 μl of rabbit
 reticulocyte lysate were mixed to give a final volume of 5 μl. The reaction
 mixture was incubated at 30 °C for 90 min.</p>
      <p>The interphase APC/C was purified from interphase <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg
 extracts using anti-APC3/Cdc27 antibody coupled to protein A support as
 described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). The expression and
 purification of human Cdc20 and Cdh1 proteins from Sf9 cells were described
 previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>). Each ubiquitination assay
 contained a 5-μl mixture of an energy-regenerating system, 150
 μ<sc>m</sc> ubiquitin, 5 μ<sc>m</sc> recombinant
 ubiquitin-activating enzyme, 2 μ<sc>m</sc> recombinant UbcH10, 1 μl of
 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed and translated substrates, and 3 μl of the
 APC/C beads.</p>
      <p><italic>Live-cell Imaging</italic>—For live-cell imaging, eGFP-H2B-expressing
 cells were plated in 4-well chambered coverslips (LabTek) and synchronized in
 early S-phase by thymidine arrest for 18 h and released into fresh medium just
 before filming. Doxycycline was added to induce Sgo1 expression 24 h before
 filming. Cells were imaged in CO<sub>2</sub>-independent medium (Invitrogen)
 at 37 °C using a Deltavision microscope. 3 <italic>z</italic>-stacks were acquired
 every 2 min for 24 h. Image manipulations were performed in ImageJ (contrast
 enhancement, cropping, and conversion to Quicktime).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <p><italic>Sgo1 Is Degraded during Mitotic Exit, and Its Degradation Depends on
 Cdh1</italic>—Previous studies have shown that the protein level of Sgo1 in
 nocodazole-arrested mitotic cells is higher than that of Sgo1 in cells
 enriched in G<sub>1</sub>/S phase by thymidine arrest
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>), suggesting that Sgo1
 levels are regulated during the cell cycle. To confirm this finding, we
 examined Sgo1 steady-state levels in synchronized cell cultures. HeLa cells
 were arrested in mitosis by nocodazole treatment and released into fresh
 medium. Then cells were harvested at different time points, and Sgo1 proteins
 levels were analyzed by Western blotting. The Sgo1 protein level was high in
 mitosis but dropped sharply upon nocodazole release
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). In
 contrast, the protein level of Apc2 remained unchanged, serving as a loading
 control. The Sgo1 profile during this experiment was similar to that of cyclin
 B1. Many proteins, including cyclin B1, undergo rapid degradation during
 mitotic exit to coordinate exit from mitosis. A sharp decrease in Sgo1 protein
 level suggests that this protein is degraded during mitotic exit.</p>
      <p>In addition to the band at about 80 kDa that corresponded to the
 full-length Sgo1, we observed two additional bands of smaller sizes
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). It is well
 documented that Sgo1 has several isoforms produced by alternative splicing
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). These two smaller
 protein bands had sizes corresponding to the proteins produced from two major
 Sgo1 splice variants, suggesting that they very likely were Sgo1 isoforms
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>). Their protein levels were
 reduced upon release from nocodazole in the same fashion as the full-length
 Sgo1, suggesting that they too were degraded during mitotic exit.</p>
      <p>Many proteins degraded during mitotic exit, such as cyclin B1, Bub1, or
 Plk1, are substrates for APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>. The <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1
 protein has been shown to be a substrate of APC/C
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). We next tested that human
 Sgo1 was a substrate of APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>. We transfected HeLa cells with
 Myc-Sgo1 in the absence or presence of HA-Cdh1. Overexpression of Cdh1 greatly
 reduced the protein levels of Myc-Sgo1, supporting that Sgo1 was a substrate
 for APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic>).</p>
      <p>APC substrates generally contain cis-elements, such as D boxes or KEN
 boxes, required for their ubiquitination. We asked whether the Sgo1 protein
 also had those elements. We carefully inspected the sequence of Sgo1 and
 identified a putative KEN box corresponding to residues 310-312 of human Sgo1.
 This motif is not conserved in mouse and <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1. We also found
 two putative D boxes with a consensus motif of R<italic>XX</italic>L<italic>XXX</italic>N in
 human Sgo1 at residues 192-200 and 457-465
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, <italic>C</italic> and
 <italic>D</italic></xref>). Both mouse and <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1 proteins contain
 an R<italic>XX</italic>L<italic>XXXX</italic>N motif that corresponds to residues 438-446 in
 human Sgo1, except that human Sgo1 contains a histidine instead of an arginine
 at position 438. We decided to consider residues 438-446 as a putative D box
 in human Sgo1. We named it D box 2 (DB2), whereas two others were named D box
 1 (DB1) and D box 3 (DB3) accordingly (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>D</italic></xref>). DB2 and DB3 are located next to each other in the
 C-terminal portion of Sgo1. DB1 is in the middle portion of the protein. DB1
 and DB3 are not conserved in mouse and <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1, whereas DB2 is
 conserved with the exception of the first arginine
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>D</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig1">
          <label>FIGURE 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>The protein levels of Sgo1 decrease rapidly during mitotic exit.</bold>
 <italic>A</italic>, HeLa cells were arrested in mitosis by nocodazole (<italic>Noc</italic>),
 released into fresh growth medium, and collected at the indicated time points.
 The cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-Sgo1, and the anti-Sgo1
 immunoprecipitates were blotted with anti-Sgo1. The cell lysates were also
 blotted with anti-cyclin B1 and anti-Apc2 (loading control).
 <italic>Asterisks</italic> indicate putative Sgo1 isoforms. <italic>B</italic>, HeLa cells
 were transfected with the indicated Sgo1 plasmids with or without the HA-Cdh1
 construct. The cell lysates were blotted with the indicated antibodies.
 <italic>C</italic>, domain structure of human Sgo1. The putative APC/C degrons, the
 coiled coil motif, and the basic domain are indicated. <italic>D</italic>, sequence
 alignment of the C-terminal regions of human, mouse, and <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1
 proteins, showing the conservation of the putative D box 2 (DB2) but not DB1
 or DB3.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960001"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>To determine whether these motifs were important for Sgo1 degradation, we
 first made mutants with either DB1 or DB3 deleted (ΔDB1 or ΔDB3),
 as they both had a perfect consensus motif. We also made a mutant with the KEN
 box deleted (ΔKEN) and a double mutant with both DB3 and the KEN box
 deleted (ΔKEN/ΔDB3). HeLa cells were transfected with these
 Myc-Sgo1 mutant constructs with or without the HA-Cdh1 expression vector, and
 the protein levels were examined by Western blotting. The protein levels of
 all Sgo1 mutants were still reduced by Cdh1 overexpression
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>). These data
 suggest that either those motifs are not functional, or deletion of each motif
 alone may not be sufficient to stabilize Sgo1. It is also possible that DB2 or
 other degradation motifs may mediate Sgo1 degradation.</p>
      <p><italic>Degradation of Sgo1 Requires Both KEN- and D-box Motifs</italic>—To
 systematically identify what regions of Sgo1 were important for its
 degradation, we made three constructs containing N-terminal (Sgo1N), middle
 (Sgo1M), or C-terminal (Sgo1C) fragments of Sgo1
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>). Sgo1N does
 not contain putative degradation motifs. Sgo1M has the putative KEN and DB1
 motifs (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>D</italic></xref>).
 Sgo1C has the putative DB2 and DB3 motifs. These constructs were expressed in
 HeLa cells in the absence or presence of Cdh1 overexpression. Myc-Sgo1N was
 stable even with overexpression of Cdh1
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes
 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic>), consistent with the lack of putative degradation
 motifs in this region. By contrast, the protein levels of both Myc-Sgo1M and
 Myc-Sgo1C were reduced by Cdh1 overexpression, suggesting that both fragments
 might be substrates of APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> and that Sgo1 might have multiple
 degradation motifs (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 3, 4, 9</italic>, and <italic>10</italic>).</p>
      <p>To determine which degradation motifs in Sgo1M were functional, we made two
 Sgo1M constructs lacking either KEN box or DB1 and examined their protein
 levels in HeLa cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 5-8</italic>). Deletion of the KEN box, but not
 DB1, stabilized Sgo1M in the presence of Cdh1 overexpression. Thus,
 degradation of Sgo1M depends on the KEN box. The KEN box is a functional APC/C
 degron capable of driving efficient degradation of Sgo1M. Removal of this
 motif alone, however, was insufficient to stabilize full-length Sgo1 protein
 in the presence of overexpressed Cdh1 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>4</italic>), suggesting that
 Sgo1 might have several degradation motifs. Consistently, Sgo1C underwent
 Cdh1-dependent degradation (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 9</italic> and <italic>10</italic>), suggesting that an
 additional degradation motif(s) was present in this region. Deletion of the
 putative DB3 did not stabilize Sgo1C in the presence of Cdh1 overexpression
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes
 11</italic> and <italic>12</italic>), indicating that this motif was not functional. To
 determine whether DB2 was critical for the degradation of Sgo1C, we made
 several constructs of Sgo1C with consecutive deletions of 5 residues in the
 region containing residues 440-469 in Sgo1. Overexpression of Cdh1 did not
 reduce protein levels of Sgo1C<sup>Δ440-444</sup> and
 Sgo1C<sup>Δ445-449</sup> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 2<italic>C</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 3-6</italic>). DB2 was partially deleted in
 both of these mutants, indicating that DB2 was required for Cdh1-dependent
 degradation of Sgo1C. By contrast, other Sgo1C mutants with residues
 neighboring DB2 deleted were not stabilized. Consistent with the putative DB3
 not being functional, two Sgo1C constructs with DB3 partially deleted,
 Sgo1C<sup>Δ455-459</sup> and Sgo1<sup>Δ460-464</sup>, were still
 degraded by Cdh1 overexpression. Thus, degradation of Sgo1 in the presence of
 an excess amount of Cdh1 depends on both its KEN-box and DB2, suggesting that
 Sgo1 might be an APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> substrate with multiple degrons.</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig2">
          <label>FIGURE 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Sgo1 degradation induced by Cdh1 overexpression depends on both its KEN
 and D boxes.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, schematic diagram of the boundaries of the
 N-terminal (Sgo1N), middle (Sgo1M), and C-terminal (Sgo1C) fragments of Sgo1.
 <italic>B</italic>, HeLa cells were transfected with the indicated Sgo1 plasmids with
 or without the HA-Cdh1 construct. The cell lysates were blotted with the
 indicated antibodies. <italic>C</italic>, HeLa cells were transfected with the
 indicated Sgo1 plasmids with or without the HA-Cdh1 construct. The cell
 lysates were blotted with the indicated antibodies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960002"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig3">
          <label>FIGURE 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Ubiquitination of Sgo1 by APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup><italic>in vitro</italic> depends
 on its KEN and D boxes.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, APC/C was immunoprecipitated from
 <italic>Xenopus</italic> egg extracts using anti-APC3/Cdc27 antibody beads and
 supplemented with recombinant Cdc20 or Cdh1. Sgo1N, Sgo1M, and Sgo1C were
 <italic>in vitro</italic> translated in the presence of [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and
 used as substrates in the ubiquitination reactions. The reaction mixtures were
 separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed using phosphorimaging. <italic>B</italic>, same as
 in <italic>A</italic> except that Sgo1C deletion mutants were used as substrates for
 ubiquitination with or without Cdh1.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960003"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p><italic>Sgo1 Is Ubiquitinated by APC/C In Vitro</italic>—To confirm that
 human Sgo1 was a substrate for APC/C, we tested whether immunopurified
 APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> or APC/C<sup>Cdc20</sup> could catalyze ubiquitination of
 Sgo1 <italic>in vitro</italic>. The three Sgo1 fragments (Sgo1N, Sgo1M, and Sgo1C)
 were translated <italic>in vitro</italic> in the presence of
 [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine and used as substrates in ubiquitination assays.
 Sgo1N was not ubiquitinated (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 3<italic>A</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 1-3</italic>), consistent with its inability to
 undergo Cdh1-mediated degradation in cells. Both Sgo1M and Sgo1C were
 efficiently ubiquitinated by APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> but not by
 APC/C<sup>Cdc20</sup> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 3<italic>A</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 4-9</italic>). Sgo1M also underwent Cdc20- and
 Cdh1-independent ubiquitination (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 3<italic>A</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 4</italic> and <italic>5</italic>). The significance of
 this ubiquitination event was unclear and was not further pursued.
 Sgo1M<sup>ΔKEN</sup> was not ubiquitinated (data not shown), indicating
 that ubiquitination of this region occurs via the KEN box. Consistent with
 results in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>,
 Sgo1C<sup>Δ440-444</sup> and Sgo1C<sup>Δ445-449</sup> that
 contained deletions of DB2 were not efficiently ubiquitinated by
 APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 3<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 3-6</italic>). Deletions of DB3 and other
 residues near DB2 did not prevent the ubiquitination of Sgo1C
 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes
 7-14</italic>). Our results indicate that Sgo1 is a substrate of
 APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup> <italic>in vitro</italic> and that it contains two functional
 APC/C degrons, the KEN box and DB2.</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig4">
          <label>FIGURE 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Sgo1 with its KEN and D boxes deleted is stable during mitotic exit.</bold>
 <italic>A</italic>, HeLa cells were transfected with the indicated Sgo1 plasmids with
 or without the HA-Cdh1 construct. The cell lysates were blotted with the
 indicated antibodies. <italic>B</italic>, HeLa Tet-on cells stably transfected with
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ΔKEN/ΔDB2</sup> (referred to as
 non-degradable Sgo1 or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>) were incubated for 24 h in the
 presence or absence of doxycycline (<italic>Dox</italic>). Cell lysates were blotted
 with the indicated antibodies. <italic>C</italic>, cell lysates in <italic>B</italic> and
 lysates of an additional Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> clone were blotted with anti-Sgo1.
 A cross-reacting band was used as the loading control. <italic>D</italic>, HeLa cells
 induced with doxycycline for Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> expression
 were treated with nocodazole, released into a fresh medium containing
 cycloheximide, and collected at different time points. Cell lysates were
 blotted with the indicated antibodies. <italic>E</italic>, mitotic chromosome spreads
 of HeLa Tet-on cells stably expressing Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in the presence of doxycycline.
 4,6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole staining is shown in <italic>blue</italic>. CREST
 staining is shown in <italic>red</italic>. Myc staining is shown in
 <italic>green</italic>.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960004"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p><italic>Sgo1 with the KEN Box and DB2 Deleted Is Stabilized during Mitotic
 Exit</italic>—We next tested whether deletion of both the KEN box and DB2
 stabilized full-length Sgo1 in HeLa cells overexpressing Cdh1. As expected,
 deletion of either KEN or DB2 alone was not sufficient to stabilize Sgo1 in
 the presence of Cdh1 overexpression (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 4<italic>A</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes 3-6</italic>). Deletion of both motifs,
 however, greatly stabilized Sgo1 in cells overexpressing Cdh1
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>, <italic>lanes
 7</italic> and <italic>8</italic>). Thus, either the KEN box or DB2 of Sgo1 is sufficient
 to drive its degradation in cells with elevated levels of Cdh1. Deletion of
 both motifs is required to stabilize Sgo1 in cells. We will hereafter refer to
 the Sgo1 mutant with both KEN and DB2 deleted as non-degradable Sgo1
 (Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>). We then established cell lines that stably expressed
 full-length Myc-tagged wild-type Sgo1 (Sgo1<sup>WT</sup>) or non-degradable
 Sgo1 (Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>) driven by a tetracycline-inducible promoter. We
 verified that Sgo1 expression was induced by doxycycline in these lines
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>B</italic></xref>). Blotting of
 the cell lysates with anti-Sgo1 readily detected Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in the presence of doxycycline but failed to detect the
 endogenous Sgo1 protein (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 4<italic>C</italic></xref>). Therefore, the expression levels of
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> were higher than that of the
 endogenous Sgo1. The signal for endogenous Sgo1 was below the detectable level
 under these blotting conditions.</p>
      <p>Next, we examined the kinetics of degradation of Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in these cells after the release from
 nocodazole-mediated mitotic arrest by blotting the total cell lysates with
 anti-Myc. As expected, Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> was degraded rapidly during
 mitotic exit, and its degradation profile was similar to that of cyclin B1 and
 the endogenous Sgo1 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 4<italic>D</italic></xref>, <italic>upper panels</italic>). By contrast,
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> was degraded with a much slower kinetics, indicating
 that deletion of KEN and DB2 greatly impeded the degradation of Sgo1 during
 mitotic exit. The kinetics of cyclin B1 degradation, however, was unchanged in
 cells expressing Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 4<italic>D</italic></xref>, <italic>lower panels</italic>), suggesting that timely Sgo1
 degradation was not required for proper mitotic exit.</p>
      <p>To ascertain that Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> was still functional and that the
 mutations did not grossly affect the functions of Sgo1, we first examined the
 kinetochore localization of Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>. Both Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> localized normally to centromeres
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>E</italic></xref>). Thus,
 Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> retains the ability to localize to centromeres. We next
 tested whether expression of Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> rescued the mitotic arrest
 phenotype of Sgo1 RNAi cells (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 5</xref>). For this purpose, we measured the mitotic indices of Sgo1 RNAi
 cells transfected with Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> using
 flow cytometry. Mitotic cells had 4N DNA content and positive MPM2 staining.
 As expected, depletion of Sgo1 by RNAi resulted in mitotic arrest
 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>). Expression of either Sgo1<sup>WT</sup>
 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>) or
 Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 5<italic>F</italic></xref>) rescued this mitotic arrest phenotype, indicating
 that Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> was functional.</p>
      <p><italic>Ectopic Expression of Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> Does Not Delay Chromosome
 Segregation</italic>—Because human Sgo1 is known to play a role in the
 protection of centromeric cohesion during mitosis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>),
 we asked whether Sgo1 degradation is required for proper chromosome
 segregation. Briefly, HeLa cells expressing Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or
 Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> were synchronized in mitosis by a single thymidine block
 followed by a 4-h incubation in nocodazole
 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>A</italic></xref>). Mitotic
 cells were collected by mitotic shake-off and released from the mitotic block.
 Samples were taken at different times. These samples were fixed with Carnoy's
 fixative, processed for chromosome spreads, and stained with Giemsa. Cells
 expressing human Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> had chromosomes
 normally cohered at their centromeres, similar to their non-induced controls
 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>).
 Furthermore, the timing of sister-chromatid separation and chromosome
 decondensation in the induced cells was indistinguishable from their
 non-induced controls (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, <italic>B</italic>
 and <italic>C</italic></xref>). These data indicate that Sgo1 degradation is not
 required for proper sister-chromatid separation or chromosome decondensation
 after release from a mitotic block.</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig5">
          <label>FIGURE 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Expression of Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> rescues the mitotic arrest phenotype of
 Sgo1 RNAi cells.</bold> Log phase HeLa cells (<italic>A</italic>), Sgo1 RNAi cells
 (<italic>B</italic>), cells transfected with Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> (<italic>C</italic>), cells
 transfected with both Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and Sgo1 siRNA (<italic>D</italic>), cells
 transfected with Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> (<italic>E</italic>), and cells transfected
 with both Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> and Sgo1 siRNA (<italic>F</italic>) were fixed and stained
 with the MPM2 antibody and propidium iodide and subjected to flow cytometry
 analysis. The mitotic cells were <italic>boxed</italic>. The mitotic indices are
 indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960005"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig6">
          <label>FIGURE 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Expression of non-degradable Sgo1 (Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>) does not delay
 chromosome segregation after the release from nocodazole-mediated mitotic
 arrest.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, schematic diagram of drug treatments for experiments
 shown in <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>B</italic>, three major categories of
 chromosome morphology observed in chromosome spreads of HeLa Tet-on cells
 stably transfected with Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in the absence or presence of
 doxycycline (<italic>Dox</italic>) after the release from nocodazole-mediated mitotic
 arrest. <italic>C</italic>, kinetics of chromosome segregation in cells expressing
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in the presence or absence of
 doxycycline after the release from nocodazole arrest. A total of 100
 chromosome spreads were analyzed for each sample. <italic>D</italic>, kinetics of
 chromosome decondensation in cells expressing Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in the presence or absence of doxycycline after the
 release from nocodazole arrest. A total of 100 chromosome spreads were
 analyzed for each sample.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960006"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>To confirm these findings, we examined the chromosome morphology and
 dynamics in cells overexpressing Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> during
 unperturbed mitoses. Cells expressing Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>
 were synchronized in early S phase by a double thymidine block and released
 into fresh medium (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7<italic>A</italic></xref>). Doxycycline was added to both cell lines during the
 second thymidine block. Samples were taken when cells reached their peak
 mitotic index and analyzed as described above. Chromosome cohesion and
 morphology in the induced cultures were indistinguishable from their
 non-induced controls (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7<italic>B</italic></xref>). All phases of mitosis were present at the expected
 ratios, indicating that the inability to degrade Sgo1 does not induce changes
 in chromosome morphology or mitotic arrest.</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig7">
          <label>FIGURE 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Expression of non-degradable Sgo1 (Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>) does not delay
 chromosome segregation during unperturbed mitosis.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, schematic
 diagram of the time course of experiments in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>B</italic>,
 chromosome spreads of HeLa Tet-on cells expressing Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> with or
 without doxycycline (<italic>Dox</italic>) made 10 h after the release from the second
 thymidine block. Major categories of morphology were shown.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960007"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig8">
          <label>FIGURE 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Live cell time-lapse analysis of cells stably expressing non-degradable
 Sgo1.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, cells stably expressing non-degradable Sgo1
 (Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>) in the absence or presence of doxycycline (<italic>Dox</italic>)
 were filmed for 20 h after release from thymidine arrest. Selected frames of
 cells in interphase and different stages of mitosis are shown. Time (h:min) is
 shown at the <italic>lower right corner of each image</italic>. Nuclear envelope
 breakdown (<italic>NEBD</italic>) is defined as time 0. <italic>B</italic>, cumulative
 frequency of cells undergoing anaphase within the indicated time windows after
 nuclear envelope breakdown. Anaphase timing in HeLa Tet-on cells expressing
 Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> was determined from time-lapse
 movies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960008"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>Last, a detailed analysis of chromosome dynamics and anaphase timing was
 performed in live cells by time-lapse microscopy
 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>A</italic></xref>). Both cells
 expressing Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> condensed their chromosomes,
 formed a metaphase plate, and underwent anaphase with similar timings
 (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that delayed
 Sgo1 degradation does not prevent chromosome segregation and that Sgo1
 degradation is not required for later mitotic processes, such as chromosome
 decondensation and cytokinesis.</p>
      <p><italic>Bub1 Regulates the Steady-state Level of Sgo1 through an
 APC/C-independent Mechanism</italic>—It has been shown previously that the
 protein levels of Sgo1 are reduced in Bub1 RNAi cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>), indicating that Bub1 is
 required for the maintenance of the steady-state levels of Sgo1. Bub1 also
 phosphorylates Sgo1 protein <italic>in vitro</italic> at several sites, including
 Ser-436 and Ser-440, which are in and around DB2 (data not shown). We, thus,
 tested whether Bub1 regulated APC/C-dependent degradation of Sgo1. We depleted
 Bub1 by RNAi in cells stably expressing Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> or
 Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> and blotted cell lysates with anti-Myc. As expected, the
 levels of Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> were regulated during the cell cycle and were
 lower in log phase cells than in thymidine- or nocodazole-arrested cells
 (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>, <italic>lanes 4-6</italic>).
 Depletion of Bub1 further reduced the levels of Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> under all
 three conditions (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>,
 compare <italic>lanes 1-3</italic> with <italic>lanes 4-6</italic>). The levels of
 Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> in log-phase cells were similar to that in thymidine- or
 nocodazole-arrested cells (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 9</xref>, <italic>lanes 10-12</italic>), consistent with it not being regulated
 by APC/C. We expected that, if Bub1 regulated Sgo1 levels through preventing
 APC/C-dependent ubiquitination of Sgo1, then Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> should not
 display a reduction in protein levels in Bub1 RNAi cells. In contrast to our
 expectations, we found that the levels of Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> were still reduced
 in Bub1 RNAi cells (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>,
 compare <italic>lanes 7-9</italic> with <italic>lanes 10-12</italic>). Thus, our data confirm
 that Bub1 regulates Sgo1 protein levels but suggest that it does so through a
 mechanism independent of APC/C.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p><italic>Sgo1 Contains Multiple APC/C Degrons</italic>—Sister-chromatid
 cohesion is crucial for faithful chromosome segregation in mitosis and meiosis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>). Sgo1 is required for the
 protection of centromeric cohesion from prophase to the metaphase-to-anaphase
 transition until all kinetochores are properly captured by the spindle
 microtubules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>). In this
 study, we have shown that human Sgo1 is degraded in an APC/C-dependent manner
 during mitotic exit. Overexpression of Cdh1 causes a significant reduction in
 Sgo1 protein levels. Consistent with our data, <italic>Xenopus</italic> Sgo1 is also a
 substrate of APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). We have further identified
 two functional APC/C degrons, a KEN box and a D box, in Sgo1. Thus, similar to
 other APC/C substrates, such as securin
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>), Cdc6
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>), and Nek2A
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>), Sgo1 contains multiple
 APC/C degrons, which ensure its robust degradation during mitotic exit.</p>
      <p>
        <fig position="float" id="fig9">
          <label>FIGURE 9.</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Depletion of Bub1 by RNAi decreases steady-state levels of
 Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> and Sgo1<sup>ND</sup>.</bold> Log phase, nocodazole
 (<italic>Noc</italic>)-treated, or thymidine (<italic>Thy</italic>)-treated HeLa Tet-on cells
 stably expressing Myc-Sgo1<sup>WT</sup> (<italic>left panel</italic>) or
 Myc-Sgo1<sup>ND</sup> (<italic>right panel</italic>) were transfected with Bub1 siRNA
 for 24 h and analyzed by Western blotting with the indicated antibodies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="zbc0070963960009"/>
        </fig>
      </p>
      <p>Sgo1 contains three putative D boxes, but only one D box (DB2) is
 functional. In another study, DB3 of human Sgo1 was identified as a functional
 APC/C degron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>). Our results
 directly contradict those data. We have carefully examined the potential role
 of DB3 in Sgo1 degradation. In our experiments, removal of DB3 alone or
 together with the KEN box does not stabilize full-length Sgo1 in the presence
 of Cdh1 overexpression (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>B</italic></xref>). Similar results were obtained when DB3 was deleted
 in a C-terminal fragment of Sgo1 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 2<italic>B</italic></xref>). A systematic deletional analysis of the C-terminal
 region of Sgo1 further confirms that DB2 is the only functional APC/C degron
 in this region, and removal of this motif is solely responsible for the
 stabilization of Sgo1C in the presence of Cdh1 overexpression
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>). Finally,
 Sgo1C mutants with DB3 partially deleted can still be efficiently
 ubiquitinated by APC/C in an <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstituted ubiquitination
 assay (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>B</italic></xref>). Thus,
 DB3 is not a functional APC/C degron.</p>
      <p><italic>Degradation of Sgo1 Is Not Required for Mitotic
 Progression</italic>—APC/C regulates orderly progression through mitosis by
 targeting key mitotic regulators for ubiquitination and degradation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>). Sgo1 localizes to
 kinetochores, protects centromeric cohesion during prophase, and prevents
 premature sister-chromatid separation in mitosis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>). In meiosis I, the
 shugoshin family of proteins also protects centromeric cohesin from cleavage
 by separase. We had initially envisioned that degradation of Sgo1 might be
 required for its inactivation, thus allowing the timely cleavage of
 centromeric cohesin by separase at the metaphase-to-anaphase transition.
 However, expression of a non-degradable mutant of Sgo1 in HeLa cells did not
 cause a delay in chromosome segregation or mitotic exit. We also did not
 observe changes in chromosome morphology at different stages of mitosis. These
 results suggest that degradation of Sgo1 itself is not crucial for proper
 progression through mitosis. Additional mechanisms may exist to inactivate
 Sgo1 at the metaphase-to-anaphase transition. Alternatively, Sgo1 does not
 prevent the cleavage of centromeric cohesin by separase in mitosis.</p>
      <p><italic>Bub1 Regulates Sgo1 Protein Levels in an APC/C-independent
 Mechanism</italic>—The spindle checkpoint kinase Bub1 is required for the
 maintenance of Sgo1 protein levels
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Bub1 phosphorylates Sgo1
 in the vicinity of its APC/C degrons <italic>in vitro</italic>. Recently, it has been
 shown that cyclin-dependent kinases phosphorylate Cdc6 in the vicinity of its
 APC/C degrons, thus rendering these motifs inaccessible for APC/C recognition
 and ubiquitination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>). We
 had hypothesized that Bub1 might regulate Sgo1 through a similar mechanism.
 This does not appear to be the case, as the levels of the non-degradable Sgo1
 mutant are still reduced in Bub1 RNAi cells. Our results, thus, suggest that
 Bub1 regulates Sgo1 levels through an APC/C-independent mechanism. The
 centromeric localization of Sgo1 depends on Bub1
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). It is possible that Sgo1
 becomes unstable in Bub1-depleted cells because it loses its centromeric
 localization. On the other hand, Bub1 targets PP2A to centromeres, which in
 turn maintains Sgo1 at centromeres by counteracting Plk1-mediated chromosome
 removal of Sgo1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>). Although
 Sgo1 also loses its centromeric localization in PP2A RNAi cells, its protein
 levels are not reduced in these cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>). Therefore, the loss of
 its centromeric localization <italic>per se</italic> does not necessarily lead to Sgo1
 degradation. Future experiments are needed to uncover the mechanisms by which
 Bub1 regulates the steady-state levels of Sgo1.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the members of the Yu laboratory for helpful discussions.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Waizenegger, I. C., Hauf, S., Meinke, A., and Peters, J. M.
 (<year>2000</year>) <source>Cell</source>
 <volume>103</volume>
 <fpage>399</fpage>-410<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11081627</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1c6ed90N0x430e750">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Losada, A., Hirano, M., and Hirano, T. (<year>2002</year>)
 <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>16</volume>
 <fpage>3004</fpage>-3016<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464631</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Onn, I., Heidinger-Pauli, J. M., Guacci, V., Unal, E., and
 Koshland, D. E. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev.
 Biol.</source> <volume>24</volume>
 <fpage>105</fpage>-129<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18616427</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Hauf, S., Roitinger, E., Koch, B., Dittrich, C. M., Mechtler, K.,
 and Peters, J. M. (<year>2005</year>) <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
 <volume>3</volume> <fpage>e69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737063</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Hauf, S., Waizenegger, I. C., and Peters, J. M. (<year>2001</year>)
 <source>Science</source> <volume>293</volume>
 <fpage>1320</fpage>-1323<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11509732</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kitajima, T. S., Kawashima, S. A., and Watanabe, Y.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nature</source>
 <volume>427</volume>
 <fpage>510</fpage>-517<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14730319</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Watanabe, Y. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Curr. Opin. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>17</volume>
 <fpage>590</fpage>-595<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16229998</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Salic, A., Waters, J. C., and Mitchison, T. J. (<year>2004</year>)
 <source>Cell</source> <volume>118</volume>
 <fpage>567</fpage>-578<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339662</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tang, Z., Sun, Y., Harley, S. E., Zou, H., and Yu, H.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
 <volume>101</volume>
 <fpage>18012</fpage>-18017<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604152</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kitajima, T. S., Hauf, S., Ohsugi, M., Yamamoto, T., and Watanabe,
 Y. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
 <volume>15</volume> <fpage>353</fpage>-359<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723797</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">McGuinness, B. E., Hirota, T., Kudo, N. R., Peters, J. M., and
 Nasmyth, K. (<year>2005</year>) <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
 <volume>3</volume> <fpage>e86</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737064</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tang, Z., Shu, H., Qi, W., Mahmood, N. A., Mumby, M. C., and Yu, H.
 (<year>2006</year>) <source>Dev. Cell</source>
 <volume>10</volume> <fpage>575</fpage>-585<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580887</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1c6ed90N0x4a736c8">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kitajima, T. S., Sakuno, T., Ishiguro, K., Iemura, S., Natsume, T.,
 Kawashima, S. A., and Watanabe, Y. (<year>2006</year>)
 <source>Nature</source> <volume>441</volume>
 <fpage>46</fpage>-52<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541025</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Riedel, C. G., Katis, V. L., Katou, Y., Mori, S., Itoh, T.,
 Helmhart, W., Galova, M., Petronczki, M., Gregan, J., Cetin, B., Mudrak, I.,
 Ogris, E., Mechtler, K., Pelletier, L., Buchholz, F., Shirahige, K., and
 Nasmyth, K. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nature</source>
 <volume>441</volume> <fpage>53</fpage>-61<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541024</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Indjeian, V. B., Stern, B. M., and Murray, A. W.
 (<year>2005</year>) <source>Science</source>
 <volume>307</volume>
 <fpage>130</fpage>-133<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15637284</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Peters, J. M. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>7</volume>
 <fpage>644</fpage>-656<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896351</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Yu, H. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source>
 <volume>27</volume> <fpage>3</fpage>-16<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17612486</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Glotzer, M., Murray, A. W., and Kirschner, M. W.
 (<year>1991</year>) <source>Nature</source>
 <volume>349</volume>
 <fpage>132</fpage>-138<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1846030</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Pfleger, C. M., and Kirschner, M. W. (<year>2000</year>)
 <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>14</volume>
 <fpage>655</fpage>-665<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733526</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Yu, H. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Curr. Opin. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>14</volume>
 <fpage>706</fpage>-714<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12473343</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <label>21</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Fang, G., Yu, H., and Kirschner, M. W. (<year>1998</year>)
 <source>Mol. Cell</source> <volume>2</volume>
 <fpage>163</fpage>-171<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9734353</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <label>22</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Gimenez-Abian, J. F., Diaz-Martinez, L. A., Wirth, K. G., Andrews,
 C. A., Gimenez-Martin, G., and Clarke, D. J. (<year>2005</year>)
 <source>Cell Cycle</source> <volume>4</volume>
 <fpage>1561</fpage>-1575<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16205119</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <label>23</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tang, Z., and Yu, H. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Methods Mol.
 Biol.</source> <volume>281</volume>
 <fpage>227</fpage>-242<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15220533</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <label>24</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Qi, W., and Yu, H. (<year>2007</year>) <source>J. Biol.
 Chem.</source> <volume>282</volume>
 <fpage>3672</fpage>-3679<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158872</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <label>25</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tang, Z., Bharadwaj, R., Li, B., and Yu, H. (<year>2001</year>)
 <source>Dev. Cell</source> <volume>1</volume>
 <fpage>227</fpage>-237<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11702782</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <label>26</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wang, X., Yang, Y., and Dai, W. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Cell
 Cycle</source> <volume>5</volume>
 <fpage>635</fpage>-640<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16582621</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <label>27</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Suzuki, H., Akiyama, N., Tsuji, M., Ohashi, T., Saito, S., and Eto,
 Y. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Cell Cycle</source>
 <volume>5</volume>
 <fpage>1094</fpage>-1101<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16687935</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <label>28</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Zur, A., and Brandeis, M. (<year>2001</year>) <source>EMBO
 J.</source> <volume>20</volume>
 <fpage>792</fpage>-801<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179223</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <label>29</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Mailand, N., and Diffley, J. F. (<year>2005</year>)
 <source>Cell</source> <volume>122</volume>
 <fpage>915</fpage>-926<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153703</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <label>30</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Hayes, M. J., Kimata, Y., Wattam, S. L., Lindon, C., Mao, G.,
 Yamano, H., and Fry, A. M. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nat. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>8</volume>
 <fpage>607</fpage>-614<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16648845</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <label>31</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Fu, G., Hua, S., Ward, T., Ding, X., Yang, Y., Guo, Z., and Yao, X.
 (<year>2007</year>) <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
 <volume>357</volume>
 <fpage>672</fpage>-678<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448445</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn3">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>The abbreviations used are: APC/C, anaphase-promoting complex/cyclosome;
 APC/C<sup>Cdh1</sup>, the complex between APC/C and Cdh1; D box, destruction
 box; KEN box, lysine-glutamate-asparagine box; RNAi, RNA interference; HA,
 hemagglutinin.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>