<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:30:58Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2199860" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2199860</identifier><datestamp>2008-05-01</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2199860</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2199860</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2199860</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647900</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">96178079</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647900</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>MDC9, a widely expressed cellular disintegrin containing cytoplasmic SH3 ligand domains</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>2</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>1996</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>132</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>717</fpage>
      <lpage>726</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cellular disintegrins are a family of proteins that are related to snake venom integrin ligands and metalloproteases. We have cloned and sequenced the mouse and human homologue of a widely expressed cellular disintegrin, which we have termed MDC9 (for metalloprotease/disintegrin/cysteine-rich protein 9). The deduced mouse and human protein sequences are 82% identical. MDC9 contains several distinct protein domains: a signal sequence is followed by a prodomain and a domain with sequence similarity to snake venom metalloproteases, a disintegrin domain, a cysteine-rich region, an EGF repeat, a membrane anchor, and a cytoplasmic tail. The cytoplasmic tail of MDC9 has two proline-rich sequences which can bind the SH3 domain of Src, and may therefore function as SH3 ligand domains. Western blot analysis shows that MDC9 is an approximately 84-kD glycoprotein in all mouse tissues examined, and in NIH 3T3 fibroblast and C2C12 myoblast mouse cell lines. MDC9 can be both cell surface biotinylated and 125I-labeled in NIH 3T3 mouse fibroblasts, indicating that the protein is present on the plasma membrane. Expression of MDC9 in COS-7 cells yields an 84-kD protein, and immunofluorescence analysis of COS-7 cells expressing MDC9 shows a staining pattern that is consistent with a plasma membrane localization. The apparent molecular mass of 84 kD suggests that MDC9 contains a membrane-anchored metalloprotease and disintegrin domain. We propose that MDC9 might function as a membrane-anchored integrin ligand or metalloprotease, or that MDC9 may combine both activities in one protein.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>