<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:28:14Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2120529" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2120529</identifier><datestamp>2008-05-01</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2120529</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2120529</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2120529</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7542657</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">95348175</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7542657</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>CENP-F is a protein of the nuclear matrix that assembles onto kinetochores at late G2 and is rapidly degraded after mitosis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>130</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>507</fpage>
      <lpage>518</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Centromere protein-F (CENP-F) is mammalian kinetochore protein that was recently identified by an autoimmune serum (Rattner, J. B., A. Rao, M. J. Fritzler, D. W. Valencia, and T. J. Yen. Cell Motil. Cytoskeleton. 26:214-226). We report here the human cDNA sequence of CENP-F, along with its expression and localization patterns at different stages of the HeLa cell cycle. CENP-F is protein of the nuclear matrix that gradually accumulates during the cell cycle until it reaches peak levels in G2 and M phase cells and is rapidly degraded upon completion of mitosis. CENP-F is first detected at the prekinetochore complex during late G2, and is clearly detectable as paired foci that correspond to all the centromeres by prophase. During mitosis, CENP-F is associated with kinetochores from prometaphase until early anaphase and is then detected at the spindle midzone throughout the remainder of anaphase. By telophase, CENP-F is concentrated within the intracellular bridge at either side of the mid-body. The predicted structure of the 367-kD CENP-F protein consists of two 1,600-amino acid-long coil domains that flank a central flexible core. A putative P-loop nucleotide binding site (ADIPTGKT) is located within the globular carboxy terminus. The structural features deduced from our sequence studies and the spatial and temperal distribution of CENP-F revealed in our cytological and biochemical studies suggest that it may play a role in several mitotic events.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>