<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:33:27Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2635056" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2635056</identifier><datestamp>2009-02-09</datestamp><setSpec>jbc</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2635056</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2635056</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2635056</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038967</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3985</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M806943200</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19038967</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Protein Structure and Folding</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Crystal Structure and Autoactivation Pathway of the Precursor Form of
 Human Tripeptidyl-peptidase 1, the Enzyme Deficient in Late Infantile Ceroid
 Lipofuscinosis<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">S⃞</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guhaniyogi</surname>
            <given-names>Jayita</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">‡</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">§</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sohar</surname>
            <given-names>Istvan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">‡</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">¶</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Das</surname>
            <given-names>Kalyan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">‡</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">∥</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stock</surname>
            <given-names>Ann M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">‡</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">§</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">**</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lobel</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">‡</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0">¶</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x3b761e0"><label>‡</label>Center for Advanced
 Biotechnology and Medicine,
 <label>§</label>Department of Biochemistry, and
 <label>¶</label>Department of Pharmacology,
 University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey-Robert Wood Johnson Medical
 School, and the <label>∥</label>Department of
 Chemistry and Chemical Biology, Rutgers University, and the
 <label>**</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute,
 Piscataway, New Jersey 08854</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="cor1">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>
 Investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. To whom correspondence
 may be addressed: 679 Hoes Lane, Piscataway, NJ 08854. Tel.: 732-235-4844;
 Fax: 732-235-5289; E-mail:
 <email>stock@cabm.rutgers.edu</email>.
 </p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="cor2">
          <label>2</label>
          <p>
 To whom correspondence may be addressed: 679 Hoes Lane, Piscataway, NJ 08854.
 Tel.: 732-235-5032; Fax: 732-235-5289; E-mail:
 <email>lobel@cabm.rutgers.edu</email>.
 </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the copyright element. -->
      <volume>284</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>3985</fpage>
      <lpage>3997</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>8</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2009, The American Society for Biochemistry and
 Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p>
            <italic>Author's Choice</italic>
          </p>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
 Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author
 Choice Articles</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zbc00609003985.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Late infantile neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis is a fatal childhood
 neurological disorder caused by a deficiency in the lysosomal protease
 tripeptidyl-peptidase 1 (TPP1). TPP1 represents the only known mammalian
 member of the S53 family of serine proteases, a group characterized by a
 subtilisin-like fold, a Ser-Glu-Asp catalytic triad, and an acidic pH optimum.
 TPP1 is synthesized as an inactive proenzyme (pro-TPP1) that is
 proteolytically processed into the active enzyme after exposure to low pH
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or targeting to the lysosome <italic>in vivo</italic>. In this
 study, we describe an endoglycosidase H-deglycosylated form of TPP1 containing
 four Asn-linked <italic>N</italic>-acetylglucosamines that is indistinguishable from
 fully glycosylated TPP1 in terms of autocatalytic processing of the proform
 and enzymatic properties of the mature protease. The crystal structure of
 deglycosylated pro-TPP1 was determined at 1.85 Å resolution. A large
 151-residue C-shaped prodomain makes extensive contacts as it wraps around the
 surface of the catalytic domain with the two domains connected by a 24-residue
 flexible linker that passes through the substrate-binding groove. The
 proenzyme structure reveals suboptimal catalytic triad geometry with its
 propiece linker partially blocking the substrate-binding site, which together
 serve to prevent premature activation of the protease. Finally, we have
 identified numerous processing intermediates and propose a structural model
 that explains the pathway for TPP1 activation <italic>in vitro</italic>. These data
 provide new insights into TPP1 function and represent a valuable resource for
 constructing improved TPP1 variants for treatment of late infantile neuronal
 ceroid lipofuscinosis.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn>
          <p>
            <italic>The atomic coordinates and structure factors (code 3EDY) have been
 deposited in the Protein Data Bank, Research Collaboratory for Structural
 Bioinformatics, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ
 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/">http://www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>).</italic>
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>This work was supported, in whole or in part, by <grant-sponsor>National
 Institutes of Health</grant-sponsor> Grant
 <grant-num>NS037918</grant-num> (to P. L.). The costs of publication of this
 article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article
 must therefore be hereby marked “<italic>advertisement</italic>” in
 accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn3">
          <label/>
          <p>The on-line version of this article (available at
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org">http://www.jbc.org</ext-link>)
 contains Figs. S1-S8, Tables S1-S4, and additional references.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2">
          <label/>
          <p><italic>Author's Choice</italic>—Final version full
 access.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body><p>Late infantile neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis
 (LINCL)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref> (OMIM number
 204500) is a neurodegenerative lysosomal storage disease of childhood that
 presents typically between the ages of 2 and 4 years with the onset of
 seizures. Disease progression is reflected by blindness, dementia, mental
 retardation, and an increase in the severity of seizures. LINCL is always
 fatal, and the life span of patients is typically 6-15 years. LINCL is caused
 by mutations in <italic>TPP1</italic> (previously named <italic>CLN2</italic>, for ceroid
 lipofuscinosis neuronal type 2 gene)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>), which normally encodes a
 lysosomal protease, tripeptidyl-peptidase 1 (TPP1, EC 3.4.14.9)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>).</p><p>There is currently no treatment of demonstrated efficacy for LINCL, but
 promising progress is being made in some directions. Proof-of-principle for
 virus-mediated gene therapy has been established in a mouse model of LINCL,
 with a significant improvement in disease phenotype achieved with the use of
 adeno-associated virus vectors expressing TPP1
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>).
 Affected children have also been treated with adeno-associated virus vectors,
 although it is too soon to determine whether significant clinical benefits
 have been achieved in these early trials
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). Enzyme replacement
 therapy, an approach that has proven successful in a number of other lysosomal
 storage diseases, has also been investigated in LINCL. Purified recombinant
 human TPP1 that contains the mannose 6-phosphate lysosomal targeting
 modification can be taken up by LINCL fibroblasts where it degrades storage
 material (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>), and the protein
 has been introduced into the cerebrospinal fluid of the LINCL mouse model via
 intraventricular injection, resulting in significant uptake into the brain and
 some correction of neuropathology
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>).</p><p>For therapeutic approaches that rely upon replacing a mutant gene product
 with a functional protein via recombinant methods, <italic>e.g.</italic> gene and
 enzyme replacement therapy, a thorough understanding of the biological and
 biophysical properties of the protein in question are essential for success.
 Thus, for LINCL, considerable effort has been directed toward the
 investigation of TPP1, and as a result, this is a well characterized enzyme at
 the functional and molecular levels (reviewed in Refs.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>). <italic>TPP1</italic> encodes a
 563-residue preproprotein with a cleavable N-terminal 19-residue signal
 sequence. The proenzyme (residues 20-563) is a soluble monomer that undergoes
 proteolytic cleavage in the lysosome, converting the zymogen to an active,
 mature protease (residues 196-563)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>). Studies on purified
 pro-TPP1 demonstrate that maturation is autocatalytic <italic>in vitro</italic>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) but may involve other
 proteases <italic>in vivo</italic>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>). TPP1 is glycosylated,
 and its <italic>N</italic>-linked oligosaccharides have been implicated in maturation,
 activity, targeting, and stability of the processed enzyme
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>).</p><p>TPP1 is a serine protease
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) that possesses two
 catalytic functions as follows: a primary tripeptidyl exopeptidase activity
 with a pH optimum of ∼5.0 that catalyzes the sequential release of
 tripeptides from the unsubstituted N termini of substrates
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>), and a much weaker
 endoproteolytic activity with a pH optimum of ∼3.0
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>). TPP1 exhibits broad
 substrate specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>) and
 is the only mammalian member of the S53 sedolisin family (reviewed in Ref.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>), which includes a number
 of unusual bacterial serine peptidases
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>). High resolution crystal
 structures of both free and inhibitor-bound complexes have been determined for
 three bacterial members of this family (sedolisin
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>),
 kumamolisin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>), and kumamolisin-As
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>)), and for one
 (kumamolisin), the structure of a mutant, inactive precursor form has also
 been obtained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>). These
 proteins share a common subtilisin-like fold, an octahedrally coordinated
 calcium-binding site, and an active site that contains an unusual Ser-Glu-Asp
 (SED) catalytic triad, rather than the Ser-His-Asp (SHD) triad of subtilisin
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>). Chemical modification
 studies of TPP1 have revealed that Ser<sup>475</sup> is the active site
 nucleophile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). Modeling
 studies suggest that Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> complete the
 catalytic triad and that Asp<sup>360</sup> is homologous to the conserved Asn
 in the subtilisin family in its role in stabilization of the oxyanion of the
 tetrahedral intermediate during catalysis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>). Site-directed
 mutagenesis studies are consistent with these conclusions
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>).</p><p>A detailed understanding of the tertiary structure of TPP1 may have
 implications for developing or improving therapeutic strategies. First, a high
 resolution model would provide the basis for targeted protein engineering
 efforts to design TPP1 derivatives with increased half-life prior to and/or
 upon delivery to the lysosome. Successful creation of a longer lived TPP1
 molecule could significantly enhance gene or enzyme replacement approaches to
 LINCL. Second, a structural model for TPP1 could be valuable in designing
 derivatives tagged with protein transduction domains to facilitate crossing of
 the blood-brain barrier for delivery to the central nervous system from the
 bloodstream. In this study, we present the crystal structure of the proform of
 human TPP1 at 1.85 Å resolution. This model provides novel insights into
 the structural basis for the pH-induced auto-activation of the proform of
 TPP1. A structure of glycosylated pro-TPP1 has been independently determined,
 displaying features similar to those of deglycosylated
 TPP1.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref></p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title><p><italic>Protein Production</italic>—Production and purification of
 recombinant human TPP1 from a Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) expression system
 were conducted using modifications of methods described previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Cells were cultured in
 1050-cm<sup>2</sup> roller bottles for 9 days with serum-free Dulbecco's
 modified Eagle's/F-12 medium containing 1 μg/ml kifunensin. Conditioned
 media were harvested and adjusted to contain 2.5 <sc>m</sc> NaCl as well as
 20 m<sc>m</sc> Tris, pH 8.0, and 20 μ<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub> (TC
 Buffer). All subsequent steps were conducted at 4 °C unless noted
 otherwise. The solution was clarified by centrifugation and filtration and
 then applied to a butyl-Sepharose 4 fast-flow column (GE Healthcare). After
 washing with 2.5 <sc>m</sc> NaCl in TC Buffer, the column was eluted with a
 7.5-column volume linear gradient of 2.5 to 0 <sc>m</sc> NaCl in TC Buffer.
 Fractions containing most of the pro-TPP1 were concentrated and equilibrated
 with 20 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl/TC Buffer by diafiltration. The solution was
 filtered, loaded onto a Mono Q12 column (Bio-Rad), and washed with 4 column
 volumes of 20 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl in TC Buffer. The column was eluted with 10
 column volumes of a linear gradient of 20 to 515 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl in TC
 Buffer. Peak fractions containing pro-TPP1 were adjusted to contain 100
 m<sc>m</sc> sodium citrate, pH 5.5. Protein was deglycosylated by incubation
 with Endo H<sub>f</sub> (New England Biolabs, 26,500 units per mg of pro-TPP1)
 at 25 °C for 15 h followed by 1 h at 37 °C. The solution was buffer
 exchanged and repurified by Mono Q12 chromatography as described above.
 Fractions containing pro-TPP1 were concentrated and applied to a Superdex 75
 column equilibrated in 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl in TC Buffer to separate
 pro-TPP1 monomer from a minor amount of aggregated material.</p><p>A similar procedure was used to isolate glycosylated pro-TPP1, omitting
 kifunensin from the cell culture media and the Endo H digestion and second
 Mono Q12 chromatography steps. Hexahistidine-tagged human pro-TPP1 was
 produced using an insect cell system and purified as described previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) except that all column
 buffers contained 20 μ<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and a final Superdex
 75 gel filtration step was performed as described above.</p><p><italic>TPP1 Activation Kinetics</italic>—TPP1 proenzyme was diluted to the
 desired concentration using 0.1% Triton X-100, 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 20
 m<sc>m</sc> Tris, pH 8.0. For experiments using hexahistidine TPP1, the
 protein was preincubated with 1 m<sc>m</sc> E-64 to inhibit an insect cell
 thiol protease contaminant that was present in trace amounts in some
 preparations. Proenzyme (20 μl) was mixed with 180 μl of 0.1% Triton
 X-100, 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, and 100 m<sc>m</sc> sodium formate adjusted
 with HCl to the indicated pH. The reaction was incubated at 25 °C for the
 indicated time, and the activation process was terminated by diluting 1 part
 sample into 9 parts ice-cold 0.1% Triton X-100, 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 500
 m<sc>m</sc> sodium acetate, pH 5.0, frozen on dry ice, and stored at -80
 °C. The amount of enzymatically active TPP1 (total final TPP1
 concentration typically 1.5 n<sc>m</sc>) was measured using the previously
 described kinetic fluorescence assay
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>) using 200
 μ<sc>m</sc> Ala-Ala-Phe-AMC substrate in 0.1% Triton X-100, 150
 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 500 m<sc>m</sc> sodium acetate, pH 5.0. Data for
 activation conducted at pH 4.0 were fit to a one-phase exponential association
 model using built in functions in Prism version 5.01 (GraphPad software). The
 activation reactions at pH 2.5 to 3.5 were fit to an irreversible consecutive
 reaction model where the inactive TPP1 zymogen (Z) is converted to an
 intermediate (I) with partial activity, which is then converted into a fully
 active mature form (M) as shown in Reaction 1,</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="Image-01.jpg"/></p><p>Using this model, one can calculate the activity at any given time from
 Equation 1,
 <disp-formula><label>(Eq.1)</label><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\;\;v_{t}\hspace{1em}=\hspace{1em}v_{max}({\alpha}_{1}[{\mathrm{Z}}]_{t}\hspace{1em}+\hspace{1em}{\alpha}_{2}[{\mathrm{I}}]_{t}\hspace{1em}+\hspace{1em}{\alpha}_{3}[{\mathrm{M}}]_{t})\;\;\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
 Here <italic>v<sub>t</sub></italic> denotes the observed TPP1 enzymatic activity at
 any given time; <italic>v</italic><sub>max</sub> denotes the enzymatic activity of the
 preparation when existing as the fully activated form; α denotes the
 relative enzymatic activity of the different forms, and for any given time
 [Z]<italic><sub>t</sub></italic> + [I]<italic><sub>t</sub></italic> + [M]<italic><sub>t</sub></italic>
 is a constant that corresponds to the total added TPP1, with all existing as Z
 at time = 0. Data were fit using the integrated rate equations given in Ref.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref> using Prism version 5.01,
 with the following constraints: no activity for the zymogen
 (α<sub>1</sub> = 0), partial activity for the intermediate form (0 ≤
 α<sub>2</sub> ≤ 1), and maximal activity for the mature form
 (α<sub>3</sub> = 1).</p><p><italic>Protein Chemistry</italic>—Pro-TPP1 was activated as described above.
 For matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization time-of-flight mass
 spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS), reactions were terminated by mixing with an equal
 volume of ice-cold solution containing 0.5% trifluoroacetic acid, 50%
 acetonitrile, mixed with sinapinic acid matrix, and analyzed using an Applied
 Biosystems/MDS-Sciex 4800 mass spectrometer operated in the linear mode. For
 SDS-PAGE analysis, reactions were terminated using reducing sample buffer and
 fractionated on 10% NuPAGE BisTris gels using MOPS running buffer
 (Invitrogen). Gels were either stained using Sypro Ruby (Molecular Probes) or
 transferred to membranes, stained with Coomassie Blue, and relevant regions of
 the membrane excised and sequenced as described previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>).</p><p><italic>Crystallization of Pro-TPP1</italic>—Purified Endo H-deglycosylated
 pro-TPP1 was dialyzed into TC buffer containing 100 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl,
 concentrated to 7 mg/ml using a 30,000 centrifugal device (Millipore), and
 filtered through 0.22-μm pore size cellulose acetate filters (Corning
 Costar). Initial crystallization conditions were identified by high throughput
 screening at the Hauptman Woodward Medical Research Institute, Buffalo, NY. In
 the optimized condition, crystals of pro-TPP1 ranging in size between 50
 × 100 × 100 μm and 50 × 100 × 300 μm appeared in
 ∼3 days when set up and grown at 4 °C using hanging drop diffusion by
 mixing 1 μl of pro-TPP1 solution at 5 mg/ml and 1 μl of reservoir
 solution containing 0.1 <sc>m</sc> citrate, 4-7% polyethylene glycol 6000,
 pH 5.0.</p><p><italic>Data Collection, Structure Determination, and
 Refinement</italic>—Data for two native, one mercury-derivatized, and one
 lead-derivatized crystals were collected to 1.85 Å at X4C at the
 National Synchrotron Light Source, Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, NY.
 The lead and mercury derivatives were obtained by soaking the crystals
 overnight at 4 °C in reservoir solutions containing heavy atom salts at
 concentrations of 2.5 m<sc>m</sc> Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub> and 0.5
 m<sc>m</sc> C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>5</sub>HgCl. Cryoprotection was achieved with
 passage of the crystals held in cryoloops through 1-μl drops of 50%
 ethylene glycol for 1 s and flash-cooling in liquid N<sub>2</sub> stream. For
 all crystals, 180° of data with 1° oscillation angle were collected.
 All four data sets were processed and scaled in the primitive orthorhombic
 P2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub> space group using DENZO and SCALEPACK
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>)
 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref> and supplemental Table
 S1). Initial attempts for structure solution with molecular replacement using
 a homology model of TPP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>)
 or homologous structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>) did not yield reliable
 solutions. Furthermore, attempts for solving the structure by multiple
 isomorphous replacement using multiple heavy atom derivatives were
 unsuccessful because of lack of isomorphism between the datasets (supplemental
 Table S1). Subsequently, the crystal structure was solved by single wavelength
 anomalous dispersion (SAD) technique using the mercury dataset. Four mercury
 sites were obtained from the anomalous differences using SHELX programs
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>) with the HKL2MAP software
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>). The sites were used for
 SAD phasing at 2.5 Å resolution through Solve/Resolve
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>) as implemented in the
 software package Phenix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>).
 Taking advantage of the anisomorphism among the data sets, the SAD phases were
 improved and extended to 1.9 Å resolution through multiple crystal form
 averaging four data sets (two native, mercury-soaked and lead-soaked) using
 DMmulti (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>) integrated into
 CCP4 version 6.0 package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>).
 The initial model consisting of 511 of the 544 residues was obtained by
 automated chain tracing with the ARP/wARP routine
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>) using the averaged
 phases. The remaining residues were modeled following iterative cycles of
 maximum likelihood and isotropic temperature refinement with Refmac 5.1.2.4
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>), and manual model
 building using Coot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>). The
 Translation/Libration/Screw (TLS) motion determination server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>)
 was used to determine the optimal number of TLS groups (five groups used) and
 to generate parameters that were used in the final stages of refinement in
 refmac 5.1.2.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>). Initial
 models for solvent molecules were obtained from the Hic-up server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>). Solvent molecules with
 Fourier difference peaks greater than 3σ were included. The final model,
 refined to 1.85 Å with <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> and
 <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub> of 0.179 and 0.205, respectively, includes all 544
 residues, 1 bound Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion, 4
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl-<sc>d</sc>-glucosamine (GlcNAc) groups, 4 ethylene glycol
 molecules, and 237 water oxygen atoms
 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The structure was
 validated using the MOLPROBITY server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>), which reported 97.05% of
 the residues in the Ramachandran favored regions. Loop regions
 Thr<sup>191</sup>-Leu<sup>196</sup> and Glu<sup>395</sup>-Thr<sup>400</sup>
 were modeled using a combination of composite omit and difference Fourier maps
 calculated with map algorithms within CNS version 1.2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>), and side chain
 conformations for residues in the aforesaid loops as well as for residues
 Lys<sup>101</sup>, Glu<sup>232</sup>, Gln<sup>264</sup>, Arg<sup>268</sup>,
 and Arg<sup>297</sup> were modeled as the most common rotamer, because of
 disordered electron density corresponding to these regions.</p><p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p><bold>Data collection and refinement statistics</bold></p><p>Values corresponding to highest resolution shells are shown in
 parentheses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc008096505t001"/></table-wrap></p><p><italic>Structural Analyses</italic>—Superposition of structural models was
 accomplished using LSQKAB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>)
 from the CCP4 program suite version 6.0
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>). Structural comparisons
 were made using the Secondary Structure Matching server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>), and overall root mean
 square deviation (r.m.s.d.) values were obtained using the r.m.s.d.
 calculation algorithm within CNS version 1.2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>). The protein-protein
 interaction server (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>), the iMOLTALK server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>), and the WHATIF web
 interface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>) were used for
 analyses of interdomain and lattice contacts. Buried surface areas were
 calculated using CNS version 1.2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>), and all structural
 figures were generated using PyMOL version 1.0
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>).</p><p><italic>Electrostatic Potential Calculations</italic>—Analysis of pH
 dependence on interdomain binding energy in pro-TPP1 was accomplished using
 the Adaptive Poisson-Boltzmann Solver version 0.5.1 (APBS)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>). The PDB2PQR server
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref>) implementing the PARSE
 forcefield and the PROPKA program
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref>) to assign specific
 protonation states at different pH conditions (pH 2.5-8.0) was used to convert
 the pro-TPP1 protein data bank (PDB) coordinates to three sets of PQR files,
 one for the intact zymogen (residues 20-563) (Z<sub>pH</sub>), one for the
 propiece (residues 20-195) (P<sub>pH</sub>), and the third for the mature
 domain (residues 196-563) (M<sub>pH</sub>) for a given pH condition. These
 pH-specific PQR files were used as input for electrostatic binding energy
 calculations at that pH using a linearized Poisson-Boltzmann equation (PB)
 using cubic B-spline discretization of the charge distributions. PB
 calculations were performed at 298 K with a dielectric constant of 78.0 for
 water and 2.0 for the protein interior. The ion concentrations were set to
 0.15 <sc>m</sc> with ionic radius of 2.0 Å. Care was taken to remove
 self-interaction energies by using exactly the same grid spacing, length and
 center, determined by the psize.py script provided in the APBS distribution.
 The electrostatic binding energy at a given pH (<italic>BE</italic><sub>pH</sub>) is
 calculated by APBS as shown in Equation 2,
 <disp-formula><label>(Eq.2)</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\;\;BE_{{\mathrm{pH}}}\hspace{1em}=\hspace{1em}Z_{{\mathrm{pH}}}\hspace{1em}-\hspace{1em}(P_{{\mathrm{pH}}}\hspace{1em}+\hspace{1em}M_{{\mathrm{pH}}})\;\;\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
 </p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p><italic>Production of Deglycosylated TPP1</italic>—Initial attempts to obtain
 suitable crystals from previously characterized glycosylated recombinant human
 pro-TPP1 produced in insect cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) and in CHO cells
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>) were unsuccessful (data not
 shown).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref> Given that
 heterogeneity in glycosylation may have been a complicating factor, we tried
 different methods to deglycosylate the protein produced from CHO cells. In our
 hands, peptide:<italic>N</italic>-glycosidase F was not completely effective in
 removing oligosaccharides unless the protein was denatured, suggesting that
 steric hindrance prevented cleavage of the GlcNAc-Asn bond. Endo H, which
 cleaves between the first two Asn-linked Glc-NAc residues, was partially
 effective in deglycosylating the native molecule, but some <italic>N</italic>-linked
 glycans were retained, reflecting the presence of oligosaccharides that had
 been processed to Endo H-resistant forms
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref>). We therefore cultured the
 CHO cells in the presence of the endoplasmic reticulum mannosidase I inhibitor
 kifunensin, which prevents further processing of <italic>N</italic>-linked glycans to
 Endo H-resistant forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref>).
 When treated with Endo H, pro-TPP1 produced in this manner yielded a single
 species by SDS-PAGE analysis, corresponding to a deglycosylated form in which
 four single Asn-linked Glc-NAc monosaccharides remain, as confirmed by the
 crystal structure (supplemental Fig. S1 and see below).</p><p><italic>Properties of Deglycosylated TPP1</italic>—Glycosylation has been
 reported to be critical for the folding, processing, and/or stability of TPP1
 in cultured cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>). In this study, it was
 therefore important to compare the functional properties of deglycosylated
 TPP1 prepared for structural studies and the previously well characterized
 glycosylated native protein.</p><p>Purified pro-TPP1 is a zymogen that undergoes low pH-triggered
 autoactivation and processing
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>). The kinetics for
 autoactivation of deglycosylated pro-TPP1 were essentially identical to those
 for glycosylated protein produced from untreated CHO cells or a
 hexahistidine-tagged protein produced from insect cells
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Rates were greatly
 accelerated at lower pH values and showed biphasic kinetics at pH 3.5 and
 below (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>We also measured the activity of preactivated glycosylated and
 deglycosylated TPP1 using two different fluorogenic substrates,
 Ala-Ala-Phe-AMC and Arg-Nle-Nle-AMC. Initial rates were determined as a
 function of substrate concentration and pH. The <italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>
 values (<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>/protein concentration) for the deglycosylated
 and glycosylated proteins were similar
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>). Although it appeared that the deglycosylated protein
 had slightly higher activity, the difference fell within the variation that we
 typically observe with independent preparations of glycosylated TPP1. The
 Michaelis constant (<italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic>)
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>B</italic></xref>) and substrate specificity constant
 (<italic>k</italic><sub>cat</sub>/<italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic>)
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>) of the
 glycosylated and deglycosylated protein were essentially indistinguishable.
 Our results do not rule out a role for glycosylation in folding or trafficking
 of pro-TPP1, nor do they address the role of the terminal Asn-linked GlcNAc
 that remains after Endo H-deglycosylation. However, they do demonstrate that
 Endo H-deglycosylated TPP1 is equivalent in terms of autocatalytic and
 enzymatic function to fully glycosylated TPP1.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Autoactivation of pro-TPP1.</bold> Highly purified human recombinant TPP1
 preparations (<italic>filled circles,</italic> hexahistidine-tagged pro-TPP1 from an
 insect cell expression system; <italic>open circles</italic>, fully glycosylated
 pro-TPP1 from CHO cells; and <italic>open squares</italic>, Endo H-deglycosylated
 pro-TPP1 from kifunensin-treated CHO cells) were incubated at the indicated pH
 for the specified time before stopping the reaction and measuring TPP1
 activity as described under “Experimental Procedures.” Data for
 each experiment were normalized to plateau values, all of which were
 comparable. The curves shown are fit to the reaction curves for the
 hexahistidine-tagged pro-TPP1 preparation as described under
 “Experimental Procedures.”</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050001"/></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Enzymatic properties of glycosylated and Endo H-deglycosylated TPP1.</bold>
 CHO cell-produced enzyme preparations described in
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> were incubated at pH 3.5
 for 2 h at 37 °C. Enzyme activity measurements were conducted using eight
 different concentrations of either Ala-Ala-Phe-AMC (800 to 6.25
 μ<sc>m</sc>) or Arg-Nle-Nle-AMC (400 to 3.12 μ<sc>m</sc>) substrate.
 Final reactions contained 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 0.1% Triton X-100, and
 either 100 m<sc>m</sc> sodium formate, pH 2.5, or sodium acetate (all other
 pH values) adjusted to the indicated pH using HCl. Kinetic constants were
 calculated using the built-in Michaelis-Menten curve fitting functions in
 Prism version 5.01. <italic>Open symbols</italic> denote deglycosylated protein;
 <italic>filled symbols</italic> denote glycosylated protein. <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B,
 circles, k</italic><sub>cat</sub>; <italic>squares, K<sub>m</sub>. C, circles</italic>,
 Ala-Ala-Phe-AMC substrate; <italic>squares</italic>, Arg-Nle-Nle-AMC substrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050002"/></fig></p><p><italic>Crystal Structure of Pro-TPP1 Reveals a Conserved Subtilisinlike
 Fold</italic>—We have determined the crystal structure of the inactive
 precursor of Endo H-deglycosylated form of TPP1 at 1.85 Å resolution
 (supplemental Fig. S1 and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 3</xref>). The data processed in the
 P2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub> space group with one molecule in the
 asymmetric unit with a Mathhews coefficient and solvent content of 2.37
 Å<sup>3</sup>/Da and 48.0%, respectively. The structure is markedly
 similar to the glycosylated form of pro-TPP1 determined at 2.35 Å
 resolution in the P2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2 space group with two molecules
 in the asymmetric unit (PDB ID 3EE6). Superposition of C<sup>α</sup>
 coordinates of deglycosylated pro-TPP1 with those of the two chains of
 glycosylated pro-TPP1 yield r.m.s.d. values of 0.61 and 0.66 Å,
 respectively, with differences in positioning of a few solvent exposed loops
 and conformations of a couple of active site residues (as discussed below).
 Pro-TPP1 exhibits a characteristic bi-domain precursor structure with a
 C-shaped prodomain (residues Ser<sup>20</sup>-Phe<sup>169</sup>) tightly
 packed against a more globular catalytic domain (residues
 Leu<sup>196</sup>-Pro<sup>563</sup>) connected by a 24-residue linker
 (Gly<sup>172</sup>-Gly<sup>195</sup>). The propiece has an
 antiparallel-α/antiparallel-β fold and the catalytic domain has a
 typical subtilisin-like fold.</p><p>The N-terminal portion (residues 172-179) of the propiece linker is well
 ordered and threads through the substrate-binding groove making strong short
 distance contacts (one hydrogen bond, one salt bridge, and three hydrophobic
 interactions) with the catalytic domain. In contrast, the remaining portion of
 the linker (residues 180-195) loops out of the interface making only minimal
 long range van der Waal contacts. The conformation of this portion of the
 linker is stabilized by a few strong lattice contacts involving residues
 180-190 as discussed below. Interestingly, the well structured nature of the
 N-terminal portion of the linker is supported by identical conformations and
 its involvement in interdomain contacts in both glycosylated and
 deglycosylated structures. The flexible nature of the C-terminal portion of
 the linker is emphasized by its involvement in lattice contacts in the
 deglycosylated structure and by its absence in the glycosylated structure,
 possibly because of disorder. Furthermore, a TLS motion analysis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>)
 for evidence of thermal motion detects significant flexibility in the linker
 region as compared with the rest of the protein (supplemental Fig. S2). Such
 flexibility may be important in positioning the linker for autocatalytic
 cleavage during zymogen activation (see below).</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Overall structure of pro-TPP1.</bold> Stereo view of pro-TPP1 backbone
 depicted in coil representation with the propiece shown in <italic>cyan</italic> and
 <italic>blue</italic> and the catalytic domain in <italic>gold</italic> and <italic>red</italic>, for
 α helices and β strands, respectively, and the linker loop shown in
 <italic>magenta</italic>. Side chains of active site catalytic triad
 (Ser<sup>475</sup>, Glu<sup>272</sup>, and Asp<sup>276</sup>) and oxyanion
 hole (Asp<sup>360</sup>) residues are shown in CPK mode. Glycosylation sites
 with residual GlcNAc moieties (<italic>circles,</italic> Asn<sup>210</sup>,
 <italic>1</italic>; Asn<sup>286</sup>, <italic>2</italic>; Asn<sup>313</sup>, <italic>3</italic>; and
 Asn<sup>443</sup>, <italic>4</italic>) and disulfide bridges (<italic>squares,</italic>
 Cys<sup>111</sup>-Cys<sup>122</sup>, <italic>1</italic>;
 Cys<sup>365</sup>-Cys<sup>526</sup>, <italic>2</italic>; and
 Cys<sup>522</sup>-Cys<sup>537</sup>, <italic>3</italic>) are depicted in <italic>stick
 mode</italic>. A bound Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion is shown as a <italic>green
 sphere</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050003"/></fig></p><p>The structure has marked similarities with those of other S53 family
 members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>) in terms of the overall
 fold, barring minor differences in the presence or absence of a few secondary
 structural elements in both the propiece and mature domain and orientation of
 the linker (supplemental Figs. S3 and S4). Superpositions of
 C<sup>α</sup> coordinates of corresponding regions of pro-TPP1 with
 propiece of prokumamolisin (PDB ID 1T1E)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>), and mature enzymes of
 sedolisin (PDB ID 1GA4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>),
 kumamolisin (PDB ID 1GTG)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>), and kumamolisin-As (PDB
 ID 1SN7) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>) yield r.m.s.d.
 values of 2.17, 2.07, 1.81, and 1.92 Å, respectively. Compared with
 prokumamolisin, the propiece and mature domain in pro-TPP1 are more compact
 with 550 Å<sup>2</sup> more buried surface area than the former, whereas
 the respective linkers are oriented at an angle of ∼30° (supplemental
 Fig. S4). The total buried surface area between the propiece and mature domain
 in pro-TPP1 is 2200 A<sup>2</sup> with 22 direct and 10 water-mediated
 hydrogen bonds, 3 salt bridges, and 6 hydrophobic interactions (supplemental
 Fig. S5 and supplemental Table S2).</p><p>Key features of the S53 family members, including C<sup>α</sup>
 positions of catalytic residues forming the charge transfer complex
 (<italic>viz</italic>. Ser<sup>475</sup>, Glu<sup>272</sup>, Asp<sup>276</sup>, and
 Asp<sup>360</sup>), two <italic>cis</italic>-peptide bonds, and the calcium-binding
 site are conserved. Three <italic>cis</italic>-Pro residues are found in pro-TPP1
 (Pro<sup>379</sup>, Pro<sup>450</sup>, and Pro<sup>563</sup>), of which the
 former two are completely conserved in the bacterial homologs (supplemental
 Fig. S3). The structural role and binding partners of the octahedrally
 coordinated calcium ion, including the side chain carboxyl groups of
 Asp<sup>517</sup> and Asp<sup>453</sup>, backbone carbonyl groups of
 Val<sup>518</sup>, Gly<sup>539</sup>, and Gly<sup>541</sup>, and a bound water
 molecule, are conserved within the S53 family. In addition, three disulfide
 linkages unique to pro-TPP1 (<italic>viz.</italic>
 Cys<sup>111</sup>-Cys<sup>122</sup>, Cys<sup>365</sup>-Cys<sup>526</sup>, and
 Cys<sup>522</sup>-Cys<sup>537</sup>) stabilize the fold. The lone
 Cys<sup>227</sup> is completely buried within the core of the mature domain
 and is within hydrogen bonding distance of the side chain carboxyl of
 Asp<sup>276</sup> (see below).</p><p>Endo H treatment leaves one GlcNAc moiety at each <italic>N</italic>-linked
 glycosylation site. Mutagenesis data indicate that all five potential
 glycosylation sites of TPP1 (<italic>viz.</italic> Asn<sup>210</sup>,
 Asn<sup>222</sup>, Asn<sup>286</sup>, Asn<sup>313</sup>, and
 Asn<sup>443</sup>) are utilized
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>). We find clear evidence
 for single GlcNAc moieties at all sites except for Asn<sup>222</sup>, a
 surface residue, which is clearly not modified in our structure. The structure
 of the glycosylated form of pro-TPP1 also shows that Asn<sup>222</sup> is not
 utilized (PDB ID 3EE6). It is formally possible that this site is
 heterogeneously glycosylated and that crystallization conditions have selected
 out the four-sugar glycosylated form from a population of four- and five-sugar
 forms. In our structure, the GlcNAc moiety linked to Asn<sup>286</sup>
 participates in lattice contacts with a symmetry-related molecule
 (supplemental Fig. S6 and supplemental Table S3).</p><p><italic>Active Site of Pro-TPP1 and Maintenance of the Zymogen in the Inactive
 State</italic>—The active site in pro-TPP1 contains an SED
 (Ser<sup>475</sup>-Glu<sup>272</sup>-Asp<sup>276</sup>) catalytic triad,
 similar to all other members of the S53 family of serine peptidases and
 contrasting with the SHD catalytic triad of canonical serine peptidases. The
 replacement of the His residue with the acidic residue Glu in the S53 family
 allows the active site serine to function in nucleophilic attack of substrate
 at acidic pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>), with the
 Glu abstracting the hydroxyl proton from the serine
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>). In addition, there is a
 second conserved Asp residue (Asp<sup>360</sup>), designated here as D′,
 in place of a conserved Asn in the subtilisin family. The role of the latter
 is to bind and stabilize the oxyanion of the tetrahedral intermediate of the
 peptidase reaction by hydrogen bond interactions, as described by NMR analyses
 and high resolution crystal structures of members of the subtilisin family
 bound to inhibitors acting as transition-state analogs that mimic the
 tetrahedral intermediate (reviewed in Ref.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref72">72</xref>). The catalytic efficiency
 in proteolytic enzymes is significantly increased by transition-state
 stabilization of the tetrahedral intermediate in the reaction. Computational
 studies on kumamolisin-As suggest that the D′ residue has multiple roles
 in catalyzing peptide bond hydrolysis, serving as a general acid to protonate
 the substrate during formation of the tetrahedral intermediate and
 subsequently functioning as a general base, extracting a proton from the
 tetrahedral intermediate during conversion to the acyl enzyme
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref74">74</xref>). In TPP1, these roles are
 likely to be performed by Asp<sup>360</sup>. The D′ residue is conserved
 in the S53 family, suggesting a common proton transfer mechanism that
 distinguishes these enzymes from canonical serine proteases.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of the active site of pro-TPP1 zymogen with that of mature
 kumamolisin.</bold> Backbones are shown as <italic>ribbon</italic> representations with
 featured side chains in <italic>ball-and-stick</italic> mode, bound water molecules
 depicted as <italic>red spheres</italic>, and hydrogen bonds shown as <italic>dashed
 lines</italic> with distances in Å. <italic>A,</italic> stereo view of TPP1 showing
 catalytic residues in a conformation that is recalcitrant to activity. In
 TPP1, Glu<sup>272</sup> (<italic>E</italic>), Asp<sup>276</sup> (<italic>D</italic>), and
 Ser<sup>475</sup> (<italic>S</italic>) form the catalytic triad, and Asp<sup>360</sup>
 (<italic>D</italic>′) forms part of the stabilizing oxyanion hole.
 Ser<sup>324</sup> (<italic>S</italic>′) is completely conserved in the S53
 family. Backbone carbonyl groups are shown only for the Ser and S′
 residues. Side chain oxygen atoms are shown in <italic>red</italic> and backbone
 carbonyl oxygens in <italic>yellow</italic>. Both Glu<sup>272</sup> and
 Asp<sup>276</sup> side chains are oriented away from Ser<sup>475</sup>. The
 position of Glu<sup>272</sup> is stabilized by a hydrogen bond to
 Gln<sup>233</sup>. A bound water molecule (<italic>1</italic>) occupies the position
 expected for one of the carboxyl oxygens of Glu<sup>272</sup>, if the active
 site were poised for activity. One of the carboxyl oxygens of
 Asp<sup>276</sup> forms a hydrogen bond to a water molecule (<italic>2</italic>), and
 the other is within weak hydrogen bond distance to the sulfhydryl of unpaired
 Cys<sup>277</sup>. The side chain hydroxyls of Ser<sup>475</sup> and
 Ser<sup>324</sup> participate in a strong hydrogen bond. A third water
 molecule (<italic>3</italic>) makes a strong hydrogen bond with the Ser<sup>475</sup>
 hydroxyl and is also within hydrogen bond distance of the Asp<sup>360</sup>
 carboxyl constituting the oxyanion hole, close to where the carbonyl oxygen of
 the scissile peptide bond is expected to be positioned. <italic>B,</italic> comparison
 of catalytic machinery of pro-TPP1 with that in mature kumamolisin. Least
 square superpositions of C<sup>α</sup> coordinates of the pro-TPP1
 catalytic domain with those of all available structures of S53 family members
 were performed and yielded similar results. Superposition of TPP1 with mature
 kumamolisin (PDB ID 1GTL) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>)
 is shown with ribbon depictions in <italic>gray</italic> and <italic>green</italic>,
 respectively. Although the corresponding oxyanion D′ residues in TPP1
 and kumamolisin are in similar conformations, the corresponding catalytic Glu
 and Asp residues are both in different conformations. Furthermore, the
 S′ residue in TPP1 (Ser<sup>324</sup>) is in a different rotameric
 conformation, and its C<sup>α</sup> position is displaced by 1.5 Å
 from the corresponding S′ (Ser<sup>316</sup>) in kumamolisin, resulting
 in different hydrogen bond schemes with the active site Ser.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050004"/></fig></p><p>The crystal structure of pro-TPP1 reveals a number of features that help
 maintain the zymogen in an inactive state, with the active site assuming a
 geometry that is suboptimal for catalysis. Low pH-mediated pro-TPP1 zymogen
 maturation is likely to be associated with different positioning of key
 elements at the active site as well as different protonation states of active
 site carboxylates that might favor conformations poised for catalysis.</p><p>Although the C<sup>α</sup> positions of key catalytic residues,
 including SEDD′ are superimposable with those of corresponding residues
 in all previously determined structures of bacterial homologs
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>), the side chain
 conformations and hydrogen bond network at the active site in pro-TPP1 are
 different (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). As revealed
 by several high resolution crystal structures of free and inhibitor-bound
 mature enzymes of sedolisin, kumamolisin, and kumamolisin-As, the geometry of
 an active site poised for catalysis is characterized by a charge transfer
 complex involving the key SED residues with hydrogen bonds between one of the
 side chain carboxyl oxygens of the Glu with the hydroxyl of the Ser and the
 other with one of the carboxyl oxygens of the Asp. In contrast, in pro-TPP1,
 side chains of both Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> are directed away
 from each other and from the active site Ser<sup>475</sup>. Such alternate
 rotameric conformations of these catalytic residues allow hydrogen bonds
 distinct from those characteristic of a charge transfer complex
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). PROPKA predictions
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref>) yield
 p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> values of 3.6 and 6.4 for Glu<sup>272</sup> and
 Asp<sup>276</sup> in the mature enzyme, respectively (supplemental Table S4).
 From this it follows that such rotameric conformations for the Glu and the
 Asp, as observed in pro-TPP1, might arise from electrostatic charge repulsions
 and could likely be favored at neutral pH, at which both of these residues are
 predicted to be deprotonated and negatively charged. However, at the
 crystallization pH condition, pH 5.0, only Glu<sup>272</sup> and not
 Asp<sup>276</sup> is predicted to be deprotonated. The active site Glu is also
 found in dual conformations in some inhibitor complexes in structures of
 homologs crystallized at higher pH
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>). In addition, the
 conformations of Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> in the glycosylated
 form of pro-TPP1 are similar to those found in mature enzymes of bacterial
 homologs. These results suggest that the acidic residues at the active site
 most likely exist in equilibrium between alternate rotameric states and that
 different conditions favoring different pH-driven protonation states increase
 the probability of one state over another.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Model of peptide substrate in the TPP1 active site.</bold> The model was
 constructed by docking a hexapeptide substrate, AAFFAA, with a fixed position
 of the carbonyl oxygen of the P1 residue (Phe) relative to the catalytic
 domain of TPP1, based on the prokumamolisin structure (PDB ID 1T1E)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>), onto the catalytic
 domain of TPP1 in which the side chains of active site residues
 Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> were reoriented in the presumed active
 conformation as found in mature bacterial homologs. A ribbon diagram and a
 transparent surface rendition of the catalytic domain are shown in
 <italic>gray</italic>, a <italic>ball-and-stick</italic> depiction of the modeled hexapeptide
 substrate in <italic>yellow,</italic> and the superimposed linker with side chains of
 featured residues shown in <italic>ball-and-stick mode</italic> in <italic>cyan</italic>.
 Overlapping residues are shown in <italic>dotted surface</italic>. This model is an
 approximation because the positions of the <italic>m</italic>α3 helix with
 Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> as well as <italic>m</italic>β4 with
 Ser<sup>324</sup> together with the <italic>m</italic>β4-<italic>m</italic>β5 loop
 with Asp<sup>327</sup> are likely to differ in the mature enzyme
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). The N terminus of the
 tripeptide substrate is likely to interact with the Asp<sup>327</sup> side
 chain carboxyl groups. The predicted protonation state of Asp<sup>327</sup>
 (see text) is consistent with a role in binding to an unsubstituted positively
 charged N terminus of the P3 residue of a putative substrate, thus providing a
 possible structural basis for the tripeptidyl peptidase activity. In addition,
 in the absence of crystal lattice contacts, positively charged
 Arg<sup>183</sup> of the linker is likely to participate in electrostatic
 interactions with negatively charged Asp<sup>360</sup> of the oxyanion hole,
 potentially restricting its role in general acid and base catalysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050005"/></fig></p><p>Furthermore, in both structures of the glycosylated and Endo
 H-deglycosylated forms of pro-TPP1, the side chain hydroxyl group of the
 active site Ser<sup>475</sup> is also involved in a strong hydrogen bond with
 the side chain hydroxyl of Ser<sup>324</sup> at 2.6 Å. Interestingly,
 this Ser (designated here as S′) is completely conserved within the S53
 family (supplemental Fig. S3). It is noteworthy that in the crystal structures
 of mature enzymes of the bacterial homologs, the region of the protein
 containing the conserved S′ residue exhibits a different conformation
 and consequently a distinct hydrogen bond geometry with the active site Ser
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). For instance, in
 mature kumamolisin, the S′ residue Ser<sup>316</sup> is in a different
 rotameric conformation, and its C<sup>α</sup> position is displaced by
 1.5 Å away from that of the pro-TPP1 S′ Ser<sup>324</sup>. This
 geometry supports a hydrogen bond between the backbone carbonyl of the active
 site Ser<sup>466</sup> and the side chain hydroxyl of Ser<sup>316</sup> at 2.8
 Å (backbone-side chain bond) and another between the side chain hydroxyl
 of the active site Ser<sup>466</sup> and the backbone carbonyl of
 Ser<sup>316</sup> at 3.5 Å (side chain-backbone bond), in place of a
 strong side chain-side chain hydrogen bond in pro-TPP1. With lack of
 mutational data on this residue, its contribution to the catalytic machinery
 is not certain but is worth consideration because of its complete
 conservation. In pro-TPP1, Ser<sup>324</sup> is located at the tip of the
 <italic>m</italic>β4 strand. The differences in positioning of structural
 elements of this region compared with those in mature enzymes are likely
 propagated as a result of interdomain contacts involving residues C-terminal
 to Ser<sup>324</sup>, <italic>viz.</italic> within the
 <italic>m</italic>β4-<italic>m</italic>β5 loop and the <italic>m</italic>β5 strand
 (region III in supplemental Fig. S5).</p><p>The side chain conformation of the D′ residue Asp<sup>360</sup>
 constituting the oxyanion hole is indistinguishable from the corresponding
 residue in homologous structures except in prokumamolisin where the
 corresponding Asp<sup>352</sup> is in a different rotameric conformation. In
 addition, a bound water molecule (water 3) occupies a similar position as the
 backbone carbonyl of the scissile peptide bond of a substrate as observed upon
 superposition of the pro-TPP1 catalytic domain with an inhibitor bound
 homologous structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>).
 This water makes strong hydrogen bonds with the side chain oxygens of active
 site Ser<sup>475</sup> and Asp<sup>360</sup>
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>Zymogens are commonly kept in their inactive states by occlusion of their
 active sites by propeptides that function as competitive inhibitors, occupying
 the substrate-binding site in a nonhydrolyzable configuration (reviewed in
 Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75">75</xref>). To test whether the
 pro-TPP1 linker can function in this role, we docked a model hexapeptide
 substrate to the catalytic domain in which the side chain conformations of
 Glu<sup>272</sup> and Asp<sup>276</sup> were reoriented to assumed active
 conformations, based on the structures of mature enzymes of bacterial
 homologs. This hexapeptide was readily accommodated in the absence of the
 propiece linker. However, when the linker was superimposed on the docked
 model, the P3 and P3′ residues overlap with linker residues
 Pro<sup>178</sup> and Arg<sup>185</sup>, respectively, suggesting steric
 occlusion. The docking study further suggests that the linker residue
 Arg<sup>183</sup> would hinder approach of the substrate to the S2′ and
 S3′ subsites (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 5</xref>).</p><p>In addition, a putative salt bridge between the positively charged
 Arg<sup>183</sup> and negatively charged Asp<sup>360</sup> is also likely to
 render a nonfunctional oxyanion hole. This is consistent with the
 p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> of 4.7 predicted for Asp<sup>360</sup> in the zymogen
 form (supplemental Table S4). A corresponding salt bridge between
 Arg<sup>169</sup> and the oxyanion hole Asp<sup>352</sup> observed in
 prokumamolisin has been implicated in substrate-mediated inactivation
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>). However, in pro-TPP1
 this salt bridge is absent (&gt;5.0 Å), presumably because of crystal
 lattice interactions involving the linker region C-terminal to
 Arg<sup>183</sup> (supplemental Fig. S6).</p><p><italic>Structural Basis for Tripeptidyl Peptidase Activity</italic>—The
 substrate-binding subsite and the active site pocket are likely to undergo
 subtle changes in the mature enzyme with different rotameric conformations of
 catalytic triad and neighboring residues (such as Ser<sup>324</sup>, see
 above). Nevertheless, a docked model of a hexapeptide substrate AAFFAA
 revealed that the Asp<sup>327</sup> side chain is a likely candidate for
 binding to the positively charged unsubstituted N termini of P3 residues of
 substrates, thus facilitating release of tripeptides after catalysis
 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Asp<sup>327</sup> is
 completely conserved in all mammalian TPP1 proteins but not among the
 bacterial homologs (supplemental Fig. S3). Interestingly, in the latter, a
 neighboring Trp side chain blocks this region. In pro-TPP1, the
 Asp<sup>327</sup> carboxyl is 5.3 Å away from the N terminus of the
 modeled hexapeptide, although this is likely to change in the mature domain.
 In addition, p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> predictions using the PROPKA program
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref>) indicate that the
 p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> of Asp<sup>327</sup> is 6.2 when it is buried as part
 of pro-TPP1, whereas it is 3.9 when exposed in the mature enzyme. From this it
 follows that at pH &lt;3.9 it is likely to be protonated when its binding to
 the positively charged N terminus of a substrate is suboptimal. This
 correlates with the <italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic> profile of the enzyme, which
 reveals a substantial increase in <italic>K<sub>m</sub></italic> below pH 4.0
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Such a role for
 Asp<sup>327</sup> was also suggested from the previously predicted homology
 model for TPP1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>), supported
 by site-directed mutagenesis
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>).</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>FIGURE 6.</label><caption><p><bold>Model for autoproteolytic endopeptidase cleavage during pH-dependent
 pro-TPP1 zymogen maturation.</bold> <italic>A,</italic> MS analysis of autoproteolytic
 cleavage products. Endo H-deglycosylated pro-TPP1 was incubated at either 25
 °C for 0.5 min (pH 2.5 and 3.0), 6.3 min (pH 3.5), 13 min (pH 4.0), or at
 37 °C for 18 h (pH 4.5). Indicated <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> are those of the
 predicted TPP1 fragments spanning residues 20-168 (<italic>16640</italic>), 20-181
 (<italic>18024</italic>), and 20-189 (<italic>19029</italic>). Satellite peaks likely
 represent matrix adducts. <italic>B,</italic> endopeptidase cleavage sites and
 positions of ionizable residues at the interdomain interface. The pro-TPP1
 backbone is shown with the catalytic domain in <italic>orange</italic>, the prodomain
 in <italic>cyan,</italic> and the propiece linker in <italic>magenta</italic>. The
 endopeptidase cleavage sites (<italic>1</italic>, Ser<sup>181</sup>-Leu<sup>182</sup>;
 <italic>2</italic>, Gln<sup>189</sup>-Val<sup>190</sup>; and <italic>3</italic>,
 Asp<sup>168</sup>-Phe<sup>169</sup>) and active site residues
 (Ser<sup>475</sup>, Glu<sup>272</sup>, Asp<sup>276</sup>, and
 Asp<sup>360</sup>) are depicted in <italic>stick</italic> mode. The
 C<sup>α</sup> positions of ionizable interface residues with
 p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> values predicted to be within the relevant
 physiological pH range for TPP1 (supplemental Table S4) are shown as spheres:
 <italic>1</italic>, Glu<sup>232</sup>; <italic>2,</italic> Glu<sup>299</sup>; <italic>3,</italic>
 Glu<sup>302</sup>; <italic>4</italic>, Glu<sup>24</sup>; <italic>5</italic>, Asp<sup>26</sup>;
 <italic>6</italic>, Asp<sup>168</sup>; <italic>7</italic>; Asp<sup>118</sup>; <italic>8</italic>,
 Glu<sup>343</sup>; and <italic>9</italic>, Asp<sup>70</sup>. Details of these
 interactions are shown in supplemental Fig. S4 and supplemental Table S2.
 <italic>C,</italic> titration curve of binding energies of the propiece and mature
 domain of pro-TPP1. Binding energies were calculated as described under
 “Experimental Procedures.” <italic>D,</italic> model for pro-TPP1 zymogen
 maturation. A schematic depiction of pro-TPP1 is shown with colors, and
 endopeptidase cleavage sites and interdomain contacts involving ionizable
 residues are indicated as in <italic>B</italic>. The active site cleft is depicted as
 a <italic>triangle</italic> within the catalytic domain. The geometry of one side of
 the cleft (<italic>top half of triangle</italic>) defined by the acidic residues is
 subject to pH-driven protonation states, whereas the structure of the other
 side (<italic>lower half of triangle</italic>) defined by Ser<sup>475</sup> and
 Ser<sup>324</sup> is subject to restructuring by propagation of long range
 prodomain interactions. At higher pH, the prodomain and mature domains are
 tightly bound, and the active site catalytic machinery is preformed, and the
 active site exists in equilibrium between two states, one suboptimal for
 activity (<italic>hatched triangle</italic> with <italic>mouth closed</italic>) and one poised
 for activity (<italic>white triangle</italic> with <italic>open mouth</italic>). As the pH is
 lowered, changes in protonation states progressively disrupt interdomain
 interactions and affect the rotameric conformations of the active site
 residues favoring an active site geometry poised for catalysis. As the pH is
 lowered to ∼pH 4.5, electrostatic interactions holding the 3-strand leaf
 of the prodomain β-sandwich weaken and peel away from the interface. This
 is likely to result in repositioning of the linker loop bringing cleavage site
 1 close to the active site. At progressively lower pH, interactions involving
 the 4-strand leaf of the propiece β-sandwich are disrupted, resulting in
 a more open conformation. This allows sufficient kinking in the linker
 conformation so that site 2 can be brought close to the active site and
 targeted for endopeptidase action. At pH &lt;3.0, the interdomain binding
 interface is completely disrupted, allowing access to site 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050006"/></fig></p><p><italic>Model for Autoproteolytic Endopeptidase Cleavage of
 Pro-TPP1</italic>—MALDI-TOF-mass spectrometric (MS) analysis revealed
 differences in the size of the liberated propeptide at different pH values
 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>A</italic></xref>). This
 indicates that the zymogen can utilize three different endopeptidase cleavage
 sites (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>) as
 follows: 1) Ser<sup>181</sup>-Leu<sup>182</sup> site within pH range 4.0-4.5;
 2) Gln<sup>189</sup>-Val<sup>190</sup> site within pH range 3.0-4.0; and 3)
 Asp<sup>168</sup>-Phe<sup>169</sup> site within pH range 2.5-4.0. Cleavages at
 sites 1 and 2 have been reported previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>). Calculations using APBS
 electrostatic analysis software
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>) with pro-TPP1 domains
 revealed that the binding energy between the propiece and mature domain is
 more positive (<italic>i.e.</italic> interactions are less stable) with lower pH
 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>C</italic></xref>). A similar
 profile is also observed for calculations done using prokumamolisin
 coordinates (data not shown). This phenomenon of pH-induced effects on binding
 is intuitive. Key salt bridge interactions as well as hydrogen bonds
 contributed by ionizable residues may be disrupted at low pH where acidic
 residues are likely to become protonated. This conclusion is supported by a
 recent report that the extent of inhibition of TPP1 activity by the prodomain
 decreases with lower pH and is negligible at pH 3.5
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>). In addition, complex
 formation between kumamolisin-As E78H/D164N mutant mature domain and wild-type
 propiece was observed to be less at lower pH
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>). These results are
 consistent with a pH-induced change in binding between the propiece and the
 mature domain. In pro-TPP1, the binding interface has many electrostatic bonds
 and ionizable residues with p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> values within the
 physiological pH range (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 6<italic>B</italic></xref> and supplemental Fig. S6 and supplemental Tables S2
 and S4). Predictions of p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> values of ionizable residues
 at the interdomain interface reveal that these residues cluster into groups
 that map to specific regions of the binding interface (supplemental Fig. S6
 and supplemental Table S4). These regions are associated with distinct ranges
 of p<italic>K<sub>a</sub></italic> values, suggesting pH-specific disruption of domain
 contacts.</p><p>We propose a model of activation that takes into the account the pH-induced
 change in binding together with the pH-specific cleavage site preference
 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6<italic>D</italic></xref>). In the
 previously determined prokumamolisin structure, the cleavage site
 His<sup>171</sup>-Phe<sup>172</sup> is positioned close to the active site Ser
 (Ser<sup>466</sup>) (supplemental Fig. S4). This corresponds to cleavage site
 1 (Ser<sup>181</sup>-Leu<sup>182</sup>) in pro-TPP1, which is relatively close
 to the active site Ser<sup>475</sup>, with the carbonyl carbon of the scissile
 peptide being 12.0 Å away. In the absence of the lattice interactions
 that alter the position of the linker in our crystals grown at pH 5.0, this
 site is likely to approach Ser<sup>475</sup>. However, under the conditions
 that we use in our <italic>in vitro</italic> activation reactions, autocatalytic
 cleavage at pH 4.5 and above is extremely slow, with the intact pro-TPP1
 zymogen persisting for days (data not shown). It is likely that tight binding
 between the prodomain and catalytic domain at this pH holds the zymogen in a
 conformation that favors the nonoptimal active site geometry, and that the
 small amount of cleavage observed might arise from local breathing motions
 that allow acquisition of a conformationally active catalytic site. However,
 given that the prodomain retains high affinity for the catalytic domain and
 remains associated even after cleavage
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>), the equilibrium would
 favor the inactive conformation. At lower pH, the prodomain-catalytic domain
 interface could become destabilized, allowing assumption of a more
 conformationally optimal active site in the catalytic domain, as well as
 reorientation of the prodomain and linker. After endoproteolytic cleavage, the
 liberated propeptide as well as portions of the linker region still attached
 to the catalytic domain could then be further digested by the free catalytic
 domain (see below).</p><p>Consistent with this model, rates of pro-TPP1 activation are greatly
 accelerated in the presence of denaturants such as urea (supplemental Fig. S7)
 and guanidine hydrochloride (data not shown). In addition, the environment of
 late endosomes and lysosomes may be conducive to destabilization of the
 prodomain-catalytic domain complex, allowing rapid activation at the
 physiological pH of these organelles (pH 6 to 4.5)
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref76">76</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">77</xref>). For instance,
 glycosaminoglycans have been shown to accelerate autoactivation of pro-TPP1 at
 mildly acidic pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>), as do
 liposomes containing bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (also called
 lysobisphosphatidic
 acid),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref> an anionic
 lipid enriched in late endosomes
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref78">78</xref>). Nonetheless, decreasing
 the pH to optimize the protonation states of residues in the catalytic center,
 combined with reorientation of the catalytic serine and glutamic acid that
 would be favored by destabilization of the prodomain-catalytic domain
 interaction, are likely to be key elements in acquisition of activity.</p><p><italic>Pathway for Pro-TPP1 Processing in Vitro</italic>—Analysis of
 hexahistidine-tagged glycosylated recombinant TPP1 using SDS-PAGE
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>A</italic></xref>), chemical
 sequencing (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>C</italic></xref>),
 and MALDI-TOF MS (data not shown) corroborates the MS analysis of the Endo
 H-deglycosylated untagged TPP1 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 6<italic>A</italic></xref>), and it also reveals that autocatalytic processing
 involves a series of pH-dependent endoproteolytic cleavages and tripeptidyl
 aminopeptidase cleavages. At pH 4.0, the predominant initial cleavage products
 correspond to an intermediate starting at Val<sup>190</sup>
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>C</italic></xref>) and residues
 20-189 of the propeptide (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7<italic>A</italic></xref>, band marked F2 and MALDI-TOF MS; data not shown).
 Over time, the intermediate undergoes two tripeptidyl-peptidase cleavages,
 yielding an intermediate starting at Thr<sup>193</sup> and the mature protein
 starting at Leu<sup>196</sup> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7<italic>C</italic></xref>), whereas the liberated propeptide is degraded
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>A</italic></xref>). At pH 2.5,
 the predominant initial cleavage products correspond to an intermediate
 starting at Phe<sup>169</sup> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7</xref>, <italic>A</italic>, band marked <sup>*</sup>, and <italic>C</italic>) and
 residues 20-168 of the propeptide (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 7<italic>A</italic></xref>, band marked <italic>F3</italic> and MALDI-TOF MS; data not
 shown). With increasing time, the intermediate undergoes a second
 endoproteolytic cleavage to liberate the intermediate form starting at
 Val<sup>190</sup> with subsequent TPP1 cleavage as above
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>C</italic></xref>). Initial
 endoproteolytic cleavages of peptide bonds Asp<sup>168</sup>-Phe<sup>169</sup>
 and Gln<sup>189</sup>-Val<sup>190</sup> occur both at pH 3.0 and 2.5
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7, <italic>A</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic></xref>). In addition to the tripeptidylpeptidase cleavages of
 the form with an N-terminal Val<sup>190</sup> observed at pH 4.0, there is
 also processing of the form starting at Phe<sup>169</sup>, yielding
 intermediates with N-terminal Gly<sup>172</sup> and Arg<sup>175</sup>.</p><p>The observed cleavage pattern can be summarized by the pathway shown in
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>D</italic></xref>. This is
 entirely consistent with the known exopeptidase specificity of TPP1, where
 peptides with prolines at either P1 or P1′ are extremely poor substrates
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>), thus preventing further
 exopeptidyl digestion past Arg<sup>175</sup>. The Leu<sup>182</sup> N terminus
 produced by cleavage at pH 4.5 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 6<italic>A</italic></xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>)
 could not be processed by progressive tripeptidyl peptidase cleavages to yield
 mature TPP1 because of both frame and specificity considerations, and would be
 predicted to undergo a second endoproteolytic cleavage at
 Gln<sup>189</sup>-Val<sup>190</sup> to yield the form with an N-terminal
 Leu<sup>196</sup>. The liberated propeptide has an N terminus SYSP that is
 unlikely to be efficiently digested by TPP1 exopeptidase activity. Thus, in
 the absence of any additional proteases, its hydrolysis probably involves TPP1
 endoproteolytic cleavage. Activation at pH 4.0 can be accelerated by other
 proteases (data not shown), and given the protease-rich environment of the
 lysosome, it is likely that downstream hydrolysis of the initial propeptide
 cleavage product is not rate-limiting <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>It has been recently reported that the propeptide can inhibit the activity
 of mature TPP1 at neutral and mildly acidic pH, with an IC<sub>50</sub> in the
 micromolar range at pH 4.0
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>). Our results on comparing
 zymogen cleavage and acquisition of TPP1 activity are consistent with this.
 There was a marked lag between the two events at pH 4.0
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>B</italic></xref>,
 <italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub> cleavage ∼20 min;
 <italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub> activation ∼8 h). In contrast, the
 appearance and disappearance of the free propeptide could be fit with a
 two-step consecutive irreversible reaction model
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref>), with the second phase
 having a <italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub> of ∼7 h, paralleling that of
 acquisition of TPP1 activity. Thus, the lag is likely to reflect the time
 required for proteolysis of the inhibitory prodomain. The lag at lower pH
 values was much less pronounced, with the difference in the half-times between
 the first phase of the activation reaction and zymogen cleavage differing by
 at most a factor of 2 and both processes occurring rapidly
 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7<italic>B</italic></xref>, pH 2.5, 3.0,
 and 3.5; <italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub> cleavage 3, 6, and 20 s; and
 <italic>t</italic><sub>½</sub> activation 5, 12, and 20 s, respectively). This
 is consistent with rapid dissociation of the cleaved propeptide at more acidic
 pH values.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig7"><label>FIGURE 7.</label><caption><p><bold>Proteolytic processing and autoactivation of pro-TPP1 zymogen.</bold>
 <italic>A</italic>, autoproteolytic processing. Activation reactions were conducted
 using 1-1.5 μ<sc>m</sc> pro-TPP1, and aliquots (typically 0.5-1 μg)
 were analyzed by SDS-PAGE as described under “Experimental
 Procedures.” <italic>Z</italic>, position of ∼66-kDa glycosylated pro-TPP1
 zymogen; <italic>asterisk</italic>, ∼49-kDa intermediate; <italic>M</italic>, ∼46-kDa
 glycosylated mature TPP1; <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>2</sub>, and
 <italic>F</italic><sub>3</sub>, fragments cleaved at sites 1, 2, and 3, respectively,
 with assignment of F<sub>1</sub> being based on MALDI-TOF analysis of
 deglycosylated TPP1 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 6<italic>A</italic></xref>). <italic>B,</italic> comparison of proteolytic processing and
 acquisition of TPP1 activity. Two to four gels for each pH were used for the
 analysis and background-corrected intensity data normalized for each gel. The
 <italic>green upward pointing triangles</italic> indicate disappearance of zymogen at
 each time point, normalized to the intensity at <italic>t</italic> = 0 (<italic>e.g.</italic>
 1 - <italic>Zt</italic>/<italic>Zo</italic>). The <italic>red downward pointing triangles</italic>
 indicate levels of liberated propeptide (<italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub> +
 <italic>F</italic><sub>2</sub> + <italic>F</italic><sub>3</sub>), normalized to intensity of
 the highest value obtained for the reaction time course. <italic>Open circles</italic>
 indicate TPP1 activity measurements on activation reactions initiated using
 1.5 μ<sc>m</sc> zymogen. For comparison, data from
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> conducted using 15
 n<sc>m</sc> protein are presented using <italic>shaded circles</italic>. Although
 the time course was similar at both concentrations for pH 4 and 3.5, there
 were noticeable differences at pH 2.5 and 3.0. For the latter reactions, the
 initial phase for acquisition of activity was similar, but the second phase
 was noticeably slower for the high concentration reactions. The reason for
 this is not entirely obvious, but it may reflect experimental considerations
 such as some reassociation of the prodomain after the activation reactions
 were arrested by dilution into pH 5.0 buffer. Similarly, the faster time
 course and coincidence of the acquisition of enzymatic activity and
 endoproteolysis at pH 4.0 that we observed previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) may reflect differences
 in experimental design, where the reactions were terminated by dilution into
 pH 4.0 buffer and then assayed immediately for TPP1 activity. Under these
 conditions, the propeptide would be expected to be largely dissociated from
 the mature protein. <italic>C</italic>, N-terminal sequence analysis of
 autocatalytically processed TPP1. Activation reactions were conducted using
 1.5 μ<sc>m</sc> pro-TPP1. Protein (17 pmol/time point) was resolved by
 SDS-PAGE and transferred to membranes. Bands of molecular mass ranging between
 46 and 49 kDa were analyzed by chemical sequencing. The <italic>table</italic> lists
 the amount of each form in picomoles as estimated from the sequencing data
 (see “Experimental Procedures” for details). <italic>D</italic>, model for
 pro-TPP1 processing. <italic>Symbols</italic> are as in <italic>C</italic> and
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> (see text for
 details).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0080965050007"/></fig></p><p><italic>Biomedical Relevance</italic>—The structure of pro-TPP1 provides some
 insights into disease-causing mutations in LINCL (discussed in the
 accompanying paper by Pal <italic>et al.</italic>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref81">81</xref>) (supplemental Fig. S8).
 There are currently 57 mutations listed in the NCL mutation data base. Roughly
 half (29 mutations) are missense mutations, some of which could respond to
 small molecule chaperone therapy directed at stabilizing the aberrant protein
 and thus rescuing function. For these, the structure of pro-TPP1 may help in
 identifying such small molecule therapeutics. However, most individuals with
 LINCL would not benefit from this approach as two mutations that encode
 totally nonfunctional proteins represent the majority of disease alleles
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref79">79</xref>). One is an invariant
 3′ splice acceptor mutation in intron five that introduces a frameshift
 upstream of the Phe<sup>169</sup> codon; the other is a nonsense mutation at
 codon Arg<sup>208</sup> that does not appear to efficiently respond to
 potential therapeutics that promote translation readthrough
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref80">80</xref>).</p><p>Based on these and other considerations, any widely applicable therapy will
 need to target sufficient amounts of TPP1 to the brain to digest both newly
 arriving substrates and pre-existing lysosomal storage material. For enzyme
 replacement therapy using peripherally administered protein, it will be
 necessary to modify pro-TPP1 so that it can cross the blood-brain barrier
 (<italic>e.g.</italic> creation of a chimeric protein containing elements that allow
 transcytosis). In addition, for both enzyme and gene therapy approaches, it
 would be extremely useful to engineer functional TPP1 derivatives that have a
 longer half-life in the lysosome, thus increasing the effectiveness of
 properly targeted protein. Knowledge of the structure of TPP1 should be
 invaluable for such efforts.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplemental Data]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="M806943200_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="M806943200_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the Steinfeld and Sheldrick laboratories for sharing their
 manuscript and coordinates prior to submission; Bill Canfield for suggesting
 the use of and providing kifunensin to produce Endo H-sensitive pro-TPP1; John
 Taylor for advice and synthesis of fluorogenic peptide substrates; and Henry
 Lackland, Yanhong Wang, Caifeng Zhao, and Haiyan Zheng for invaluable
 assistance in protein production and analysis. We also thank the beamline
 staff at X4C and Seetharaman Jayaraman at the National Synchrotron Light
 Source at Brookhaven National Laboratories for technical help during data
 collection, Matthew Miller for assistance with data processing, and David
 Sleat and Vikas Nanda for helpful discussions.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sleat, D. E., Donnelly, R. J., Lackland, H., Liu, C. G., Sohar, I.,
 Pullarkat, R. K., and Lobel, P. (<year>1997</year>)
 <source>Science</source> <volume>277</volume>
 <fpage>1802</fpage>-1805<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9295267</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Rawlings, N. D., and Barrett, A. J. (<year>1999</year>)
 <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
 <volume>1429</volume>
 <fpage>496</fpage>-500<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9989235</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Vines, D. J., and Warburton, M. J. (<year>1999</year>)
 <source>FEBS Lett.</source> <volume>443</volume>
 <fpage>131</fpage>-135<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9989590</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Cabrera-Salazar, M. A., Roskelley, E. M., Bu, J., Hodges, B. L.,
 Yew, N., Dodge, J. C., Shihabuddin, L. S., Sohar, I., Sleat, D. E., Scheule,
 R. K., Davidson, B. L., Cheng, S. H., Lobel, P., and Passini, M. A.
 (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mol. Ther.</source>
 <volume>15</volume>
 <fpage>1782</fpage>-1788<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17637720</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x45e8e50">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Passini, M. A., Dodge, J. C., Bu, J., Yang, W., Zhao, Q., Sondhi,
 D., Hackett, N. R., Kaminsky, S. M., Mao, Q., Shihabuddin, L. S., Cheng, S.
 H., Sleat, D. E., Stewart, G. R., Davidson, B. L., Lobel, P., and Crystal, R.
 G. (<year>2006</year>) <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
 <volume>26</volume>
 <fpage>1334</fpage>-1342<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452657</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x45e90d8">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sondhi, D., Hackett, N. R., Peterson, D. A., Stratton, J., Baad,
 M., Travis, K. M., Wilson, J. M., and Crystal, R. G. (<year>2007</year>)
 <source>Mol. Ther.</source> <volume>15</volume>
 <fpage>481</fpage>-491<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17180118</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sondhi, D., Peterson, D. A., Edelstein, A. M., del Fierro, K.,
 Hackett, N. R., and Crystal, R. G. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Exp.
 Neurol.</source> <volume>213</volume>
 <fpage>18</fpage>-27<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18639872</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Worgall, S., Sondhi, D., Hackett, N. R., Kosofsky, B., Kekatpure,
 M. V., Neyzi, N., Dyke, J. P., Ballon, D., Heier, L., Greenwald, B. M.,
 Christos, P., Mazumdar, M., Souweidane, M. M., Kaplitt, M. G., and Crystal, R.
 G. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Hum. Gene Ther.</source>
 <volume>19</volume> <fpage>463</fpage>-474<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18473686</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lin, L., and Lobel, P. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Biochem.
 J.</source> <volume>357</volume>
 <fpage>49</fpage>-55<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11415435</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Chang, M., Cooper, J. D., Sleat, D. E., Cheng, S. H., Dodge, J. C.,
 Passini, M. A., Lobel, P., and Davidson, B. L. (<year>2008</year>)
 <source>Mol. Ther.</source> <volume>16</volume>
 <fpage>649</fpage>-656<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18362923</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Golabek, A. A., and Kida, E. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Biol.
 Chem.</source> <volume>387</volume>
 <fpage>1091</fpage>-1099<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16895480</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Sohar, I., Sleat, D. E., and Lobel, P. (<year>2004</year>) in
 <source>Handbook of Proteolytic Enzymes</source> (Barrett, A. J.,
 Rawlings, N. D., and Woessner, J. F., eds) 2nd Ed., pp.
 <fpage>1893</fpage>-1896 Elsevier/Academic Press, San
 Diego</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Golabek, A. A., Wujek, P., Walus, M., Bieler, S., Soto, C.,
 Wisniewski, K. E., and Kida, E. (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol.
 Chem.</source> <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>31058</fpage>-31067<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15143070</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lin, L., Sohar, I., Lackland, H., and Lobel, P. (<year>2001</year>)
 <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>276</volume>
 <fpage>2249</fpage>-2255<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11054422</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Golabek, A. A., Kida, E., Walus, M., Wujek, P., Mehta, P., and
 Wisniewski, K. E. (<year>2003</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>278</volume>
 <fpage>7135</fpage>-7145<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12488460</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Golabek, A. A., Walus, M., Wisniewski, K. E., and Kida, E.
 (<year>2005</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>280</volume>
 <fpage>7550</fpage>-7561<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15582991</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tsiakas, K., Steinfeld, R., Storch, S., Ezaki, J., Lukacs, Z.,
 Kominami, E., Kohlschutter, A., Ullrich, K., and Braulke, T.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Glycobiology</source>
 <volume>14</volume> <fpage>C1</fpage>-C5</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Page, A. E., Fuller, K., Chambers, T. J., and Warburton, M. J.
 (<year>1993</year>) <source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source>
 <volume>306</volume>
 <fpage>354</fpage>-359<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8215436</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Ezaki, J., Takeda-Ezaki, M., Oda, K., and Kominami, E.
 (<year>2000</year>) <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
 <volume>268</volume>
 <fpage>904</fpage>-908<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10679303</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Tian, Y., Sohar, I., Taylor, J. W., and Lobel, P.
 (<year>2006</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>281</volume>
 <fpage>6559</fpage>-6572<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339154</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <label>21</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Li, M., Gustchina, A., Oyama, H., Dunn, B. M., and
 Oda, K. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Acta Biochim. Pol.</source>
 <volume>50</volume> <fpage>81</fpage>-102<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12673349</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <label>22</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Rawlings, N. D., Tolle, D. P., and Barrett, A. J.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
 <volume>32</volume>
 <fpage>D160</fpage>-D164<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681384</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <label>23</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dauter, Z., Li, M., and Wlodawer, A. (<year>2001</year>)
 <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>57</volume> <fpage>239</fpage>-249<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11173470</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <label>24</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Li, M., Dauter, Z., Gustchina, A., Uchida, K., Oyama,
 H., Dunn, B. M., and Oda, K. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Nat. Struct.
 Biol.</source> <volume>8</volume>
 <fpage>442</fpage>-446<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11323721</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <label>25</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Li, M., Gustchina, A., Dauter, Z., Uchida, K., Oyama,
 H., Goldfarb, N. E., Dunn, B. M., and Oda, K. (<year>2001</year>)
 <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>40</volume>
 <fpage>15602</fpage>-15611<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11747435</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <label>26</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Li, M., Gustchina, A., Oyama, H., Oda, K., Beyer, B.
 B., Clemente, J., and Dunn, B. M. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Biochem.
 Biophys. Res. Commun.</source> <volume>314</volume>
 <fpage>638</fpage>-645<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14733955</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <label>27</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Comellas-Bigler, M., Fuentes-Prior, P., Maskos, K., Huber, R.,
 Oyama, H., Uchida, K., Dunn, B. M., Oda, K., and Bode, W. (<year>2002</year>)
 <source>Structure (Lond.)</source> <volume>10</volume>
 <fpage>865</fpage>-876</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <label>28</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Comellas-Bigler, M., Maskos, K., Huber, R., Oyama, H., Oda, K., and
 Bode, W. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Structure (Lond.)</source>
 <volume>12</volume>
 <fpage>1313</fpage>-1323</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <label>29</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Okubo, A., Li, M., Ashida, M., Oyama, H., Gustchina, A., Oda, K.,
 Dunn, B. M., Wlodawer, A., and Nakayama, T. (<year>2006</year>)
 <source>FEBS J.</source> <volume>273</volume>
 <fpage>2563</fpage>-2576<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16704427</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <label>30</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Li, M., Gustchina, A., Tsuruoka, N., Ashida, M.,
 Minakata, H., Oyama, H., Oda, K., Nishino, T., and Nakayama, T.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>21500</fpage>-21510<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15014068</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <label>31</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dodson, G., and Wlodawer, A. (<year>1998</year>) <source>Trends
 Biochem. Sci.</source> <volume>23</volume>
 <fpage>347</fpage>-352<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9787641</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <label>32</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kraut, J. (<year>1977</year>) <source>Annu. Rev.
 Biochem.</source> <volume>46</volume>
 <fpage>331</fpage>-358<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">332063</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <label>33</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wlodawer, A., Durell, S. R., Li, M., Oyama, H., Oda, K., and Dunn,
 B. M. (<year>2003</year>) <source>BMC Struct. Biol.</source>
 <volume>3</volume> <fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14609438</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <label>34</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Walus, M., Kida, E., Wisniewski, K. E., and Golabek, A. A.
 (<year>2005</year>) <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
 <volume>579</volume>
 <fpage>1383</fpage>-1388<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733845</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <label>35</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sohar, I., Lin, L., and Lobel, P. (<year>2000</year>)
 <source>Clin. Chem.</source> <volume>46</volume>
 <fpage>1005</fpage>-1008<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10894849</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <label>36</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Ferscht, A. (<year>1999</year>) <source>Structure and Mechanism
 in Protein Science: A Guide to Enzyme Catalysis and Protein
 Folding</source>, p. <fpage>144</fpage>, W. H. Freeman &amp;
 Co., New York</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <label>37</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Otwinowski, Z., and Minor, W. (<year>1997</year>)
 <source>Methods Enzymol.</source> <volume>276</volume>
 <fpage>307</fpage>-326</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <label>38</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Schneider, T. R., and Sheldrick, G. M. (<year>2002</year>)
 <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>58</volume>
 <fpage>1772</fpage>-1779<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12351820</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <label>39</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Pape, T., and Schneider, T. R. (<year>2004</year>) <source>J.
 Appl. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>37</volume>
 <fpage>843</fpage>-844</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <label>40</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Terwilliger, T. C. (<year>2000</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr.
 Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>56</volume>
 <fpage>965</fpage>-972<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944333</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <label>41</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Terwilliger, T. C., and Berendzen, J. (<year>1999</year>)
 <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>55</volume> <fpage>849</fpage>-861<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10089316</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <label>42</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Adams, P. D., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Hung, L. W., Ioerger, T. R.,
 McCoy, A. J., Moriarty, N. W., Read, R. J., Sacchettini, J. C., Sauter, N. K.,
 and Terwilliger, T. C. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect.
 D Biol. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>58</volume>
 <fpage>1948</fpage>-1954<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12393927</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref43">
        <label>43</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Cowtan, K. D., and Main, P. (<year>1993</year>) <source>Acta
 Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>49</volume> <fpage>148</fpage>-157<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299555</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref44">
        <label>44</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Project, C. C. (<year>1994</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr.
 Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>50</volume>
 <fpage>760</fpage>-763<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299374</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref45">
        <label>45</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lamzin, V. S., and Wilson, K. S. (<year>1993</year>)
 <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>49</volume> <fpage>129</fpage>-147<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299554</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref46">
        <label>46</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Murshudov, G. N., Vagin, A. A., and Dodson, E. J.
 (<year>1997</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol.
 Crystallogr.</source> <volume>53</volume>
 <fpage>240</fpage>-255<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299926</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref47">
        <label>47</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Emsley, P., and Cowtan, K. D. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Acta
 Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>60</volume>
 <fpage>2126</fpage>-2132<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref48">
        <label>48</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Painter, J., and Merritt, E. A. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Acta
 Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>61</volume> <fpage>465</fpage>-471<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809496</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x40d7f80">
        <label>49</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Painter, J., and Merritt, E. A. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Acta
 Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>62</volume> <fpage>439</fpage>-450<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16552146</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref50">
        <label>50</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Painter, J., and Merritt, E. A. (<year>2006</year>) <source>J.
 Appl. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>39</volume>
 <fpage>109</fpage>-111</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref51">
        <label>51</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kleywegt, G. J., and Jones, T. A. (<year>1998</year>)
 <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>54</volume>
 <fpage>1119</fpage>-1131<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10089488</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref52">
        <label>52</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Davis, I. W., Leaver-Fay, A., Chen, V. B., Block, J. N., Kapral, G.
 J., Wang, X., Murray, L. W., Arendall, W. B., III, Snoeyink, J., Richardson,
 J. S., and Richardson, D. C. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids
 Res.</source> <volume>35</volume>
 <fpage>W375</fpage>-W383<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452350</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref53">
        <label>53</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Brunger, A. T., Adams, P. D., Clore, G. M., DeLano, W. L., Gros,
 P., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W., Jiang, J. S., Kuszewski, J., Nilges, M., Pannu,
 N. S., Read, R. J., Rice, L. M., Simonson, T., and Warren, G. L.
 (<year>1998</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol.
 Crystallogr.</source> <volume>54</volume>
 <fpage>905</fpage>-921<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9757107</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref54">
        <label>54</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kabsch, W. (<year>1976</year>) <source>Acta Crystallogr. Sect.
 A</source> <volume>32</volume>
 <fpage>922</fpage>-923</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref55">
        <label>55</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Krissinel, E., and Henrick, K. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Acta
 Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
 <volume>60</volume>
 <fpage>2256</fpage>-2268<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572779</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref56">
        <label>56</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Jones, S., and Thornton, J. M. (<year>1996</year>) <source>Proc.
 Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source> <volume>93</volume>
 <fpage>13</fpage>-20<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552589</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref57">
        <label>57</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Reynolds, C., Damerell, D., and Jones, S. (<year>2008</year>)
 <source>Bioinformatics (Oxf.)</source></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref58">
        <label>58</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Diemand, A. V., and Scheib, H. (<year>2004</year>)
 <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> <volume>32</volume>
 <fpage>W512</fpage>-W516<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215439</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref59">
        <label>59</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Vriend, G. (<year>1990</year>) <source>J. Mol.
 Graphics</source> <volume>8</volume>
 <fpage>52</fpage>-56, 29</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref60">
        <label>60</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">DeLano, W. L. (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Pymol Molecular
 Graphics System</source>, DeLano Scientific, San Carlos, CA</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref61">
        <label>61</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Baker, N. A., Sept, D., Joseph, S., Holst, M. J., and McCammon, J.
 A. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
 <volume>98</volume>
 <fpage>10037</fpage>-10041<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11517324</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref62">
        <label>62</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dolinsky, T. J., Czodrowski, P., Li, H., Nielsen, J. E., Jensen, J.
 H., Klebe, G., and Baker, N. A. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids
 Res.</source> <volume>35</volume>
 <fpage>W522</fpage>-W525<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488841</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref63">
        <label>63</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dolinsky, T. J., Nielsen, J. E., McCammon, J. A., and Baker, N. A.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
 <volume>32</volume>
 <fpage>W665</fpage>-W667<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215472</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref64">
        <label>64</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Li, H., Robertson, A. D., and Jensen, J. H. (<year>2005</year>)
 <source>Proteins</source> <volume>61</volume>
 <fpage>704</fpage>-721<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16231289</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref65">
        <label>65</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Junaid, M. A., Wu, G., and Pullarkat, R. K. (<year>2000</year>)
 <source>J. Neurochem.</source> <volume>74</volume>
 <fpage>287</fpage>-294<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10617131</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref66">
        <label>66</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Chang, V. T., Crispin, M., Aricescu, A. R., Harvey, D. J.,
 Nettleship, J. E., Fennelly, J. A., Yu, C., Boles, K. S., Evans, E. J.,
 Stuart, D. I., Dwek, R. A., Jones, E. Y., Owens, R. J., and Davis, S. J.
 (<year>2007</year>) <source>Structure (Lond.)</source>
 <volume>15</volume> <fpage>267</fpage>-273</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref67">
        <label>67</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wujek, P., Kida, E., Walus, M., Wisniewski, K. E., and Golabek, A.
 A. (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>279</volume>
 <fpage>12827</fpage>-12839<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14702339</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref68">
        <label>68</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Golabek, A. A., Dolzhanskaya, N., Walus, M., Wisniewski, K. E., and
 Kida, E. (<year>2008</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>283</volume>
 <fpage>16497</fpage>-16504<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18411270</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x43553c8">
        <label>69</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Diederichs, K., and Karplus, P. A. (<year>1997</year>)
 <source>Nat. Struct. Biol.</source> <volume>4</volume>
 <fpage>269</fpage>-275<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9095194</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x4355650">
        <label>70</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Weiss, M. S. (<year>2001</year>) <source>J. Appl.
 Crystallogr.</source> <volume>34</volume>
 <fpage>130</fpage>-135</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1e9e6d0N0x43558d8">
        <label>71</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Weiss, M. S., and Hilgenfeld, R. (<year>1997</year>) <source>J.
 Appl. Crystallogr.</source> <volume>30</volume>
 <fpage>203</fpage>-205</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref72">
        <label>72</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Menard, R., and Storer, A. C. (<year>1992</year>) <source>Biol.
 Chem. Hoppe-Seyler</source> <volume>373</volume>
 <fpage>393</fpage>-400<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1387535</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref73">
        <label>73</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Guo, H., Wlodawer, A., Nakayama, T., and Xu, Q. (<year>2006</year>)
 <source>Biochemistry</source> <volume>45</volume>
 <fpage>9129</fpage>-9137<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16866358</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref74">
        <label>74</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Xu, Q., Guo, H. B., Wlodawer, A., Nakayama, T., and Guo, H.
 (<year>2007</year>) <source>Biochemistry</source>
 <volume>46</volume>
 <fpage>3784</fpage>-3792<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326662</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref75">
        <label>75</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Khan, A. R., and James, M. N. (<year>1998</year>)
 <source>Protein Sci.</source> <volume>7</volume>
 <fpage>815</fpage>-836<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568890</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref76">
        <label>76</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Majumdar, A., Cruz, D., Asamoah, N., Buxbaum, A., Sohar, I., Lobel,
 P., and Maxfield, F. R. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mol. Biol.
 Cell</source> <volume>18</volume>
 <fpage>1490</fpage>-1496<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314396</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref77">
        <label>77</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Maxfield, F. R., and McGraw, T. E. (<year>2004</year>)
 <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
 <volume>5</volume> <fpage>121</fpage>-132<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15040445</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref78">
        <label>78</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kolter, T., and Sandhoff, K. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Annu.
 Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>21</volume>
 <fpage>81</fpage>-103<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16212488</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref79">
        <label>79</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sleat, D. E., Gin, R. M., Sohar, I., Wisniewski, K.,
 Sklower-Brooks, S., Pullarkat, R. K., Palmer, D. N., Lerner, T. J., Boustany,
 R. M., Uldall, P., Siakotos, A. N., Donnelly, R. J., and Lobel, P.
 (<year>1999</year>) <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
 <volume>64</volume>
 <fpage>1511</fpage>-1523<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330339</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref80">
        <label>80</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sleat, D. E., Sohar, I., Gin, R. M., and Lobel, P.
 (<year>2001</year>) <source>Eur. J. Paediatr. Neurol.</source>
 <volume>5</volume> Suppl. A,
 <fpage>57</fpage>-62</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref81">
        <label>81</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Pal, A., Kraetzner, R., Gruene, T., Grapp, M., Schreiber, K.,
 Gronborg, M., Urlaub, H., Becker, S., Asif, A. R., Gärtner, J.,
 Sheldrick, G. M., and Steinfeld, R. (<year>2009</year>) <source>J. Biol.
 Chem</source>. <volume>264</volume> in press</citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn4">
        <label>3</label>
        <p>The abbreviations used are: LINCL, late infantile ceroid lipofuscinosis;
 TPP1, tripeptidyl-peptidase 1; CHO, Chinese hamster ovary; MOPS,
 3-(<italic>N</italic>-morpholino)propanesulfonic acid; PDB, Protein Data Bank; TLS,
 translation/libration/screw; GlcNAc,
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl-<sc>d</sc>-glucosamine; r.m.s.d., root mean square
 deviation; PB, Poisson-Boltzmann; APBS, adaptive PB solver; MS, mass
 spectrometry; MALDI-TOF, matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization
 time-of-flight; BisTris,
 2-[bis(2-hydroxyethyl)amino]-2-(hydroxymethyl)-propane-1,3-diol; Endo H,
 endoglycosidase H; SAD, single wavelength anomalous dispersion.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn5">
        <label>4</label>
        <p>R. Steinfeld and G. M. Sheldrick laboratories, personal communication.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn6">
        <label>5</label>
        <p>J. Clardy, personal communication.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn7">
        <label>6</label>
        <p>I. Sohar and P. Lobel, unpublished data.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>