<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:33:00Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2585845" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2585845</identifier><datestamp>2009-05-24</datestamp><setSpec>jexpmed</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jem</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2585845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2585845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2585845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955570</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20080990</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20080990</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955570</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Definitive Reports</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Brief Definitive Report</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Familial pulmonary alveolar proteinosis caused by mutations in <italic>CSF2RA</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Suzuki</surname>
            <given-names>Takuji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sakagami</surname>
            <given-names>Takuro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rubin</surname>
            <given-names>Bruce K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nogee</surname>
            <given-names>Lawrence M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wood</surname>
            <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zimmerman</surname>
            <given-names>Sarah L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smolarek</surname>
            <given-names>Teresa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dishop</surname>
            <given-names>Megan K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wert</surname>
            <given-names>Susan E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Whitsett</surname>
            <given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Grabowski</surname>
            <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Carey</surname>
            <given-names>Brenna C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stevens</surname>
            <given-names>Carrie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van der Loo</surname>
            <given-names>Johannes C.M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Trapnell</surname>
            <given-names>Bruce C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="N0x1cc3280N0x1e236d0"><label>1</label>Division of Pulmonary Biology, <label>2</label>Division of Pulmonary Medicine, <label>3</label>Division of Human Genetics, and <label>4</label>Division of Experimental Hematology and Cancer Biology, Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati, OH 45229</aff>
      <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Departments of Pediatrics and Biomedical Engineering, Wake Forest University School of Medicine, Winston-Salem, NC 27157</aff>
      <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21205</aff>
      <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Pathology, Texas Children's Hospital, Houston, TX 77030</aff>
      <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Division of Pulmonary, Critical Care, and Sleep Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, Cincinnati, OH 45267</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>CORRESPONDENCE Bruce C. Trapnell: <email>Bruce.Trapnell@cchmc.org</email></p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>24</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>205</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <fpage>2703</fpage>
      <lpage>2710</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2008 Suzuki et al.</copyright-statement>
        <license>
          <p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/misc/terms.shtml">http://www.jem.org/misc/terms.shtml</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jem2052703.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Primary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (PAP) is a rare syndrome characterized by accumulation of surfactant in the lungs that is presumed to be mediated by disruption of granulocyte/macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) signaling based on studies in genetically modified mice. The effects of GM-CSF are mediated by heterologous receptors composed of GM-CSF binding (GM-CSF-Rα) and nonbinding affinity-enhancing (GM-CSF-Rβ) subunits. We describe PAP, failure to thrive, and increased GM-CSF levels in two sisters aged 6 and 8 yr with abnormalities of both GM-CSF-Rα–encoding alleles (<italic>CSF2RA</italic>). One was a 1.6-Mb deletion in the pseudoautosomal region of one maternal X chromosome encompassing <italic>CSF2RA</italic>. The other, a point mutation in the paternal X chromosome allele encoding a G174R substitution, altered an N-linked glycosylation site within the cytokine binding domain and glycosylation of GM-CSF-Rα, severely reducing GM-CSF binding, receptor signaling, and GM-CSF–dependent functions in primary myeloid cells. Transfection of cloned cDNAs faithfully reproduced the signaling defect at physiological GM-CSF concentrations. Interestingly, at high GM-CSF concentrations similar to those observed in the index patient, signaling was partially rescued, thereby providing a molecular explanation for the slow progression of disease in these children. These results establish that GM-CSF signaling is critical for surfactant homeostasis in humans and demonstrate that mutations in <italic>CSF2RA</italic> cause familial PAP.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body><p>Pulmonary surfactant homeostasis is maintained by the balanced production of surfactant by alveolar epithelium and its clearance by pulmonary alveolar macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>). GM-CSF is a critical regulator of surfactant homeostasis in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>). GM-CSF, via heterologous cell surface receptors comprised of α and β glycoprotein subunits (GM-CSF-Rα and GM-CSF-Rβ, respectively), activates STAT5 and other signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>). N-linked glycosylation of the α subunit is required for GM-CSF binding and receptor signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>). In mice, deficiency of GM-CSF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>) or its receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>) impairs multiple functions of alveolar macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>), including surfactant catabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>), which results in progressive surfactant accumulation.</p><p>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (PAP) is a syndrome characterized by respiratory failure caused by pulmonary surfactant accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>), which can be grouped into distinct categories based on clinical, histopathologic, biochemical, and genetic data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>). Primary PAP occurs when GM-CSF signaling is disrupted, for example in individuals with high levels of GM-CSF autoantibodies, which are presumed to mediate pathogenesis by neutralizing GM-CSF and reducing surfactant catabolism by alveolar macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>). This form, referred to as autoimmune PAP, comprises 90% of cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>). Primary PAP has also been associated with reduced detection of GM-CSF-Rβ on myeloid cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>), but definitive studies demonstrating heritable deficiency of either GM-CSF or its receptors as the cause of PAP in humans are lacking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>). Secondary PAP occurs as a consequence of an underlying disease presumed to impair surfactant clearance by reducing either the numbers or functions of alveolar macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>). Hereditary disorders of surfactant production, for example, because of mutations in the genes encoding surfactant protein (SP)–B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>), SP-C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref>), or ABCA3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>), exhibit disordered surfactant homeostasis to varying degrees but are distinguished from PAP by their surfactant dysfunction, disruption of alveolar wall architecture, and clinical course (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>). In this paper, we describe a family in which two children developed primary PAP in association with loss of GM-CSF responsiveness caused by mutations in the gene encoding GM-CSF-Rα.</p><sec><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>Clinical presentation and phenotype</title><p>The index patient presented at age six with a 2-yr history of progressive tachypnea and failure to thrive (height and weight were third percentile for age [Fig. S1 A, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>]). Gestation, delivery, birth weight (3.66 kg, 50th percentile), and development were all normal, but weight gain slowed by 6–9 mo as did height by 2–3 yr. There was no history of cough, fever, chest pain, pneumonia or other pulmonary disease, environmental exposure, or drug use. Both parents were well-developed and healthy with no history of lung disease. Examination revealed moderate tachypnea, mild tachycardia, and inspiratory crackles but was otherwise unremarkable. Pulmonary function testing revealed severe restrictive impairment. Oxygen saturation was 88% while breathing room air and decreased while talking or walking a short distance. A diagnosis of PAP was suspected based on chest radiography (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 A</xref>) and established by histopathologic examination of lung tissue (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 B</xref>). A serum GM-CSF autoantibody test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>) was negative on two occasions. The patient was transferred to Cincinnati Children's Hospital and underwent whole lung lavage therapy with marked symptomatic and radiographical improvement (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 C</xref>). MCP-1 and M-CSF levels in the lavage were increased compared with healthy controls (supplemental text, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>), which is similar to findings in autoimmune PAP patients and GM-CSF KO mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Phenotypic characterization of patients with familial PAP.</bold> (A) Chest radiograph (top) and high-resolution computed tomogram of the chest (bottom) of the index patient at presentation. (B) Histopathologic appearance of the open lung biopsy from the index patient after staining with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) or immunostaining for SP-A, mature SP-B, Pro–SP-C, SP-D, and ABCA3. Note the lymphocytosis in the low-power hematoxylin and eosin–stained section and the intact alveolar wall in the high-powered hematoxylin and eosin–stained section. Images were obtained at a total magnification of 50× (top) or 400× (all others). Bars: (top) 100 μm; (all others) 10 μm. (C) Chest radiograph of the index patient 4 mo after presentation immediately before (top) and 5 d after (bottom) whole lung lavage therapy. (D) Serum SP-D levels in affected siblings, parents, and a control. The mean ± SD serum SP-D concentration in 67 healthy controls was 63.5 ± 39 ng/ml (hatched region) and in 12 patients with autoimmune PAP was 174 ± 83 ng/ml (not indicated). (E) High-resolution computed tomogram showing diffuse patchy ground glass opacities representing mild PAP in the affected sister.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052703f01"/></fig><p>An inherited defect in GM-CSF receptor function was suspected based on the constellation of histopathology showing well-preserved alveolar wall architecture (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 B</xref>), the absence of GM-CSF autoantibodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>), and an abnormal CD11b stimulation index test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>). Therefore, all immediate family members were evaluated. Because SP is in serum in PAP and levels reflect lung disease severity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref>), serum SP-D was measured and found to be increased in the patient compared with her parents and controls (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 D</xref>). Unexpectedly, the patient's 8-yr-old sister, who was previously thought to be healthy, had increased serum SP-D. Subsequent clinical evaluation revealed that the sister had poor growth (height and weight, 10th percentile for age; Fig. S1B), a diffusion capacity for carbon dioxide of 57% that predicted, and mild patchy ground glass opacities throughout both lungs, which are consistent with a diagnosis of PAP (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 E</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Structure and function of the GM-CSF receptor</title><p>Flow cytometry indicated that GM-CSF-Rα and GM-CSF-Rβ were present on blood leukocytes in all family members (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 A</xref>). Western blotting revealed an abnormal electrophoretic pattern for GM-CSF-Rα in the patient and her sister with predominantly lower molecular mass forms compared with the control (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 B</xref>). The father was heterozygous for normal and lower molecular mass forms. Unexpectedly, the mother exhibited only a normal pattern. To evaluate cell-mediated clearance of GM-CSF, blood mononuclear cells from the patient (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 C</xref>) and her sister (Fig. S2, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>) were incubated with GM-CSF, and both failed to clear GM-CSF in contrast to control and parental leukocytes. The concentration of GM-CSF in lung lavage was markedly increased in the patient compared with healthy controls, in whom it was undetectable (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 D</xref>). The in vivo concentration of pulmonary GM-CSF in the epithelial lining fluid of the lungs was estimated to be 6.9 and 27 ng/ml (right and left lungs, respectively) using the urea dilution method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>). Pulmonary GM-CSF was also increased in <italic>CSF2RB</italic>-deficient mice (Fig. S3), confirming the relationship between GM-CSF receptor dysfunction and increased pulmonary GM-CSF levels. Serum GM-CSF was increased in both affected siblings and undetectable in both parents and control, indicating that the abnormality was systemic (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 E</xref>). GM-CSF receptor function was impaired in both affected siblings, as shown by reduced GM-CSF–stimulated phosphorylation of STAT5 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 F</xref>) and failure of GM-CSF to increase CD11b levels on leukocytes from the patient compared with controls (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 G</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Structural and functional analysis of GM-CSF receptor defects.</bold> (A) Flow cytometry demonstrating GM-CSF-Rα and GM-CSF-Rβ on the cell surface of peripheral blood leukocytes in all family members. (B) Western blots of PBMC lysates using antibodies to detect GM-CSF-Rα or actin as indicated. (C) GM-CSF clearance assay. Blood leukocytes from the patient were unable to remove exogenous GM-CSF added to culture medium at time zero in contrast to leukocytes from two controls that rapidly bound and cleared GM-CSF. Error bars show the means ± SE. (D and E) Measurement of GM-CSF concentration by ELISA. GM-CSF was readily detected in lavage from the patient but was not detected (ND) in lung lavage from nine healthy controls (D). GM-CSF was detected in the serum of affected siblings but not their parents or a control (E). (F) Blood leukocytes isolated from the indicated family members were incubated for 15 min in the absence (−) or presence (+) of 10 ng/ml GM-CSF, followed by Western blotting of cell lysates to detect total STAT5 (STAT5), phosphorylated STAT5 (pSTAT5), or actin. (G) Measurement of the GM-CSF–stimulated increase in CD11b levels on leukocytes in whole blood. The CD11b stimulation index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>) was calculated as the mean fluorescence of CD11b on leukocytes incubated with GM-CSF minus that of unstimulated cells divided by that of unstimulated cells and multiplied by 100. (H) Similar to F except that a higher GM-CSF concentration (1,000 ng/ml) was used and cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-STAT5 antibody before Western blotting to detect total STAT5 (STAT5) or phosphorylated STAT5 (pSTAT5).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052703f02"/></fig><p>The slower-than-expected rate of progression of PAP in both affected siblings led us to hypothesize that the GM-CSF-Rα abnormality may not completely abolish GM-CSF signaling. This was confirmed by incubation of primary blood mononuclear cells with a higher concentration of GM-CSF (1,000 ng/ml), which resulted in partial receptor signaling as shown by an increase in phosphorylated STAT5 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 H</xref>). Thus, although both GM-CSF-Rα and β chains were present on leukocytes in all family members, in the two affected siblings, the GM-CSF-Rα chain was structurally abnormal, which severely reduced but did not completely abolish GM-CSF binding and GM-CSF–dependent signaling and cellular functions.</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic analysis of the GM-CSF receptor</title><p>The nucleotide sequence of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic> gene in genomic DNA from both siblings revealed a single G→A point mutation in exon 7 that encoded a nonconservative amino acid change (glycine to arginine) at position 174, G174R (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 A</xref>). This change alters one of the 11 potential sites of N-glycosylation, which is required for GM-CSF receptor function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>). The father was heterozygous for mutant <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> and WT (<italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup>) alleles (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 A</xref>), whereas only the <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup> sequence was detected in the mother (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 A</xref>). The sequence of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> in leukocyte messenger RNA (mRNA) was similar to the respective DNA sequence for each family member, even when cDNA was overamplified to detect potentially underrepresented mRNA sequences (unpublished data). This absence of a normal sequence for <italic>CSF2RA</italic> exon 7 in both siblings and the absence of the point mutation in the mother suggested that one maternal <italic>CSF2RA</italic> allele may be deleted in the patient, her sister, and their mother. The nucleotide sequence of <italic>CSF2RB</italic> in leukocyte mRNA from all family members was normal (unpublished data).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Genetic analysis of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> gene defects.</bold> (A) Nucleotide sequence of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> in genomic DNA from each family member, including nt 580–591 of the coding sequence (numbered relative to the initiation codon; from GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession no. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_006140.3">NM_006140.3</ext-link>). The index patient and her sister exhibited only a G→A point mutation at nt 586. The father was heterozygous for this substitution and the mother exhibited only the normal sequence. (B) FISH analysis to detect <italic>CSF2RA</italic> sequences in genomic DNA from the father and the patient. The probe (CTD-3047L21), which maps to the pseudoautosomal region (Xp22.33 and Yp11.32), hybridized to both X and Y chromosomes in the father (white arrows) and to one (white arrow), but not the other (yellow arrow), X chromosome in the patient. 8–10 metaphase cells and 25 interphase cells were evaluated for each individual. Similar FISH analyses are shown for each family member in the supplemental material (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>). Images were obtained at a total magnification of 1000×. (C) CGH analysis for the patient in the region of Xp22.33. The relative fluorescence of fluorescently labeled DNA from the patient (open circles) compared with a same-sex reference DNA (filled circles) after hybridization to various BAC clones on the SignatureSelect V2 chip representing the Xp22.33 region is shown. Reduced hybridization to several BAC clones (clones B and C) is indicated by the lower fluorescence of the patient's DNA compared with the reference DNA for these BAC clones. The telomeric breakpoint is mapped to between clones A and B and the centromeric breakpoint is mapped to between clones C and D. These data indicate an interstitial deletion of ∼1.264 Mb at Xp22.33 encompassing ∼1,610,183–2,873,864 bp. The dashed line represents a relative fluorescence of zero. (D) High-resolution SNP mapping of the Xp22 region for paternal and maternal X chromosomes. A schematic shows the locations of the point mutation (<italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup>) in the paternal X chromosome and the 1.6-Mb deletion at Xp22.33 in the maternal X chromosome and the genes encompassed. The base 2 ratio of normalized hybridization intensities for patient and reference samples (log R ratio) is shown. Similar SNP analyses for each family member are shown in the supplemental material (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>). (E) Map showing a portion of the X chromosome summarizing the genetic analysis used to identify the small maternal X chromosomal deletion at Xp22.33 encompassing <italic>CSF2RA</italic>. The probe used for FISH analysis (hatched bar) is the same as clone B on the CGH microarray chip. The locations of selected CGH microarray probes in the region of the CSF2RA gene are shown. Those CGH probes showing balanced hybridization to patient and control DNA are shown as clear boxes (A and D), whereas those showing an unbalanced hybridization representing sequences deleted in the patient are shown in black. High-resolution SNP analysis revealed that the deletion (red bar) extended from 1,308,324 to 2,881,011 bp. Sequence analysis (A) and PCR quantification of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> exon 7 (Fig. S4, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>) demonstrated that the deletion included <italic>CSF2RA</italic> exon 7. The chromosomal location of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic> gene (1,347,701–1,388,827 bp) is indicated. (F) Pedigree of the family deduced from sequencing and <italic>CSF2RA</italic> allelic copy number determination experiments. The index case is indicated (arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052703f03"/></fig><p>PCR amplification demonstrated a reduced copy number of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> in genomic DNA from both siblings and their mother compared with the father and a healthy control (Fig. S4, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>). In contrast, the genomic copy number of <italic>CSF2RB</italic> was similar in all family members and a control (Fig. S4). Routine cytogenetic analysis was normal in all family members (Fig. S5), ruling out a large chromosomal abnormality. Fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) demonstrated a deletion in the pseudoautosomal region 1 of the X chromosome in the patient (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 B</xref>), her sister, and mother (Fig. S6) that was not present in the father (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 B</xref>). Further evaluation using comparative genomic hybridization (CGH) demonstrated an interstitial deletion encompassing the region from ∼1,610,183 to 2,873,864 bp on one maternal-derived X chromosome in the patient (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 C</xref>), her sister, and mother (not depicted). High-resolution single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) mapping further defined this small deletion as extending from 1,308,324 to 2,881,011 bp in one maternal X chromosome (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 D</xref>) and in both siblings (Fig. S7). Importantly, this deletion encompassed the <italic>CSF2RA</italic> allele (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 E</xref>), thereby explaining the unexpected <italic>CSF2RA</italic> DNA and mRNA sequence results.</p><p>These results demonstrate the inheritance of compound heterozygous abnormalities of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> in both siblings (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 F</xref>). The G174R mutation present on the paternal X chromosome, localized to the extracellular cytokine binding domain of GM-CSF-Rα, alters a potential site of glycosylation and impairs GM-CSF binding and receptor signaling. However, it is unclear if the functional impairment is caused by the change in primary amino acid sequence or loss of glycosylation.</p></sec><sec><title>Reproduction of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> abnormality</title><p>To reproduce the GM-CSF receptor signaling defect identified in this family, plasmids expressing <italic>CSF2RB</italic> and either <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> or <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup> were cotransfected into 293 cells. Western blotting showed receptor proteins of the expected size from <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup> and smaller molecular forms from <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4 A</xref>), which is similar to results for primary leukocytes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 B</xref>). Treatment of transduced cell lysates with Peptide: N-Glycosidase F, an amidase that cleaves between the innermost GlcNAc and asparagine residues of high mannose oligosaccharides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>), resulted in a similar electrophoretic pattern for normal and G174R GM-CSF-Rα. This confirmed the G174R mutation alters N-linked glycosylation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4 A</xref>) by disrupting a functional N-linked glycosylation site and that glycosylation is responsible for the smaller molecular forms from this allele. GM-CSF-Rβ was expressed in <italic>CSF2RB</italic>-transfected cells but was undetectable in nontransfected cells (unpublished data). GM-CSF binding studies demonstrated that cells expressing <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup> and <italic>CSF2RB</italic> rapidly bound GM-CSF and removed it from the media, whereas cells expressing <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> and <italic>CSF2RB</italic> or <italic>CSF2RB</italic> alone did not clear GM-CSF (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4 B</xref>). Cotransfection of <italic>CSF2RB</italic> together with <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup>, but not with <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup>, resulted in expression of functional GM-CSF receptors as demonstrated by GM-CSF–dependent phosphorylation of STAT5 only with the former combination (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4 C</xref>). Incubation of <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup>/<italic>CSF2RB</italic>-transduced cells with higher concentrations of GM-CSF in the range of those observed in the index patient gave results similar to those obtained with primary leukocytes and clearly demonstrated a modest dose-dependent increase in STAT5 phosphorylation, which is consistent with a partial rescue of the signaling abnormality (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4 D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Reproduction of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> gene defect.</bold> (A) Western blots of nontransfected 293 cell lysates (control) or lysates of cells transfected with plasmids expressing <italic>CSF2RB</italic> and either <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup> (WT) or <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> (G174R), followed by incubation with (+) or without (−) Peptide: N-Glycosidase F (PNGase F) and detection with antibodies against GM-CSF-Rα or actin. (B) Evaluation of cell-mediated binding and removal of exogenous GM-CSF from the culture media. Asterisks indicate significant differences in levels of GM-CSF in media from cells expressing <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>WT</sup>/<italic>CSF2RB</italic> compared with cells expressing <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup>/<italic>CSF2RB</italic>, <italic>CSF2RB</italic> alone or media without cells. Error bars show the means ± SE. (C) Evaluation of GM-CSF–stimulated phosphorylation of STAT5 in 293 cells transfected as described in A and incubated for 15 min in the absence (−) or presence (+) of 10 ng/ml GM-CSF. Lysates were evaluated by Western blotting (WB) to detect total STAT5 (STAT5) or were immunoprecipitated with anti-STAT5 antibody and then evaluated by Western blotting (IP + WB) to detect total STAT5 or phosphorylated STAT5 (pSTAT5). (D) Similar to C, except that increased concentrations of GM-CSF were used for evaluate GM-CSF receptor function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052703f04"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Clinical relevance of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic><sup>G174R</sup> mutation</title><p>Our findings demonstrate that familial primary PAP in humans is caused by compound heterozygous abnormalities of <italic>CSF2RA</italic>, including loss of heterozygosity and a function-altering point mutation that severely reduces GM-CSF receptor signaling. These are the first results to demonstrate familial primary PAP in humans and that GM-CSF-Rα is critical for surfactant homeostasis. They extend previous findings that PAP is caused by the absence of GM-CSF or GM-CSF-Rβ in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>) or is specifically associated with the presence of neutralizing GM-CSF autoantibodies or a reduction in alveolar macrophage numbers or function in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). The allelic frequency of these mutations has not been determined but may be rare given that autoantibodies against GM-CSF account for most individuals with PAP.</p><p>Both affected siblings had impaired pulmonary function and failure to thrive, supporting the conclusion that prolonged respiratory insufficiency in children retards growth. Important to this conclusion is the observation that Xp22.33 deletion did not include the <italic>SHOX</italic> (<italic>short stature homeobox</italic>) gene, the deletion of which impairs growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>). Further, heterozygous loss of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> in the mother did not impair growth. Early results suggest that whole lung lavage therapy was followed by an increase in growth acceleration in the index patient.</p><p>This study highlights the usefulness of several novel biomarkers in the diagnostic evaluation of PAP. The combination of a negative GM-CSF autoantibody test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>) and an abnormal CD11b stimulation index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>) predicted the GM-CSF receptor dysfunction, which was confirmed by the lack of GM-CSF binding and defective GM-CSF receptor signaling. GM-CSF levels were increased in lung lavage from the patient and, in serum from the patient and her sister, compared with family members and healthy controls. Because primary PAP is presumed to be caused by a defect in GM-CSF regulation of alveolar macrophage surfactant catabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>), an elevated serum GM-CSF level may be useful as a biomarker to distinguish primary PAP caused by GM-CSF autoantibodies (90% of all cases of PAP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref>) from PAP caused by GM-CSF receptor dysfunction (this study; references <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>) and PAP caused by GM-CSF deficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>) (not yet reported in humans). Finally, an increased serum SP-D level predicted the occurrence of PAP in the sister, which was confirmed by subsequent clinical and radiographical evaluation.</p><p>The slow progression and differences in severity of the lung disease between affected siblings with the same <italic>CSF2RA</italic> mutations and GM-CSF-Rα dysfunction indicates that penetrance is important in familial PAP because of GM-CSF receptor defects. The increased levels of GM-CSF likely reflect impaired clearance but are also consistent with interruption of a negative-feedback regulatory loop. Results strongly suggest that the high levels of pulmonary GM-CSF present in epithelial lining fluid result in a reduced but not abrogated receptor signaling and provide a molecular explanation the slow progression of PAP in both affected siblings. It is currently unclear if the level of increased pulmonary GM-CSF correlates with disease severity. They also suggest that aerosolized delivery of GM-CSF to the lungs may be therapeutic because this approach could theoretically achieve pulmonary GM-CSF levels several thousand–fold higher than endogenous levels measured in the patient and 20-fold higher than levels that appeared to completely restore GM-CSF receptor signaling in the transfection experiments. BM transplantation and <italic>CSF2RA</italic> gene transfer represent other potentially therapeutic approaches.</p><p>The identification of mild PAP in the older sister provides a unique and important opportunity to observe PAP at a very early stage of disease development. Finally, this case exemplifies the utility of a collaborative approach to the diagnosis and treatment of individuals with very rare diseases involving geographically disparate clinical centers and the benefit derived from integrating basic science, clinical medicine, and translational research.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="3"><title>Participants.</title><p>The institutional review board of the Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center approved the study, and all participants gave written informed consent or assent. Detailed case histories and laboratory data for the participants are included in the supplemental text (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>GM-CSF receptor structure and function.</title><p>GM-CSF receptors were evaluated by flow cytometry using antibodies recognizing GM-CSF-Rα (BD) or β (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) and by Western blotting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>) with chain-specific antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). The effects of glycosylation on GM-CSF-Rα were evaluated by incubating cell lysates with PNGase F (New England Biolabs, Inc.) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>). Actin was measured as a loading control using anti-actin antibodies (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). To evaluate receptor-mediated clearance of GM-CSF, Ficoll-purified blood leukocytes or 293 cells (American Type Culture Collection) were cultured in DMEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum and human GM-CSF (Leukine; Bayer) at 1 ng/ml. At subsequent times, GM-CSF was measured in the culture medium by ELISA (R&amp;D Systems) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>). To evaluate GM-CSF receptor signaling, heparinized blood was incubated with or without 10 ng/ml of human GM-CSF Leukine for 15 min. After lysing RBC, leukocytes were evaluated by Western blotting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>) using anti–human STAT5 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) and anti–phospho-STAT5 (Millipore) antibodies. The CD11b stimulation index was measured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>ELISA.</title><p>SP-D, GM-CSF, MCP-1 (monocyte chemotactic protein-1), M-CSF, and urea were measured using commercial ELISA kits (BioVendor, R&amp;D Systems, BD, R&amp;D Systems, and BioAssay Systems, respectively) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>). The concentration of cytokines in epithelial lining fluid of the lungs was estimated by multiplying the concentration in lavage fluid by the ratio of urea concentrations in serum and lavage fluid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Genetic analysis.</title><p>Genomic DNA or total mRNA was purified from blood leukocytes with commercially available kits (QIAGEN). The PCR was used to generate products spanning exons and flanking intronic sequences (genomic DNA) or the coding sequences and 5′ and 3′ flanking untranslated sequences (mRNA) of the <italic>CSF2RA</italic> and <italic>CSF2RB</italic> genes, which were then analyzed by direct sequencing. The resulting sequences were compared with published sequences (from GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession nos. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_006140.3">NM_006140.3</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="BC070085">BC070085</ext-link>, respectively). The relative copy number of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> and <italic>CSF2RB</italic> genes among family members and a healthy control was measured by amplification of genomic DNA using PCR with gene-specific oligonucleotides followed by analysis of products by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gels. Experimental methods for measuring gene copy number, evaluating the genes encoding SP-B, SP-C, and ABCA3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>) for function-altering mutations, cytogenetic analysis, CGH analysis, FISH, and high-resolution SNP array analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>) are described in the supplemental Materials and methods (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Reproduction of the GM-CSF receptor defect.</title><p>The methods used to clone and express mRNA transcripts encoding GM-CSF-Rα and β chains in cultured cells and evaluate protein glycosylation are described in the supplemental Materials and methods.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p>Numeric data are presented as means ± SE. Statistical comparisons were made with Student's <italic>t</italic> test for two-group comparisons and with one-way analysis of variance with posthoc analysis according to the Holm-Sidak method for multiple-group comparisons. P-values of &lt;0.05 were considered to indicate statistical significance.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Online supplemental material.</title><p>Fig. S1 shows normalized growth curves for the index patient and her sister. Fig. S2 shows GM-CSF binding and clearance by blood leukocytes from affected and unaffected family members and control. Fig. S3 shows increased pulmonary GM-CSF levels in GM-CSF receptor β chain (<italic>Csf2rb</italic>) KO mice. Fig. S4 shows evaluation of <italic>CSF2RA</italic> and CSF2FB gene copy number by PCR amplification. Fig. S5 shows karyotypes of high-resolution GTG-banded chromosomes. Fig. S6 shows evaluation of heterozygosity at the <italic>CSF2RA</italic> locus by FISH. Fig. S7 shows high-resolution SNP analysis. The supplemental text contains additional details regarding the case histories and clinical laboratory and other data cited throughout the text. Online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20080990/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplemental Material Index]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_1.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS1.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS1-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_2.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS2.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS2-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_3.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS3.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS3-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_4.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS4.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS4-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_5.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS5.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS5-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_6.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS6.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS6-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20080990_7.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS7.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20080990_JEM_20080990_FS7-01.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="jem.20080990_8.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Diana Koch, Diane Black, Paula Blair, and Ralph Stanley (Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center) for excellent technical assistance, Dr. Denis McGraw (University of Cincinnati Medical Center) for performing bronchoalveolar lavage in healthy controls, Dr. Frank McCormack (University of Cincinnati College of Medicine) for helpful discussions, and Lauren Vannoy (Wake Forest University School of Medicine and the Translational Research Trials Office, Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical) for clinical research coordination.</p>
      <p>This work was supported in part by the grants from the National Center For Research Resources (RR019498 to B.C. Trapnell to support the Rare Lung Diseases Consortium) and the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (HL085453 to B.C. Trapnell and HL085610 to J.A. Whitsett), and the Division of Pulmonary Biology at the Children's Hospital Medical Center.</p>
      <p>The authors have no conflicting financial interests.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Trapnell, B.C., and J.A. Whitsett. <year>2002</year>. GM-CSF regulates pulmonary surfactant homeostasis and alveolar macrophage-mediated innate host defense. <source>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</source> <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>–802.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826288</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Guthridge, M.A., J.A. Powell, E.F. Barry, F.C. Stomski, B.J. McClure, H. Ramshaw, F.A. Felquer, M. Dottore, D.T. Thomas, B. To, et al. <year>2006</year>. Growth factor pleiotropy is controlled by a receptor Tyr/Ser motif that acts as a binary switch. <source>EMBO J.</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>–489.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16437163</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shibuya, K., S. Chiba, K. Miyagawa, T. Kitamura, K. Miyazono, and F. Takaku. <year>1991</year>. Structural and functional analyses of glycosylation on the distinct molecules of human GM-CSF receptors. <source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source> <volume>198</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>–666.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1828762</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dranoff, G., A.D. Crawford, M. Sadelain, B. Ream, A. Rashid, R.T. Bronson, G.R. Dickersin, C.J. Bachurski, E.L. Mark, J.A. Whitsett, et al. <year>1994</year>. Involvement of granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor in pulmonary homeostasis. <source>Science.</source> <volume>264</volume>:<fpage>713</fpage>–716.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8171324</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Stanley, E., G.J. Lieschke, D. Grail, D. Metcalf, G. Hodgson, J.A. Gall, D.W. Maher, J. Cebon, V. Sinickas, and A.R. Dunn. <year>1994</year>. Granulocyte/macrophage colony-stimulating factor-deficient mice show no major perturbation of hematopoiesis but develop a characteristic pulmonary pathology. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source> <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>5592</fpage>–5596.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8202532</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Robb, L., C.C. Drinkwater, D. Metcalf, R. Li, F. Kontgen, N.A. Nicola, and C.G. Begley. <year>1995</year>. Hematopoietic and lung abnormalities in mice with a null mutation of the common beta subunit of the receptors for granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor and interleukins 3 and 5. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source> <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>9565</fpage>–9569.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7568173</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shibata, Y., P.Y. Berclaz, Z.C. Chroneos, M. Yoshida, J.A. Whitsett, and B.C. Trapnell. <year>2001</year>. GM-CSF regulates alveolar macrophage differentiation and innate immunity in the lung through PU.1. <source>Immunity.</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>–567.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11672538</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Ikegami, M., T. Ueda, W. Hull, J.A. Whitsett, R.C. Mulligan, G. Dranoff, and A.H. Jobe. <year>1996</year>. Surfactant metabolism in transgenic mice after granulocyte macrophage-colony stimulating factor ablation. <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source> <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>L650</fpage>–L658.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8928826</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Seymour, J.F., and J.J. Presneill. <year>2002</year>. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis: progress in the first 44 years. <source>Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med.</source> <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>–235.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119235</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Trapnell, B.C., J.A. Whitsett, and K. Nakata. <year>2003</year>. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>349</volume>:<fpage>2527</fpage>–2539.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14695413</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Presneill, J.J., K. Nakata, Y. Inoue, and J.F. Seymour. <year>2004</year>. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>Clin. Chest Med.</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>–613.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331195</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Seymour, J.F., and J.J. Presneill. <year>2004</year>. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. What is the role of GM-CSF in disease pathogenesis and treatment? <source>Treat. Respir. Med.</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>–234.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15350161</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Inoue, Y., B.C. Trapnell, R. Tazawa, T. Arai, T. Takada, N. Hizawa, Y. Kasahara, K. Tatsumi, M. Hojo, T. Ichiwata, et al. <year>2008</year>. Characteristics of a large cohort of patients with autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis in Japan. <source>Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med.</source> <volume>177</volume>:<fpage>752</fpage>–762.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202348</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dirksen, U., R. Nishinakamura, P. Groneck, U. Hattenhorst, L. Nogee, R. Murray, and S. Burdach. <year>1997</year>. Human pulmonary alveolar proteinosis associated with a defect in GM-CSF/IL-3/IL-5 receptor common beta chain expression. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source> <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>2211</fpage>–2217.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9410898</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Dirksen, U., U. Hattenhorst, P. Schneider, H. Schroten, U. Gobel, A. Bocking, K.M. Muller, R. Murray, and S. Burdach. <year>1998</year>. Defective expression of granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor/interleukin-3/interleukin-5 receptor common beta chain in children with acute myeloid leukemia associated with respiratory failure. <source>Blood.</source> <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1097</fpage>–1103.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694696</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Bewig, B., X.D. Wang, D. Kirsten, K. Dalhoff, and H. Schafer. <year>2000</year>. GM-CSF and GM-CSF beta c receptor in adult patients with pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>Eur. Respir. J.</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>–357.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706504</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Nogee, L.M., D.E. de Mello, L.P. Dehner, and H.R. Colten. <year>1993</year>. Brief report: deficiency of pulmonary surfactant protein B in congenital alveolar proteinosis. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>328</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>–410.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8421459</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Nogee, L.M., A.E. Dunbar III, S.E. Wert, F. Askin, A. Hamvas, and J.A. Whitsett. <year>2001</year>. A mutation in the surfactant protein C gene associated with familial interstitial lung disease. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>344</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>–579.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11207353</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shulenin, S., L.M. Nogee, T. Annilo, S.E. Wert, J.A. Whitsett, and M. Dean. <year>2004</year>. ABCA3 gene mutations in newborns with fatal surfactant deficiency. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>350</volume>:<fpage>1296</fpage>–1303.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044640</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Whitsett, J.A., S.E. Wert, and B.C. Trapnell. <year>2004</year>. Genetic disorders influencing lung formation and function at birth. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>R207</fpage>–R215.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15358727</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <label>21</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Uchida, K., K. Nakata, B.C. Trapnell, T. Terakawa, E. Hamano, A. Mikami, I. Matsushita, J.F. Seymour, M. Oh-Eda, I. Ishige, et al. <year>2004</year>. High-affinity autoantibodies specifically eliminate granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor activity in the lungs of patients with idiopathic pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>Blood.</source> <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>1089</fpage>–1098.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14512323</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <label>22</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Iyonaga, K., M. Suga, T. Yamamoto, H. Ichiyasu, H. Miyakawa, and M. Ando. <year>1999</year>. Elevated bronchoalveolar concentrations of MCP-1 in patients with pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>Eur. Respir. J.</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>–389.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515418</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <label>23</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Paine, R. III, S.B. Morris, H. Jin, S.E. Wilcoxen, S.M. Phare, B.B. Moore, M.J. Coffey, and G.B. Toews. <year>2001</year>. Impaired functional activity of alveolar macrophages from GM-CSF-deficient mice. <source>Am. J. Physiol. Lung Cell. Mol. Physiol.</source> <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>L1210</fpage>–L1218.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11597913</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <label>24</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Uchida, K., D.C. Beck, T. Yamamoto, P.Y. Berclaz, S. Abe, M.K. Staudt, B.C. Carey, M.D. Filippi, S.E. Wert, L.A. Denson, et al. <year>2007</year>. GM-CSF autoantibodies and neutrophil dysfunction in pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source> <volume>356</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>–579.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287477</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <label>25</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Seymour, J.F., I.R. Doyle, K. Nakata, J.J. Presneill, O.D. Schoch, E. Hamano, K. Uchida, R. Fisher, and A.R. Dunn. <year>2003</year>. Relationship of anti-GM-CSF antibody concentration, surfactant protein A and B levels, and serum LDH to pulmonary parameters and response to GM-CSF therapy in patients with idiopathic alveolar proteinosis. <source>Thorax.</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>–257.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612307</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <label>26</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Rennard, S.I., G. Basset, D. Lecossier, K.M. O'Donnell, P. Pinkston, P.G. Martin, and R.G. Crystal. <year>1986</year>. Estimation of volume of epithelial lining fluid recovered by lavage using urea as marker of dilution. <source>J. Appl. Physiol.</source> <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>–538.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3512509</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <label>27</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Ding, D.X., J.C. Vera, M.L. Heaney, and D.W. Golde. <year>1995</year>. N-glycosylation of the human granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor receptor alpha subunit is essential for ligand binding and signal transduction. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>24580</fpage>–24584.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7592677</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <label>28</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shears, D.J., H.J. Vassal, F.R. Goodman, R.W. Palmer, W. Reardon, A. Superti-Furga, P.J. Scambler, and R.M. Winter. <year>1998</year>. Mutation and deletion of the pseudoautosomal gene SHOX cause Leri-Weill dyschondrosteosis. <source>Nat. Genet.</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>–73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9590293</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <label>29</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kitamura, T., K. Uchida, N. Tanaka, T. Tsuchiya, J. Watanabe, Y. Yamada, K. Hanaoka, J.F. Seymour, O.D. Schoch, I. Doyle, et al. <year>2000</year>. Serological diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. <source>Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med.</source> <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>658</fpage>–662.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10934102</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <label>30</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kitamura, T., N. Tanaka, J. Watanabe, K. Uchida, S. Kanegasaki, Y. Yamada, and K. Nakata. <year>1999</year>. Idiopathic pulmonary alveolar proteinosis as an autoimmune disease with neutralizing antibody against granulocyte/macrophage colony-stimulating factor. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source> <volume>190</volume>:<fpage>875</fpage>–880.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10499925</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <label>31</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Nogee, L.M. <year>2004</year>. Alterations in SP-B and SP-C expression in neonatal lung disease. <source>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>–623.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977415</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <label>32</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Redon, R., S. Ishikawa, K.R. Fitch, L. Feuk, G.H. Perry, T.D. Andrews, H. Fiegler, M.H. Shapero, A.R. Carson, W. Chen, et al. <year>2006</year>. Global variation in copy number in the human genome. <source>Nature.</source> <volume>444</volume>:<fpage>444</fpage>–454.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122850</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>