<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:29:08Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2171813" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2171813</identifier><datestamp>2008-03-05</datestamp><setSpec>jcellbiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Cell Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2171813</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2171813</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2171813</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15738269</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200409028</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200409028</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15738269</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Article</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Regulation of the interaction between PIPKIγ and talin by proline-directed protein kinases</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Sang Yoon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Voronov</surname>
            <given-names>Sergey</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Letinic</surname>
            <given-names>Kresimir</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nairn</surname>
            <given-names>Angus C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Di Paolo</surname>
            <given-names>Gilbert</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Camilli</surname>
            <given-names>Pietro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510</aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Cell Biology, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510</aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Department of Neurobiology, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510</aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>Department of Psychiatry, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT 06510</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn>
          <p>Correspondence to Pietro De Camilli: <email>pietro.decamilli@yale.edu</email>
</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>168</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>789</fpage>
      <lpage>799</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2005, The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The interaction of talin with phosphatidylinositol(4) phosphate 5 kinase type Iγ (PIPKIγ) regulates PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> synthesis at synapses and at focal adhesions. Here, we show that phosphorylation of serine 650 (S650) within the talin-binding sequence of human PIPKIγ blocks this interaction. At synapses, S650 is phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 and mitogen-activated protein kinase at rest, and dephosphorylated by calcineurin upon stimulation. S650 is also a substrate for cyclin B1/Cdk1 and its phosphorylation in mitosis correlates with focal adhesion disassembly. Phosphorylation by Src of the tyrosine adjacent to S650 (Y649 in human PIPKIγ) was shown to enhance PIPKIγ targeting to focal adhesions (Ling, K., R.L. Doughman, V.V. Iyer, A.J. Firestone, S.F. Bairstow, D.F. Mosher, M.D. Schaller, and R.A. Anderson. 2003. <italic>J. Cell Biol.</italic> 163:1339–1349). We find that Y649 phosphorylation does not stimulate directly PIPKIγ binding to talin, but may do so indirectly by inhibiting S650 phosphorylation. Conversely, S650 phosphorylation inhibits Y649 phosphorylation by Src. The opposite effects of the phosphorylation of Y649 and S650 likely play a critical role in regulating synaptic function as well as the balance between cell adhesion and cell motility.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn>
          <p>Abbreviations used in this paper: 2-D, two-dimensional; FERM, band 4.1/ezrin/radixin/moesin; ITC, isothermal titration calorimetry; PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub>, phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate; PIPKIγ, phosphatidylinositol(4)phosphate 5-kinase type Iγ.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub>), a phosphoinositide highly enriched at the plasma membrane, plays a key role in intracellular signaling (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">De Camilli et al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Martin, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Takenawa and Itoh, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Yin and Janmey, 2003</xref>). The main pathway for the generation of PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> is phosphorylation of phosphatidylinositol(4)phosphate (PI(4)P) by the so-called type I PIP kinases, which function primarily as PI(4)P 5-kinases (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Ishihara et al., 1998</xref>). The three catalytically active members of this family differ in cellular and subcellular distribution and, thus, control specific PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> pools (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Doughman et al., 2003</xref>). PIP kinase type Iγ (PIPKIγ), which is expressed at high levels in the brain, comprises splice variants (PIPKIγ87 and PIPKIγ90) that differ because of the presence of a 28-aa tail (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Ishihara et al., 1998</xref>). An additional splice variant that contains a 26-aa insert before the 28-aa tail was described recently (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Giudici et al., 2004</xref>). Via the sequence WVYSPL contained within the 28-aa tail, PIPKIγ90 interacts with, and is activated by, talin (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2002</xref>), which is an adaptor between the cytoplasmic domain of most β integrins (cell-surface receptors involved in cell adhesion) and the actin cytoskeleton (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood and Ginsberg, 2003</xref>). Isoforms including the 28-aa tail predominate in brain, where they are concentrated at synapses (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Wenk et al., 2001</xref>). Accordingly, talin is present at synapses (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Morgan et al., 2004</xref>), and the relatively smaller pools of PIPKIγ90 present in nonneuronal cells are concentrated at focal adhesion sites (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2002</xref>). Disruption of the talin–PIPKIγ90 interaction at synapses disrupts synaptic vesicle recycling and actin dynamics (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Morgan et al., 2004</xref>), while its perturbation in nonneuronal cells affects cell adhesion (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>Binding of talin to the cytoplasmic domain of integrin β subunits induces conformational changes in the extracellular portion of the α/β integrin dimer leading to increased affinity for extracellular ligands (the so-called inside-out signaling) (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hynes, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood and Ginsberg, 2003</xref>). Conversely, cell adhesion to substrates induces the nucleation of focal adhesions and the nucleation of the associated actin cytoskeleton. PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> is known to play an important regulatory role in this bidirectional signaling by its interactions with many proteins of focal adhesions, including talin (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Martel et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Takenawa and Itoh, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Yin and Janmey, 2003</xref>). Talin binds to PIPKIγ90 via its band 4.1/ezrin/radixin/moesin (FERM) domain, primarily by its F3 subdomain (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2002</xref>), which also comprises the binding site for β integrin (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood et al., 1999</xref>). In fact, the interactions of PIPKIγ90 and β integrin with the F3 subdomain are mutually exclusive (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barsukov et al., 2003</xref>). Accordingly, overexpression of constructs composing the 28-aa tail of PIPKIγ90 produces a “trans-dominant inhibition” of integrin function, by competing for its binding to talin (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood et al., 2004</xref>). The tyrosine of the sequence WVYSPL undergoes endogenous phosphorylation by Src (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2003</xref>). This phosphorylation reaction, which may contribute to the stimulatory effect of focal adhesion kinase on focal adhesions, was reported to enhance the interaction between PIPKIγ90 and talin's F3 subdomain, which has a phosphotyrosine binding domain-like fold (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Alvarez et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>PIPKIγ, in concert with the polyphosphoinositide phosphatase synaptojanin (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Cremona et al., 1999</xref>), plays an important regulatory function in synaptic physiology. Based on genetic studies and other experimental approaches, it was proposed that PIPKIγ controls a plasma membrane pool of PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> implicated in synaptic vesicle exo-endocytosis (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Wenk et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2004</xref>) and that synaptojanin dephosphorylates PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> during the endocytic reaction (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Cremona et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Wenk and De Camilli, 2004</xref>). At synapses, both PIPKIγ (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Wenk et al., 2001</xref>) and synaptojanin (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>), as well as several other proteins implicated in vesicle recycling and actin function (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Cousin and Robinson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Tomizawa et al., 2003</xref>), undergo constitutive phosphorylation and stimulation-dependent, Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent dephosphorylation. At least for some of these proteins, phosphorylation at rest as well as rapid rephosphorylation after a depolarization stimulus is mediated by Cdk5 (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Tomizawa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>). Conversely, dephosphorylation is mediated by the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent phosphatase calcineurin (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Cousin and Robinson, 2001</xref>). In the case of synaptojanin 1, its dephosphorylation by calcineurin triggers its recruitment and activation at endocytic sites from a cytosolic pool (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
      <p>The goal of the present study was to examine the regulation by phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90. Our results demonstrate that S650 within the talin-binding sequence WVYSPL is a main target of regulation by phosphorylation and that S650 phosphorylation blocks talin binding. Furthermore, a mutually antagonistic relationship exists between Src and proline-directed kinases with regard to the phosphorylation of adjacent sites on PIPKIγ90, thereby providing a mechanism for the bidirectional modulation of interactions between PIPKIγ90 and talin. This regulation is not restricted to synapses and may play an important and general function at focal adhesions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>p35/Cdk5 phosphorylates PIPKIγ90 at serine 650</title>
        <p>As a first step to determine whether Cdk5 may be responsible, at least in part, for the constitutive phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 in resting synapses, we tested the ability of PIPKIγ90 to serve as a substrate for Cdk5 in vitro. Incubation of GST fusion protein of human PIPKIγ90 with purified p35/Cdk5 at an ∼1:1 stoichiometric ratio resulted in its efficient phosphorylation (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A). Similar results were obtained with His<sub>6</sub>-tagged PIPKIγ90 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B), which was used for all subsequent phosphorylation experiments. p35, a prominent physiological substrate for the kinase activity of Cdk5 (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhavan and Tsai, 2001</xref>), was also efficiently phosphorylated, as expected, and with similar kinetics during a 30-min incubation (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> C). Two Cdk5 inhibitors, roscovitine (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2003</xref>) and butyrolactone I (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>), inhibited the phosphorylation of both proteins (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A). A stoichiometric analysis revealed the incorporation of 2 mol phosphate/mol PIPKIγ90, which suggests at least two phosphorylation sites (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> D).</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>PIPKIγ90 is phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 at S650</bold> in vitro<bold>.</bold> Recombinant PIPKIγ90 fusion proteins were incubated with p35–Cdk5 complex in the presence of [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP for 30 min. Protein phosphorylation was analyzed by autoradiography after SDS-PAGE. (A) GST-PIPKIγ90 was phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 in the absence and presence of the Cdk5 inhibitors, roscovitine or butyrolactone I (20 μM each). (B and C) Phosphorylation of His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 by p35/Cdk5 and time course of the phosphorylation. (D) Stoichiometry of the phosphorylation of His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 by p35/Cdk5. Purified proteins phosphorylated in vitro in the presence of [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP were separated by SDS-PAGE and stained with Coomassie brilliant blue. PIPKIγ90 bands were excised and incorporation of <sup>32</sup>P was measured. (E) Diagram indicating the position of the phosphorylation site S650 in the COOH-terminal 28-aa tail of PIPKIγ90. (F) 2-D phosphopeptide mapping of His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ87, His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90, and S650A mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 for 30 min in vitro. A circle outlines the spots present only in the protein that contains S650.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f1"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To identify the residues phosphorylated by Cdk5, His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 was phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 in the presence of <sup>32</sup>P[ATP] and subjected to trypsin fragmentation followed by HPLC separation. Matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization/mass spectrometry (MALDI/MS) analysis and Edman radio-sequencing of the major radioactive peptide identified serine 650 (S650) (human sequence) as likely being a major site of phosphorylation. S650 is found within the sequence (S/T)PX(H/K/R) that fits the known Cdk5 consensus motif (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhavan and Tsai, 2001</xref>). Notably, this sequence is part of the talin-binding site (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> E; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>). The identification of S650 was confirmed by two-dimensional (2-D) phosphopeptide mapping of in vitro–phosphorylated His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 and His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ87 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> F), which differ only by the presence or absence of the 28-aa tail. Although several identical radioactive peptides were observed for both isoforms, one major peptide and an adjacent accessory peptide (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> F, circled region) were observed only for PIPKIγ90 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> F). Phosphorylation of these two peptides saturated more rapidly than the other peptides based on comparison of autoradiograms obtained from 5-, 30-, and 60-min phosphorylation reactions (unpublished data). When S650 was mutated to alanine (S650A), these peptides were no longer observed. These data indicate that, at least in vitro, S650 is the most rapidly phosphorylated, although not the only, site for Cdk5 in PIPKIγ90. Two other sites, serine 453 and threonine 123, that are common to PIPKIγ90 and PIPKIγ87 fit the Cdk5 consensus motif. Preliminary experiments indicate that Cdk5 may phosphorylate S453; in contrast, mutation of T123 to alanine did not alter the 2-D phosphopeptide mapping pattern (unpublished data). In this study, we have focused on S650 because of its location within the minimal talin-binding motif (WVYSPL).</p>
        <p>To further confirm the site of phosphorylation and for use in the studies described later, an antibody that specifically recognizes PIPKIγ90 phosphorylated at S650 (anti–phospho-S650 [pS650] antibody) was raised. The pS650 antibody selectively recognized WT PIPKIγ90 phosphorylated in vitro by p35/Cdk5 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). Under the same conditions (after 30-min incubation), the S650A mutant was phosphorylated to a much lower extent as revealed by the incorporation of <sup>32</sup>P (reflecting one or other phosphorylation sites besides S650), and no signal was detected with the pS650 antibody (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A). WT or S650A HA-PIPKIγ90 was transfected into CHO cells with p35 plus Cdk5. Using the pS650 antibody to analyze immunoprecipitated PIPKIγ90, the WT, but not the S650 mutant, protein was found to be phosphorylated (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> B). Omission of p35 and Cdk5, or transfection with catalytically inactive mutant of Cdk5 (mut-Cdk5; <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Patrick et al., 1999</xref>) resulted in a significantly lower phosphorylation of S650 compared with that observed after transfection with p35/Cdk5 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C). Under these conditions, S650 may be phosphorylated by low levels of endogenous Cdk5 (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhavan and Tsai, 2001</xref>) and/or by other proline-directed protein kinases (see <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figs. 7</xref> and <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>PIPKIγ90 is phosphorylated by p35/Cdk5 at S650</bold> in vivo<bold>.</bold> (A) Generation and characterization of a polyclonal antibody specific for phospho-S650 (pS650). Purified WT and S650A mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 were incubated with or without p35/Cdk5 and with either nonradioactive ATP (for Western blotting) or [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (for autoradiography) for 30 min. Samples were analyzed by autoradiography, and Western blotting with the anti-pS650 antibody was performed. Coomassie brilliant blue (CBB) staining shows loading of equal amounts of substrate proteins. The autoradiographic signal was quantified by a phosphorimager analysis and values were expressed as a percentage of the radioactivity incorporated into the WT sample. Bar graphs represent mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). (B) CHO cells were transfected with WT or S650A mutant HA-PIPKIγ90 together with p35 and Cdk5. PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitates were obtained from cell lysates 24 h after transfection. S650 phosphorylation and PIPKIγ90 expression were analyzed by Western blotting with anti-pS650 and anti-HA antibodies, respectively. (C) CHO cells were cotransfected with HA-PIPKIγ90, p35, and Cdk5 or mut-Cdk5. PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitates from transfected and control cells were analyzed by Western blotting as described above. The faint band visible in nontransfected CHO cells may represent phosphorylated hamster PIPKIγ90. The pS650 immunoreactivity was quantified using an NIH image analysis software and shown as mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Phosphorylation of S650 inhibits the interaction of PIPKIγ90 with talin in vitro and in vivo</title>
        <p>Given the location of S650 in the middle of the talin-binding sequence (WVYSPL; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>), the possibility that phosphorylation of S650 of PIPKIγ90 inhibits its interaction with talin was next examined. Isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) was used to analyze the binding of the GST-talin head (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>), which comprises the FERM domain, to synthetic 12-mer dephospho- and phosphopeptides encompassing the talin-binding sequence of PIPKIγ90. <italic>K</italic>
<sub>d</sub> values of 2 μM and &gt;1 mM were observed for the dephosphopeptide and the pS650 peptide, respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> A), indicating a strongly negative role of S650 phosphorylation in talin binding. A <italic>K</italic>
<sub>d</sub> of 2 μM (see Fig. 6 A) value for the WT peptide is in agreement with the dissociation constant of the same interaction measured with tryptophan fluorescence by <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barsukov et al. (2003)</xref>, but is higher than the dissociation constant observed by <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref> using fluorescence anisotropy measurement. Differences in the assays and the experimental conditions may explain the discrepancy. For example, our values were obtained at 37<sup>o</sup>C, whereas the value of <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref> was recorded at room temperature.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Cdk5 phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 inhibits its interaction with talin</bold> in vivo<bold>.</bold> (A) ITC analysis of the binding of 12-mer WT and pS650 peptides from the 28-aa tail of PIPKIγ90 to GST-talin head. Raw data as a function of time are shown in the top panels, and plots of the total heat released as a function of the molar ratio of each ligand are shown in the bottom panels. The continuous line in the bottom panels represents the nonlinear, least-squares best fits to the experimental data using a one-site model of binding. Note the roughly 1:1 stoichiometry indicated by the half-height point of the sigmoidal curve (bottom left; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Turnbull and Daranas, 2003</xref>), and the complete absence of heat release in the case of the pS650 peptide. (B) CHO cells were cotransfected with HA-PIPKIγ90, p35, and Cdk5 or mut-Cdk5. Protein contents of the starting lysates were revealed by Western blotting. PIPKIγ90 and talin were immunoprecipitated from the cell lysates and presence of PIPKIγ90 and talin in each immunoprecipitate was detected by Western blotting.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f3"/>
        </fig>
        <p>We further examined whether the in vivo interaction of PIPKIγ90 with talin is inhibited by Cdk5-dependent phosphorylation. CHO cells were transfected with HA-PIPKIγ90, p35, and either Cdk5 or mut-Cdk5 (as in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> C). Cell lysates were then processed for anti-PIPKIγ90 or antitalin immunoprecipitation, and the starting lysates and the resulting pellets were analyzed by Western blotting for transfected and control proteins (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> B). Talin coprecipitated with HA-PIPKIγ90, and HA-PIPKIγ90 coprecipitated with talin, as expected. However, expression of Cdk5, but not mut-Cdk5, strongly inhibited the coprecipitation of the two proteins.</p>
        <p>We next determined whether a phosphomimetic mutation of S650 to aspartic acid (S650D) affected the interaction with talin. WT and S650D His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 were overlaid in a “far-Western” assay with a GST fusion protein of the F3 subdomain of the FERM domain of talin (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, A and C</xref>). The F3 domain clearly bound to the WT protein, as expected (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>), but no binding was observed for the S650D mutant (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> A). Binding of the F3 domain to the S650A mutant was also reduced, although not abolished, and this is in agreement with a potential role of the side chain of serine in the binding (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Liddington et al., 2003</xref>). These results were qualitatively confirmed by His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 pull-down assays from rat brain extracts (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, B and C</xref>). In this case, the loss of binding produced by the S650A mutation was nearly as large as that produced by the S650D mutation.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Phosphomimetic mutation at S650 (S650D) disrupts the interaction of PIPKIγ90 with talin</bold> in vitro<bold>.</bold> (A) GST-F3 overlay assay. Nitrocellulose blots of WT and mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 were overlaid with or without GST-F3 fusion protein, and then overlaid with anti-GST antibody. CBB staining reveals equal load of the lanes. (B) Pull-down assay from rat brain extracts on bead-immobilized WT and mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90. Bound talin was revealed by Western blotting, and equal amount of bait proteins was revealed by CBB staining. (C) The intensities of the GST-F3 and talin bands shown in A and B were quantified by an NIH image analysis software. Values from mutant proteins were normalized to that from WT and are represented as mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 4). (D) Localization of transfected GFP-PIPKIγ90. NIH3T3 cells were transfected with GFP-PIPKIγ90 or its S650D mutant, and then were processed by immunofluorescence for vinculin immunoreactivity. Bar, 10 μm. (E) Pull-down assay from lysates of CHO cells transfected with WT and S650D mutant GFP-PIPKIγ90. Bead-immobilized GST-integrin β<sub>1</sub> tail was used as a bait. Talin and PIPKIγ90 in the lysates or bead fractions were detected by Western blotting. (F) NIH3T3 cells transfected with mutant (S650N) GFP-PIPKIγ90 were immunostained with antivinculin antibody. Bar, 10 μm. (G) CHO cells were transfected with WT, S650D, or S650N GFP-PIPKIγ90. After 24 h of transfection, cell lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-PIPKIγ90 antibody, and the presence of talin and PIPKIγ90 in the immunoprecipitates was analyzed by Western blotting.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f4"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The effect of the phosphomimetic S650D mutation on the properties of PIPKIγ90 was further investigated in living cells. WT, but not mutant (S650D) GFP-PIPKIγ90, accumulated at focal adhesions when expressed in NIH3T3 cells (mouse fibroblast), as shown by colocalization with the focal adhesion marker vinculin (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> D). This result demonstrates the inhibitory effect of the presence of an acidic charge at position 650 in the recruitment of PIPKIγ90 at focal adhesions, which is consistent with the blocking effect on the interaction with talin. As reported previously, the interaction of talin with PIPKIγ90 competes with the interaction of talin with β integrin, because both proteins bind to the same surface of talin's F3 domain (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barsukov et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Liddington et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood et al., 2004</xref>). Accordingly, pull-downs with a GST fusion protein of integrin β<sub>1</sub> tail from lysates of CHO cells transfected with mutant (S650D) or wild-type PIPKIγ90 yielded a higher level of talin in the case of cells transfected with the mutant protein, which is not expected to compete (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> E). Collectively, these results indicate that talin binding is incompatible with the presence of a negative charge at S650 in PIPKIγ90 and that S650 phosphorylation has an important role in the regulation of PIPKIγ90–talin–integrin interactions.</p>
        <p>PIPKIγ90 and β integrin share amino acid similarity in the talin-binding region. Within these similar sequences, S650 of PIPKIγ90 was proposed to functionally replace the asparagine of the sequence NPXY in β integrin. When S650 of PIPKIγ90 was replaced by an asparagine (S650N), the resulting mutant protein was still able to bind to talin, confirming this prediction. Thus, transfected GFP-PIPKIγ90 harboring the S650N mutation colocalized with vinculin at focal adhesions (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> F) and coprecipitated with talin from lysates of transfected cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> G). The presence of a serine at this position in PIPKIγ90, but not in β integrin, allows for a differential regulation of the two interactions by phosphorylation.</p>
        <p>If the binding of PIPKIγ90 to talin is important for focal adhesion dynamics, overexpression of p35/Cdk5 would be expected to affect focal adhesion dynamics by enhancing the phosphorylation state of S650. Consistent with this prediction, overexpression of p35/Cdk5 in NIH3T3 cells disrupted focal adhesions and stress fibers, as detected by antivinculin immunostaining and phalloidin staining, respectively (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Inhibitory effects of p35/Cdk5 overexpression on focal adhesion.</bold> NIH3T3 cells were cotransfected with both p35 and Cdk5 for 24 h, and the overexpressed proteins were detected by immunofluorescence microscopy with the antibodies indicated. Focal adhesions were visualized by antivinculin immunostaining, and actin was visualized by fluorescent phalloidin. Bar, 10 μm.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f5"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>PIPKIγ90 phosphorylation by Cdk5 and Src is mutually exclusive</title>
        <p>
<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref> reported that the COOH-terminal region of mouse PIPKIγ90 undergoes phosphorylation by Src at tyrosine 644 (Y649 of human PIPKIγ90) and that this phosphorylation enhances its interaction with talin. Y649 is adjacent to S650 in the talin-binding sequence (WVYSPL), which is identical in mice and humans. The juxtaposition of the two sites raised the possibility that phosphorylation of one might regulate phosphorylation of the other. This possibility was tested using synthetic peptides centered around the talin-binding consensus. Both 12-mer peptides, as well as 17-mer peptides identical to those used by <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref>, were tested. First, we revisited the effect of Y649 phosphorylation on talin binding. Surprisingly, an ITC assay did not demonstrate a difference between the affinities of the WT peptides and of the pY649 peptides for GST-talin head (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A). Phosphorylation of tyrosine 654, which is a weak Src target site (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2003</xref>), also had no positive effect on talin binding, and in fact, it slightly decreased the binding (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> A). The pS650 12-mer peptide exhibited negligible binding to talin, as expected (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref> A and 3 A). In agreement with the results of the ITC assay, the WT peptide (12-mer) and the pY649 peptide (12-mer) equally competed with the tail for talin binding in pull-down assays from rat brain extracts using GST–28-aa tail (unpublished data).</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Phosphorylation of either Y649 or S650 inhibits the phosphorylation of the adjacent site.</bold> (A) Binding of PIPKIγ90 peptides to GST-talin head as determined by ITC. Note that both the dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic>
<sub>d</sub>) and the enthalpy (ΔH) of the binding are similar for WT and pY649 peptides. The pY654 peptide has lower affinity, but the pS650 peptide did not bind. N/A, not available. (B) In vitro phosphorylation by Cdk5 and c-Src of WT, pY649 and pS650 12-mer PIPKIγ90 peptides. Each peptide was incubated in the presence of [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP and of either p35/Cdk5 or c-Src for 20 min at 30°C. Peptides were then recovered on phosphocellulose paper, and the associated radioactivity was measured by Cerenkov counting. Incorporation of radioactivity into pY649 and pS650 peptides was normalized to that of the WT peptide and presented as mean ± SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 4)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f6"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Next, we tested whether the presence of a phosphate at position 649 or 650 affected the phosphorylation of the adjacent site. The 12-mer WT, pY649, and pS650 peptides were incubated under linear rate conditions with purified c-Src or p35/Cdk5 and <sup>32</sup>P[ATP]. The pY649 peptide was a poor substrate for Cdk5 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> B). Likewise, the pS650 peptide was a poor substrate for c-Src. As expected, the pY649 and pS650 peptides were hardly phosphorylated by c-Src and Cdk5, respectively. These data suggest that phosphorylation of either site has a strong inhibitory effect on the phosphorylation of the other site.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>S650 phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 is regulated by Cdk5 and calcineurin at synapses</title>
        <p>In the next series of experiments, the in vivo phosphorylation of S650 in endogenous PIPKIγ90 was investigated. Rat brain synaptosomes, including samples exposed to a 1-h metabolic labeling step with <sup>32</sup>Pi, were incubated for 20 min in control buffer, and then were depolarized for 1 min with high K<sup>+</sup> (55 mM) in the absence or presence of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup>. As detected by using <sup>32</sup>P incorporation or by using the pS650 antibody, we found that PIPKIγ90 was constitutively phosphorylated at rest, and dephosphorylated upon high K<sup>+</sup> stimulation, but only in the presence of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A). The stimulation-dependent dephosphorylation of pS650 was blocked by cyclosporin A, a calcineurin inhibitor (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B). Furthermore, rephosphorylation of S650 upon reexposure to the control buffer was partially inhibited by incubation with butyrolactone I (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> C) or roscovitine (unpublished data). The pattern of PIPKIγ90 dephosphorylation was qualitatively similar to that of amphiphysin 2, whose upper band (phospho-form) collapses into lower bands (dephospho form) upon calcineurin-dependent dephosphorylation (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> A; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Cousin and Robinson, 2001</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig7" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>Regulation of S650 phosphorylation in synaptosomes.</bold> In all panels shown in the figure, with the exception of E and F, levels of total PIPKIγ90 and of its pS650 epitope were analyzed by Western blots of anti-PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitates obtained from synaptosomal lysates. For other proteins, Western blots were performed directly on synaptosomal lysates. (A) Freshly prepared rat brain synaptosomes, or synaptosomes exposed to a 1-h labeling step with <sup>32</sup>Pi, were incubated for 1 min with either control buffer or stimulation buffer (high K<sup>+</sup>) in the absence or presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>). Anti-PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitates prepared from these samples were analyzed by autoradiography (<sup>32</sup>P-labeled samples) or by Western blotting for pS650 and total PIPKIγ90. Western blotting for amphiphysin 2 revealed the previously described stimulation-dependent mobility shift of the upper band (because of its dephosphorylation), thus confirming the occurrence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent stimulation. (B) Synaptosomes were stimulated with high K<sup>+</sup> for 1 min in the absence or presence of 2 μM cyclosporin A, and then were analyzed with antibodies directed against pS650 or phospho-sites 4 and 5 (MAPK sites) of synapsin I. (C) Synaptosomes were exposed for 1 min to either control buffer (resting) or high K<sup>+</sup> buffer (depolarization). Aliquots of stimulated synaptosomes were then returned for 15 min to control buffer (repolarization) with and without the Cdk5 inhibitor butyrolactone I (10 μM). (D) Synaptosomes were incubated for 1 min with control buffer or high K<sup>+</sup> buffer in the absence or presence of 1 μM okadaic acid, and then were analyzed for levels of pS650, PIPKIγ90, phospho-MAPK1/2, and total MAPK1/2. (E) Synaptosomes were stimulated for 1 min in the absence or presence of 1 μM okadaic acid and the MAPK inhibitor PD98059. (F) In vitro phosphorylation of WT and S650A mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 with purified MAPK1. S650 phosphorylation by MAPK1 was detected by the anti-pS650 antibody.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f7"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The only partial effect of Cdk5 inhibitors on the phosphorylation of S650 suggested that other kinases may phosphorylate this site. Interestingly, the phosphorylation/dephosphorylation of S650 in resting and stimulated synaptosomes was reminiscent of that of the phosphorylation sites 4 and 5 of synapsin I (corresponding to serine 62 and serine 67, respectively, of rat synapsin I) (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> B; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jovanovic et al., 2001</xref>). Notably, these sites in synapsin I were found to be phosphorylated by MAPK (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jovanovic et al., 2001</xref>). MAPK is a proline-directed serine/threonine kinase whose substrate specificity [(S/T)P] (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Songyang et al., 1996</xref>) overlaps with the substrate preference of Cdk5 and may therefore be involved in S650 phosphorylation.</p>
        <p>The potential involvement of MAPK as well as of phosphatases other than calcineurin in the regulation of S650 phosphorylation was investigated. Synaptosomes were treated with either okadaic acid, an inhibitor of protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A), or PD98059, an inhibitor of MAPK1/2 (p42/p44). Okadaic acid alone strongly enhanced the phosphorylation state of S650 both at rest and after high K<sup>+</sup> depolarization (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> D), although a stimulation-dependent dephosphorylation of S650 still occurred upon exposure to high K<sup>+</sup> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> D, compare the second and fourth lanes). Okadaic acid also increased the level of phospho-MAPK1/2 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> D). This was expected because PP2A is known to dephosphorylate MAPK, with a resulting inhibition of its activity (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Alessi et al., 1995</xref>). PD98059 partially prevented the increase in S650 phosphorylation produced by okadaic acid (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> E). The increase of pS650 produced by okadaic acid may result both from a direct inhibition of pS650 dephosphorylation by PP2A and/or indirectly from the enhanced MAPK activity caused by inhibition of PP2A. Note that, as previously reported, depolarization in the presence of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases the phosphorylation state of MAPK1/2 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> D, compare the first and third lanes; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Yamagata et al., 2002</xref>). This is in contrast to the depolarization-dependent dephosphorylation of S650, thus indicating that calcineurin can override the action of MAPK on S650. Consistent with PIPKIγ90 being a substrate for MAPK, purified MAPK1 phosphorylated S650 in WT His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 in vitro, but did not phosphorylate S650A mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> F), as determined by anti-p5650 Western blotting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>S650 of PIPKIγ90 undergoes mitotic phosphorylation</title>
        <p>Entry of cells into mitosis is accompanied by massive structural changes. For example, cells grown in culture round up and partially detach from the substrates, a change which correlates with the disruption of focal adhesions (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Maddox and Burridge, 2003</xref>). The property of S650 of PIPKIγ90 to function as a substrate for Cdk5, a member of the Cdk family, prompted us to examine its phosphorylation state during mitosis. Disruption of the interaction between talin and PIPKIγ90 could be one of the biochemical modifications that correlate with focal adhesion disassembly. CHO cells transfected with WT or mutant HA-PIPKIγ90 were either treated with nocodazole to arrest cells in pro-metaphase, or treated with nocodazole and then allowed to progress to G<sub>1</sub> interphase by re-addition of serum. pS650 immunoreactivity was detected only in cells expressing WT PIPKIγ90 and phosphorylation was dramatically increased in mitotic cells (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> A). These results were corroborated by the analysis of endogenous PIPKIγ90 in cells (U87MG cells, derived from a human astrocytoma) that express high levels of this enzyme. In this case, cell lysates were subjected to immunoprecipitation with anti-PIPKIγ90 antibody prior to Western blotting (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> B). Not only S650 phosphorylation was strongly stimulated in mitosis, but coprecipitation of talin with the kinase was nearly abolished in the mitotic state. The mitotic synchronization of these cells was validated by Western blotting of total lysates with antibodies directed against phospho-histone H3, a marker of mitosis (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ajiro et al., 1996</xref>). In support of a role for cyclin-activated kinases in the phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 during mitosis, purified cyclin B1–Cdk1 complex phosphorylated purified WT His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 in vitro but weakly phosphorylated its S650A mutant (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> C). Cyclin B1, a physiological substrate of Cdk1 (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Borgne et al., 1999</xref>), was phosphorylated at roughly similar levels in both samples (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> C).</p>
        <fig id="fig8" position="float">
          <label>Figure 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
<bold>S650 of PIPKIγ90 undergoes mitotic phosphorylation by cyclin B1/Cdk1.</bold> (A) CHO cells transfected with WT or S650A mutant HA-PIPKIγ90 for 24 h were arrested in the mitotic state (M) by nocodazole treatment. G<sub>1</sub> interphase cells (G) were further prepared from mitotically synchronized cells after removal of nocodazole. Cell lysates of both M and G cells were analyzed by Western blotting with anti-pS650 and anti-PIPKIγ90 antibodies. (B) U87MG cells were processed as described in A to generate mitotic and interphase cells. PIPKIγ90 was immunoprecipitated from cell lysates for analysis of pS650, talin and total PIPKIγ90. Cell lysates were also analyzed by Western blotting for levels of histone H3 phosphorylation using a phosphospecific antibody. Bar graphs represent normalized talin immunoreactivity (mean ± SD; <italic>n</italic> = 4) after quantification as shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> C. (C) WT and S650A mutant His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 were incubated in vitro with or without the cyclin B1–Cdk1 complex in the presence of [<sup>32</sup>P]ATP. His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 phosphorylation and cyclin B1 autophosphorylation were examined by autoradiography after SDS-PAGE. In parallel, samples phosphorylated under the same conditions with nonradioactive ATP were processed for Western blotting with anti-pS650 antibody. CBB staining demonstrates equal amounts of proteins.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="200409028f8"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We and others have recently identified an interaction between talin and PIPKIγ90 that plays an important role at synapses and focal adhesions (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2002</xref>). This interaction is thought to control the synthesis of specific pools of PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> at these sites, but has an additional impact on adhesion. PIPKIγ90 competes with the binding of integrin to talin and can, therefore, transdominantly inhibit integrin activation (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Barsukov et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood et al., 2004</xref>). Thus, the binding of PIPKIγ90 to talin must be highly regulated. <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref> suggested one mechanism for positive regulation as being the Src-dependent phosphorylation of Y649 within the talin-binding sequence WVYSPL. We have now identified and characterized another mechanism, phosphorylation of S650, that negatively regulates the talin–PIPKIγ90 interaction and that is the point of convergence of multiple signaling pathways. In addition, our results suggest that Src-mediated phosphorylation of Y649 likely acts indirectly on talin binding, rather than directly, as previously proposed (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>At synapses, the generation of PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> by PIPKIγ is thought to play an important regulatory role both in exocytosis and in endocytosis (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Wenk et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Wenk and De Camilli, 2004</xref>). The initial goal of this study was to determine whether PIPKIγ90, like several other synaptic proteins that participate in synaptic vesicle traffic, primarily endocytic traffic (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Cousin and Robinson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Tomizawa et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>), is regulated by the serine/threonine phosphorylation. We have now demonstrated that PIPKIγ90 is efficiently phosphorylated at S650 by Cdk5 both in vitro and in vivo, and that this Cdk5 site is dephosphorylated by calcineurin. Importantly, we have shown that phosphorylation of this site negatively regulates the talin–PIPKIγ90 interaction. Such an interaction is vital for synaptic physiology, because its perturbation by peptides microinjected into giant axons perturbs synaptic vesicle recycling and the dynamics of presynaptic actin (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Morgan et al., 2004</xref>). Restoration of the interaction by depolarization-triggered dephosphorylation may serve to recruit and activate PIPKIγ90 at sites of exo-endocytosis and may underlie, together with interaction of PIPKIγ90 with small GTPases (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aikawa and Martin, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Krauss et al., 2003</xref>), the increase in PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> synthesis occurring in stimulated synaptosomes (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2004</xref>). Interestingly, in preliminary experiments, we have found that a guanyl nucleotide–independent interaction of PIPKIγ90 with Rac1 is also inhibited by Cdk5-dependent phosphorylation at a site distinct from S650 (unpublished data). These findings support a model according to which Cdk5 phosphorylation keeps the synapse in a “resting mode,” whereas calcineurin triggers an “active mode” (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Sahin and Bibb, 2004</xref>).</p>
      <p>Our results suggest that phosphorylation of S650 may also be regulated by other proline-directed kinases and at least one other phosphatase. A potential role of MAPK can be inferred from the inhibitory action of the MAPK inhibitor PD98059 on the levels of pS650 in vivo and from the in vitro phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 by purified MAPK1. The powerful stimulatory effect of okadaic acid, an inhibitor of the PP2A (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Jovanovic et al., 2001</xref>), on the levels of pS650 is also consistent with an action of MAPK, because PP2A could act indirectly by dephosphorylating and, therefore, inhibiting MAPK (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Alessi et al., 1995</xref>). In the presence of okadaic acid, such activity would be greatly stimulated. Additionally, PP2A may act directly on pS650. If this is the case, the large increase of pS650 observed in the presence of okadaic acid in unstimulated synaptosomes would indicate the occurrence of a very rapid turnover of phosphate on S650 even at rest. Among the questions that remain to be addressed is whether different kinases and phosphatases act on pools of PIPKIγ90 with distinct subcellular localization, because PIPKIγ90 is concentrated in, but not restricted to, nerve terminals. However, important conclusions from this study are that S650 represents the point of convergence of different regulatory pathways and that its state of phosphorylation controls an important targeting and activation mechanism of this enzyme.</p>
      <p>Cdk5 phosphorylation was found to have only a negligible (positive) effect on the catalytic activity of PIPKIγ90 (unpublished data). Because Cdk5 also phosphorylated PIPKIγ87 and slightly activated its catalytic activity (unpublished data), S650 does not seem to participate in this regulation. However, it is possible, that sites phosphorylated by other kinases may directly control its catalytic activity. An inhibitory role on PIPKIγ activity produced by protein kinase A phosphorylation at serine 264 (human sequence) was previously suggested, based on studies of the homologous mouse PIPKIα (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2001</xref>). The precise coordination of different phosphorylation reactions remains to be investigated.</p>
      <p>Our study also shows that S650 of PIPKIγ90 can undergo phosphorylation in nonneuronal cells, where PIPKIγ90 is primarily localized at focal adhesions. However, although transfected Cdk5—a protein kinase expressed predominantly, but not exclusively, in neurons (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhavan and Tsai, 2001</xref>)—can phosphorylate transfected PIPKIγ90 in CHO cells, the protein kinase that performs this phosphorylation reaction physiologically in interphase nonneuronal cells remains to be identified. As suggested by the phosphomimetic S650D mutant, phosphorylation of S650 prevents the localization of PIPKIγ90 at focal adhesions. In addition, the S650D mutant of PIPKIγ90 did not compete with the interaction of talin and β integrin. Therefore, one can expect that regulation of the turnover of phosphate on S650 may have a key role in the regulation of the balance between adhesion and motility (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Calderwood and Ginsberg, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Carragher and Frame, 2004</xref>). It is of interest, in this context, that Cdk5 plays a major role in the regulation of cell migration and neurite outgrowth in the nervous system (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dhavan and Tsai, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2003</xref>) and of cell adhesion and migration in nonneuronal cells (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2002</xref>). As we have shown here, its overexpression strongly affects focal adhesion.</p>
      <p>As we also show here, S650 of PIPKIγ90 undergoes phosphorylation in mitosis and is a very good in vitro, and a likely in vivo, substrate for the cyclin B1–Cdk1 complex. It will be of interest to determine whether phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90 at S650 helps drive focal adhesion disassembly during mitosis, or simply correlates with this process. We note that other proteins implicated in membrane traffic at synapses are also physiological substrates for both cyclin B1/Cdk1 and p35/Cdk5. These include epsin, Eps15, and amphiphysin (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Floyd et al., 2001</xref>). Mechanisms that regulate entry into the mitotic state, where much of the exo-endocytic traffic is blocked (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Pypaert et al., 1991</xref>), may be closely related to mechanisms that limit exo-endocytic traffic at neuronal synapses at rest.</p>
      <p>At variance with what was reported previously (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2003</xref>), studies with purified peptides, including the same peptides used by <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al. (2003)</xref>, did not reveal an effect of Y649 phosphorylation on the interaction of PIPKIγ90 with talin. Furthermore, structural data indicate that phosphorylation of Y649 would be unlikely to directly perturb the interaction between these two proteins (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Liddington et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">de Pereda et al., 2004</xref>). In contrast, the negative effect of S650 phosphorylation on the interaction of PIPKIγ90 with talin is consistent with structural predictions pointing to an intimate interaction of S650 with talin (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Liddington et al., 2003</xref>) and with the mutagenesis experiments reported here.</p>
      <p>However, we did find that the presence of phosphate on Y649 strongly inhibits the phosphorylation of S650, and vice versa. Thus, Src-dependent phosphorylation of Y649 may act indirectly to enhance talin binding by inhibiting phosphorylation of S650. Conversely, in addition to directly blocking the interaction with talin, phosphorylation of S650, in a feed-forward mechanism, blocks the phosphorylation reaction at Y649 that inhibits S650 phosphorylation. Src family kinases have been implicated both in synaptic function and in focal adhesion dynamics (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Purcell and Carew, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Carragher and Frame, 2004</xref>), thus supporting a physiological significance of this bidirectional control of PIPKIγ90.</p>
      <p>While our manuscript was in review, a study by <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">de Pereda et al. (2004)</xref> reported a crystallographic analysis of the interaction between the F3 subdomain of talin and the COOH-terminal tail of mouse PIPKIγ. The structure is consistent with the results of our phosphorylation studies. It predicts that phosphorylation of serine 650 of human PIPKIγ90 would block the interaction, and explains the lack of effect that we report here for the phosphorylation of tyrosine 649. Dissociation constant values determined by ITC for the talin–PIPKIγ90 peptide interaction in this new study (see Fig. S1 in <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">de Pereda et al., 2004</xref>) are in the same range of those reported by us and show only a minor (1.6-fold) positive effect of phosphorylation of tyrosine 644, which corresponds to human tyrosine 649, on the interaction (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">de Pereda et al., 2004</xref>). Overall, these new findings are in very good agreement with our results.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Antibodies</title>
        <p>Polyclonal antibodies against human PIPKIγ90 and GST were prepared as described previously (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">McPherson et al., 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>). A polyclonal anti-GFP antibody was a gift from Susan Ferro-Novick (Yale University, New Haven, CT). For the pS650-specific antibody, we immunized a rabbit with a synthetic phosphopeptide corresponding to residues 646–654 (SWVYpSPLHYC) of human PIPKIγ90. The COOH-terminal cysteine residue was added to the peptide for affinity purification using Sulfolink gel (Pierce Chemical Co.). The following antibodies were obtained from commercial sources; rat mAb to HA tag (Roche); mouse mAb to Cdk5 and amphiphysin 2 (Upstate Biotechnology), to talin and tubulin (Sigma-Aldrich) and to phospho-MAPK1/2 (New England Biolabs); rabbit polyclonal Ab to MAPK1/2 (New England Biolabs, Inc.) and to phospho-histone H3 (Upstate Biotechnology).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>DNA constructs and protein expression</title>
        <p>Constructs of human PIPKIγ87 (640 aa), PIPKIγ90 (668 aa) and 28--aa tail (641–668) of PIPKIγ90, and the F3 subdomain and head domain of talin were subcloned into pcDNA3-HA, pGEX-6P-1, or pEGFP-C2 vectors, as described previously (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Krauss et al., 2003</xref>). We also subcloned PIPKIγ87 and PIPKIγ90 into a modified version of pET15 vector (Novagen) with an NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tag. S650 in the PIPKIγ90 constructs was mutated to alanine, aspartic acid, or asparagine by a QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Promega), and the mutations were confirmed by DNA sequencing. Full-length GST- and His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 fusion proteins expressed in Sf9 cells and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain BL21, respectively, were purified using glutathione-Sepharose beads (Amersham Biosciences) and Talon metal affinity resin (BD Biosciences) following the manufacturer's protocols and dialyzed against TBS. Expression constructs encoding p35, Cdk5, and mut-Cdk5 in the pCMV vector were gifts from L.-H. Tsai (Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA). A construct of GST-integrin β<sub>1</sub> tail was a gift from J. Ylanne (University of Oulu, Oulu, Finland).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>In vitro phosphorylation</title>
        <p>p35–Cdk5 and cyclin B1–Cdk1 complexes, expressed and purified from Sf9 cells coinfected with baculovirus encoding each component, were gifts from Y. Kim and P. Greengard (The Rockefeller University, New York, NY) and Y. Wang and G. Warren (Yale University), respectively. Purified GST-PIPKIγ90 or His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKγ87/90 fusion proteins (200–300 ng) were incubated with p35–Cdk5 complex (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>) or cyclin B1–Cdk1 complex (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2003</xref>) at an ∼1:1 stoichiometric ratio in the presence of 10 μCi γ-[<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (1 Ci = 37 GBq) for up to 30 min at 30<sup>o</sup>C. PIPKIγ90 phosphorylation by MAPK1 (Upstate Biotechnology) was performed according to the manufacturer's protocol. Kinase reactions (30–40 μl final volume) were stopped by the addition of SDS-PAGE sample buffer, and samples were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and autoradiography. In case of peptide phosphorylation by c-Src (Upstate Biotechnology) and p35/Cdk5, each kinase was mixed with the 12-mer peptides (each 25 μM) in the presence of 400 μM ATP and 40 μCi γ-[<sup>32</sup>P]ATP. c-Src phosphorylation was performed in 25 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.2, 30 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 mM EGTA, and 62.5 μM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, and p35/Cdk5 phosphorylation was assayed as described above. After a 20-min incubation at 30<sup>o</sup>C, reaction mixtures (40 μl) were stopped by adding 20 μl of 40% TCA solution, and a portion of reaction mixtures (25 μl) was spotted onto P81 phosphocellulose paper (Whatman). All reactions were in the linear range and consumed &lt;1% of peptide substrates. After washing five times with 0.75% phosphoric acid and once with acetone, radiolabeling of the peptides was quantified by Cerenkov counting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification of phosphorylation sites and 2-D peptide mapping</title>
        <p>12 μg His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKγ90 labeled with γ-[<sup>32</sup>P]ATP by p35–Cdk5, as described in the previous paragraph, was excised from SDS-PAGE and digested with trypsin (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>). The resulting peptides were separated by HPLC and detected by Cerenkov counting. Peptide masses containing a phosphate group were determined by MALDI/MS, and the phosphorylation sites were confirmed by further radio sequencing of the peptides. 2-D phosphopeptide mapping was performed as previously described (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Hsieh-Wilson et al., 2003</xref>). In brief, after centrifugation of the trypsin-digested radiolabeled material, supernatants were collected and lyophilized. Pellets were then washed with distilled water and running buffer (10% acetic acid and 1% pyridine in water) several times. Lyophilized pellets were dissolved in running buffer and spotted onto cellulose TLC plates. The plates were sequentially subjected to electrophoresis in the running buffer, pH 3.5, at 400 V, and then to chromatography in a buffer (25% 1-butanol, 7.5% acetic acid, and 37.5% pyridine in water). After drying the plates, autoradiography was performed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>In vitro talin-binding assay and ITC</title>
        <p>The talin overlay assay was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">McPherson et al., 1994</xref>). 100–200 ng of purified His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 fusion proteins transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes were incubated without or with GST-F3 fusion protein (2 μg/ml). Membranes were blotted with anti-GST antibody. For the pull-down assay from rat brain extracts, His<sub>6</sub>-PIPKIγ90 fusion proteins (4–5 μg) coupled to Talon metal affinity beads in TBS containing 1% (vol/vol) Triton X-100 were mixed with rat brain extracts (6.4 mg) prepared in buffer A (20 mM Hepes, pH 7.4, 120 mM KCl, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM Na<sub>3</sub>VO<sub>4</sub>, 1 mM PMSF, and 1% [vol/vol] Triton X-100) for 3 h at 4<sup>o</sup>C. ITC measurements were performed using a Microcal VP-ITC isothermal titration calorimeter equipped with a PC running VPViewer software. Dissociation constant values were obtained from the data collected automatically and analyzed with Origin software. In each experiment, 3-μl aliquots of peptide solution (1 mM) were injected into a calorimetric cell preloaded with 1.4267 ml GST-talin head domain (16.4 μM) using a rotating stirrer syringe (250-μl vol) every 250 s at 37°C. All solutions included 20 mM sodium phosphate, pH 7.4, and 150 mM NaCl and were degassed. To estimate a blank heat effect associated with dilution and mechanical phenomena, peptide injections were performed after saturation of binding.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Cell culture, transfection, and immunoprecipitation</title>
        <p>CHO cells were grown in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS and antibiotics and transfected for 24 h with expression constructs of WT or mutants of HA-PIPKIγ90 and of GFP-PIPKIγ90, p35, Cdk5 or mut-Cdk5 using Lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies) according to the instruction manual. For immunoprecipitation of PIPKIγ90 and talin, the cell lysates prepared in the buffer A were incubated with anti-PIPKIγ90 and antitalin antibodies for 3 h at 4<sup>o</sup>C, and then were incubated with protein A– and protein G–Sepharose beads (Amersham Biosciences) for 2 h, respectively. Cell lysates and bound materials washed with the buffer A five times were analyzed by SDS-PAGE and Western blotting. A similar protocol was used for the affinity chromatography of talin from transfected CHO cells on the GST-integrin β<sub>1</sub> tail, except that glutathione Sepharose beads were used.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Synaptosomes</title>
        <p>Rat brain synaptosomes were prepared as described previously (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bauerfeind et al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2004</xref>). In brief, 200-μl aliquots of synaptosomes were preincubated in the “control buffer” with or without Ca<sup>2+</sup> for 20 min at 37<sup>o</sup>C, and then diluted with an equal volume of either control buffer or stimulation buffer containing high K<sup>+</sup>. When inhibitors of protein kinases and phosphatases were used, the inhibitors were present during both the preincubation and the stimulation steps. For analysis of total phosphorylation of PIPKIγ90, synaptosomes were labeled with 2 mCi/ml γ-[<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate for 1 h prior to the preincubation. After a 1-min stimulation, 100 μl of buffer B (20 mM Hepes, pH 7.4, 50 mM NaCl, 50 mM Na<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 50 mM NaF, 5 mM EDTA, 5 mM EGTA, 5 mM β-glycerophosphate, 1 mM PMSF, and 1% Triton X-100 [vol/vol]) supplemented with 10% SDS (final 2% SDS) was directly added to synaptosomes for lysis and incubation mixtures were boiled for 10 min. For repolarization, synaptosomes stimulated by high K<sup>+</sup> were rapidly harvested, resuspended in control buffer, and were further incubated for 15 min before lysis. For PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitation, synaptosomal lysates were diluted with 9 vol of the buffer B and added to protein A–Sepharose beads precoated with anti-PIPKIγ90 antibody for 2 h at 4<sup>o</sup>C. Western blotting or autoradiography of synaptosomal lysates and PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitates were performed after SDS-PAGE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mitotic synchronization</title>
        <p>U87MG cells were grown in minimum essential medium with Earle's salts supplemented with 10% FBS, 0.1 mM nonessential amino acids, 2 mM <sc>l</sc>-glutamine, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 0.15% sodium bicarbonate, and antibiotics. To prepare both mitotic and G<sub>1</sub> interphase cells, subconfluent U87MG cells were treated with 250 ng/ml nocodazole (Sigma-Aldrich) for 18 h (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1999</xref>). Mitotic cells released into culture medium were collected by mechanical shake-off and washed with PBS. To harvest G<sub>1</sub> interphase cells, the mitotic cells were replated into fresh culture medium and further incubated for 10 h. CHO cells transfected with HA-PIPKIγ90 constructs were processed as described above. Preparation of cell lysates in the buffer A, PIPKIγ90 immunoprecipitation, SDS-PAGE, and Western blotting were performed as described above.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunofluorescence</title>
        <p>Immunofluorescence of transfected NIH3T3 cells was performed as described previously (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Di Paolo et al., 2002</xref>). Fluorescence was visualized with a microscope (Axioplan 2; Carl Zeiss MicroImaging, Inc.) equipped with a cooled CCD camera (Orca ER2; Hamamatsu) using a Plan-Apochromat (63×, 1.4 NA) oil immersion objective at room temperature. Images were acquired with Metamorph software (Universal Imaging) and processed using Adobe Photoshop.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Miscellaneous</title>
        <p>Amounts of proteins were calculated by a BCA assay kit (Pierce). SDS-PAGE and Western blotting were conducted using standard procedures.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank the Yale Keck Foundation Biotechnology Resource Laboratory for assistance in performing a phosphorylation site analysis, Markus Wenk for discussion in the initial stages of this work, David Calderwood for advice and suggestions, Yong Kim and Paul Greengard for help in the 2-D peptide mapping experiments and for providing purified p35–Cdk5 complex, Yanzhuang Wang and Graham Warren for providing purified cyclin B1–Cdk1 complex, and Li-Huei Tsai and Jari Ylanne for providing expression constructs.</p>
      <p>This work was supported in part by grants from the National Institutes of Health (NS36251 and CA46128 to P.D. Camilli; DA10044 to A.C. Nairn; Yale/National Institute on Drug Abuse Neuroproteomics Center, P30 DA018343 to P.D. Camilli and A.C. Nairn) and from the Yale Center for Genomics and Proteomics to P.D. Camilli., a Brown-Coxe fellowship to S. Voronov, a Howard Hughes Medical Institute fellowship to K. Letinic, and grants from the Yale Diabetes and Endocrinology Center to P. Di Camilli and G. Di Paolo.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Aikawa, Y., and T.F. Martin. <year>2003</year>. ARF6 regulates a plasma membrane pool of phosphatidylinositol(4,5)bisphosphate required for regulated exocytosis. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>–659.
<?supplied-pmid 12925709?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ajiro, K., K. Yoda, K. Utsumi, and Y. Nishikawa. <year>1996</year>. Alteration of cell cycle-dependent histone phosphorylations by okadaic acid. Induction of mitosis-specific H3 phosphorylation and chromatin condensation in mammalian interphase cells. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>271</volume>:<fpage>13197</fpage>–13201.
<?supplied-pmid 8662672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8662672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Alessi, D.R., N. Gomez, G. Moorhead, T. Lewis, S.M. Keyse, and P. Cohen. <year>1995</year>. Inactivation of p42 MAP kinase by protein phosphatase 2A and a protein tyrosine phosphatase, but not CL100, in various cell lines. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>–295.
<?supplied-pmid 7780739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7780739</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Barsukov, I.L., A. Prescot, N. Bate, B. Patel, D.N. Floyd, N. Bhanji, C.R. Bagshaw, K. Letinic, G. Di Paolo, P. De Camilli, et al. <year>2003</year>. Phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase type 1γ and β<sub>1</sub>-integrin cytoplasmic domain bind to the same region in the talin FERM domain. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>31202</fpage>–31209.
<?supplied-pmid 12782621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12782621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bauerfeind, R., K. Takei, and P. De Camilli. <year>1997</year>. Amphiphysin I is associated with coated endocytic intermediates and undergoes stimulation-dependent dephosphorylation in nerve terminals. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>272</volume>:<fpage>30984</fpage>–30992.
<?supplied-pmid 9388246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9388246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Borgne, A., A.C. Ostvold, S. Flament, and L. Meijer. <year>1999</year>. Intra-M phase-promoting factor phosphorylation of cyclin B at the prophase/metaphase transition. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>11977</fpage>–11986.
<?supplied-pmid 10207019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10207019</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Calderwood, D.A., and M.H. Ginsberg. <year>2003</year>. Talin forges the links between integrins and actin. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>694</fpage>–697.
<?supplied-pmid 12894175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12894175</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Calderwood, D.A., R. Zent, R. Grant, D.J. Rees, R.O. Hynes, and M.H. Ginsberg. <year>1999</year>. The talin head domain binds to integrin β subunit cytoplasmic tails and regulates integrin activation. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>28071</fpage>–28074.
<?supplied-pmid 10497155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10497155</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Calderwood, D.A., V. Tai, G. Di Paolo, P. De Camilli, and M.H. Ginsberg. <year>2004</year>. Competition for talin results in trans-dominant inhibition of integrin activation. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>28889</fpage>–28895.
<?supplied-pmid 15143061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15143061</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Carragher, N.O., and M.C. Frame. <year>2004</year>. Focal adhesion and actin dynamics: a place where kinases and proteases meet to promote invasion. <source>Trends Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>–249.
<?supplied-pmid 15130580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15130580</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chen, H., V.I. Slepnev, P.P. Di Fiore, and P. De Camilli. <year>1999</year>. The interaction of epsin and Eps15 with the clathrin adaptor AP-2 is inhibited by mitotic phosphorylation and enhanced by stimulation-dependent dephosphorylation in nerve terminals. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>3257</fpage>–3260.
<?supplied-pmid 9920862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920862</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cousin, M.A., and P.J. Robinson. <year>2001</year>. The dephosphins: dephosphorylation by calcineurin triggers synaptic vesicle endocytosis. <source>Trends Neurosci.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>–665.
<?supplied-pmid 11672811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11672811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cremona, O., G. Di Paolo, M.R. Wenk, A. Luthi, W.T. Kim, K. Takei, L. Daniell, Y. Nemoto, S.B. Shears, R.A. Flavell, et al. <year>1999</year>. Essential role of phosphoinositide metabolism in synaptic vesicle recycling. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>–188.
<?supplied-pmid 10535736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535736</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">De Camilli, P., S.D. Emr, P.S. McPherson, and P. Novick. <year>1996</year>. Phosphoinositides as regulators in membrane traffic. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>271</volume>:<fpage>1533</fpage>–1539.
<?supplied-pmid 8599109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599109</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">de Pereda, J.M., K. Wegener, E. Santelli, N. Bate, M.H. Ginsberg, D.R. Critchley, I.D. Campbell, and R.C. Liddington. 2004. Structural basis for phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase type I-gamma binding to talin at focal adhesions. <italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M413180200</pub-id>.
<?supplied-pmid 15623515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15623515</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Dhavan, R., and L.H. Tsai. <year>2001</year>. A decade of CDK5. <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>–759.
<?supplied-pmid 11584302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Di Paolo, G., L. Pellegrini, K. Letinic, G. Cestra, R. Zoncu, S. Voronov, S. Chang, J. Guo, M.R. Wenk, and P. De Camilli. <year>2002</year>. Recruitment and regulation of phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase type 1γ by the FERM domain of talin. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>420</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>–89.
<?supplied-pmid 12422219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12422219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Di Paolo, G., H.S. Moskowitz, K. Gipson, M.R. Wenk, S. Voronov, M. Obayashi, R. Flavell, R.M. Fitzsimonds, T.A. Ryan, and P. De Camilli. <year>2004</year>. Impaired PtdIns(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> synthesis in nerve terminals produces defects in synaptic vesicle trafficking. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>431</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>–422.
<?supplied-pmid 15386003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15386003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Doughman, R.L., A.J. Firestone, and R.A. Anderson. <year>2003</year>. Phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinases put PI4,5P<sub>2</sub> in its place. <source>J. Membr. Biol.</source>
<volume>194</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>–89.
<?supplied-pmid 14502432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14502432</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Floyd, S.R., E.B. Porro, V.I. Slepnev, G.C. Ochoa, L.H. Tsai, and P. De Camilli. <year>2001</year>. Amphiphysin 1 binds the cyclin-dependent kinase (cdk) 5 regulatory subunit p35 and is phosphorylated by cdk5 and cdc2. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>8104</fpage>–8110.
<?supplied-pmid 11113134?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113134</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gao, C., S. Negash, H.T. Guo, D. Ledee, H.-S. Wang, and P. Zelenka. <year>2002</year>. Cdk5 regulates cell adhesion and migration in corneal epithelial cells. <source>Mol. Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>–24.
<?supplied-pmid 12496365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496365</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Garcia-Alvarez, B., J.M. de Pereda, D.A. Calderwood, T.S. Ulmer, D. Critchley, I.D. Campbell, M.H. Ginsberg, and R.C. Liddington. <year>2003</year>. Structural determinants of integrin recognition by talin. <source>Mol. Cell.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>–58.
<?supplied-pmid 12535520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12535520</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Giudici, M.L., P.C. Emson, and R.F. Irvine. <year>2004</year>. A novel neuronal-specific splice variant of type I phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate 5-kinase isoform γ. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>379</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>–496.
<?supplied-pmid 14741049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14741049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hsieh-Wilson, L.C., F. Benfenati, G.L. Snyder, P.B. Allen, A.C. Nairn, and P. Greengard. <year>2003</year>. Phosphorylation of spinophilin modulates its interaction with actin filaments. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>278</volume>:<fpage>1186</fpage>–1194.
<?supplied-pmid 12417592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417592</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hynes, R.O. <year>2002</year>. Integrins: bidirectional, allosteric signaling machines. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>–687.
<?supplied-pmid 12297042?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297042</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ishihara, H., Y. Shibasaki, N. Kizuki, T. Wada, Y. Yazaki, T. Asano, and Y. Oka. <year>1998</year>. Type I phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate 5-kinases. Cloning of the third isoform and deletion/substitution analysis of members of this novel lipid kinase family. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>273</volume>:<fpage>8741</fpage>–8748.
<?supplied-pmid 9535851?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535851</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jovanovic, J.N., T.S. Sihra, A.C. Nairn, H.C. Hemmings Jr., P. Greengard, and A.J. Czernik. <year>2001</year>. Opposing changes in phosphorylation of specific sites in synapsin I during Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent glutamate release in isolated nerve terminals. <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>7944</fpage>–7953.
<?supplied-pmid 11588168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11588168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Krauss, M., M. Kinuta, M.R. Wenk, P. De Camilli, K. Takei, and V. Haucke. <year>2003</year>. ARF6 stimulates clathrin/AP-2 recruitment to synaptic membranes by activating phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase type Iγ. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>–124.
<?supplied-pmid 12847086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12847086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lee, S.Y., M.R. Wenk, Y. Kim, A.C. Nairn, and P. De Camilli. <year>2004</year>. Regulation of synaptojanin 1 by cyclin-dependent kinase 5 at synapses. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>–551.
<?supplied-pmid 14704270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14704270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Liddington, R.C., L.A. Bankston, and J.M. de Pereda. <year>2003</year>. Cell adhesion: a FERM grasp of membrane dynamics. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>R94</fpage>–R95.
<?supplied-pmid 12573235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573235</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ling, K., R.L. Doughman, A.J. Firestone, M.W. Bunce, and R.A. Anderson. <year>2002</year>. Type Iγ phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase targets and regulates focal adhesions. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>420</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>–93.
<?supplied-pmid 12422220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12422220</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ling, K., R.L. Doughman, V.V. Iyer, A.J. Firestone, S.F. Bairstow, D.F. Mosher, M.D. Schaller, and R.A. Anderson. <year>2003</year>. Tyrosine phosphorylation of type Iγ phosphatidylinositol phosphate kinase by Src regulates an integrin-talin switch. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>1339</fpage>–1349.
<?supplied-pmid 14691141?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14691141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Maddox, A.S., and K. Burridge. <year>2003</year>. RhoA is required for cortical retraction and rigidity during mitotic cell rounding. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>–265.
<?supplied-pmid 12538643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538643</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martel, V., C. Racaud-Sultan, S. Dupe, C. Marie, F. Paulhe, A. Galmiche, M.R. Block, and C. Albiges-Rizo. <year>2001</year>. Conformation, localization, and integrin binding of talin depend on its interaction with phosphoinositides. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>21217</fpage>–21227.
<?supplied-pmid 11279249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11279249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martin, T.F. <year>1998</year>. Phosphoinositide lipids as signaling molecules: common themes for signal transduction, cytoskeletal regulation, and membrane trafficking. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>–264.
<?supplied-pmid 9891784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891784</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McPherson, P.S., A.J. Czernik, T.J. Chilcote, F. Onofri, F. Benfenati, P. Greengard, J. Schlessinger, and P. De Camilli. <year>1994</year>. Interaction of Grb2 via its Src homology 3 domains with synaptic proteins including synapsin I. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>6486</fpage>–6490.
<?supplied-pmid 8022809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8022809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Morgan, J.R., G. Di Paolo, H. Werner, V.A. Shchedrina, M. Pypaert, V.A. Pieribone, and P. De Camilli. <year>2004</year>. A role for talin in presynaptic function. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–50.
<?supplied-pmid 15479735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479735</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Park, S.J., T. Itoh, and T. Takenawa. <year>2001</year>. Phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate 5-kinase type I is regulated through phosphorylation response by extracellular stimuli. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>4781</fpage>–4787.
<?supplied-pmid 11087761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Patrick, G.N., L. Zukerberg, M. Nikolic, S. de la Monte, P. Dikkes, and L.H. Tsai. <year>1999</year>. Conversion of p35 to p25 deregulates Cdk5 activity and promotes neurodegeneration. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>402</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>–622.
<?supplied-pmid 10604467?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10604467</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Purcell, A.L., and T.J. Carew. <year>2003</year>. Tyrosine kinases, synaptic plasticity and memory: insights from vertebrates and invertebrates. <source>Trends Neurosci.</source>
<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>–630.
<?supplied-pmid 14585603?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14585603</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pypaert, M., D. Mundy, E. Souter, J.C. Labbe, and G. Warren. <year>1991</year>. Mitotic cytosol inhibits invagination of coated pits in broken mitotic cells. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>–1166.
<?supplied-pmid 1910051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1910051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sahin, B., and J.A. Bibb. <year>2004</year>. Protein kinases talk to lipid phosphatases at the synapse. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1112</fpage>–1113.
<?supplied-pmid 14745021?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Songyang, Z., K.P. Lu, Y.T. Kwon, L.H. Tsai, O. Filhol, C. Cochet, D.A. Brickey, T.R. Soderling, C. Bartleson, D.J. Graves, et al. <year>1996</year>. A structural basis for substrate specificities of protein Ser/Thr kinases: primary sequence preference of casein kinases I and II, NIMA, phosphorylase kinase, calmodulin-dependent kinase II, CDK5, and Erk1. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>6486</fpage>–6493.
<?supplied-pmid 8887677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8887677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Takenawa, T., and T. Itoh. <year>2001</year>. Phosphoinositides, key molecules for regulation of actin cytoskeletal organization and membrane traffic from the plasma membrane. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta.</source>
<volume>1533</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>–206.
<?supplied-pmid 11731330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tan, T.C., V.A. Valova, C.S. Malladi, M.E. Graham, L.A. Berven, O.J. Jupp, G. Hansra, S.J. McClure, B. Sarcevic, R.A. Boadle, et al. <year>2003</year>. Cdk5 is essential for synaptic vesicle endocytosis. <source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>701</fpage>–710.
<?supplied-pmid 12855954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12855954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tomizawa, K., S. Sunada, Y.F. Lu, Y. Oda, M. Kinuta, T. Ohshima, T. Saito, F.Y. Wei, M. Matsushita, S.T. Li, et al. <year>2003</year>. Cophosphorylation of amphiphysin I and dynamin I by Cdk5 regulates clathrin-mediated endocytosis of synaptic vesicles. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>163</volume>:<fpage>813</fpage>–824.
<?supplied-pmid 14623869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14623869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Turnbull, W.B., and A.H. Daranas. <year>2003</year>. On the value of <italic>c</italic>: Can low affinity systems be studied by isothermal titration calorimetry? <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>14859</fpage>–14866.
<?supplied-pmid 14640663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14640663</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang, Y., J. Seemann, M. Pypaert, J. Shorter, and G. Warren. <year>2003</year>. A direct role for GRASP65 as a mitotically regulated Golgi stacking factor. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>3279</fpage>–3290.
<?supplied-pmid 12839990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12839990</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wenk, M.R., and P. De Camilli. <year>2004</year>. Protein-lipid interactions and phosphoinositide metabolism in membrane traffic: insights from vesicle recycling in nerve terminals. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>8262</fpage>–8269.
<?supplied-pmid 15146067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wenk, M.R., L. Pellegrini, V.A. Klenchin, G. Di Paolo, S. Chang, L. Daniell, M. Arioka, T.F. Martin, and P. De Camilli. <year>2001</year>. PIP kinase Iγ is the major PI(4,5)P<sub>2</sub> synthesizing enzyme at the synapse. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>–88.
<?supplied-pmid 11604140?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604140</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xie, Z., K. Sanada, B.A. Samuels, H. Shih, and L.H. Tsai. <year>2003</year>. Serine 732 phosphorylation of FAK by Cdk5 is important for microtubule organization, nuclear movement, and neuronal migration. <source>Cell.</source>
<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>–482.
<?supplied-pmid 12941275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941275</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yamagata, Y., J.N. Jovanovic, A.J. Czernik, P. Greengard, and K. Obata. <year>2002</year>. Bidirectional changes in synapsin I phosphorylation at MAP kinase-dependent sites by acute neuronal excitation in vivo. <source>J. Neurochem.</source>
<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>–842.
<?supplied-pmid 11948247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11948247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib53">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yin, H.L., and P.A. Janmey. <year>2003</year>. Phosphoinositide regulation of the actin cytoskeleton. <source>Annu. Rev. Physiol.</source>
<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>761</fpage>–789.
<?supplied-pmid 12471164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>