<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:28:00Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2118775" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2118775</identifier><datestamp>2008-04-17</datestamp><setSpec>jexpmed</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2118775</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2118775</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2118775</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1703205</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">91108327</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1703205</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genomic structure of the human Ig lambda 1 gene suggests that it may be expressed as an Ig lambda 14.1-like protein or as a canonical B cell Ig lambda light chain: implications for Ig lambda gene evolution</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>1</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>1991</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>173</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>305</fpage>
      <lpage>311</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In pre-B cells, immunoglobulin mu (Ig mu) is associated with pre-B cell- specific proteins to form a multimeric complex that is found on the cell surface. One of these proteins is encoded by the three exon Ig lambda-like gene 14.1, whose expression is restricted to pre-B cells and occurs from an unrearranged gene. A comparison of the 14.1 gene structure to the seven-gene human Ig lambda locus revealed that the most 5' gene, Ig lambda 1, is organized in a three-exon structure very similar to the 14.1 gene. Transcription and splicing of these three- exon sequences would lead to an mRNA with an open reading frame which could encode a light (L) chain-like protein with a molecular weight of 23,045. Our analysis suggests that two transcripts may be produced from the Ig lambda 1 gene that share the same Ig lambda 1 constant region- containing third exon. One transcript would include all three 14.1- related exons and be expressed from the germline gene, and the second transcript would be produced after variable-joining (V-J) recombination has occurred to Ig lambda J1 and would encode a classic Ig lambda L chain protein. The conservation of the genomic organization of the human 14.1 and Ig lambda 1 genes and the mouse homolog, lambda 5, relative to the classic Ig lambda L chain genes provides insight into the evolution of Ig genes.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>