<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:33:54Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2666608" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2666608</identifier><datestamp>2009-04-13</datestamp><setSpec>jbc</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2666608</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2666608</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2666608</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19202191</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9558</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M808906200</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19202191</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>DNA: Replication, Repair, Recombination, and Chromosome  Dynamics</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Human CtIP Mediates Cell Cycle Control of DNA End Resection and Double
 Strand Break
 Repair<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">S⃞</xref></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Huertas</surname>
            <given-names>Pablo</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jackson</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="N0x1d278b0N0x43ab078">Gurdon Institute and Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge,
 Cambridge CB2 1QN, United Kingdom</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="cor1">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>
 To whom correspondence should be addressed: Gurdon Institute, Tennis Court
 Road, Cambridge CB2 1QN, UK. Tel.: 44-1223-334102; Fax: 44-1223-334089;
 E-mail:
 <email>s.jackson@gurdon.cam.ac.uk</email>.
 </p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on 
		/art/copyright. -->
      <volume>284</volume>
      <issue>14</issue>
      <fpage>9558</fpage>
      <lpage>9565</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2009, The American Society for Biochemistry and
 Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p>
            <italic>Author's Choice</italic>
          </p>
          <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
 Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author
 Choice Articles</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zbc01409009558.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>In G<sub>0</sub> and G<sub>1</sub>, DNA double strand breaks are repaired
 by nonhomologous end joining, whereas in S and G<sub>2</sub>, they are also
 repaired by homologous recombination. The human CtIP protein controls double
 strand break (DSB) resection, an event that occurs effectively only in
 S/G<sub>2</sub> and that promotes homologous recombination but not
 non-homologous end joining. Here, we mutate a highly conserved
 cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK) target motif in CtIP and reveal that mutating
 Thr-847 to Ala impairs resection, whereas mutating it to Glu to mimic
 constitutive phosphorylation does not. Moreover, we show that unlike cells
 expressing wild-type CtIP, cells expressing the Thr-to-Glu mutant resect DSBs
 even after CDK inhibition. Finally, we establish that Thr-847 mutations to
 either Ala or Glu affect DSB repair efficiency, cause hypersensitivity toward
 DSB-generating agents, and affect the frequency and nature of
 radiation-induced chromosomal rearrangements. These results suggest that
 CDK-mediated control of resection in human cells operates by mechanisms
 similar to those recently established in yeast.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>This work was supported by grants from <grant-sponsor>Cancer Research
 UK</grant-sponsor> and the <grant-sponsor>European Community</grant-sponsor>
 (<grant-sponsor>Integrated Project DNA repair</grant-sponsor>, Grant
 <grant-num>LSHG-CT-2005-512113</grant-num>, and <grant-sponsor>Genomic
 Instability in Cancer and Precancer</grant-sponsor>, Grant
 <grant-num>HEALTH-F2-2007-201630</grant-num>) (to S. P. J.) and
 <grant-sponsor>Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council
 Research</grant-sponsor> Grant <grant-num>BBF0016651</grant-num> (to P.
 H.).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn3">
          <label/>
          <p>The on-line version of this article (available at
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org">http://www.jbc.org</ext-link>)
 contains five supplemental figures.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2">
          <label/>
          <p><italic>Author's Choice</italic>—Final version full
 access.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body><p>DNA double strand breaks
 (DSBs)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">2</xref> are highly
 cytotoxic lesions that can lead to mutations, chromosomal aberrations, or cell
 death. Defects in DSB signaling and/or repair can cause pathologies, including
 neurodegenerative disease and cancer predisposition. DSBs are repaired by two
 main mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>): non-homologous end joining
 (NHEJ) and homologous recombination (HR). NHEJ ligates broken DNA ends without
 requiring extensive sequence complementarity and assumes the greatest
 importance in G<sub>0</sub> and G<sub>1</sub>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>). By contrast, HR is
 generally restricted to S and G<sub>2</sub>, where it can ensure accurate
 repair by using sister chromatid sequences as the repair template
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>).
 Such cell cycle control of DSB repair is important because if HR is employed
 in G<sub>1</sub>, it can generate gross chromosomal rearrangements by using
 spurious homologous sequences as repair templates.</p><p>Although various mechanisms likely control HR, a prime site of regulation
 is at the level of 5′ to 3′ DSB resection. Resection is needed for
 HR but not for NHEJ and is governed by CDK activity in yeast and mammalian
 cells, occurring effectively in S/G<sub>2</sub> but not
 G<sub>0</sub>/G<sub>1</sub>
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>).
 Recent work has shown that a key target for this control in yeast is the Sae2
 protein, which is phosphorylated on Ser-267 by CDK to promote resection
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). Notably, Sae2 counterparts
 have been identified in other organisms, including vertebrates
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>),
 and with the exception of <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> Ctp1
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>), they all share a short
 homologous region in their C termini containing a CDK consensus site that
 aligns with Ser-267 of Sae2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>).
 We have recently shown that mutating Sae2 Ser-267 to Ala to prevent its
 phosphorylation impairs resection and consequently reduces HR, whereas
 altering Ser-267 to Glu mimics constitutive phosphorylation and allows some
 resection even in the absence of CDK activity
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). Here, we carry out
 analogous studies on the equivalent CDK consensus motif of CtIP and thus
 provide evidence that CDK-mediated control of DSB resection operates by
 conserved mechanisms in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and humans.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title><p><italic>Cell Culture, siRNA Transfection, and Cell Survival</italic>—U2OS
 cells stably expressing GFP-CtIP variants were grown in Dulbecco's modified
 Eagle's medium (Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum
 (BioSera), 100 units/ml penicillin, and 100 μg/ml streptomycin
 (Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 0.5 mg/ml G418 (Invitrogen). siRNA duplex
 against CtIP (GCUAAAACAGGAACGAAUC; MWG Biotec) was previously described
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>), and siRNA transfections
 were performed with 50 n<sc>m</sc> final oligonucleotide concentrations and
 Oligofectamine (Invitrogen). Experiments were performed 48 h after
 transfection. Cell survival assays were performed as described previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>).</p><p><italic>Immunoblotting</italic>—Extracts were prepared in 4% SDS, 20%
 glycerol, 120 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, and proteins were resolved by
 SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose followed by immunoblotting. R. Baer
 (Columbia University) provided a mouse monoclonal CtIP antibody, and X. Yu
 (University of Michigan Medical School) provided the phospho-Ser-327 antibody.
 Other antibodies were from AbCam (Mre11, RPA32), Bethyl Laboratories
 (RPA32-pS4/S8), Santa Cruz Biotechnology (BRCA1, GST), and Roche Applied
 Science (GFP).</p><p><italic>In Vitro CDK Assay</italic>—A GST-fused version of the CtIP
 C-terminal region (residues 790-897) was affinity-purified with
 glutathione-Sepharose 4B (Amersham Biosciences), incubated with recombinant
 CDK2/cyclin A (Upstate Biotechnology) in the presence of
 [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP according to the manufacturer's instructions,
 separated by 10% SDS-PAGE, and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane.
 Proteins were detected with an anti-GST antibody, and phosphorylation was
 visualized by autoradiography.</p><p><italic>Laser Microirradiation</italic>—Generation of localized DNA damage by
 laser was done as previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>). Cells were fixed with 4%
 paraformaldehyde (w/v) in PBS for 15 min, treated with 0.2% Triton X-100 in
 PBS for 10 min, washed three times with PBS, and then co-immunostained with
 antibodies against γH2AX (Cell Signaling Technology), cyclin A (Santa
 Cruz Biotechnology), and RPA32 (Lab Vision Corp.). For detection, Alexa Fluor
 594- (red) and 647- (far red) conjugated secondary antibodies were used
 (Molecular Probes, Paisley, UK). Samples were visualized with an Olympus
 inverted confocal laser microscope by sequential scanning of the emission
 channels.</p><p><italic>Immunofluorescence Microscopy</italic>—For RPA focus detection, U2OS
 cells expressing GFP-CtIP fusions were transfected with CtIP siRNA, and 2 days
 later, they were treated with 1 μ<sc>m</sc> camptothecin or 10 Gy of
 ionizing radiation (IR) and collected 1 h afterward. Following pre-extraction
 for 5 min on ice (25 m<sc>m</sc> Hepes, pH 7.4, 50 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 1
 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 3 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 300 m<sc>m</sc>
 sucrose, and 0.5% Triton X-100), cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde
 (w/v) in PBS for 15 min. Coverslips were washed three times with PBS and then
 co-immunostained as above.</p><p><italic>Random Plasmid Integration</italic>—Assays were as described
 previously with minor modifications
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). One day after
 transfection with CtIP siRNA, cells were transfected with PvuI-linearized
 pCDNA4-HISMAX-LacZ (Invitrogen). The following day, cells were collected,
 counted, and plated on three plates, one containing 1 mg/ml Zeocin. One day
 after plating, cells on a plate lacking Zeocin were assessed for transfection
 efficiency by a β-galactosidase staining kit (Invitrogen), and the other
 two plates were incubated for 10-14 days at 37 °C for colony formation.
 Colonies were stained with 0.5% crystal violet, 20% ethanol and counted.
 Integration events (number of colonies on plates containing Zeocin) were
 normalized to transfection (number of β-galactosidase-positive cells) and
 plating efficiencies (colonies after 14 days of growth without Zeocin).</p><p><italic>Chromosomal Analyses</italic>—Following CtIP depletion, cells were
 exposed to 2 Gy of IR and then allowed to recover at 37 °C for 8 h in
 fresh medium before chromosome preparation. Within these 8 h, cells were
 treated with caffeine (2 m<sc>m</sc> final concentration) for the last 5 h
 to allow cells with gross chromosomal rearrangements (GCRs) to overcome the
 G<sub>2</sub>/M checkpoint and enter mitosis, and for the last 3 h, they were
 treated with Colcemid (KaryoMAX, Invitrogen; final concentration 0.1 mg/ml) to
 induce chromosome condensation. Cells were then harvested and treated with
 0.075 <sc>m</sc> KCl for 10 min at 37 °C, fixed in methanol/acetic acid
 (3/1), washed twice with methanol/acetic acid (3/1), and then spread on a
 glass microscope slide, air-dried, and
 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole-stained.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p><italic>CtIP Function Is Impaired by Mutating Thr-847</italic>—A similar CDK
 consensus sequence to that encompassing Sae2 Ser-267 is present in nearly all
 Sae2/CtIP orthologues, with the analogous residue of human CtIP being Thr-847
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). To
 investigate the potential functions of Thr-847 phosphorylation, we generated
 stable U2OS cell clones that expressed siRNA-resistant wild-type GFP-tagged
 CtIP, or siRNA-resistant CtIP derivatives in which Thr-847 was changed to an
 unphosphorylatable Ala (GFP-CtIP-T847A) or to a negatively charged Glu residue
 (GFP-CtIP-T847E) to mimic constitutive phosphorylation. We selected for clones
 that expressed the engineered protein at similar levels to endogenous CtIP
 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>), and a
 stable cell line expressing GFP alone was generated as a negative control. As
 shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>,
 transfection with the CtIP siRNA oligonucleotide effectively depleted
 endogenous CtIP but not the siRNA-resistant GFP-CtIP fusion proteins.</p><p>As an approach to detect phosphorylation on CtIP Thr-847, we made several
 attempts to generate phospho-specific antisera against this site. When we
 assessed the resulting antisera by Western immunoblotting, however, this
 strategy was undermined by the antibodies recognizing additional
 phosphorylation sites on CtIP (data not shown). By contrast, when we used the
 antibodies in indirect immunofluorescence studies, we observed that a
 subpopulation (∼60%) of cells expressing wild-type GFP-CtIP exhibited a
 strongly positive signal, whereas staining was much weaker in cells expressing
 the CtIP variant, GFP-CtIP-T847A (we assume that the remaining, weak signal
 observed with the T847A mutant was due to cross-reactivity with other
 phosphorylation sites). Consistent with the strongly positive signal
 reflecting CDK-mediated modification of CtIP on Thr-847, this signal was
 markedly diminished when cells were pretreated with the CDK inhibitor
 roscovitine (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref>).
 To further substantiate the idea that CtIP is phosphorylated on Thr-847 by
 CDK, we purified bacterially expressed wild-type and Thr-847 mutated versions
 of a C-terminal fragment of CtIP tagged with GST. Next, we subjected these
 proteins to <italic>in vitro</italic> CDK phosphorylation assays with purified
 CDK/cyclin A and radioactive ATP (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>D</italic></xref>). Notably, when the wild-type CtIP fragment was used,
 radioactive phosphate was incorporated in a CDK-dependent manner. By contrast,
 little or no radioactivity was incorporated into the CtIP derivative bearing
 the Thr-847 Thr-to-Ala mutation (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 1<italic>D</italic></xref>). Collectively, these findings thereby provided strong
 support for CtIP Thr-847 indeed being a CDK target.</p><p>To assess the potential functions of CtIP Thr-847 phosphorylation, we
 siRNA-depleted endogenous CtIP from the cell clones expressing GFP-CtIP
 variants (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>) and
 then assessed their survival following acute (1 h) treatments with various
 concentrations of camptothecin. In agreement with our previous data
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>), cells expressing the T847A
 CtIP mutant were more sensitive to camptothecin than cells expressing
 wild-type CtIP and were essentially as sensitive as control cells expressing
 GFP alone (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>).
 By contrast, cells expressing the T847E CtIP mutant were not hypersensitive to
 camptothecin and were, in fact, more resistant than cells expressing wild-type
 CtIP (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>). As
 camptothecin cytotoxicity depends on DNA replication, it was possible that the
 above differences in survival reflected different cell cycle distributions
 among the various cell clones. However, fluorescence-activated cell sorter
 analyses revealed only minor differences in cell cycle distributions between
 the cell lines (supplemental Fig. 1<italic>A</italic>). Furthermore, all cell lines
 exhibited similar levels of camptothecin-induced DSB formation, as assessed by
 the appearance of phosphorylated histone H2AX (γH2AX) foci
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>black
 bars</italic>). However, when we analyzed the same γH2AX-positive cells for
 formation of RPA-coated ssDNA, significant differences were observed. RPA foci
 formed efficiently in cells expressing wild-type CtIP or the T847E mutant but
 not in cells expressing the T847A mutant or GFP alone
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>, <italic>white
 bars</italic>). These results indicated that the ability of CtIP to promote
 camptothecin resistance is impaired when Thr-847 is mutated to an
 unphosphorylatable Ala residue but not when it is altered to a
 phospho-mimicking Glu residue. Furthermore, the camptothecin sensitivity
 phenotype imparted by the CtIP T847A mutation might reflect impaired
 processing of camptothecin-induced DSBs into ssDNA.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Functional effects of mutating Thr-847 of CtIP.</bold> <italic>A</italic>,
 alignment of the region conserved among Sae2/CtIP orthologues. <italic>Arrows</italic>
 show the position of the conserved CtIP Thr-847 and Sae2 Ser-267. <italic>A.
 thaliana, Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>; <italic>C. elegans, Caenorhabditis
 elegans</italic>; <italic>P. nodorum, Phaeosphaeria nodorum</italic>; <italic>C. globosum,
 Chaetomium globosum</italic>; <italic>N. crassa, Neurospora crassa</italic>; <italic>C.
 neoformans, Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>; <italic>Y. lipolytica, Yarrowia
 lipolytica</italic>; <italic>A. gossypii, Ashbya gossypii. B</italic>, expression levels
 of GFP-CtIP derivatives in stably transfected clones before (<italic>left</italic>) or
 after (<italic>right</italic>) siRNA depletion of endogenous CtIP (<italic>siCtIP</italic>).
 <italic>C</italic>, representative confocal microscope images of cells expressing
 wild-type or T847A CtIP variants after immunostaining with a phospho-specific
 antibody raised against phosphorylated Thr-847. Cells were incubated in the
 presence of the CDK inhibitor roscovitine where indicated. <italic>D</italic>, a
 GST-fused wild-type or T847A mutant CtIP C-terminal fragment (residues
 750-897) was affinity-purified with glutathione-Sepharose 4B and then
 incubated with [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP in the presence or absence of
 recombinant CDK2/cyclin A, separated by 10% SDS-PAGE, and transferred to
 nitrocellulose membrane. Proteins were detected with an anti-GST antibody
 (<italic>bottom</italic>), and phosphorylation was visualized by autoradiography (CDK
 assay; <italic>top</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0190972190001"/></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of CtIP mutations on cellular responses to camptothecin-induced
 DNA damage.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, cell survival after exposing cells expressing
 GFP-CtIP fusions to the indicated doses of camptothecin; averages and standard
 deviations (<italic>error bars</italic>) of three independent experiments are shown.
 <italic>B</italic>, quantification of γH2AX and RPA foci-positive cells and
 γH2AX focus-positive cells for the indicated CtIP variants after 1 h of
 treatment with 1 μ<sc>m</sc> camptothecin. Averages and standard
 deviations (<italic>error bars</italic>) of four independent experiments are shown. At
 least 200 cells were counted per experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0190972190002"/></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of CtIP mutations on recruitment of proteins to laser-induced
 damage.</bold> Representative images of cells expressing GFP-CtIP variants after
 laser damage are shown. Cells were immunostained for RPA (<italic>magenta</italic>)
 and γH2AX plus cyclin A (<italic>red</italic>). Damaged cells not expressing
 cyclin A (G<sub>1</sub>) and cells positive for cyclin A (S/G<sub>2</sub>) are
 marked with <italic>empty</italic> and <italic>filled arrows</italic>, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0190972190003"/></fig></p><p><italic>CtIP Mutations Affect Recruitment of CtIP and RPA to DNA
 Damage</italic>—CtIP modulates responses to DNA damage in a cell
 cycle-dependent manner and is only effectively recruited to sites of
 laser-induced damage in cyclin A-positive cells (S and G<sub>2</sub> cells),
 when RPA tracts are also formed
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). As CtIP depletion
 impairs ssDNA formation after camptothecin treatment, this suggests that
 assessment of camptothecin-induced RPA focus formation would be an effective
 way to test the effects of mutating CtIP Thr-847. However, this approach has
 several limitations. First, camptothecin primarily yields DSBs only in
 S-phase; second, CtIP recruitment into discernible foci is difficult to
 observe after camptothecin treatment
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>); and third, to observe
 RPA recruitment to sites of DNA damage, cellular preextraction is required,
 which impedes co-staining for soluble cell cycle markers such as cyclins. To
 overcome these problems, we used laser DNA-damaging microirradiation. Thus, we
 laser-irradiated the previously described cell clones stably expressing
 wild-type or mutated CtIP derivatives after they had been siRNA-depleted of
 endogenous CtIP. Next, we assessed the appearance of DNA damage tracts by
 immunofluorescence with antibodies against RPA (to detect RPA-coated ssDNA),
 γH2AX (to detect damaged chromatin), and cyclin A (to distinguish
 G<sub>1</sub> cells from S/G<sub>2</sub> cells. Due to limitations in the
 number of channels available in the microscope and in the number of
 non-cross-reacting secondary antibodies, γH2AX and cyclin A were
 analyzed in the same channel). As shown in
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, <italic>A-D</italic></xref>,
 laser-induced γH2AX tracts were clearly evident in all irradiated cells,
 irrespective of whether or not they displayed pannuclear cyclin A staining. By
 contrast, and as reported previously
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>), wild-type GFP-CtIP was
 recruited to damage sites in all S/G<sub>2</sub> cells that stained positive
 for cyclin A (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>E</italic></xref>,
 <italic>filled arrows</italic>) but not in cyclin A-negative G<sub>1</sub> cells
 (<italic>open arrows</italic>). Notably, although a similar recruitment kinetics was
 observed for the CtIP-T847A mutant (supplemental Fig. 2), RPA recruitment was
 readily observed in S/G<sub>2</sub> cells expressing wild-type CtIP but not in
 S/G<sub>2</sub> cells expressing CtIP-T847A
 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, <italic>I</italic> and
 <italic>J</italic></xref>), implying that Thr-847 phosphorylation regulates the
 ability of CtIP to promote resection. In line with this, whereas CtIP-T847E
 was effectively recruited to damage sites in S/G<sub>2</sub>
 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>G</italic></xref>, <italic>filled
 arrows</italic>; supplemental Fig. 2 for kinetics), it was also recruited to some
 degree in G<sub>1</sub> cells (more than 80% of G<sub>1</sub> cells showed
 weak but visible GFP lines; <italic>open arrows</italic>). This suggests that
 mimicking constitutive phosphorylation enhances CtIP activity and raises the
 possibility that this might allow some CtIP function even in G<sub>1</sub>
 cells. Indeed, cells expressing CtIP-T847E generally displayed more pronounced
 RPA recruitment than cells expressing wild-type CtIP
 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, <italic>K</italic> and
 <italic>I</italic></xref>, respectively), and furthermore, weak RPA recruitment
 was evident in more than 90% of G<sub>1</sub> cells expressing CtIP-T847E
 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>K</italic></xref>, <italic>open
 arrows</italic>), although this was less pronounced than in S/G<sub>2</sub> cells
 (<italic>filled arrows</italic>). These findings thus suggest that CtIP Thr-847
 controls resection during the cell cycle but imply that other CDK-mediated
 phosphorylations are also needed for optimal resection to occur.</p><p><italic>CtIP-T847E Promotes Resection Even Following CDK
 Inhibition</italic>—Although the above data suggest that mimicking
 constitutive phosphorylation of CtIP Thr-847 can partially overcome the CDK
 requirement for DNA DSB processing, it was formally possible that the cyclin
 A-negative CtIP-T847E cells displaying RPA recruitment in
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> were in early S-phase,
 when CDK was already active, but cyclin A levels were too weak for detection.
 To address this possibility, we siRNA-depleted endogenous CtIP from cells
 stably expressing siRNA-resistant GFP-CtIP variants and then treated them with
 DMSO (negative control) or with the CDK inhibitor, roscovitine. (Supplemental
 Fig. 1<italic>B</italic> shows that the fluorescence-activated cell sorter
 distributions of DMSO- and roscovitine-treated samples were similar,
 presumably reflecting inhibition of cell cycle transitions by roscovitine.)
 Next, we treated the cells with X-rays. We chose x-ray treatment because it
 generates DSBs in all cell cycle phases and allowed us to damage a larger
 number of cells than we could with laser microirradiation. Subsequently, we
 assessed cells for DSB formation (γH2AX foci) and ssDNA production (RPA
 foci). In line with our previous results, DMSO-treated cells expressing
 wild-type GFP-CtIP or GFP-CtIP-T847E effectively formed RPA foci, whereas
 cells expressing GFP-CtIP T847A or GFP alone did not
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). Similar
 results were obtained when we detected ssDNA with an anti-bromodeoxyuridine
 antibody labeling method (supplemental Fig. 3), indicating that CtIP Thr-847
 indeed controls ssDNA formation. Taken together with our other data, these
 findings therefore indicate that CtIP phosphorylation on Thr-847 controls
 ssDNA formation and RPA recruitment to sites of damaged DNA induced by
 camptothecin, laser microirradiation, or X-rays. Furthermore, we found that
 although roscovitine severely curtailed RPA focus formation following exposure
 to IR in cells expressing wild-type CtIP, it did not prevent RPA focus
 formation in cells expressing CtIP-T847E
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>).
 Nevertheless, careful comparisons revealed that roscovitine treatment did
 reduce the intensity and number of RPA foci in cells expressing CtIP-T847E
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, <italic>B</italic> and
 <italic>C</italic></xref>), showing that although CtIP-T847E permits resection
 even after CDK inhibition, this resection is less extensive than in the
 presence of CDK activity.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p><bold>CtIP mutations affect DSB processing.</bold> <italic>A</italic>, cells expressing
 CtIP variants were treated with DMSO (-) or 25 μ<sc>m</sc> roscovitine
 (<italic>Rosc.</italic>)(+) and then irradiated with 10 Gy of IR. One h later, cells
 were immunostained for RPA or γH2AX. Averages and standard deviations
 (<italic>error bars</italic>) of three independent experiments are shown. At least 200
 cells were counted per experiment. <italic>B</italic>, representative images of cells
 treated in <italic>A. C</italic>, the number of RPA foci per cell in cells expressing
 the GFP-CtIP-T847E mutant in the presence or absence of the CDK inhibitor
 roscovitine. <italic>Error bars</italic>, standard deviations. <italic>D</italic>, an
 immunoblot of protein extracts, collected 1 h after irradiation (10 Gy), of
 cells expressing the indicated GFP-CtIP fusions. Panels to the <italic>left</italic>
 and <italic>right</italic> contain samples derived from cells treated in the absence
 or presence of roscovitine, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0190972190004"/></fig></p><p>Although the study of focus formation by microscopy is used commonly in the
 DNA damage-response field, it has some limitations. On the one hand, foci are
 complex structures in which several types of damage can coexist and,
 therefore, different DNA repair pathways can operate at the same locations. In
 addition, to be visible, the foci must contain thousands of protein molecules,
 meaning that more subtle events close to the DNA lesions might be missed. To
 complement our data with focus formation, we therefore prepared extracts from
 DNA-damaged or control cells and then analyzed them by Western immunoblotting
 for phosphorylation on Ser-4 and Ser-8 of the 32-kDa subunit of RPA (RPA32).
 These modifications are generated after different types of DNA damage
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>) by mechanisms that involve
 the DNA-dependent protein kinase (DNA-PK
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>)). Although the precise
 roles for these RPA32 phosphorylations are not known, because they affect the
 affinity of RPA toward both ssDNA and double-stranded DNA
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>) and increase the
 interaction of RPA with the recombination proteins Rad51 and Rad52
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>), it has been proposed
 that RPA Ser-4/8 phosphorylation facilitates RPA eviction and homologous
 recombination. Importantly, as RPA Ser-4/8 phosphorylation appears to only
 occur after DNA resection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>), the detection of this
 modified form of RPA is a very sensitive readout of DNA end processing.
 Notably, we readily detected RPA32 Ser-4/8 phosphorylation, both by using
 phospho-specific antisera and by reduced mobility of the protein on SDS-PAGE,
 in irradiated cells expressing wild-type CtIP or CtIP-T847E but not in cells
 expressing GFP alone or GFP-CtIP T847A
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>).
 Furthermore, we found that RPA32 Ser-4/8 phosphorylation was slightly higher
 in cells expressing CtIP-T847E than in cells expressing wild-type CtIP
 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>, <italic>left
 panels</italic>). Moreover, although roscovitine abolished RPA Ser-4/8
 phosphorylation in cells expressing wild-type CtIP, residual RPA
 phosphorylation was still evident after roscovitine treatment of cells
 expressing CtIP-T847E (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 4<italic>D</italic></xref>, <italic>right panels</italic>). These data therefore provide
 strong support for CtIP Thr-847 phosphorylation playing a key role in
 mediating cell cycle control of DSB resection and RPA recruitment.</p><p><italic>Mutation of CtIP Thr-847 Influences Genome
 Stability</italic>—Controlling DSB resection is thought to help ensure that
 the most appropriate DSB repair pathway is used at each cell cycle stage. In
 budding yeast, we have shown that this control depends on Sae2 Ser-267
 phosphorylation by CDK and that defects in this mechanism lead to imbalances
 between NHEJ and HR, with the Sae2-S267A mutant favoring the former and
 Sae2-S267E the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>).
 Consequently, although Sae2-S267E mutant cells can repair S-phase-induced DSBs
 (such as are generated by camptothecin) that are mainly repaired by HR, they
 are mildly hypersensitive to IR due to deregulated ssDNA formation that
 appears to impair NHEJ in G<sub>1</sub>. To determine whether a similar
 phenomenon occurs in human cells, we siRNA-depleted endogenous CtIP from cells
 stably expressing siRNA-resistant wild-type or Thr-847 mutated GFP-CtIP
 derivatives and then assessed cell survival after IR. Strikingly, and in
 contrast to the survival data after camptothecin exposure
 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>), both CtIP
 T847A and CtIP-T847E mutant cells were mildly hypersensitive to IR, similar to
 cells lacking CtIP (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 5<italic>A</italic></xref>). To test the idea that hypersensitivity of CtIP-T847E
 cells might reflect impaired NHEJ, we assessed the ability of these and the
 other cells to randomly integrate plasmid DNA into their genome, a process
 that is mediated by NHEJ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>). As shown in
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref>, CtIP-T847E
 cells but not CtIP T847A or CtIP-depleted cells were mildly but significantly
 defective in this process, thus suggesting that the IR hypersensitivity of
 CtIP-T847E cells at least partly reflected impaired NHEJ.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Effects of CtIP mutations on DNA repair and chromosome integrity.</bold>
 <italic>A</italic>, the survival of U2OS cells expressing GFP-CtIP fusions after
 treatment with IR. Averages and standard deviations (<italic>error bars</italic>) of
 three independent experiments are shown. <italic>B</italic>, the effects of CtIP
 mutations on NHEJ efficiency as measured by random plasmid integration.
 Frequencies of integration were normalized to the values of wild-type
 GFP-CtIP, set as 100%. Averages and standard deviations (<italic>error bars</italic>)
 of three independent experiments are shown. <italic>C</italic>, the percentage of
 mitoses showing 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5 GCRs in cells expressing GFP-CtIP variants
 either untreated (<italic>left</italic>) or treated with 2 Gy of IR (<italic>right</italic>).
 At least 100 mitoses were analyzed per experiment. <italic>Error bars</italic>,
 standard deviations. <italic>D</italic>, the percentage of each GCR type in the cells
 analyzed in <italic>C</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0190972190005"/></fig></p><p>As a complementary approach to assess the effects of CtIP Thr-847
 mutations, we examined the cell lines for radiation-induced GCRs. These
 studies revealed that 2 Gy of irradiation increased GCR formation in cells
 expressing wild-type CtIP, with around 50% of ensuing mitoses presenting at
 least one GCR event (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). Furthermore, somewhat more pronounced increases in
 GCR formation were observed in cells depleted of CtIP (GFP control) or
 expressing the CtIP mutants. Moreover, especially for cells expressing
 CtIP-T847A or the GFP control, there was an increase in the proportion of
 mitoses exhibiting multiple GCR events
 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). In addition
 to determining overall GCR frequencies in the various cell lines, we also
 analyzed the data qualitatively by classifying GCRs into the following
 categories (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>
 and supplemental Fig. 4): “two-end fusions” in which both arms of
 two chromosomes are fused; “one-end fusions” in which only one
 chromosomal arm of two chromosomes is fused (both one-end and two-end fusions
 probably result from NHEJ); “arms of different length” in which
 chromosome arms exhibit different lengths, probably due to insertions,
 deletions, or non-reciprocal exchanges; “chromatid breaks” in
 which one of the chromatids is broken but is held together by cohesion with
 its sister chromatid; and “complex GCRs” in which two or more
 chromosomes have suffered reciprocal exchanges, probably through aberrant HR.
 Strikingly, when compared with cells expressing wild-type CtIP, those
 expressing CtIP-T847E displayed an increased prevalence of complex GCRs and a
 reduction of fusions, which would be in agreement with increased aberrant HR
 and decreased NHEJ in the CtIP-T847E mutant
 (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>). By
 contrast, cells expressing CtIP-T847A displayed the opposite pattern,
 exhibiting decreased complex GCRs and increased fusions, which would be
 consistent with increased NHEJ and reduced HR in this context (this pattern
 was similar to that of control cells expressing GFP alone;
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic></xref>).
 Collectively, these data therefore support a model in which CDK-mediated
 phosphorylation of CtIP Thr-847 controls DSB resection and thereby influences
 choice between the NHEJ and HR pathways of DSB repair.</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We have investigated the mechanisms by which human cells control DNA end
 resection during the cell cycle. Collectively, our data provide strong support
 for a model in which resection is controlled by CDK-mediated modification of
 CtIP on Thr-847 in a manner that is analogous to CDK targeting of a related
 consensus site (Ser-267) on the budding yeast CtIP counterpart, Sae2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). In light of these findings
 and the fact that analogous CDK target sites are found in almost all
 eukaryotic Sae2/CtIP counterparts, we speculate that this mode of resection
 control represents a widespread mechanism to regulate DSB repair during the
 cell cycle.</p><p><italic>Modification of CtIP Thr-847 Modulates DNA Resection during the Cell
 Cycle</italic>—Our results reveal that CtIP Thr-847 is needed for effective
 ssDNA generation, RPA recruitment, and RPA phosphorylation in response to
 camptothecin, laser-induced DNA damage, or ionizing radiation. Furthermore, we
 have established that mutating Thr-847 to Glu to mimic constitutive
 phosphorylation allows some resection in the absence of CDK activity, although
 this is not as effective as resection in S or G<sub>2</sub> cells. Although it
 is possible that the T847E mutation does not fully mimic phosphorylation on
 this site, we think that this is unlikely because in S/G<sub>2</sub> cells,
 the CtIP-T847E mutant promoted resection at least as well as wild-type CtIP.
 Instead, we favor a model (similar that to proposed for yeast Sae2 (Ref.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>)) in which CDK targeting of
 CtIP Thr-847 contributes to DSB resection but in which additional CDK targets,
 on other proteins or on CtIP itself, are needed for optimal resection. In this
 regard, we note that CtIP is CDK-phosphorylated on Ser-327 to promote
 interactions with BRCA1, a protein implicated in events occurring at resected
 DSBs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). Furthermore,
 although we have generated phospho-specific antisera against peptides
 containing CtIP Thr-847 and they recognize CtIP only when CDKs are active,
 phospho-reactivity on Western blots was not abolished when CtIP was mutated on
 Thr-847 or was doubly mutated on Ser-327 and Thr-847 (data not shown).
 Although these results have unfortunately precluded the use of such antibodies
 to study Thr-847 phosphorylation by Western blot analyses, they nevertheless
 point to there being other CDK-dependent sites on CtIP that might potentially
 control its function.</p><p><italic>Effects of Phosphorylation on CtIP Activity</italic>—How
 phosphorylation of CtIP modulates resection is still not well understood. The
 CtIP counterpart in budding yeast, Sae2, has been shown to be an endonuclease
 that acts cooperatively with the Mre11-Rad50-Xrs2 (MRX) complex <italic>in
 vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>). Furthermore,
 combining CtIP with human Mre11 and Rad50 was shown to produce an endonuclease
 activity that neither component exhibited alone, although it is not yet known
 whether CtIP stimulates Mre11 or <italic>vice versa</italic> or both
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). Notably, the <italic>in
 vitro</italic> results for the yeast and human proteins were obtained in the
 absence of any known protein phosphorylation events, suggesting that
 phosphorylation of Sae2/CtIP is not absolutely required for its observed
 biochemical functions. Nevertheless, it is established that both CDK-dependent
 and checkpoint-dependent phosphorylations are required for activation of
 Sae2/CtIP <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>). Although it is not yet
 clear why there are these apparent differences between the <italic>in vivo</italic>
 and <italic>in vitro</italic> data, it is possible that, within the cell, Sae2/MRX and
 CtIP/MRN (Mre11-Rad50-Nbs1) operate in a more stringent environment and/or do
 so in the presence of inhibitory proteins such that their resection functions
 are only exhibited upon activating phosphorylations. Alternatively, or in
 addition, it is possible that these modifications promote interactions with
 additional factors that might act as positive regulators of DNA resection in
 S/G<sub>2</sub>. In this regard, it is noteworthy that the interaction between
 CtIP and BRCA1 is controlled by CDK-mediated phosphorylation of CtIP Ser-327
 and that such an interaction is required for CtIP recruitment to repair
 centers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>). Although this
 suggests that CDK-mediated Thr-847 phosphorylation might prime CtIP for
 further phosphorylation on Ser-327, thus allowing CtIP recruitment to repair
 foci, several lines of evidence argue against this. First, CtIP T847A is
 recruited to sites of DNA damage with similar kinetics to those of wild-type
 CtIP or the T847E mutant (supplemental Fig. 2). Second, we have found that the
 T847A mutant is still phosphorylated on Ser-327 and that it is still able to
 interact with BRCA1 (supplemental Fig. 5). Notably, we have also found that
 Thr-847 phosphorylation does not control the interaction between CtIP and MRN
 (supplemental Fig. 5) despite the fact that this interaction occurs through
 interactions that involve the CtIP C-terminal region
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>). Hence, we propose that
 CDK activity is likely to control CtIP activity in at least two ways: one
 operating through Thr-847 that affects CtIP function by a mechanism that also
 operates in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (via Sae2 Ser-267) and a second, higher
 eukaryote-specific mechanism that operates through BRCA1 interacting with CtIP
 phosphorylated on Ser-327. Notably, this latter mechanism seems to play a
 crucial role in bringing about CtIP recruitment to DNA damage sites
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>), a mechanism that does
 not appear to exist in budding yeast, where it has been shown that Sae2 is
 always chromatin-bound and can localize to sites of DNA damage in both
 G<sub>1</sub> and S/G<sub>2</sub> independently of any factors tested so far
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>).</p><p><italic>Deregulated DNA End Resection Leads to DNA Damage
 Hypersensitivity</italic>—Irrespective of the precise mechanisms at play,
 what seems clear is that CDK targeting of CtIP/Sae2 is used to restrict
 resection in phases of the cell cycle when NHEJ is favored and activate
 resection in S and G<sub>2</sub>, when HR is employed. Indeed, we have shown
 that lack of CtIP or an inability to activate CtIP by CDK-mediated
 phosphorylation on Thr-847 causes hypersensitivity toward DSB-generating
 agents, at least partly due to defective HR in S/G<sub>2</sub>. This is
 especially relevant when DNA DSBs are generated by agents such as camptothecin
 in S-phase, when HR is required for DNA replication restart. Conversely, our
 data imply that artificial activation of CtIP by mimicking constitutive
 phosphorylation of Thr-847 (which allows some DNA resection in the absence of
 CDK activity) can also result in deleterious consequences and DNA damage
 hypersensitivity. Therefore, the fine regulation of DNA resection during the
 cell cycle appears to be critical to ensure that the cell uses the DSB repair
 pathway most appropriate to its cell cycle status. Notably, we have found that
 both impaired resection and constitutive activation of resection (by blocking
 or mimicking constitutive phosphorylation of CtIP Thr-847, respectively) lead
 to increased sensitivity to DNA-damaging agents and increased formation of
 GCRs, although by differing mechanisms. Thus, although hampering resection in
 S/G<sub>2</sub> leads to increased chromosomal fusions, probably due to
 increased NHEJ, hyperactivation of resection results in DSBs being processed
 at inappropriate times. Such aberrantly processed ends can then engage in
 futile HR cycles, resulting in complex GCRs and causing cell mortality,
 probably by mitotic catastrophe.</p><p>It is noteworthy that not only CtIP mutations but also reduced CtIP levels
 and CtIP overexpression have been reported in various cancer cell lines
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>)
 and that reduced CtIP levels lead to tumor formation in mouse models
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>). Although these effects
 could reflect transcriptional functions for CtIP
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>), it is tempting to
 speculate that they arise due to deregulated DSB resection, thus causing
 mutations and GCRs that foster tumor formation. For instance, overexpression
 of CtIP, especially in G<sub>1</sub> when CtIP levels are normally low, might
 hyperactivate the DNA resection machinery, thus causing spurious HR or leading
 to large deletions at sites of NHEJ. On the other hand, CtIP-inactivating
 mutations or CtIP haplo-insufficiency could resemble what we have observed
 with CtIP T847A mutants, in which GCRs apparently arise due to reduced HR. If
 deregulated DSB resection is found in certain cancer cells, this raises the
 exciting prospect that such defects could be exploited by intelligent
 tailoring of existing DNA-damaging chemotherapies and/or by using compounds
 that selectively target specific DNA repair pathways.</p><p><italic>Conserved Mechanisms for Regulating DSB Processing by CtIP/Sae2
 Orthologues</italic>—The data we have obtained through mutating CtIP Thr-847
 have a strong resonance with results derived through analyzing the effects of
 mutating the analogous motif of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Sae2
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>). It therefore seems that
 this aspect of CDK-mediated control of DSB processing and repair has been
 highly conserved throughout evolution. As analogous CDK target sites are
 present in almost all eukaryotic counterparts of Sae2/CtIP
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>),
 it is tempting to speculate that similar control mechanisms operate in diverse
 eukaryotes to modulate DSB repair pathway choice during the cell cycle.
 Strikingly, the only Sae2/CtIP homologue known that lacks a site analogous to
 Thr-847 of human CtIP is <italic>S. pombe</italic> Ctp1
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). Nevertheless, <italic>S.
 pombe</italic> Ctp1 is phosphorylated on other sites by CDK, and its abundance is
 strongly regulated during the cell cycle at the transcriptional level,
 suggesting that these mechanisms serve to control its activity
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>). Contrary to <italic>S.
 cerevisiae</italic> Sae2, which is constitutively expressed in all phases of the
 cell cycle, human CtIP is also regulated at the transcriptional level, its
 amounts being highest in S and G<sub>2</sub>. It is therefore tempting to
 speculate that human CtIP combines characteristics exhibited by both <italic>S.
 cerevisiae</italic> Sae2 and <italic>S. pombe</italic> Ctp1. Furthermore, it is noteworthy
 that the functions of CtIP-interacting proteins such as BRCA1, which promotes
 CtIP recruitment to sites of DNA damage, and retinoblastoma protein 1 (RB),
 which controls the G<sub>1</sub>/S transition, are also cell cycle-regulated
 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>).
 This suggests that multiple layers of regulation combine to fine-tune CtIP
 activity during the cell cycle, perhaps to provide even more stringent control
 of DSB resection than is evident in the yeast systems.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplemental Data]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="M808906200_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="M808906200_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Andreas Meier for providing the U2OS-GFP strain and Julia Coates,
 Jeanine Harrigan, Andreas Meier, Sophie Polo, Yaron Galanty, and Alessandro
 Sartori for technical advice. We also thank J. Harrigan and K. Dry for
 critical reading of the manuscript. CtIP and CtIP phospho-Ser-327 antibodies
 were kindly provided by R. Baer (Columbia University) and X. Yu (University of
 Michigan Medical School).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shrivastav, M., De Haro, L. P., and Nickoloff, J. A.
 (<year>2008</year>) <source>Cell Res.</source>
 <volume>18</volume> <fpage>134</fpage>-147<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18157161</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sonoda, E., Hochegger, H., Saberi, A., Taniguchi, Y., and Takeda,
 S. (<year>2006</year>) <source>DNA Repair</source>
 <volume>5</volume>
 <fpage>1021</fpage>-1029<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807135</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lieber, M. R. (<year>2008</year>) <source>J. Biol.
 Chem.</source> <volume>283</volume>
 <fpage>1</fpage>-5<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17999957</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">West, S. C. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>4</volume>
 <fpage>435</fpage>-445<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778123</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Aylon, Y., Liefshitz, B., and Kupiec, M. (<year>2004</year>)
 <source>EMBO J.</source> <volume>23</volume>
 <fpage>4868</fpage>-4875<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15549137</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Ira, G., Pellicioli, A., Balijja, A., Wang, X., Fiorani, S.,
 Carotenuto, W., Liberi, G., Bressan, D., Wan, L., Hollingsworth, N. M., Haber,
 J. E., and Foiani, M. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Nature</source>
 <volume>431</volume>
 <fpage>1011</fpage>-1017<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496928</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Jazayeri, A., Falck, J., Lukas, C., Bartek, J., Smith, G. M.,
 Lukas, J., and Jackson, S. P. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nat. Cell
 Biol.</source> <volume>8</volume>
 <fpage>37</fpage>-45<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16327781</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Huertas, P., Cortés-Ledesma, F., Sartori, A. A., Aguilera,
 A., and Jackson, S. P. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Nature</source>
 <volume>455</volume>
 <fpage>689</fpage>-692<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18716619</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Limbo, O., Chahwan, C., Yamada, Y., de Bruin, R. A., Wittenberg,
 C., and Russell, P. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source>
 <volume>28</volume> <fpage>134</fpage>-146<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17936710</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Penkner, A., Portik-Dobos, Z., Tang, L., Schnabel, R., Novatchkova,
 M., Jantsch, V., and Loidl, J. (<year>2007</year>) <source>EMBO
 J.</source> <volume>26</volume>
 <fpage>5071</fpage>-5082<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18007596</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sartori, A. A., Lukas, C., Coates, J., Mistrik, M., Fu, S., Bartek,
 J., Baer, R., Lukas, J., and Jackson, S. P. (<year>2007</year>)
 <source>Nature</source> <volume>450</volume>
 <fpage>509</fpage>-514<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17965729</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Uanschou, C., Siwiec, T., Pedrosa-Harand, A., Kerzendorfer, C.,
 Sanchez-Moran, E., Novatchkova, M., Akimcheva, S., Woglar, A., Klein, F., and
 Schlogelhofer, P. (<year>2007</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source>
 <volume>26</volume>
 <fpage>5061</fpage>-5070<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18007598</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Chapman, J. R., and Jackson, S. P. (<year>2008</year>)
 <source>EMBO Rep.</source> <volume>9</volume>
 <fpage>795</fpage>-801<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18583988</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Stucki, M., Clapperton, J. A., Mohammad, D., Yaffe, M. B., Smerdon,
 S. J., and Jackson, S. P. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Cell</source>
 <volume>123</volume>
 <fpage>1213</fpage>-1226<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16377563</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Shao, R. G., Cao, C. X., Zhang, H., Kohn, K. W., Wold, M. S., and
 Pommier, Y. (<year>1999</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source>
 <volume>18</volume>
 <fpage>1397</fpage>-1406<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10064605</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Sakasai, R., Shinohe, K., Ichijima, Y., Okita, N., Shibata, A.,
 Asahina, K., and Teraoka, H. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Genes
 Cells</source> <volume>11</volume>
 <fpage>237</fpage>-246<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16483312</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Cruet-Hennequart, S., Glynn, M. T., Murillo, L. S., Coyne, S., and
 Carty, M. P. (<year>2008</year>) <source>DNA Repair</source>
 <volume>7</volume> <fpage>582</fpage>-596<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18289945</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Binz, S. K., Sheehan, A. M., and Wold, M. S. (<year>2004</year>)
 <source>DNA Repair</source> <volume>3</volume>
 <fpage>1015</fpage>-1024<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15279788</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wu, Xiaoming, Yang, Zhengguan, Liu, Yiyong, Zou, Yue
 (<year>2005</year>) <source>Biochem. J.</source>
 <volume>391</volume>
 <fpage>473</fpage>-480<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15929725</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Harrington, J., Chih-lin, H., Gerton, J., Bosma, G., and Lieber, M.
 R. (<year>1992</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
 <volume>12</volume>
 <fpage>4758</fpage>-4768<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1406659</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <label>21</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Yu, X., and Chen, J. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Mol. Cell.
 Biol.</source> <volume>24</volume>
 <fpage>9478</fpage>-9486<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485915</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <label>22</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lengsfeld, B. M., Rattray, A. J., Bhaskara, V., Ghirlando, R., and
 Paull, T. T. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source>
 <volume>28</volume> <fpage>638</fpage>-651<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042458</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <label>23</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Baroni, E., Viscardi, V., Cartagena-Lirola, H., Lucchini, G., and
 Longhese, M. P. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
 <volume>24</volume>
 <fpage>4151</fpage>-4165<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121837</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <label>24</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Kim, H.-S., Vijayakumar, S., Reger, M., Harrison, J. C., Haber, J.
 E., Weil, C. F., and Petrini, J. H. J. (<year>2008</year>)
 <source>Genetics</source> <volume>178</volume>
 <fpage>711</fpage>-723<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18245357</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <label>25</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Lisby, M., Barlow, J. H., Burgess, R. C., and Rothstein, R.
 (<year>2004</year>) <source>Cell</source>
 <volume>118</volume>
 <fpage>699</fpage>-713<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15369670</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <label>26</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Liu, F., and Lee, W.-H. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Mol. Cell.
 Biol.</source> <volume>26</volume>
 <fpage>3124</fpage>-3134<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581787</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1d278b0N0x43be5f8">
        <label>27</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Xu, J., Lv, S., Qin, Y., Shu, F., Xu, Y., Chen, J., Xu, B., Sun,
 X., and Wu, J. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Biochim. Biophys.
 Acta</source> <volume>1770</volume>
 <fpage>273</fpage>-278<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17112672</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <label>28</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wong, A. K., Ormonde, P. A., Pero, R., Chen, Y., Lian, L., Salada,
 G., Berry, S., Lawrence, Q., Dayananth, P., Ha, P., Tavtigian, S. V., Teng, D.
 H., and Bartel, P. L. (<year>1998</year>) <source>Oncogene</source>
 <volume>17</volume>
 <fpage>2279</fpage>-2285<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811458</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <label>29</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Vilkki, S., Launonen, V., Karhu, A., Sistonen, P., Vastrik, I., and
 Aaltonen, L. A. (<year>2002</year>) <source>J. Med. Genet.</source>
 <volume>39</volume> <fpage>785</fpage>-789<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414815</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <label>30</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Chen, P.-L., Liu, F., Cai, S., Lin, X., Li, A., Chen, Y., Gu, B.,
 Lee, E. Y.-H. L., and Lee, W.-H. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Mol. Cell.
 Biol.</source> <volume>25</volume>
 <fpage>3535</fpage>-3542<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831459</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <label>31</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Wu, G., and Lee, W.-H. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Cell
 Cycle</source> <volume>5</volume>
 <fpage>1592</fpage>-1596<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16880746</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <label>32</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Akamatsu, Y., Murayama, Y., Yamada, T., Nakazaki, T., Tsutsui, Y.,
 Ohta, K., and Iwasaki, H. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Mol. Cell.
 Biol.</source> <volume>28</volume>
 <fpage>3639</fpage>-3651<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378696</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <label>33</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Fusco, C., Reymond, A., and Zervos, A. S. (<year>1998</year>)
 <source>Genomics</source> <volume>51</volume>
 <fpage>351</fpage>-358<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9721205</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="N0x1d278b0N0x3d4d8d0">
        <label>34</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Yu, X., Wu, L. C., Bowcock, A. M., Aronheim, A., and Baer, R.
 (<year>1998</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>273</volume>
 <fpage>25338</fpage>-25392</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <label>35</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">Chen, L., Nievera, C. J., Lee, A. Y.-L., and Wu, X.
 (<year>2008</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
 <volume>283</volume>
 <fpage>7713</fpage>-7720<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171670</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn4">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>The abbreviations used are: DSB, double strand break; NHEJ, non-homologous
 end joining; HR, homologous recombination; CDK, cyclin-dependent kinase;
 siRNA, small interfering RNA; GFP, green fluorescent protein; DMSO, dimethyl
 sulfoxide; GST, glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase; PBS, phosphate-buffered
 saline; IR, ionizing radiation; Gy, grays; GCR, gross chromosomal
 rearrangement; ssDNA, single-stranded DNA.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>