<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:35:18Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2759337" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2759337</identifier><datestamp>2009-10-09</datestamp><setSpec>brain</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">brainj</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">brain</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Brain</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-8950</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2156</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2759337</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2759337</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2759337</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19651702</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awp198</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">awp198</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Genes for hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies: a genotype–phenotype correlation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rotthier</surname>
            <given-names>Annelies</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baets</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vriendt</surname>
            <given-names>Els De</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jacobs</surname>
            <given-names>An</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
            <given-names>Michaela</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lévy</surname>
            <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bonello-Palot</surname>
            <given-names>Nathalie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kilic</surname>
            <given-names>Sara Sebnem</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF8">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Weis</surname>
            <given-names>Joachim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF9">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nascimento</surname>
            <given-names>Andrés</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF10">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Swinkels</surname>
            <given-names>Marielle</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF11">
            <sup>11</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kruyt</surname>
            <given-names>Moyo C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF12">
            <sup>12</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jordanova</surname>
            <given-names>Albena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Timmerman</surname>
            <given-names>Vincent</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="AFF1">1 Peripheral Neuropathy Group, VIB Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Antwerp, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff>
      <aff id="AFF2">2 Neurogenetics Laboratory, Institute Born-Bunge, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff>
      <aff id="AFF3">3 Neurogenetics Group, VIB Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Antwerp, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff>
      <aff id="AFF4">4 Division of Neurology, University Hospital Antwerp, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff>
      <aff id="AFF5">5 Institute of Human Genetics and Division of Endocrinology and Nuclear Medicine, Medical University of Graz, Graz, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="AFF6">6 AP-HM, Département de Génétique Médicale, Laboratoire de Génétique Moléculaire, Hôpital d’enfants de la Timone, Marseille, France</aff>
      <aff id="AFF7">7 Inserm UMR_S 910: Génétique Médicale et Génomique Fonctionnelle, Faculté de Médecine de Marseille, Université de la Méditerranée, Marseille, France</aff>
      <aff id="AFF8">8 Department of Paediatric Immunology, Uludağ University School of Medicine, Bursa, Turkey</aff>
      <aff id="AFF9">9 Institute of Neuropathology, Medical Faculty, RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="AFF10">10 Neuromuscular Unit, Sant Joan de Deu Hospital, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
      <aff id="AFF11">11 Department of Medical Genetics, University Medical Center, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff>
      <aff id="AFF12">12 Department of Orthopaedics, University Medical Center, Utrecht, The Netherlands</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="FN1">
          <p>* These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp>Correspondence to: Prof. Dr Vincent Timmerman, PhD, Peripheral Neuropathy Group, VIB - Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Antwerp, Universiteitsplein 1, B-2610 Antwerpen, Belgium E-mail: <email>vincent.timmerman@molgen.vib-ua.be</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>132</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>2699</fpage>
      <lpage>2711</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2009 The Author(s). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Brain.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies (HSAN) are clinically and genetically heterogeneous disorders characterized by axonal atrophy and degeneration, exclusively or predominantly affecting the sensory and autonomic neurons. So far, disease-associated mutations have been identified in seven genes: two genes for autosomal dominant <italic>(SPTLC1</italic> and <italic>RAB7</italic>) and five genes for autosomal recessive forms of HSAN (<italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic>, <italic>NTRK1</italic>, <italic>NGFB</italic>, <italic>CCT5</italic> and <italic>IKBKAP</italic>). We performed a systematic mutation screening of the coding sequences of six of these genes on a cohort of 100 familial and isolated patients diagnosed with HSAN. In addition, we screened the functional candidate gene <italic>NGFR (p75/NTR)</italic> encoding the nerve growth factor receptor. We identified disease-causing mutations in <italic>SPTLC1, RAB7, WNK1/HSN2</italic> and <italic>NTRK1</italic> in 19 patients, of which three mutations have not previously been reported. The phenotypes associated with mutations in <italic>NTRK1</italic> and <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> typically consisted of congenital insensitivity to pain and anhidrosis, and early-onset ulcero-mutilating sensory neuropathy, respectively. <italic>RAB7</italic> mutations were only found in patients with a Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 2B (CMT2B) phenotype, an axonal sensory-motor neuropathy with pronounced ulcero-mutilations. In <italic>SPTLC1</italic>, we detected a novel mutation (S331F) corresponding to a previously unknown severe and early-onset HSAN phenotype. No mutations were found in <italic>NGFB</italic>, <italic>CCT5</italic> and <italic>NGFR</italic>. Overall disease-associated mutations were found in 19% of the studied patient group, suggesting that additional genes are associated with HSAN. Our genotype–phenotype correlation study broadens the spectrum of HSAN and provides additional insights for molecular and clinical diagnosis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>HSAN</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>SPTLC1</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>RAB7</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>NTRK1</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies (HSAN) are a clinically and genetically heterogeneous group of inherited peripheral neuropathies, primarily affecting the peripheral sensory and autonomic neurons (Dyck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1993</xref>). Patients usually exhibit prominent distal sensory loss with manifest insensitivity to pain in some. The prominent distal sensory loss frequently leads to chronic ulcerations in feet and hands, sometimes resulting in severe complications such as extensive soft tissue infections, osteomyelitis necessitating amputations of toes and fingers or, in rare instances, even of more proximal parts of the extremities (Dyck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1993</xref>). Autonomic dysfunction, such as anhidrosis, fever, blood pressure fluctuations and gastro-intestinal disturbances are present in some patients. Electrophysiologically, axonal nerve damage of the sensory neurons is often found, but additional demyelination may also be present (Auer-Grumbach <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>HSAN can be transmitted as an autosomal dominant (AD) or autosomal recessive (AR) trait. Isolated patients have also been described (Dyck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1993</xref>; Auer-Grumbach, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">2004</xref>). The AD types of HSAN usually present in the second or third decade of life with marked sensory involvement and minimal autonomic and variable motor involvement, while AR HSAN present either as congenital syndromes with striking sensory and autonomic abnormalities or as almost pure autonomic disorders (Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2006<italic>a</italic></xref>).</p>
      <p>A classification of the hereditary sensory neuropathies into types HSAN I–V (Dyck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1993</xref>) was made based on age at onset, inheritance pattern and additional features. Although the clinical classification of these HSAN types is based on a small number of individuals, it still stands after the molecular characterization of the subtypes in recent years. There is variable motor involvement in the AD form of HSAN, making the distinction with hereditary motor and sensory neuropathies (HMSN) or Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease (CMT) difficult. In CMT2B, sensory loss and the associated ulcerations are such prominent phenotypic features that inclusion within the HSAN-spectrum is justified (Vance <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">1996</xref>; Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2006<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, due to the concomitant motor involvement with distal muscle atrophy and weakness, this phenotype was originally classified as HMSN (Kwon <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">1995</xref>).</p>
      <p>So far, seven genes have been identified for the different types of HSAN (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molgen.ua.ac.be/CMTMutations/">http://www.molgen.ua.ac.be/CMTMutations/</ext-link>). Two genes have been associated with AD HSAN: missense mutations in serine palmitoyltransferase long chain subunit 1 (<italic>SPTLC1</italic>) are found in families and individuals with HSAN type I, an adult-onset sensory neuropathy (Bejaoui <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2001</xref>; Dawkins <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2001</xref>). Mutations in the small GPTase late endosomal protein <italic>RAB7</italic>, cause CMT2B (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>; Meggouh <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">2006</xref>). Mutations in the <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> gene [protein kinase with-no-lysine(K)-1/hereditary sensory neuropathy type 2] cause AR HSAN type II, an early-onset ulcero-mutilating sensory neuropathy (Lafreniere <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2004</xref>). HSAN type III, also known as Familial Dysautonomia or Riley–Day syndrome, presents with typical prominent autonomic manifestations early in life and is caused by mutations in the inhibitor of kappa-light polypeptide gene enhancer in B cells, kinase complex associated protein (<italic>IKBKAP</italic>) (Slaugenhaupt <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">2001</xref>). Mutations in neurotrophic tyrosine kinase, receptor type 1 (<italic>NTRK1</italic>) are reported in families with congenital insensitivity to pain, anhidrosis and mental retardation (CIPA or HSAN type IV) (Indo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">1996</xref>). HSAN type V, a phenotype closely related to CIPA but with normal mental development and less pronounced anhidrosis, can be caused by mutations in nerve growth factor beta (<italic>NGFB</italic>) (Einarsdottir <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2004</xref>) but also by <italic>NTRK1</italic>-mutations (Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2001</xref>; Einarsdottir <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2004</xref>). Apart from these six HSAN subtypes other forms with distinct additional features exist, e.g. HSAN with gastroesophageal reflux and cough (Kok <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">2003</xref>) and HSAN with spastic paraplegia (Bouhouche <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>). Recently, the gene for this last form has been identified as cytosolic chaperonin-containing <italic>t</italic>-complex peptide-1 <italic>(CCT5)</italic> (Bouhouche <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2006<italic>a</italic></xref>). The identification of causative genes for the HSAN forms in recent years has provided preliminary insights in the pathogenesis of these rare neuropathies although the fundamental underlying pathomechanisms still remain to be unveiled (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this study, we investigated a cohort of 100 familial and isolated patients who had a clinical diagnosis compatible with any of the subtypes of HSAN listed above, and we determined the contribution of mutations in the known genes associated to the distinct phenotypes. <italic>IKBKAP</italic> was not screened since our cohort did not contain patients with familial dysautonomia. The cohort included 16 index patients of families that have previously been reported in manuscripts describing novel genes and related phenotypes. We broadened the screening of the individual genes to non-associated phenotypes in order to establish potential new genotype–phenotype correlations. Furthermore, we performed the first large-scale mutation screening of <italic>WNK1</italic> and <italic>CCT5</italic>. Additionally, we screened the functional candidate gene <italic>NGFR</italic> (<italic>p75/NTR</italic>) because of its importance in development and function of sensory neurons (Lee <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">1992</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="subjects|methods">
      <title>Patients and Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Selection criteria</title>
        <p>For this study, we selected a group of 100 individuals from our patient database. These were individuals presenting with a clinical phenotype compatible with any of the HSAN subforms described earlier (Dyck, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1993</xref>; Auer-Grumbach <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref>). The majority of patients presented with progressive distal sensory loss, often associated with one or several of the following additional features: skin changes (e.g. hyperkeratosis, ulcerations), spontaneous fractures, amputations and autonomic features. Because variable motor involvement under the form of distal muscle wasting and weakness can be present in some subtypes of sensory neuropathies, we also included a group of patients diagnosed with CMT2B, a variant of axonal motor and sensory neuropathy (HMSN II), with prominent ulcero-mutilations (Vance <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">1996</xref>; Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2006<italic>a</italic></xref>). To avoid inclusion of classic axonal CMT variants unrelated to the HSAN spectrum, we only included patients with motor and sensory neuropathies if their clinical presentation was complicated by the development of ulcerations. Overall, the cohort in this study could be described as a group of hereditary ulcero-mutilating and sensory neuropathies. Autonomic symptoms were only seen in patients who also presented with sensory abnormalities. Our cohort did not contain patients with predominant or pure dysautonomia, the hallmark feature of HSAN type III or Riley–Day syndrome. Diagnosis was based on clinical presentation, complemented with nerve conduction velocity (NCV) measurements and EMG. No strict electrophysiological selection criteria were applied to our cohort, given the broad range of electrophysiological features associated with the various HSAN phenotypes. Typically, a predominantly sensory axonal neuropathy was found, which was often more severe in the lower limbs. Occasional electrophysiological signs of demyelination can also be found in HSAN. Electrophysiological abnormalities in motor nerves such as reduced amplitudes of compound muscle action potentials and slightly reduced motor NCV can be found, illustrating the overlap between HSAN and HMSN. In CIPA patients, nerve conduction studies can be within normal range (Shatzky <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">2000</xref>; Auer-Grumbach <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2003</xref>; Axelrod and Gold-von Simson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2007</xref>). In several patients, nerve and skin biopsies were performed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="subjects">
        <title>Patient cohort</title>
        <p>The cohort consisted of 100 index patients who were referred to our laboratory for molecular genetic testing in the context of HSAN. Genomic DNA samples were provided through Neurologic and Paediatric Departments and Neuromuscular Centres worldwide. The majority of samples were of European origin. In 43 patients, autonomic features were noted, 44 had a pure sensory neuropathy and the remaining 13 were diagnosed as sensory-motor neuropathy with ulcero-mutilations. In two patients, the HSAN phenotype presented with an associated spastic paraplegia. For 21 out of 100 index patients, a dominant inheritance pattern, based on a parent to child transmission, could be determined. For eight index patients, a recessive inheritance pattern characterized by the presence of affected siblings in the pedigree could be determined. Twenty-four patients were referred as ‘isolated’ since they did not have a familial history of neuropathy in the first- and second-degree relatives. No family history was available for the remaining 47 patients. In five index patients, there was a clear indication of consanguinity of the parents. For 44 patients, detailed information about the age at onset was available; in nine patients, first symptoms occurred in the first year of life, in 11 patients the disease started in the first decade and in 12 patients in the second decade. In the remaining 12 patients, onset was after the age of 20 years. In 35 patients, ulcerations were present and 17 out of them displayed additional complications such as osteomyelitis or amputations. Detailed electrophysiological data were available for 37 patients, the remaining patients had an electrophysiological evaluation by their referring physician but detailed information was not available. In 17 patients, a nerve biopsy or a combined sural nerve/muscle biopsy was performed showing abnormalities compatible with a diagnosis of HSAN. All referring clinicians were neurologists, orthopaedic surgeons or paediatricians active in the field of rare neuromuscular diseases and well acquainted with the clinical presentation of HSAN and related phenotypes. The referring clinicians obtained informed consent from all patients or their legal representatives prior to enrolment in this study.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Molecular genetic analysis</title>
        <p>All DNA samples were amplified using the whole genome amplification kit ‘GenomiPhi V2 DNA Amplication Kit’ (GE Healthcare, Waukesha, USA). The protocol was performed according to the manufacturer's instruction.</p>
        <p>The coding regions and exon–intron boundaries up to 100 bp up- and downstream of the exons of <italic>SPTLC1, RAB7, WNK1/HSN2, NTRK1, NGFB</italic>, <italic>CCT5</italic> and <italic>NGFR</italic> were PCR-amplified using primer oligonucleotides designed with the Primer3 and SNPbox software tools (Rozen and Skaletsky, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2000</xref>; Weckx <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">2004</xref>). PCR conditions are available upon request. PCR products were cleaned up using the Exonuclease I-Shrimp Alkaline Phosphatase enzyme (USB, Cleveland, USA). Mutation screening was performed by direct sequencing of the purified PCR fragments using the BigDye® Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, USA). Fragments were separated on an ABI3730xl DNA Analyser (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, USA). The resulting sequences were aligned and analysed with the novoSNP (Weckx <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">2005</xref>) and SeqMan™II (DNASTAR Inc., Madison, USA) programs. The nucleotide numbering of the genes is relative to the ATG translation initiation site with A as +1 of the corresponding cDNA sequences (<italic>SPTLC1</italic>: NM_006415.2; <italic>RAB7</italic>: NM_004637.5; <italic>NTRK1</italic>: NM_002529.3; <italic>NGFB</italic>: NM_002506.2; <italic>CCT5</italic>: NM_012073.3; <italic>NGFR</italic>: NM_002507). The nucleotide numbering of <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> is relative to the first nucleotide of the HSN2-specific exon of <italic>WNK1</italic> (NM_213665.1). Mutations are described according to the latest conventions on the nomenclature of DNA sequence variants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgvs.org/mutnomen">http://www.hgvs.org/mutnomen</ext-link>). Sequence variants were confirmed by repeated PCR on original DNA samples and bidirectional sequencing. Where possible, segregation of the mutation with the disease phenotype was analysed in the family.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genotyping and paternity testing</title>
        <p>Paternity was tested using 15 highly informative short tandem repeats (STRs) distributed throughout the genome (ATA38A05, D1S1646, D1S1653, D1S1360, D2S2256, D3S3037, D4S2382, D4S3240, D7S509, D8S1759, D9S1118, D12S1056, D12S2082, D16S2619 and GATA152H04). STRs were PCR-amplified and PCR fragments were loaded on an ABI3730xl DNA Analyser. Genotypes were analysed using Local Genotype Viewer, a software program developed in-house (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vibgeneticservicefacility.be/">http://www.vibgeneticservicefacility.be/</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Analysis of exon skipping</title>
        <p>Analysis of exon skipping was performed by RT-PCR on mRNA isolated from lymphoblast cell lines of patients CMT-841.01 and CMT-886.01. mRNA was first purified from peripheral blood lymphoblasts using the RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). DNA inactivation was performed using the Turbo DNA free kit (Ambion, Austin, USA) and subsequently analysed for splicing defects by RT-PCR and sequencing using exonic primers located in exons 1 and 5 for patient CMT-886.01 (forward: 5′-CTGCTGGCTTGGCTGATACT-3′, reverse: 5′-CACTGCAGCTTCTGTTCAGG-3′) and exonic primers in exons 12 and 16 for CMT-841.01 (forward: 5′-CCTTGTGCTCAACAAATGTGG-3′, reverse: 5′-AGCCAGCAGCTTGGCAT-3′) (Superscript III First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR; Life Technologies, San Diego, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>In 19 index patients, out of a cohort of 100, pathogenic mutations were found in four HSAN disease associated genes: <italic>SPTLC1, RAB7, NTRK1</italic> and <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic>. These mutations were absent from 600 European control chromosomes. No pathogenic variations could be detected in <italic>NGFB</italic>, <italic>CCT5</italic> and <italic>NGFR</italic>. Clinical and electrophysiological data on these 19 index patients are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical features of HSAN patients with proven mutation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inheritance</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensory loss</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin changes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amputations</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bone complications</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autonomic symptoms</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SPTLC1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ala352Val</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensory abnormalities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-791.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SPTLC1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ser331Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France (Gypsy)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe loss of superficial touch distal LL, insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eschar and ulceration foot</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastro- oesophageal reflux</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PN-626.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diminished L&gt;R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (toes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis in the toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-90.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe in distal LL, position sense conserved, UL less pronounced</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (all toes R foot)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-126.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakness in LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations feet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis and -necrosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-140.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations and foot callus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (toes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis and -necrosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe in LL (toes and feet)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis and -necrosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage gait</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No clinical sensory loss</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple ulceration toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (lower leg L, several toes R)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-195.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ad</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gait disturbances</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations feet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-178.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ile355AsnfsX7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;2y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations hand and feet, poor healing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distally severely reduced for all modalities, LL&gt;UL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations toes and fingers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous fractures LL + Charcot atropathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-260.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gln184X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">inf</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clumsiness hands, osteomyelitis in the foot</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distally severely reduced for all modalities, LL&gt;UL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (fingers and toes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis in the foot</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-451.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pro85ProfsX14 + Gln364SerfsX16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difficulties in hand manipulation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distally severely reduced for all modalities, LL&gt;UL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ulcerations in hands and feet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (progressive spontaneous amputations hands, and LL to knees)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Painless pathologic fractures LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-179.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gly181GlyfsX16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delayed motor milestones?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thickening and ulcerations LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-197.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.359+ 5G&gt;T aberrant splicing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;8m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever of unknown cause</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis, fever episodes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-366.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg761Trp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis, hyperthermia, hypotonia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Painless fracture right calcaneus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis, fever episodes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-826.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.2046+ 3 A&gt;C aberrant splicing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin ulcerations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain and temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperkeratosis, ulcerations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (toes)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis, fever episodes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-841.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arg565Gln</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands (Moroccan origin)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR (cons)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Painless tibial fracture, poor healing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple factures (pelvic bone, upper and lower limbs and foot bones), osteomyelitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PN-1192.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gln626GlnfsX7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands (Moroccan origin)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC (cons)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypotonia, recurrent episodes of fever</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keratodermatitis, xerodermia, selfmutilation of fingers and tongue, necrotizing fasciitis of right hand</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis, fevers</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-886.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.354_359+3 delTCGCCTGAA aberront splicing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN4/CIPA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5m</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever, recurrent infections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity to pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperkeratosis, ulcerations, nail dystrophy, automutilations, neck abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avascular necrosis left talus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anhidrosis</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AA = amino acid; AAO = age at onset (years); SAO = symptoms at onset; ALE = age at last exam (y); cong = congenital; inf = infancy; ad = adulthood; IC = isolated case; AD = autosomal dominant; AR = autosomal recessive; Fam = familial; cons = consanguineous; LL = lower limb; UL = upper limb; + = present; − = absent; unk = unknown; dist = distal; prox = proximal; R = right; L = left.; y = year; m = month.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Clinical features of HSAN patients with proven mutation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene/AA change</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foot deformities</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Walking difficulties</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakness</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrophy</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflexes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental retardation</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nerve conduction studies + electromyography<hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensory</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motor</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SPTLC1</italic> Ala352Val</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild pes cavus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroneal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+, Ach absent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe hypesthesia and spontaneaous lancinating pain LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novel family</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-791.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SPTLC1</italic> Ser331Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pes cavus/equinovarus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (global)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global amyotrophy UL and LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓/−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+, microcephaly</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severe growth retardation, hypotonia, joint hyperlaxity, vocal cord paralysis, bilateral cataract, respiratory involvement with sleep apnea requiring non-invasive ventilation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novel family</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PN-626.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage L&gt;R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal and proximal LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓ (L&lt;R)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brown-Séquard syndrome and quadriplegia due to bleeding cervical spinal angioma, IgA nephropathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-90.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple toe amputations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal in LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroneal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓ to −</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UL normal, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-126.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pes cavus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL&gt;UL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroneal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL, absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-140.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pes cavus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild steppage gait</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal UL and LL, mild</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild in UL and in LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal UL, axonal loss LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal- demyelinating NCVs in UL and LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Leu129Phe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charcot foot deformity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild steppage gait</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL, mild</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL, small foot muscles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↑</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal UL, axonal loss LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal UL, axonal loss LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-186.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toe deformities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage, after amputation, wheelchair dependent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL&gt;UL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peroneal and hands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ to ↑</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-195.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic> Val162Met</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pes cavus, hammer toes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Steppage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-178.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic> Ile355AsnfsX7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Coen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2006</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-260.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic> Gln184X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deformed due to recurrent infections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbed due to amputations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓ to −</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UL normal, LL axonal loss</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Coen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2006</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-451.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>HSN2</italic> Pro85HisfsX14 + Gln364SerfsX16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbed due to amputations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent responses UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sural nerve biopsy: complete loss of myelinated fibers, endoneuronal fibrosis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Coen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2006</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-179.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> Gly181GlyfsX16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henoch-Schönlein vasculitis, pseudotumor cerebri, tooth abscesses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-197.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> c.359+5G&gt;T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin biopsy: innervation of blood vessels and eccrine sweat glands absent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-366.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> Arg761Trp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charcot joint on the right ankle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-826.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> c.2046+3A&gt;C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charcot joint on both ankles and knees</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbed due to Charcot joint</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axonal loss UL/LL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corneal opacities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novel family</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-841.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> Arg565Gln</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charcot deformity right ankle and knee</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Walks with rollator</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">↓ to −</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">− (younger affected sister has learning difficulties)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unk</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sural nerve biopsy: loss of thinly myelinated fibers, partial caudacompression syndrome age 34 yrs. traumatic cataract right eye, hearing loss due to ear drum perforation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Novel family, clinical description previously reported (Kruyt <italic>et al</italic>., 2007)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PN-1192.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> Gln626GlnfsX7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin biopsy: absent innervation of capillaries and sweat glands, loss of myelinated and unmyelinated axons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT-886.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic> c.354_359+ 3 delTCGCCTGAA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delayed motor milestones</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent infections respiratory and gastrointestinal tract due to hypogammaglobulinemia, recurrent hip dislocation left</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Kilic <italic>et al</italic>., 2009)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AA = amino acid; LL = lower limb; UL = upper limb; + = present; − = absent; ↓ = decreased; ↑ = increased; unk = unknown; R = right; L = left; Ach = Achilles tendon.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <sec>
        <title>Mutations in <italic>SPTLC1</italic></title>
        <p>In Patient CMT-791.01, we detected a heterozygous missense mutation (c.992C&gt;T; p.Ser331Phe), which was absent in both healthy parents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>A). Paternity was confirmed in this family, pointing to a <italic>de novo</italic> mutation. In contrast to previously reported HSAN type I patients, the patient displayed a severe phenotype characterized by congenital onset with severe growth and mental retardation, hypotonia and vocal cord paralysis. In Patient CMT-186.05 a missense mutation (c.1055C&gt;T; p.Ala352Val) was identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>B). A third heterozygous missense mutation (c.1160G&gt;C; p.Gly387Ala) was found in Patient CMT-155.01 and her twin sister CMT-155.02 (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">2004</xref>). This mutation was also found in Patient CMT-820.01. However, the healthy mother of this index patient has the same variant in the homozygous state. This finding suggests that the Gly387Ala variation is not pathogenic, but a rare polymorphism. This has recently been confirmed by the analysis of serine palmitoyl transferase (SPT) activity by measuring the incorporation of [U-<sup>13</sup>C]-L-serine in protein extracts from stably transfected HEK293 cells and complementation testing using an SPTLC1-deficient CHO cell line (Hornemann <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2009</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Segregation of p.Ser331Phe and p.Ala352Val missense mutations in SPTLC1 (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) and segregation and cDNA analysis of the p.Arg565Gln missense mutation in <italic>NTRK1</italic> (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>). Segregation analysis of the p.Ser331Phe missense mutation in SPTLC1 reveals that this mutation occurred <italic>de novo</italic> (<bold>A</bold>). Panel B shows the sequence trace file of the p.Ala352Val missense mutation found in SPTLC1 in an isolated Patient CMT-186.05. Segregation of the p.Arg565Gln mutation in NTRK1 is shown in panel C. Two CIPA patients in family CMT-841 (CMT-841.01 and CMT-841.02) had a homozygous Arg565Gln mutation in NTRK1. The healthy siblings of these patients had either the wild-type allele (CMT-841.03 and CMT-841.07) or carried the Arg565Gln mutation in the heterozygous state (CMT-841.04, CMT-841.05 and CMT-841.06). The parents of the patients were first cousins. The mutated nucleotide (c.1697G &gt; A) was the last nucleotide of exon 14, which could affect proper splicing of this exon. cDNA analysis of CMT-841.01 showed the absence of the expected band (528 bp), which was present in the control and confirmed by direct DNA sequencing (<bold>D</bold>). We could not determine the sequence of the three lower bands present in the patient. square = male, circle = female, black filled symbol = affected, empty symbol = unaffected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="awp198f1"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mutations in <italic>RAB7</italic></title>
        <p>In our cohort, two different missense mutations in <italic>RAB7</italic> have been identified in seven anamnestically unrelated index patients. The index Patients CMT-90.01 and CMT-195.01 of two multigenerational pedigrees as well as two additional Patients with a positive familial history (CMT-186.28 and PN-626.01) carried the same heterozygous transition c.484G&gt;A resulting in a Val162Met missense mutation. The c.385C&gt;T (p.Leu129Phe) missense mutation was detected in three Austrian index Patients: CMT-126.01, CMT-140.01 and CMT-186.26. Additional haplotype analysis revealed that the Val162Met mutation arose independently in the reported families/patients, but the Leu129Phe mutation resides on a common disease haplotype indicating a founder effect (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>). All index patients carrying a <italic>RAB7</italic> mutation present with an adolescent or adult-onset HMSN II phenotype and are characterized by distal atrophy and weakness in the lower limbs with pronounced distal sensory loss complicated by ulcerations and amputations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mutations in <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic></title>
        <p>A recent report showed that <italic>HSN2</italic> is a nervous system-specific exon of the <italic>WNK1</italic>-gene. A compound heterozygous mutation in <italic>WNK1</italic> and <italic>HSN2</italic> was identified as the cause for HSAN type II (Shekarabi <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2008</xref>). In view of this recent finding, the entire coding region of <italic>WNK1</italic> was screened in our patient cohort. No additional disease-related sequence variants were identified outside of the <italic>HSN2</italic> exon.</p>
        <p>We identified a total of four different <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> mutations in three previously reported patients: one compound heterozygous mutation consisting of a 1bp-deletion resulting in a frameshift mutation with a premature stop codon (c.254delC; p.Pro85HisfsX14) and an insertion of a thymine (c.1089_1090insT) predicted to cause a frameshift mutation with premature stop codon (p.Gln364SerfsX16) in Patient CMT-451.01. One homozygous non-sense mutation (c.550C&gt;T; p.Gln184X) and one homozygous 2-bp deletion (c.1064_1065delTC) predicted to cause a frameshift and premature stop codon (p.Ile355AsnfsX7) were detected in Patients CMT-260.01 and CMT-178.01, respectively (Coen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2006</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Mutations in <italic>NTRK1</italic></title>
        <p>In our cohort, seven mutations in <italic>NTRK1</italic> were found, of which one was a novel homozygous missense mutation (c.1697G&gt;A; p.Arg565Gln) in Patient CMT-841.01 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). An affected sibling CMT-841.02 carried the same homozygous mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>C). This mutation targets the tyrosine kinase domain of the neurotrophin tyrosine kinase receptor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The mutated nucleotide is the last base pair of exon 14, resulting in aberrant splicing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>D). Furthermore, we identified a known 9 bp-deletion (c.354_359 + 3delTCGCCTGAA) (Tuysuz <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2008</xref>) in a recently reported Turkish Patient (CMT-886.01) (Kilic <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2009</xref>). This deletion spans the splice-donor site of exon 3. cDNA analysis revealed two splice variants; one with skipping of exon 3 and the second with skipping of exons 2 and 3. These exons contain a part of the leucine-rich motif of NTRK1, important for ligand binding and signal transduction. The patient displayed a CIPA phenotype complicated by recurrent infections secondary to hypogammaglobulinemia, a feature not previously known to be associated with CIPA.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Schematic presentation of protein structures of SPTLC1, RAB7 (Pereira-Leal and Seabra, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2000</xref>), WNK1/HSN2 and NTRK1 (Indo, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">2001</xref>) with mutations identified in this study causing HSAN.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="awp198f2"/></fig></p>
        <p>Six additional known mutations were found in six index patients. Homozygous splice site mutations were found in Patients CMT-197.01 (c.359+5G&gt;T) and CMT-826.01 (IVS15 +3A&gt;C). Homozygous frameshift mutations were present in Patients PN-1192.03 (c.1877-1878insA; p.Gln626GlnfsX7) and CMT-179.01 (c.543delG; p.Gly181GlyfsX16). Finally, we identified a homozygous splice site mutation in Patient CMT-197.01 (c.359 + 5G&gt;T) and a homozygous missense mutation (c.2281C&gt;T; p.Arg761Trp) in Patient CMT-366.01 (Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>). Haplotype analysis suggested a common founder effect with previously described patients carrying this missense mutation (Indo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">2001</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we investigated a cohort of 100 HSAN patients and determined the relative contribution of mutations in six genes known to be involved in various forms of HSAN (<italic>SPTLC1, RAB7, WNK1/HSN2, NTRK1, NGFB</italic> and <italic>CCT5</italic>). In addition, we studied the functional candidate gene <italic>NGFR</italic>. The known subforms of HSAN and their most important clinical characteristics have been summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. In four genes (<italic>SPTLC1, RAB7, WNK1/HSN2, NTRK1</italic>), we identified disease-causing mutations in 19 index patients representing a mutation frequency of 19%. Only nine of these patients had a clear familial history suggestive of HSAN with the remaining 10 being isolated patients. This results in a relative mutation frequency of 31% (9/29) for familial patients and 14% (10/71) for isolated patients. In the group of dominantly inherited HSAN (<italic>RAB7</italic> and <italic>SPTLC1</italic>), the mutation frequency is 33% (7/21) and for recessive HSAN (<italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> and <italic>NTRK1</italic>), the frequency is 25% (2/8). Conversely, 20 familial patients in our screening cohort (14 dominant and 6 recessive) remain unsolved. These findings clearly indicate that additional genes must be involved in the pathogenesis of HSAN. <italic>RAB7</italic> and <italic>NTRK1</italic> were the most frequently mutated genes in our cohort (both 7%), followed by <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> with 3% and <italic>SPTLC1</italic> with 2%.
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Overview of HSAN types with corresponding gene/locus, inheritance pattern, cardinal phenotypic features and references to the Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM) database and literature</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locus</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inh</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical features</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OMIM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SPTLC1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9q22.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predominant loss of pain and temperature sensation, preservation of vibration sense, lancinating pain, variable distal motor involvement<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">162400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bejaoui <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2001</xref>; Dawkins <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2001</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN IB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3p24-p22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predominant sensory neuropathy with cough and gastroesophageal reflux, rarely foot ulcerations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">608088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kok <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">2003</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMT2B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>RAB7</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3q21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prominent distal motor involvement, sensory loss of all qualities, acro-mutilating complications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">600882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN II</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12p13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prominent sensory loss and mutilations in hands and feet, acropathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Childhood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">201300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lafreniere <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2004</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN III (Riley–Day syndrome)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>IKBKAP</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9q31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Familial dysautonomia, prominent autonomic disturbances and complications, absence of fungiform papillae of the tongue, alacrimia, excessive sweating</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">223900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slaugenhaupt <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">2001</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN IV (CIPA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NTRK1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1q21-22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No or reduced response to painful stimuli, anhidrosis, episodic fever, mild mental retardation, skin and cornea lesions, joint deformities, hypogammaglobulinemia in one patient (this study)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">1996</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN V</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>NGFB</italic> (<italic>NTRK1</italic> in rare cases)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1p13.1 (1q21-22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital insensitivity to pain, severe loss of deep pain perception, painless fractures, joint deformities, normal intelligence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congenital</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">608654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Einarsdottir <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2004</xref> (Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2001</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSAN with spastic paraplegia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CCT5</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5p15-p14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prominent sensory neuropathy with sensory loss of all qualities, mutilating acropathy, spastic paraplegia.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early childhood</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">256840</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bouhouche <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2006<italic>a</italic></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>a Congenital onset in one patient with hypotonia, cataract, microcephaly and vocal cord paralysis (this study).</p></fn><fn><p>Inh = inheritance; AAO = age at onset; (updated from Auer-Grumbach <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref> and Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">2006</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The three mutations previously described in <italic>SPTLC1</italic> (Cys133Trp, Cys133Tyr and Val144Asp) are associated with an ulcero-mutilating sensory neuropathy with a spectrum of clinical and electrophysiological features that is variable within and between families (Bejaoui <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2001</xref>; Dawkins <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2001</xref>; Auer-Grumbach, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">2004</xref>; Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2006</xref>). A fourth <italic>SPTLC1</italic> mutation (Gly387Ala) was recently shown not to be disease causing (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">2004</xref>; Hornemann <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the present study, we describe a novel <italic>SPTLC1</italic> mutation (Ser331Phe) in a patient who presented with a severe congenital phenotype. This mutation occurred <italic>de novo</italic>, was absent from 600 control chromosomes and affected a highly conserved amino acid. So far, all known missense mutations are located within a 12-amino acid segment encoded by exons 5 and 6 of <italic>SPTLC1</italic>. The Ser331Phe mutation is located downstream of this segment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). It is possible that the Ser331Phe mutation, due to its different location in the protein, exerts a different effect on SPT activity leading to a more severe phenotype. These results suggest a broadening of the phenotype associated with HSAN type I. We identified a second sequence variant (Ala352Val) in <italic>SPTLC1</italic>, in an isolated patient with a sensory neuropathy. However, the pathogenicity of this sequence variant could not be verified because DNA of the family members was not available for segregation analysis. Furthermore, the amino acid targeted is not well-conserved in evolution and the change from alanine to valine is mild considering their similar chemical properties.</p>
      <p>We found mutations in <italic>SPTLC1</italic> in only 2% of our patients confirming the rare occurrence of <italic>SPTLC1</italic> mutations in isolated and familial HSAN, as found in previous studies (Klein <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2005</xref>; Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>To date, four missense mutations (Leu129Phe, Lys157Asn, Asn161Thr and Val162Met) have been reported in <italic>RAB7</italic> (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>; Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; Meggouh <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">2006</xref>). In our cohort, we found the Leu129Phe mutation in two families (CMT-126 and CMT-140) and one isolated Patient (CMT-186.26), and the Val162Met mutation in families CMT-90 and CMT-195 and in two additional patients with a positive family history (CMT-186.28 and PN626.01) (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">2003</xref>). The patients carrying the Leu129Phe mutation were all of Austrian descent and shared a common disease haplotype, indicating a founder effect. However, the patients with the Val162Met mutation did not share a common haplotype, suggesting independently arising mutations in the same residue, possibly pointing towards a mutational hotspot for <italic>RAB7</italic>. This mutation is located in a highly conserved domain, important for the formation of the nucleotide-binding site of RAB7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The functional importance of this domain in peripheral neuron integrity is further underlined by the identification of mutations in adjacent amino acids (Lys157Asn and Asn161Thr) in patients with CMT2B (Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; Meggouh <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>In our cohort, <italic>RAB7</italic> mutations were exclusively found in patients diagnosed with HSMN II, with ulcero-mutilations also known as CMT2B. Apart from the rare exception of a patient with a typical HSAN type I phenotype carrying the Asn161Thr <italic>RAB7</italic> mutation (Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2004<italic>b</italic></xref>), the phenotype associated with <italic>RAB7</italic> mutations seems to be largely confined to HMSN II (CMT2B). Because of the marked motor involvement, <italic>RAB7</italic>-neuropathy was originally classified as hereditary motor and sensory neuropathy type 2B (CMT2B) (Kwon <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">1995</xref>). Due to the prominent presence of ulcerations, however, CMT2B should be considered part of the spectrum of HSAN (Vance <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">1996</xref>).</p>
      <p>The mutation frequency in the CMT2B-subgroup of our study cohort was very high (7 out of 13 CMT2B patients). The high mutation frequency of <italic>RAB7</italic> found in the present study contrasts with a previous report (Klein <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">2005</xref>), where the known <italic>RAB7</italic> mutations were shown to be absent from a group of 25 families with adult-onset HSAN I or HMSN II with prominent sensory involvement and from an additional 92 idiopathic patients. The frequency of the <italic>RAB7</italic> mutation in our cohort remained high, even when the founder effect of the Leu129Phe mutation was taken into account.</p>
      <p>The phenotype associated with mutations in <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> is a severe AR ulcero-mutilating sensory neuropathy with mild autonomic disturbances beginning in early childhood (Axelrod and Gold-von Simson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2007</xref>). So far, 11 different non-sense and frameshift mutations in <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> have been reported in the literature, all resulting in a complete loss of protein. Recently, it was shown that <italic>HSN2</italic> is not a separate gene residing in intron 8 of <italic>WNK1</italic> but in fact is a neuron-specific exon of <italic>WNK1</italic> itself, with high expression in dorsal root ganglia (DRG) and sciatic nerves (Shekarabi <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2008</xref>). In our cohort, we identified four loss-of-function mutations in <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic>, in three patients, all of which resided in the <italic>HSN2</italic> exon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) (Coen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2006</xref>). From the first large-scale screening of <italic>WNK1</italic> in HSAN patients performed in this study, we can conclude that mutations outside of the <italic>HSN2</italic> exon are likely to be rare.</p>
      <p>The most frequently mutated gene in this study, together with <italic>RAB7</italic>, was <italic>NTRK1</italic>. The NTRK1 protein is a receptor tyrosine kinase, which is phosphorylated in response to nerve growth factor (NGF), supporting survival of sympathetic ganglion neurons and nociceptive sensory neurons in DRG (Levi-Montalcini, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">1987</xref>). To date, more than 40 different missense, non-sense, frameshift and splice site mutations in <italic>NTRK1</italic> have been described in families from various ethnic origins (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molgen.ua.ac.be/CMTMutations/">http://www.molgen.ua.ac.be/CMTMutations/</ext-link>). The corresponding syndrome, CIPA, consists of characteristic features: recurrent episodic fevers due to anhidrosis, absence of reaction to painful stimuli, self-mutilating behaviour and mental retardation (Axelrod and Gold-von Simson, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>In our cohort of 100 HSAN patients, seven different mutations were identified in <italic>NTRK1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), of which six were previously reported (Verpoorten <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">2006<italic>b</italic></xref>; Kilic <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2009</xref>). We identified a previously unreported splice site mutation (Arg565Gln), which comprised the last nucleotide of exon 14 and further broadens the genetic spectrum of <italic>NTRK1</italic> mutations. This mutation resides in the tyrosine kinase domain of the NTRK1 receptor, which regulates autophosphorylation of NTRK1 in response to NGF. Both the index patient (CMT-841.01) and her affected sister (CMT-841.02) were diagnosed with CIPA and carried the same homozygous mutation. However, Patient CMT-841.01 had a normal intelligence whereas the affected sib (CMT-841.02) had learning difficulties. The phenotype of these patients has been described previously (Kruyt <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">2007</xref>).</p>
      <p>Interestingly, a 9-bp deletion (c.354_359 + 3delTCGCCTGAA), resulting in skipping of exon 3 and of exons 2 and 3, was found in a CIPA patient of Turkish origin (CMT-860.01). This patient presented with a multisystem involvement including recurrent infections due to immunological abnormalities as hypogammaglobulinemia (Kilic <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2009</xref>). The same 9-bp deletion was recently reported in an unrelated Turkish HSAN type IV patient (Tuysuz <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2008</xref>). Therefore, this mutation is likely to be a founder mutation in the Turkish population. The phenotype in our patient broadens the clinical spectrum of CIPA.</p>
      <p>It has previously been suggested (Indo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">2001</xref>) that the current literature reveals little to no genetic and clinical heterogeneity in HSAN IV. Although some degree of phenotypic variability was observed in our CIPA-patients with proven <italic>NTRK1</italic> mutations, overall the clinical presentation seems to correspond to a readily recognizable syndrome that is indeed genetically homogenous.</p>
      <p>The phenotype caused by <italic>NGFB</italic> mutations (HSAN type V) is similar to the CIPA phenotype (HSAN type IV). So far, only one homozygous missense mutation has been reported, in a recessive Swedish family (Einarsdottir <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2004</xref>; Minde <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">2004</xref>). Detailed clinical, neurophysiological and genetic analysis of this family revealed that the heterozygous carriers presented with a variable but mild phenotype (Minde <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">2009</xref>). The main difference with CIPA was the absence of obvious mental retardation and less-pronounced anhidrosis. However, one family with the HSAN type V phenotype was described with pathogenic mutations in <italic>NTRK1</italic> indicating the overlap between HSAN types IV and V (Houlden <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2004<italic>a</italic></xref>). These findings underscore the relevance of genetic screenings outside of the known phenotypes and modes of inheritance. In our study cohort, no heterozygous or homozygous sequence variations were found in <italic>NGFB</italic> confirming the rare occurrence of <italic>NGFB</italic> mutations in HSAN patients.</p>
      <p>Recessive mutations in <italic>CCT5</italic> were identified in a consanguineous Moroccan family presenting with HSAN with spastic paraplegia (Bouhouche <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2006<italic>a</italic></xref>). In our cohort, only two HSAN patients presented with an associated spastic paraplegia. However, we did not identify mutations in <italic>CCT5</italic>. Additional screening of 25 unrelated index patients with hereditary spastic paraplegia with sensory involvement did not reveal any mutations in <italic>CCT5</italic> (data not shown). Our results suggest that mutations in <italic>CCT5</italic> are a rare cause for HSAN and make it unlikely to find any mutations outside of the known phenotype.</p>
      <p>Because of the phenotypical resemblance among Ntrk1<sup>−/−</sup>, Ngfb<sup>−/−</sup> and Ngfr<sup>−/−</sup> knockout mice, the patient cohort was screened for <italic>NGFR</italic> (<italic>p75/NTR</italic>) (Lee <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">1992</xref>). No mutations were found in this gene making its contribution to the pathogenesis of HSAN uncertain.</p>
      <p>In summary, we examined the distribution of mutations in genes associated with AD and AR forms of HSAN in a large group of familial and sporadic patients. The genotype–phenotype correlations in this study revealed little variability when compared with previous reports, with the sole exception of a <italic>de novo SPTLC1</italic> mutation in a severe phenotype with congenital onset. Taken together, these results show that the relevant clinical phenotypes are recognizable and should be used to orient molecular diagnosis. Screening of <italic>NTRK1</italic> should be confined to patients presenting with a CIPA phenotype (both AR and isolated patients) as no <italic>NTRK1</italic> mutations were found in other HSAN phenotypes. <italic>RAB7</italic> screening is mandatory in patients presenting with an AD axonal sensory-motor neuropathy with ulcerations (CMT2B) as we found a high mutation frequency in this subgroup (54% or 7/13). Mutations in <italic>WNK1/HSN2</italic> and <italic>SPTLC1</italic> seem to be rare in HSAN. We found no mutations in <italic>NGFB</italic> and <italic>CCT5</italic> indicating that these genes are only rarely involved in HSAN. No pathogenic sequence variations were identified in the functional candidate gene <italic>NGFR</italic>, making its contribution to the pathogenesis of HSAN uncertain. The overall mutation rate was relatively low (19%) suggesting that other genes must be involved in the pathogenesis of HSAN.</p>
      <p>At the present time, the precise nature of the mechanism underlying the pathogenesis of the various HSAN forms remains unclear. Although it is particularly challenging to link the different genes, some preliminary disease pathways may already take form. Of special interest are disturbances of vesicular transport. Both RAB7 and SPTLC1 have a function in endocytotic membrane trafficking. In addition, the NGFB/NTRK1 signalling complex, which is critically important in the development and function of nociceptive neurons, is also dependent upon retrograde transport through signalling endosomes (Verhoeven <italic>et al</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">2006</xref>). Future research is needed to improve our still very incomplete understanding of these mechanisms.</p>
      <p>Additional descriptions of HSAN families and patients with known or novel genetic defects are needed to further refine the existing classification and to get a better insight into the molecular basis of these disorders.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>University of Antwerp; the Fund for Scientific Research (FWO-Flanders); the Medical Foundation Queen Elisabeth (GSKE); the ‘Association Belge contre les Maladies Neuromusculaires’ (ABMM); the Interuniversity Attraction Poles P6/43 program of the Belgian Federal Science Policy Office (BELSPO); the IZKF RWTH Aachen (TV M3); the German Research Council (DFG; WE1406/13-1); Austrian Science Fond (FWF; P19455-B05); PhD fellowships of the Institute for Science and Technology (IWT; to A.R.) and FWO-Flanders (J.B.).</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We are grateful to the patients and their families for their willingness to co-operate in our research project. We also wish to thank the Genetic Service Facility (VIB) for the sequencing support (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vibgeneticservicefacility.be/">http://www.vibgeneticservicefacility.be/</ext-link>).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hereditary sensory neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>Drugs Today</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>385</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319794</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmerman</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartung</surname>
              <given-names>HP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autosomal dominant inherited neuropathies with prominent sensory loss and mutilations: a review</article-title>
          <source>Arch Neurol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12633143</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauko</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieber</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular genetics of hereditary sensory neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>Neuromolecular Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775373</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Axelrod</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gold-von Simson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies: types II, III, and IV</article-title>
          <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17915006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bejaoui</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheffler</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haan</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashby</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SPTLC1 is mutated in hereditary sensory neuropathy, type 1</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>261</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242106</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouhouche</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benomar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouslam</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chkili</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yahyaoui</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation in the epsilon subunit of the cytosolic chaperonin-containing t-complex peptide-1 (Cct5) gene causes autosomal recessive mutilating sensory neuropathy with spastic paraplegia</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2006a</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>441</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16399879</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bouhouche</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benomar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bouslam</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ouazzani</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chkili</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yahyaoui</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autosomal recessive mutilating sensory neuropathy with spastic paraplegia maps to chromosome 5p15.31–14.1</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2006b</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16333315</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pareyson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buyse</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goemans</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claeys</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel mutations in the HSN2 gene causing hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type II</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>748</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534117</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dawkins</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hulme</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brahmbhatt</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in SPTLC1, encoding serine palmitoyltransferase, long chain base subunit-1, cause hereditary sensory neuropathy type I</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>309</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242114</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dyck</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Dyck</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffin</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Low</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poduslo</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neuronal atrophy and degeneration predominantly affecting peripheral sensory and autonomic neurons</article-title>
          <source>Peripheral neuropathy</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <edition>3rd</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>W.B. Saunders</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1065</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Einarsdottir</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlsson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minde</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toolanen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Svensson</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solders</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A mutation in the nerve growth factor beta gene (NGFB) causes loss of pain perception</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>799</fpage>
          <lpage>805</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976160</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hornemann</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penno</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richard</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rotthier</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A systematic comparison of all mutations in hereditary sensory neuropathy type I (HSAN I) reveals that the G387A mutation is not disease associated</article-title>
          <source>Neurogenetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19132419</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Houlden</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reilly</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hereditary sensory neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Neurol</source>
          <year>2004a</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>569</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367861</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Houlden</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groves</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Love</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Woodward</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical, pathological and genetic characterization of hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type 1 (HSAN I)</article-title>
          <source>Brain</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364956</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Houlden</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hashemi-Nejad</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wood</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mathias</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reilly</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel TRK A (NTRK1) mutation associated with hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V</article-title>
          <source>Ann Neurol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>521</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11310631</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Houlden</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muddle</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warner</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reilly</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orrell</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel RAB7 mutation associated with ulcero-mutilating neuropathy</article-title>
          <source>Ann Neurol</source>
          <year>2004b</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>586</fpage>
          <lpage>90</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15455439</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Indo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular basis of congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis (CIPA): mutations and polymorphisms in TRKA (NTRK1) gene encoding the receptor tyrosine kinase for nerve growth factor</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>462</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11748840</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Indo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuruta</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashida</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karim</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohta</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawano</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in the TRKA/NGF receptor gene in patients with congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>485</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8696348</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Indo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mardy</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miura</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moosa</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ismail</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toscano</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis (CIPA): novel mutations of the TRKA (NTRK1) gene, a putative uniparental disomy, and a linkage of the mutant TRKA and PKLR genes in a family with CIPA and pyruvate kinase deficiency</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>308</fpage>
          <lpage>18</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11668614</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kilic</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozturk</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarisozen</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rotthier</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baets</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmerman</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Humoral immunodeficiency in congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis</article-title>
          <source>Neurogenetics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>161</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19089473</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Klein</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruckeberg</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hebbring</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cunningham</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SPTLC1 and RAB7 mutation analysis in dominantly inherited and idiopathic sensory neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>1022</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15965219</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kok</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennerson</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spring</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ing</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pollard</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A locus for hereditary sensory neuropathy with cough and gastroesophageal reflux on chromosome 3p22-p24</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>632</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12870133</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kruyt</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruyt</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oner</surname>
              <given-names>FC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanlo</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verbout</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>[Congenital pain-insensitivity syndrome; a rare indication of the benefit of pain]</article-title>
          <source>Ned Tijdschr Geneeskd</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>151</volume>
          <fpage>1527</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17763813</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elliott</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yee</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ivanovich</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scavarda</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moolsintong</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Assignment of a second Charcot-Marie-Tooth type II locus to chromosome 3q</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>853</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7573046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lafreniere</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MacDonald</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dube</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MacFarlane</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Driscoll</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brais</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of a novel gene (HSN2) causing hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type II through the Study of Canadian Genetic Isolates</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>1064</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15060842</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Landis</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharpe</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chao</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Targeted mutation of the gene encoding the low affinity NGF receptor p75 leads to deficits in the peripheral sensory nervous system</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1317267</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levi-Montalcini</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The nerve growth factor: thirty-five years later</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>1145</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3301324</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meggouh</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bienfait</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weterman</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Visser</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baas</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease due to a de novo mutation of the RAB7 gene</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>1476</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060578</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Minde</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toolanen</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nennesmo</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Remahl</surname>
              <given-names>IN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Svensson</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Familial insensitivity to pain (HSAN V) and a mutation in the NGFB gene. A neurophysiological and pathological study</article-title>
          <source>Muscle Nerve</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>752</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15468048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Minde</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersson</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fulford</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aguirre</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nennesmo</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Remahl</surname>
              <given-names>IN</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel NGFB point mutation: a phenotype study of heterozygous patients</article-title>
          <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>188</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18420729</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira-Leal</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seabra</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The mammalian Rab family of small GTPases: definition of family and subfamily sequence motifs suggests a mechanism for functional specificity in the Ras superfamily</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>301</volume>
          <fpage>1077</fpage>
          <lpage>87</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966806</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rozen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skaletsky</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title>
          <source>Meth Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shatzky</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moses</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levy</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinsk</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hershkovitz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herzog</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis (CIPA) in Israeli-Bedouins: genetic heterogeneity, novel mutations in the TRKA/NGF receptor gene, clinical findings, and results of nerve conduction studies</article-title>
          <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>353</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10861667</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shekarabi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Girard</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riviere</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dion</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toulouse</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in the nervous system—specific HSN2 exon of WNK1 cause hereditary sensory neuropathy type II</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>2496</fpage>
          <lpage>505</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18521183</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Slaugenhaupt</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blumenfeld</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leyne</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mull</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cuajungco</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tissue-specific expression of a splicing mutation in the IKBKAP gene causes familial dysautonomia</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>598</fpage>
          <lpage>605</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179008</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tuysuz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayrakli</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diluna</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bilguvar</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bayri</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yalcinkaya</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel NTRK1 mutations cause hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type IV: demonstration of a founder mutation in the Turkish population</article-title>
          <source>Neurogenetics</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>119</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18322713</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vance</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Speer</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stajich</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolpert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaskell</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Misclassification and linkage of hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type 1 as Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, type 2B</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>258</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8659534</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Vriendt</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobs</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Gerwen</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smouts</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SPTLC1 mutation in twin sisters with hereditary sensory neuropathy type I</article-title>
          <source>Neurology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>1001</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15037712</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verpoorten</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwon</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in the small GTP-ase late endosomal protein RAB7 cause Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 2B neuropathy</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>722</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12545426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verpoorten</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmerman</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disease mechanisms in hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>Neurobiol Dis</source>
          <year>2006a</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183296</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmerman</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauko</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieber</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auer-Grumbach</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recent advances in hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Neurol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>474</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16969157</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verpoorten</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claeys</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deprez</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobs</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Gerwen</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lagae</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel frameshift and splice site mutations in the neurotrophic tyrosine kinase receptor type 1 gene (NTRK1) associated with hereditary sensory neuropathy type IV</article-title>
          <source>Neuromuscul Disord</source>
          <year>2006b</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16373086</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weckx</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Rijk</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Broeckhoven</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del-Favero</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SNPbox: web-based high-throughput primer design from gene to genome</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>W170</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215373</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weckx</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Del-Favero</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rademakers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claes</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cruts</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Jonghe</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>novoSNP, a novel computational tool for sequence variation discovery</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>436</fpage>
          <lpage>42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15741513</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <def-list>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G1">AD</term>
          <def>
            <p>autosomal dominant</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G2">AR</term>
          <def>
            <p>autosomal recessive</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G3">CIPA</term>
          <def>
            <p>congenital insensitivity to pain and anhidrosis</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G4">CMT</term>
          <def>
            <p>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G5">HMSN</term>
          <def>
            <p>hereditary motor and sensory neuropathy</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G6">HSAN</term>
          <def>
            <p>hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G7">NCV</term>
          <def>
            <p>nerve conduction velocity</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G8">STRs</term>
          <def>
            <p>short tandem repeats</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G9">TM</term>
          <def>
            <p>transmembrane domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G10">SF</term>
          <def>
            <p>Rab subfamily domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G11">PG/M</term>
          <def>
            <p>conserved domain implicated in binding of phosphate/Mg2+ and guanine binding</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G12">F</term>
          <def>
            <p>Ras family domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G13">PK</term>
          <def>
            <p>protein kinase domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G14">AI</term>
          <def>
            <p>autoinhibitory domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G15">CC</term>
          <def>
            <p>coiled coil domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G16">SP</term>
          <def>
            <p>signal peptide</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G17">Cys</term>
          <def>
            <p>cysteine cluster</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G18">LRM</term>
          <def>
            <p>leucine rich motif</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="G19">Ig</term>
          <def>
            <p>immunoglobulin-like domain</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>