<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:37:13Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2882165" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:2882165</identifier><datestamp>2010-06-08</datestamp><setSpec>nihpa</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec><setSpec>manuscript</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9502015</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">8791</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Med</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Med.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature medicine</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1078-8956</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1546-170X</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC2882165</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2882165</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">2882165</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668192</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668192</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2018</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa131529</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Alternatively spliced VEGF receptor-2 is an essential endogenous inhibitor of lymphatic vessels</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Albuquerque</surname>
            <given-names>Romulo J.C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hayashi</surname>
            <given-names>Takahiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">14</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Won Gil</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">14</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kleinman</surname>
            <given-names>Mark E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">14</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dridi</surname>
            <given-names>Sami</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takeda</surname>
            <given-names>Atsunobu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baffi</surname>
            <given-names>Judit Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamada</surname>
            <given-names>Kiyoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaneko</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Green</surname>
            <given-names>Martha G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chappell</surname>
            <given-names>Joe</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilting</surname>
            <given-names>Jörg</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Weich</surname>
            <given-names>Herbert A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamagami</surname>
            <given-names>Satoru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Amano</surname>
            <given-names>Shiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mizuki</surname>
            <given-names>Nobuhisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Alexander</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peterson</surname>
            <given-names>Martha L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Brekken</surname>
            <given-names>Rolf A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hirashima</surname>
            <given-names>Masanori</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Capoor</surname>
            <given-names>Seema</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Usui</surname>
            <given-names>Tomohiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ambati</surname>
            <given-names>Balamurali K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ambati</surname>
            <given-names>Jayakrishna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Sciences, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky 40536, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Physiology, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky 40536, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Yokohama City University, Yokohama, 221-0044, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Plant &amp; Soil Sciences, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky 40536, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, Georg-August-University, Goettingen, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department Gene Regulation and Differentiation, Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research, Braunschweig, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Ophthalmology, University of Tokyo School of Medicine, Tokyo, 113-8655, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center, Shreveport, Louisiana 71130-3932, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Microbiology, Immunology and Molecular Genetics, University of Kentucky, Lexington, Kentucky 40536, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Hamon Center for Therapeutic Oncology Research, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, Texas 75390-8593, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Division of Vascular Biology, Department of Physiology and Cell Biology, Kobe University Graduate School of Medicine, Kobe 650-0017, Japan</aff>
      <aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences, Moran Eye Center, University of Utah School of Medicine, Salt Lake City, Utah 84132, USA</aff>
      <aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Department of Ophthalmology, Veterans Affairs Salt Lake City Healthcare System, Salt Lake City, Utah 84148, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="equal" id="FN1">
          <label>14</label>
          <p id="P1">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="CR1">Correspondence should be addressed to J.A. (<email>jamba2@email.uky.edu</email>).</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
        <day>14</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>08</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <fpage>1023</fpage>
      <lpage>1030</lpage>
      <!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/nm.2018-->
      <permissions>
        <license xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">
          <license-p>Users may view, print, copy, and download text and data-mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p id="P2">Disruption of the precise balance of positive and negative molecular regulators of blood and lymphatic vessels can lead to myriad diseases that affect one in four people worldwide. Although dozens of natural inhibitors of hemangiogenesis have been identified, an endogenous selective inhibitor of lymphatic vessels has not yet been described. We report the existence of a secreted, splice variant of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2 (sVegfr-2) that inhibits developmental and reparative lymphangiogenesis by blocking Vegf-c. Tissue-specific loss of sVegfr-2 in mice induced, at birth, spontaneous lymphatic invasion of the normally alymphatic cornea and hyperplasia of skin lymphatics without accompanying changes in blood vasculature. sVegfr-2 inhibited lymphangiogenesis but not hemangiogenesis induced by corneal suture injury or transplantation, enhanced corneal allograft survival, and suppressed lymphangioma cellular proliferation. Naturally occurring sVegfr-2 is a molecular uncoupler of blood and lymphatic vessels whose modulation might have a therapeutic role in lymphatic vascular malformations, transplantation, and potentially in tumor lymphangiogenesis and lymphedema.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="P3">The blood and lymphatic vessel networks are jointly essential for development, wound healing, and immune surveillance and activation. Pathological responses of these parallel circulatory systems can lead to diseases as varied as age-related macular degeneration, atherosclerosis, cancer, lymphedema, rheumatoid arthritis, and tumor metastasis<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>. Collectively, exuberant or inadequate responses of hemangiogenesis and lymphangiogenesis are estimated to affect nearly two billion people<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. The prevalence of such diseases has fueled intense efforts to develop proand anti-angiogenic therapeutics. Several anti-hemangiogenic drugs are FDA-approved but not one specific lymphangiogenesis inhibitor is even in clinical trials. As such there is great interest in identifying such specific inhibitors both to alleviate disease burden and to better understand lymphatic vascular biology. However, despite concerted efforts, it has been challenging to approach lymphangiogenesis selectively due to the difficulty in mechanistically disassociating it from hemangiogenesis.</p>
    <p id="P4">The vascular endothelial growth factors (Vegf) family of molecules is indispensable for growth of blood<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and lymphatic<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> vessels. Hemangiogenesis requires a precise balance of positive and negative regulators<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>; however, the mechanisms governing lymphangiogenesis equilibria remain nebulous. Soluble splice variants of Vegf receptor-1 (sVegfr-1) act as potent natural inhibitors of hemangiogenesis by trapping the blood endothelial mitogen Vegf-a (refs. <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>-<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and are the only reported secreted splice variants of any of the Vegf receptor tyrosine kinases since their discovery in the early 1990s. Here we describe the detection and function of a new secreted splice variant within the Vegf receptor family, which we demonstrate is a critical endogenous antagonist of Vegf-c and a physiological regulator of lymphatic vessels.</p>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="S1">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec id="S2">
        <title>Cloning of sVegfr-2</title>
        <p id="P5">During our studies uncovering the non-redundant function of sVegfr-1 in corneal avascularity<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, which is critical for optimal vision, we observed, on western blotting, anomalous migration of a 75 kDa protein species that was immunoreactive to an antibody (T014; ref. <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) recognizing the amino-terminus of Vegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>). Given the homology in the exon-intron structure between <italic>Vegfr1</italic> and <italic>Vegfr2</italic>, we hypothesized that this unidentified protein represented a novel truncated splice variant of the 230 kDa membrane-bound form of Vegfr-2 (mbVegfr-2) and that it might have anti-lymphangiogenic activity because the lymphatic mitogen Vegf-c (ref. <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) is capable of binding mbVegfr-2 (ref. <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p>
        <p id="P6">By modeling the putative alternative splicing event of <italic>Vegfr2</italic> to that of <italic>Vegfr1</italic> (ref. <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), we found that retention of intron 13 would yield a truncated transcript variant whose protein product would lack the transmembrane and intracellular tyrosine kinase domains of mbVegfr-2 due to the presence of an in-frame early termination TAA codon 39 nucleotides downstream from the aforementioned exon/intron junction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1c</xref>). To verify the existence of this novel soluble splicing variant in the mouse cornea, we devised primers targeting intron 13 and exon 12 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1c and Supplementary Fig. 2a</xref>). Targeting exon 12 allowed us to distinguish between amplification of mRNA-derived cDNA and genomic DNA contamination based on amplicon size. PCR yielded a 393-bp product encompassing the locus of the splicing event (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1d</xref>). Bioinformatic analysis of intron 13 revealed three potential polyadenylation (polyA) signal sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1c</xref>). Using rapid amplification of cDNA 3′ ends PCR, we found the third potential polyA signal at position 3956-61 to be active (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1c,e and Supplementary Fig. 2a</xref>). From mouse cornea cDNA, we cloned the 2022-bp open reading frame of <italic>sVegfr2</italic> encoding a polypeptide of 673 amino acids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 2b</xref>, for detailed sequence of the <italic>sVegfr2</italic> transcript see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 2a</xref>). This novel protein contained a unique 13-aa carboxyl-terminus sequence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1b</xref>) not present in mbVegfr-2 or any other known protein and against which we raised a rabbit polyclonal antibody (AA21127; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S3">
        <title>sVegfr-2 is expressed in the cornea</title>
        <p id="P7">This <italic>sVegfr2</italic> transcript was localized by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization principally to the corneal epithelium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Immunolocalization using AA21127 in the newborn mouse demonstrated the presence of sVegfr-2 in the corneal epithelium and stroma (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>). In the adult cornea, sVegfr-2 was more abundant in the epithelium than in the stroma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>). sVegfr-2 was distributed uniformly in the cornea with enhanced expression near the limbus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4b</xref>). In contrast, sVegfr-2 was not immunolocalized in the conjunctiva (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4b,c</xref>). sVegfr-2 was identified in the cornea as a 75 kDa species by western blotting both by AA21127 and T014 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4d</xref>). However, 230 kDa mbVegfr-2 was not detected in the cornea by western blotting using T014 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>) or by immunofluorescence using an antibody targeting the carboxyl-terminus of mbVegfr-2, which is not present in sVegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4e</xref>). Neither was the <italic>mbVegfr2</italic> transcript detected in the cornea by RT-PCR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4f</xref>). Thus, the mouse cornea expresses sVegfr-2 but not mbVegfr-2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S4">
        <title>sVegfr-2 is essential for alymphatic cornea</title>
        <p id="P8">To define the function of sVegfr-2 in the cornea, we targeted it using multiple strategies. Because <italic>Vegfr2</italic><sup>–/–</sup> mice die <italic>in utero</italic><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, we conditionally ablated corneal sVegfr-2 using a Cre-loxP strategy. This strategy enabled the specific targeting of sVegfr-2 because mbVegfr-2 is not expressed in the cornea (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 4e,f</xref>). We created <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice by targeting exon 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>) and interbred them with <italic>LeCre</italic> mice that constitutively and uniformly express Cre recombinase in the cornea<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. Mice of all genotypes were born at the expected mendelian ratios and were macroscopically indistinguishable from one another. Strikingly however, all <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mouse corneas (<italic>n</italic> = 30), which verifiably lacked sVegfr-2 expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 6a</xref>), were densely covered with lymphatic vessels at birth (P0) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). These vessels were identified as lymphatics by virtue of their intense Lyve-1 reactivity, moderate Cd31 reactivity, nuclear Prox1 expression, and blind-ended morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c-e</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 6b</xref>). Although Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> macrophages have been described in the cornea<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, co-expression of Prox1 in these vessels confirms their lymphatic endothelial fate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1d,e</xref>). Furthermore, ultrastructural examination showed that these vessels lacked erythrocytes, did not have a continuous basement membrane, and contained partly overlapping thin endothelial cells free of pericyte coverage, all features typical of lymphatics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>). Surprisingly these corneas were not invaded by blood vessels as demonstrated by the absence of Cd31<sup>+</sup> Lyve-1<sup>–</sup> vessels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c,g</xref>). We confirmed this independently by demonstrating that the vessels in these corneas did not express Meca-32, a blood vessel-specific marker (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 6c,d</xref>). All littermate control corneas (<italic>n</italic> =30) were, like wild-type mice, devoid of both lymphatic and blood vessels. <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice had normal limbal blood vessel morphology and an unimpaired corneal hemangiogenesis response to suture injury (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig 6d,e</xref>), confirming intact vascular endothelial cell Vegfr-2 function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S5">
        <title>sVegfr-2 is a Vegf-c antagonist</title>
        <p id="P9">These results indicate that the developing mouse cornea is exposed to pro-lymphangiogenic stimuli that are counterbalanced by sVegfr-2 to create an alymphatic cornea. Indeed wild-type P0 corneas, unlike adult corneas, expressed Vegf-c (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 7</xref>). We reasoned that sVegfr-2 ablation led to spontaneous corneal lymphangiogenesis because sVegfr-2 trapped Vegf-c. Indeed, the levels of sVegfr-2 (1,655.8±44.62 pg per mg of total protein) in the wild-type P0 cornea were sufficiently in excess of Vegf-c (45.4±3.2 pg per mg of total protein) to fulfill a trapping function. sVegfr-2, which contains the Vegf-c binding Ig-like domain 2 of mbVegfr-2 (ref. <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), interacted with Vegf-c by immunoprecipitation and inhibited both Vegfr-3 phosphorylation and proliferation of lymphatic endothelial cells (LECs) stimulated by Vegf-c (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1h-j</xref>). Also, Vegf-c-induced corneal lymphangiogenesis was inhibited by intracorneal administration<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> of a plasmid encoding for sVegfr-2 (psVegfr-2) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). Collectively, these data are consistent with a model of sVegfr-2 acting as an endogenous sink for Vegf-c during corneal development and thereby establishing an alymphatic cornea.</p>
        <p id="P10">Consistent with the report that mouse Vegfr-2 binds human VEGF-D but not mouse Vegf-d (ref. <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), psVegfr-2 inhibited corneal lymphangiogenesis induced by human VEGF-D but not mouse Vegf-d (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). Also, unlike Vegf-c, Vegf-d was not expressed in the newborn mouse cornea (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 9</xref>), thus accounting for the ability of sVegfr-2 to maintain the alymphatic nature of the cornea.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S6">
        <title>sVegfr-2 inhibits reparative lymphangiogenesis</title>
        <p id="P11">To determine the function of sVegfr-2 in the adult, we studied a clinically relevant mouse model of suture-induced corneal neovascularization<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Suture injury increased corneal sVegfr-2 expression (in the epithelium and not in infiltrating macrophages) in wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref>). Ablating sVegfr-2 by intracorneal administration<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> of pCre in <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice markedly increased suture-induced lymphangiogenesis but not hemangiogenesis compared to pNull administration by 161±9% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> = 5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a-c</xref>). This outstripping of hemangiogenesis by lymphangiogenesis suggests that induction of endogenous sVegfr-2 by injury is a compensatory anti-lymphangiogenic response. Both pCre and pNull-injected corneas of wild-type mice showed similar degrees of lymphangiogenesis following suture injury, excluding a non-specific effect of Cre recombinase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). pCre induced enhancement of suture-induced lymphangiogenesis in <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice was reduced by a Vegfr-3 tyrosine kinase inhibitor<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, supporting the concept that endogenous sVegfr-2 is an <italic>in vivo</italic> Vegf-c antagonist (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Conversely, augmenting sVegfr-2 via <italic>in vivo</italic> transfection<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> of wild-type mouse corneas with psVegfr-2, but not pNull, reduced suture injury-induced lymphangiogenesis but not hemangiogenesis by 76±6% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> = 5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d,e</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S7">
        <title>sVegfr-2 enhances corneal transplant survival</title>
        <p id="P12">Because lymphangiogenesis has been implicated in corneal allograft rejection<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, we studied the function of sVegfr-2 in a mouse model of corneal transplantation. A single intracorneal administration of dimeric Vegfr-2/Fc more than doubled transplant survival rate (105% increase compared to the IgG/Fc treatment and 101% compared to no treatment; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> = 10–13; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>). The dramatic reduction in rejection rate induced by Vegfr-2/Fc administration (75% compared to the IgG/Fc treatment and 74% compared to no treatment) is consistent with the observed reduction in blood vessel and lymphatic sprouting through the donor-recipient interface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g,h</xref>). Surprisingly, a single intracorneal administration of monomeric sVegfr-2 induced the same degree of corneal allograft survival as dimeric Vegfr-2/Fc despite reducing sprouting only of lymphatic but not blood vessels through the donor-recipient interface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f-h</xref>). These data suggest that impairment of the establishment of the afferent arm of the immune-arc-reflex<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> alone is sufficient to enhance corneal allograft survival. Further, the rate of allograft survival following a single local administration of sVegfr-2 was at least as great as the rate of survival induced by multiple systemic administrations of a Vegfr-3 antagonist in a prior study<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>. Apart from reducing lymphangiogenesis, it also is possible that sVegfr-2 promoted allograft survival by inhibiting Vegf-c-induced Vegfr-3 signaling in corneal dendritic cells and preventing their transmigration into the draining lymph node<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>. Collectively, these data provide a novel experimental strategy to uncouple hemangiogenesis from lymphangiogenesis and a new endogenous therapeutic target for improving survival of this most common solid transplant in humans.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S8">
        <title>Endogenous Vegf-c promotes lymphangiogenesis</title>
        <p id="P13">Selective lymphangiogenesis inhibition by sVegfr-2 is consistent with the selective effect of endogenous Vegf-c on the lymphatic vasculature<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>-<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>. However, implantation of pellets containing 160–200 ng of recombinant VEGF-C into the 2 μl mouse cornea has been reported to induce hemangiogenesis<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>-<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>. To reconcile these findings, we injected neutralizing anti-Vegf-c antibodies into the cornea of wild-type mice after suture injury and found that this resulted in inhibition of lymphangiogenesis (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> = 8) but not hemangiogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a,b</xref>). These data directly demonstrate that endogenous Vegf-c selectively promotes lymphangiogenesis in the cornea, and help explain the selective effect of sVegfr-2. The lack of Vegfr-3 expression by conjunctival and corneal blood vessels<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> also support a model where endogenous Vegf-c preferentially binds Vegfr-3 on lymphatic vessels over Vegfr-2 on blood vessels in these tissues, based on relative receptor affinities<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>. Also, Vegf-c is far less efficient at activating Vegfr-2 than Vegf-a<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, the principal driver of corneal hemangiogenesis<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>.</p>
        <p id="P14">We quantified VEGF-C levels following 160 ng VEGF-C pellet implantation and found that this resulted in corneal VEGF-C levels that were 100–125 times greater than the levels observed after suture injury and 45–66 times greater than neonatal levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). Such exaggerated levels that are supra-physiological and far greater than those achieved in pathophysiologically relevant states could explain the reported hemangiogenic effects of exogenous VEGF-C in this artificial context.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S9">
        <title>Monomeric sVegfr-2 does not block hemangiogenesis</title>
        <p id="P15">These selective anti-lymphangiogenic effects of sVegfr-2 also were unexpectedly specific because mbVegfr-2 is capable of binding Vegf-a and promoting hemangiogenesis. To explain this selectivity, we first sought to determine whether sVegfr-2 existed in monomeric or dimeric form because a recombinant form of the ectodomain of mbVegfr-2 has been shown to be a monomer that has little or no affinity for Vegf-a compared to a dimeric recombinant Vegfr-2/Fc fusion protein<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>-<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>. Expression studies revealed that sVegfr-2 secreted by mouse corneal epithelial, human embryonic kidney, and Chinese hamster ovary cells, as well as recombinant sVegfr-2, all migrated at equivalent apparent molecular masses under both non-reducing and reducing conditions of western blotting, data consistent with its existence as a monomer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d,e</xref>). In contrast, the migration of Vegfr-2/Fc was consistent with it being a dimer.</p>
        <p id="P16">Next we tested the effects of monomeric sVegfr-2 and dimeric Vegfr-2/Fc on models of corneal neovascularization induced by injury or Vegf-a. Suture-induced corneal hemangiogenesis, which is driven principally by upregulation of endogenous Vegf-a (ref. <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), was inhibited by Vegfr-2/Fc but not sVegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). Similarly, Vegf-a-induced phosphorylation of mbVegfr-2 in porcine aortic endothelial cells was inhibited by Vegfr-2/Fc but not sVegfr-2, and Vegf-a-induced corneal hemangiogenesis was inhibited by Vegfr-2/Fc but not by sVegfr-2 or psVegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g,h</xref>). These functional data provide a mechanistic basis for the absence of an anti-hemangiogenic effect of endogenous sVegfr-2, and corroborate the previously reported <italic>in vitro</italic> differential Vegf-a binding avidity between monomeric and dimeric forms of Vegfr-2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S10">
        <title>Non-ocular role of sVegfr-2</title>
        <p id="P17">We found <italic>sVegfr2</italic> expression by Northern blotting of poly A-enriched RNA isolated from various mouse organs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 11</xref>), suggesting that sVegfr-2 might have functions outside the eye. <italic>sVegfr2</italic> mRNA was abundant in the alymphatic epidermis of the skin as well as in the hair follicles of wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). sVegfr-2 protein was immunolocalized in the epidermis, hair follicles, and, consistent with its ability to diffuse, also in the dermis of wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>). In contrast, mbVegfr-2 was expressed in the skin vasculature, but not in the epithelial cells or hair follicles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 12a</xref>). As in the cornea, Vegf-c was expressed in the P0 wild-type mouse skin but undetectable in the adult (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 12b</xref>). Excess Vegf-c in the skin, achieved by either transgenic overexpression or implantation of overexpressing cells, leads to hyperplasia but not sprouting of lymphatic vessels<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>. To determine the function of sVegfr-2 in the skin, we interbred <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice with <italic>K14Cre</italic> mice that constitutively and uniformly express Cre recombinase in the epidermis and hair follicles<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>. This strategy specifically targets sVegfr-2 because the epidermis and hair follicles express sVegfr-2 but not mbVegfr-2. Strikingly, in all P0 <italic>K14Cre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mouse skin, which lacked sVegfr-2 expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>), there was dramatic enlargement of lymphatic vessels compared to those in littermate control skin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d-f</xref>). These dilated skin lymphatics in <italic>K14Cre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice also were hyperplastic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e,g</xref>). However, the density of lymphatic structures, as quantified by branch point analysis, was not greater in <italic>K14Cre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref>), just as in mouse skin exposed to excess Vegf-c (refs. <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In contrast to the lymphatic architectural changes, there was no increase in skin blood vessel diameter or density in <italic>K14Cre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d,e</xref>). The recapitulation of Vegf-c overexpression induced selective lymphatic hyperplasia in mice lacking sVegfr-2 supports the concept that sVegfr-2 is an <italic>in vivo</italic> antagonist of Vegf-c.</p>
        <p id="P18">A protein immunoreactive to an antibody recognizing the amino-terminus of Vegfr-2 has been detected in plasma and shown to be a surrogate biomarker of tumor growth<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>-<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>. However, its molecular identity (whether it is encoded by a splice variant of <italic>Vegfr2</italic> or derived from ectodomain shedding or proteolytic cleavage of mbVegfr-2) and cellular source have been elusive. Circulating Vegfr-2 in plasma was immunoreactive to both AA21127 and T014 but not an antibody recognizing the carboxyl-terminus of mbVegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref>), suggesting that it was encoded by the <italic>sVegfr2</italic> splice variant. Mouse blood endothelial cell (BEC) lines derived from the microvasculature of the brain, pancreas, or skin all synthesized and secreted sVegfr-2, far in excess of LEC production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b,c</xref>). Also sVegfr-2 was detected by immunofluorescence using AA21127 in mouse lung microvasculature, identifying BECs as sources of plasma sVegfr-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>). The production of anti-lymphangiogenic sVegfr-2 by BECs could be one of the mechanisms underlying the observation that lymphangiogenesis typically lags behind hemangiogenesis in many neovascular models. Surprisingly, plasma levels of sVegfr-2 were significantly lower in <italic>K14Cre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice compared to littermate controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5e</xref>), suggesting that the skin epithelium also is a source of circulating sVegfr-2. An earlier report showing that <italic>K14</italic>-driven recombinant soluble Vegfr-3 led to measurable circulating levels of the engineered protein<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> supports the concept that endogenous skin-derived sVegfr-2 also can enter the circulation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S11">
        <title>sVEGFR-2 exists in humans and inhibits lymphangioma cellular proliferation</title>
        <p id="P19">We confirmed the existence of <italic>sVEGFR2</italic> in humans using RT-PCR to clone the 2159-bp open reading frame of a transcript in human umbilical vein endothelial cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6a</xref>), that, as with mouse <italic>sVegfr2</italic>, resulted from retention of intron 13 also containing an in-frame early termination stop codon in human <italic>VEGFR2</italic>. Translation of <italic>sVEGFR2</italic> results in a protein containing 679 amino acids with a unique 16-aa carboxyl-terminus sequence not present in mbVEGFR-2 and against which we developed a polyclonal antibody (AA21129, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Fig. 13</xref>). sVEGFR-2 was expressed in human cornea with a distribution similar to that in mouse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6b</xref>), suggesting that it plays a similar role in maintaining an alymphatic state. The potential anti-lymphangiogenic property of sVEGFR-2 in humans was tested <italic>in vitro</italic>. Lymphangioma is a common disfiguring childhood neoplasia whose etiology is unknown. Human lymphangioma endothelial cells (LaECs) produce VEGF-C and express VEGFR-3 (refs. <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>-<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), suggesting that their growth could be inhibited by disrupting this axis. Previously we described the isolation of LaECs from axillary lymphangiomas in two human infants<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>. We found that sVEGFR-2 abolished VEGF-C-induced proliferation of both these LaECs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6c,d</xref>), raising the exciting possibility that these pediatric tumors could be molecularly targeted.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="S12">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p id="P20">As an endogenous uncoupler of the intertwined blood and lymphatic circulatory systems, sVegfr-2 represents a new molecular tool to selectively dissect the individual contributions of these parallel vasculatures in development and disease. More importantly the identification of sVegfr-2 can enable new therapeutic strategies by selectively modulating aberrant lymphatic proliferation without encountering the potential adverse effects of non-specific anti-angiogenic therapy.</p>
      <p id="P21">The importance of pure lymphangiogenesis suppression is nowhere more apparent than in the setting of lymphangioma, which occurs in roughly 1 in 50 children<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>. These tumors, although classified as benign, can be locally invasive and terribly disfiguring. Their pediatric preponderance highlights the need to develop selective anti-lymphangiogenic therapy. Our finding that sVEGFR-2 can prevent VEGF-C induced proliferation of human lymphangioma endothelial cells raises the exciting possibility that these pediatric tumors could be targeted on a molecular level.</p>
      <p id="P22">Our discovery of sVegfr-2 in the cornea endorses this tissue as a rich source of angiogenesis modulators, and introduces the yin-yang concept of opposing natural molecular forces that regulate blood vessel growth<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> to lymphangiogenesis. Just as sVegfr-1 is required for corneal avascularity<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, we now show that sVegfr-2 is essential for corneal alymphaticity. The dual presence of sVegfr-1 and sVegfr-2 attests to the premium placed by the cornea on impeding both blood and lymphatic vessel growth to preserve optical clarity and relative immunological privilege, and illustrates the conservation of alternative splicing in generating these tandem traps.</p>
      <p id="P23">The surprising finding that sVegfr-2 enhanced corneal allograft survival despite not inhibiting hemangiogenesis suggests that impairment of the establishment of the afferent arm of the immune-arc-reflex<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> alone is sufficient to enhance corneal allograft survival. Interestingly, the rate of allograft survival following a single local administration of sVegfr-2 was at least as great as the rate of survival induced by multiple systemic administrations of a Vegfr-3 antagonist in a prior study<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>. Apart from reducing lymphangiogenesis, it also is possible that sVegfr-2 promoted allograft survival by inhibiting Vegf-c-induced Vegfr-3 signaling in corneal dendritic cells and preventing their transmigration into the draining lymph node<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>. In addition to identifying a new endogenous therapeutic target for improving survival of this most common solid transplant in humans, our data also provide a mechanistic basis for evaluating selective lymphangiogenesis suppression in other transplants, such as kidney, whose rejection is associated with lymphangiogenesis<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>.</p>
      <p id="P24">Unlike collagen XVIII fragments, semaphorin 3F, and transforming growth factor-β, the only other reported endogenous inhibitors of lymphangiogenesis<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>-<xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, native sVegfr-2 is a specific and direct lymphangiogenesis inhibitor that did not inhibit hemangiogenesis in multiple models, which often is intimately intertwined with lymphangiogenesis. One reason for this specificity is that native sVegfr-2 as a monomer, unlike dimeric mbVegfr-2, has poor avidity for Vegf-a. Nevertheless, we cannot exclude a minor anti-hemangiogenic role for sVegfr-2 that might be masked by the dominant role of coexisting molecules such as sVegfr-1 that have much greater affinity for Vegf-a, or in experimental contexts where high levels of exogenous Vegf-c promote hemangiogenesis. A complete molecular resolution of why endogenous sVegfr-2 binds Vegf-c and not Vegf-a must await structure solutions of the Vegfr-2 ectodomain alone and in complex with Vegf-a as well as of Vegf-c. Collectively our findings demonstrate that sVegfr-2 is a broad and non-redundant physiological regulator of lymphatic vessels. Further studies will reveal whether sVegfr-2 can arrest solid tumor lymphangiogenesis and metastasis, which can be promoted by Vegf-c overexpression<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>-<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> and inhibited by blocking Vegf-c activity<xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="S13">
      <title>METHODS</title>
      <sec id="S14">
        <title>Animals</title>
        <p id="P25">Balb/C, C57Bl/6J, and <italic>K14Cre</italic> mice were purchased from The Jackson Laboratory. <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> (flox) mice were generated as described below. <italic>LeCre</italic> mice<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, which constitutively express Cre recombinase in the cornea were a gift of R. Ashery-Padan and P. Gruss via D.C. Beebe. For all procedures, anesthesia was achieved by intraperitoneal injection of 50 mg/kg ketamine hydrochloride (Fort Dodge Animal Health, Wyeth) and 10 mg/kg xylazine (Phoenix Scientific, San Marcos, CA). All animal procedures were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committees at the University of Kentucky or Yokohama City University, and conformed to the Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology Statement on Animal Research.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S15">
        <title>Conditional <italic>Vegfr2</italic> gene ablation</title>
        <p id="P26">We achieved embryonic conditional genetic ablation of <italic>Vegfr2</italic> in the cornea by cross-breeding <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice with <italic>LeCre</italic> mice<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. Alternatively, to target <italic>Vegfr2</italic> in the adult mouse cornea, we performed intrastromal injections of naked plasmids<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> containing the sequence for Cre recombinase (pCre; 20 μg; gift of R.K. Nordeen, University of Colorado) or an empty plasmid (pNull; 20 μg) in fellow eyes of <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> or BALB/c mice 3 days prior to suture placement. To achieve embryonic conditional genetic ablation of <italic>Vegfr2</italic> in the epidermis, we cross-bred <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice with <italic>K14Cre</italic> mice that constitutively express Cre recombinase in the skin epidermis and hair follicle.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S16">
        <title>Transmission electron microscopy</title>
        <p id="P27">Eyes were enucleated from wild-type and <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice and fixed in 3.5% glutaraldehyde/4% paraformaldehyde for 2 h followed by preparation of uranyl acetate- and lead citrate-stained ultrathin sections for transmission electron microscopy studies (Phillips Biotwin).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S17">
        <title>Corneal injury</title>
        <p id="P28">Two intrastromal 11-0 sutures (Mani, Japan) were placed in the mouse cornea 180° from each other. All sutures were placed in the midpoint between the limbus and the corneal apex. They were left in place for up to 14 days. Naked plasmids coding for Cre-recombinase (gift of R.K.Nordeen, University of Colorado), mouse sVegfr-2 (psVegfr-2), were utilized for <italic>in vivo</italic> enforced expression studies as shown earlier<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. To block Vegfr-3 activity, daily intraperitoneal injections of Vegfr-3 tyrosine kinase inhibitor (MAZ51, EMD Chemicals, 8 mg/kg) were performed in pCre treated <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice after corneal suture placement for 14 consecutive days. Vehicle only (DMSO) was administered as control treatment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S18">
        <title>Vegf-c neutralization</title>
        <p id="P29">Neutralizing rabbit anti-Vegf-c (Angio-Proteomie, pV1006R-r, 16 μg) antibody and control rabbit IgG (16 μg) were injected intrastromally into fellow eyes on the day of suture placement and every 3 days thereafter for 14 days.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S19">
        <title>Vegfr-2 phosphorylation assay</title>
        <p id="P30">Porcine aortic endothelial cells stably transfected with Vegfr-2 (PAE-KDR) were cultured in DMEM (Invitrogen) containing 10% FBS, penicillin G (100 units/ml), streptomycin sulfate (0.1 mg/ml) (all from Sigma Aldrich) at 37 °C, 10% CO<italic><sub>2</sub></italic> and 90% room air. Upon attaining 80% confluence these cells were serum starved for 24 h, after which time they were exposed to Vegf-a (R&amp;D Systems, 2.5 n<italic>M</italic>) or media alone (negative control) and monomeric sVegfr-1 (Reliatech, 15 n<italic>M</italic>) , monomeric sVegfr-2 (Reliatech, 75 n<italic>M</italic>), dimericVegfr-2/Fc (R&amp;D Systems, 75 n<italic>M</italic>) or IgG/Fc control (Jackson ImmunoResearch, 75 n<italic>M</italic>) for 15 min. Cell lysates were processed in RIPA buffer and resolved by SDS 8% polyacrylamide gradient gel electrophoresis (PAGE) and transferred to nitrocellulose (NC) membranes. Immunoblotting was performed using a rabbit antibody against phosphorylated Vegfr-2 (1:500, Upstate, 36-019), and loading was assessed using an antibody against Vegfr-2 (1:1000, R&amp;D Systems, AF357) and Vinculin (1:2000, Sigma, V4139).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S20">
        <title>Silver staining</title>
        <p id="P31">Vegfr-2/Fc or sVegfr-2 were resolved by SDS 10% PAGE and stained using SilverSNAP (R) Stain (Pierce) according to manufacturer instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S21">
        <title>Immuno-morphometric analyses</title>
        <p id="P32">Immunostaining and flat mounting were performed as previously shown<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> using rabbit anti-mouse Lyve-1 antibody (Abcam; 1:333), rat anti-mouse Cd31 antibody (BD Biosciences; 1:50), rat-anti-mouse Meca-32 antibody (BD Biosciences; 1:10), goat anti-mouse Lyve-1 antibody (R&amp;D, 1:100), and rabbit anti-mouse Prox-1 (Angiobio;1:500) for 48 h at 4 °C. Alexa Fluor 488 (goat anti-rabbit; 1:200) and Alexa Fluor594 (goat anti-rat; 1:200), Alexa Fluor488 (donkey anti-goat; 1:200, Invitrogen), or Cy3 conjugated donkey anti-rabbit (Jackson ImmunoResearch; 1:400) for 24 h were used as secondary antibodies. Tissue mounts were visualized under fluorescent microscopy (Leica SP-5) and analyzed with ImageJ (NIH). Mean percentage Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> (lymphatic vessels) or Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup> (blood vessels) areas were calculated for corneal flat mounts and skin whole mounts using ImageJ software. The number of Prox1<sup>+</sup> nuclei within Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> skin lymphatic vessels were counted in 12 random fields and expressed as LEC density per 100 μm. The density of lymphatic structures was determined by counting lymphatic vessel branch points per unit area (750 μm × 750 μm) on standard low-magnification Lyve-1-stained images of the mouse skin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S22">
        <title>Mouse endothelial cell culture</title>
        <p id="P33">Mouse blood endothelial cells from brain (Bend3, gift of C.D. Kontos, Duke University), pancreas (MS1) and skin (Py4, both gifts from J.L. Arbiser, Emory University) and mouse lymphatic endothelial cells (mLEC; ref. <xref rid="R60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>) were cultured in DMEM (Invitrogen) containing 10% FBS, penicillin G (100 units/ml), streptomycin sulfate (0.1 mg/ml) (all from Sigma Aldrich) at 37 °C, 10% CO<italic><sub>2</sub></italic> and 90% room air. Upon attaining 80% confluence these cells were serum starved for 24 h when supernatant fractions were collected for sVegfr-2 protein quantification by ELISA. Total RNA was also extracted for RT-PCR.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S23">
        <title>Human lymphatic microvascular endothelial cell proliferation assay</title>
        <p id="P34">Cultured human lymphatic microvascular endothelial cells (Cambrex) were maintained in EGM-2 MV (Clonetics) supplemented with 10%FBS and antibiotics at 37 °C under 5% CO2. Once confluent cells were plated at 96-well plate at a density of 30,000 cells/well. Cells were serum starved for 2 h and then exposed to media alone (MCDB 131 + 5% FBS), VEGF-C (200 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) enriched media or VEGF-C enriched media with sVEGFR-2 (13.6 μg/ml). This concentration of sVEGFR-2 corresponds to a molar ratio of approximately 11-13:1 compared to VEGF-C, and is therefore physiological in view of our finding that sVegfr-2 levels in the cornea are ~20-fold higher than Vegf-c levels on a molar basis. Proliferation was quantified using BrdU uptake (Chemicon International) at 36 h after incubation with VEGF-C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S24">
        <title>Lymphangioma proliferation assay</title>
        <p id="P35">Lymphatic endothelial cells were isolated from lymphangiomas from two individuals, 4 and 10 months of age<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, with the approval of the ethics committee of the Georg-August-University and with the informed consent of the patients’ parents. These cells were grown in EGM2-MV growth media containing 5% FBS. Cells were passaged onto a 96-well plate (5000 cells/well) in basal media (MCDB131) containing 2% FBS, and allowed to adhere overnight. Cultures were then treated with 200 ng/ml recombinant human wild-type (WT) VEGF-C (Reliatech) alone or together with 25 μg/ml of sVegfr-2 (Reliatech) in basal media with 0.1% FBS. Cell proliferation was measured after 24 h by using BrdU cell proliferation kit (Chemicon) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S25">
        <title>Western blotting</title>
        <p id="P36">Mouse cornea lysates as well as cell culture supernatant were resolved by SDS 8% or 4-20% polyacrylamide gradient gel electrophoresis (PAGE) and transferred to nitrocellulose (NC) membranes. Immunoblotting was performed using a rabbit antibody against the amino terminus of mouse Vegfr-2 (1:1000; clone T014; ref. <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), custom made sVegfr-2 specific antibody (1:1000; AA21127) and loading was assessed using rabbit antibody against human GAPDH (1:2000; Abcam).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S26">
        <title>Immunoprecipitation studies</title>
        <p id="P37">Recombinant mouse sVegfr-2 (2 μg) was incubated with mouse recombinant Vegf-c (100 ng, Biovision) in PBS at 4 °C for 1 h. Immunoprecipitation was carried out with 2 μg of an anti-Vegfr-2 antibody or an isotype control IgG. Immobilized protein A/G beads (20 μl, Pierce) were used for precipitation. Samples were boiled, resolved by SDS-PAGE with respective positive controls (rsVegfr-2 and rVegf-c) and transferred to a NC membrane. Rabbit antibodies against Vegf-c (1:1000, Santa Cruz) and Vegfr-2 (1:1000, T014) were used to probe for Vegf-c and Vegfr-2 respectively. Immunoprecipitation of Vegfr-2 from mouse plasma was performed as described previously by others <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>. Rabbit antibody against Vegfr-2 (T014, 2 μg) was employed for immunoprecipitation. T014 (1:1000), goat anti-Vegfr-2 (C) antibody (1:1000, Abcam-ab2349) or rabbit anti-sVegfr-2 antibody (1:1000, AA21127) was used for immunoblotting. Mouse LECs were incubated with media only or Vegf-c (200 ng/ml, Biovision) with or without sVegfr-2 (13.8 μg/ml) or Vegfr-1/Fc (20 μg/ml, R&amp;D Systems) for 15 min. The sVegfr-2 and Vegfr-1/Fc concentrations are equimolar. The lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-Vegfr-3 antibody (Santa Cruz, C-20), immunoblotted with anti-phosphotyrosine (Millipore, 4G10, 1:1000), and reblotted with anti-Vegfr-3 antibody (eBioscience, AFL4, 1:500).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S27">
        <title>Statistical analyses</title>
        <p id="P38">Mann Whitney U test with Bonferroni correction was used for statistical comparison of multiple variables. Comparison of corneal transplant survival was performed by Kaplan-Meier Survival. The null hypothesis was rejected at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
        <label>1</label>
        <media xlink:href="NIHMS131529-supplement-1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1239" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2">
        <label>2</label>
        <media xlink:href="NIHMS131529-supplement-2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d37e1243" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="S28">
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <p>We thank various collaborators for gifts of transgenic mice, cell lines, and plasmids; R. King, L. Xu, M. McConnell, K. Emerson, A. Blanford, M. Baker, S. Furlow, M. LaFalce and C. Long for technical assistance, and R. Mohan, F. Cambi, S. Bondada, M. Detmar, M.W. Fannon, T.V. Getchell, R.K. Jain, T.S. Khurana, B.J. Raisler, J.E. Springer, P.A. Pearson, J.G. Woodward, A.M. Rao, G.S. Rao, K. Ambati, and L. Garcia for valuable discussions. This work was supported by U.S. National Institutes of Health/National Eye Institute grants EY015422, EY018350 and EY018836 to J.A. and EY017182 and EY017950 to B.K.A.; Research to Prevent Blindness Lew R. Wassermann Merit Award (J.A.), Physician Scientist Award (J.A., B.K.A.), Medical Student Fellowship (R.J.C.A.), and departmental unrestricted grant (J.A.); University of Kentucky University Research Professorship (J.A.); Fight for Sight (R.J.C.A.); Japan Society for the Promotion of Science for Young Scientists (A.T.); VA Merit Award (B.K.A.); Department of Defense (B.K.A.). J.A. is also supported by Doris Duke Distinguished Clinical Scientist Award, Burroughs Wellcome Fund Clinical Scientist Award in Translational Research, and Dr. E. Vernon Smith and Eloise C. Smith Macular Degeneration Endowed Chair. The <italic>sVegfr2</italic> and <italic>sVEGFR2</italic> sequences are deposited in GenBank as accession numbers 1113431 and 1206797.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerbel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Angiogenesis as a therapeutic target.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>438</volume>
<fpage>967</fpage>
<lpage>974</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16355214</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmeliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Angiogenesis in life, disease and medicine.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>438</volume>
<fpage>932</fpage>
<lpage>936</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16355210</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenwick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Waterborne infectious diseases--could they be consigned to history?</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>313</volume>
<fpage>1077</fpage>
<lpage>1081</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16931751</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmeliet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Abnormal blood vessel development and lethality in embryos lacking a single Vegf allele.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>380</volume>
<fpage>435</fpage>
<lpage>439</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8602241</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Heterozygous embryonic lethality induced by targeted inactivation of the Vegf gene.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>380</volume>
<fpage>439</fpage>
<lpage>442</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8602242</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karkkainen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor C is required for sprouting of the first lymphatic vessels from embryonic veins.</article-title>
<source>Nat Immunol</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>74</fpage>
<lpage>80</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14634646</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folkman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Angiogenesis in cancer, vascular, rheumatoid and other disease.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>31</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7584949</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of vascular endothelial cell growth factor activity by an endogenously encoded soluble receptor.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>10705</fpage>
<lpage>10709</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8248162</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A novel human-specific soluble vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 1: cell-type-specific splicing and implications to vascular endothelial growth factor homeostasis and preeclampsia.</article-title>
<source>Circ Res</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>1566</fpage>
<lpage>1574</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515749</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajakumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Novel soluble Flt-1 isoforms in plasma and cultured placental explants from normotensive pregnant and preeclamptic women.</article-title>
<source>Placenta</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19010535</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambati</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Corneal avascularity is due to soluble Vegf receptor-1.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>443</volume>
<fpage>993</fpage>
<lpage>997</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17051153</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekken</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of soluble Vegf receptor 2 and characterization of its binding by surface plasmon resonance.</article-title>
<source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>252</volume>
<fpage>643</fpage>
<lpage>648</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9837760</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeltsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hyperplasia of lymphatic vessels in VEGF-C transgenic mice.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>1423</fpage>
<lpage>1425</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9162011</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joukov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A novel vascular endothelial growth factor, VEGF-C, is a ligand for the Flt4 (VEGFR-3) and KDR (VEGFR-2) receptor tyrosine kinases.</article-title>
<source>Embo J</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>290</fpage>
<lpage>298</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8617204</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalaby</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Failure of blood-island formation and vasculogenesis in Flk-1-deficient mice.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>376</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>
<lpage>66</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7596435</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashery-Padan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pax6 activity in the lens primordium is required for lens formation and for correct placement of a single retina in the eye.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>2701</fpage>
<lpage>2711</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069887</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Inflammation-induced lymphangiogenesis in the cornea arises from CD11b-positive macrophages.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>115</volume>
<fpage>2363</fpage>
<lpage>2372</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16138190</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeltsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor (Vegf)/VEGF-C mosaic molecules reveal specificity determinants and feature novel receptor binding patterns.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>281</volume>
<fpage>12187</fpage>
<lpage>12195</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505489</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The specificity of receptor binding by vascular endothelial growth factor-d is different in mouse and man.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>19166</fpage>
<lpage>19171</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11279005</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streilein</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immunosuppressive properties of tissues obtained from eyes with experimentally manipulated corneas.</article-title>
<source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>413</fpage>
<lpage>424</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8603847</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of indolinones which preferentially inhibit VEGF-C- and VEGF-D-induced activation of VEGFR-3 rather than VEGFR-2.</article-title>
<source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>268</volume>
<fpage>5530</fpage>
<lpage>5540</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11683876</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cursiefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Streilein</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Corneal lymphangiogenesis: evidence, mechanisms, and implications for corneal transplant immunology.</article-title>
<source>Cornea</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>273</fpage>
<lpage>281</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12658100</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamrah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Draining lymph nodes of corneal transplant hosts exhibit evidence for donor major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II-positive dendritic cells derived from MHC class II-negative grafts.</article-title>
<source>J Exp Med</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>195</volume>
<fpage>259</fpage>
<lpage>268</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805152</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The critical role of lymph nodes in corneal alloimmunization and graft rejection.</article-title>
<source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>1293</fpage>
<lpage>1298</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11328742</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-3 mediates induction of corneal alloimmunity.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>813</fpage>
<lpage>815</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15235599</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>VEGF-C gene therapy augments postnatal lymphangiogenesis and ameliorates secondary lymphedema.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>717</fpage>
<lpage>725</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618526</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R27">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of lymphangiogenesis with resulting lymphedema in transgenic mice expressing soluble Vegf receptor-3.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>199</fpage>
<lpage>205</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175851</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R28">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karpanen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lymphangiogenic growth factor responsiveness is modulated by postnatal lymphatic vessel maturation.</article-title>
<source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>169</volume>
<fpage>708</fpage>
<lpage>718</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16877368</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R29">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor C induces angiogenesis in vivo.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>14389</fpage>
<lpage>14394</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9826710</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R30">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Blockade of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-3 signaling inhibits fibroblast growth factor-2-induced lymphangiogenesis in mouse cornea.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>8868</fpage>
<lpage>8873</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12070340</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R31">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative evaluation of FGF-2-, VEGF-A-, and VEGF-C-induced angiogenesis, lymphangiogenesis, vascular fenestrations, and permeability.</article-title>
<source>Circ Res</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>664</fpage>
<lpage>670</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739162</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R32">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cursiefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>VEGF-A stimulates lymphangiogenesis and hemangiogenesis in inflammatory neovascularization via macrophage recruitment.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>113</volume>
<fpage>1040</fpage>
<lpage>1050</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057311</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R33">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cursiefen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lymphatic vessels in vascularized human corneas: immunohistochemical investigation using LYVE-1 and podoplanin.</article-title>
<source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>2127</fpage>
<lpage>2135</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12091407</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R34">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamrah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-3 (VEGFR-3) on monocytic bone marrow-derived cells in the conjunctiva.</article-title>
<source>Exp Eye Res</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>553</fpage>
<lpage>561</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15381039</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R35">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joukov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Proteolytic processing regulates receptor specificity and activity of VEGF-C.</article-title>
<source>Embo J</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>3898</fpage>
<lpage>3911</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9233800</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R36">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirois</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relative effects of VEGF-A and VEGF-C on endothelial cell proliferation, migration and PAF synthesis: Role of neuropilin-1.</article-title>
<source>J Cell Biochem</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>629</fpage>
<lpage>639</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11968003</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R37">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeckl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Differential binding characteristics and cellular inhibition by soluble Vegf receptors 1 and 2.</article-title>
<source>Exp Cell Res</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>241</volume>
<fpage>161</fpage>
<lpage>170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9633524</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R38">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Requirements for binding and signaling of the kinase domain receptor for vascular endothelial growth factor.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>273</volume>
<fpage>11197</fpage>
<lpage>11204</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9556609</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R39">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiesmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Crystal structure at 1.7 A resolution of Vegf in complex with domain 2 of the Flt-1 receptor.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>91</volume>
<fpage>695</fpage>
<lpage>704</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9393862</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R40">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name><name><surname>Skobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Overexpression of VEGF-C causes transient lymphatic hyperplasia but not increased lymphangiogenesis in regenerating skin.</article-title>
<source>Circ Res</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>1193</fpage>
<lpage>1199</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890974</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R41">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasioukhin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Degenstein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The magical touch: genome targeting in epidermal stem cells induced by tamoxifen application to mouse skin.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>8551</fpage>
<lpage>8556</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411913</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R42">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A naturally occurring soluble form of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 2 detected in mouse and human plasma.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cancer Res</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>326</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15235107</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R43">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor-mediated decrease in plasma soluble vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2 levels as a surrogate biomarker for tumor growth.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>521</fpage>
<lpage>529</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18199548</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R44">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsaers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerbel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple circulating proangiogenic factors induced by sunitinib malate are tumor-independent and correlate with antitumor efficacy.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>104</volume>
<fpage>17069</fpage>
<lpage>17074</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942672</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R45">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaipainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Expression of the fms-like tyrosine kinase 4 gene becomes restricted to lymphatic endothelium during development.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1995</year>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>3566</fpage>
<lpage>3570</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7724599</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R46">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Co-expression of VEGF-C and its receptors, VEGFR-2 and VEGFR-3, in endothelial cells of lymphangioma. Implication in autocrine or paracrine regulation of lymphangioma.</article-title>
<source>Lab Invest</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>1729</fpage>
<lpage>1734</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742043</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R47">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norgall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Elevated expression of VEGFR-3 in lymphatic endothelial cells from lymphangiomas.</article-title>
<source>BMC Cancer</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17584927</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R48">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilting</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Embryonic development and malformation of lymphatic vessels.</article-title>
<source>Novartis Found Symp</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>283</volume>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>227</lpage>
<comment>discussion 227-229, 238-241</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18300425</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R49">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Corneal angiogenic privilege: angiogenic and antiangiogenic factors in corneal avascularity, vasculogenesis, and wound healing (an American Ophthalmological Society thesis)</article-title>
<source>Trans Am Ophthalmol Soc</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>104</volume>
<fpage>38</fpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R50">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerjaschki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lymphatic endothelial progenitor cells contribute to de novo lymphangiogenesis in human renal transplants.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>230</fpage>
<lpage>234</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16415878</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R51">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brideau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Endostatin overexpression inhibits lymphangiogenesis and lymph node metastasis in mice.</article-title>
<source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>11528</fpage>
<lpage>11535</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18089781</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R52">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neostatin-7 regulates bFGF-induced corneal lymphangiogenesis.</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>582</volume>
<fpage>2515</fpage>
<lpage>2520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18570894</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R53">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bielenberg</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Semaphorin 3F, a chemorepulsant for endothelial cells, induces a poorly vascularized, encapsulated, nonmetastatic tumor phenotype.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>1260</fpage>
<lpage>1271</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520858</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R54">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of endogenous TGF-beta signaling enhances lymphangiogenesis.</article-title>
<source>Blood</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>4571</fpage>
<lpage>4579</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310502</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R55">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skobe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Induction of tumor lymphangiogenesis by VEGF-C promotes breast cancer metastasis.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>192</fpage>
<lpage>198</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175850</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R56">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandriota</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vascular endothelial growth factor-C-mediated lymphangiogenesis promotes tumour metastasis.</article-title>
<source>Embo J</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>672</fpage>
<lpage>682</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179212</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R57">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brakenhielm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Modulating metastasis by a lymphangiogenic switch in prostate cancer.</article-title>
<source>Int J Cancer</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>2153</fpage>
<lpage>2161</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17583576</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R58">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Suppression of tumor lymphangiogenesis and lymph node metastasis by blocking vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 3 signaling.</article-title>
<source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>819</fpage>
<lpage>825</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12048269</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R59">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>VEGF-C-induced lymphangiogenesis in sentinel lymph nodes promotes tumor metastasis to distant sites.</article-title>
<source>Blood</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>1010</fpage>
<lpage>1017</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032920</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R60">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of a novel mouse lymphatic endothelial cell line: SV-LEC.</article-title>
<source>Lymphat Res Biol</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>115</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16190815</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Loss of endogenous sVegfr-2, which antagonizes Vegf-c, leads to spontaneous corneal lymphangiogenesis. <bold>(a) </bold><italic>sVegfr2</italic> mRNA detection (purple-blue) by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in the mouse cornea. Epi, epithelium; Str, stroma. (<bold>b)</bold> sVegfr-2 immunolocalization (brown) in the mouse cornea using AA21127. Cell nuclei stained blue by hematoxylin. (<bold>c)</bold> Representative corneal flat mounts of a <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mouse (<italic>n</italic> = 30). Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> (green) lymphatic and Cd31<sup>+</sup> (red) Lyve-1<sup>–</sup> blood vessels are shown. (<bold>d,e)</bold> Immunofluorescent detection of Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> (green) Prox1<sup>+</sup> (red) lymphatic vessels in corneal whole mounts (<bold>d</bold>) and cross sections (<bold>e</bold>) of <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice. <bold>(f)</bold> Transmission electron microscopy of lymphatic vessel in cornea of <italic>LeCre/Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice. Inset (right). (<bold>g</bold>) Quantification of vessel area in corneal flat mounts (<italic>n</italic> = 20). Error bars depict s.e.m. <bold>(h)</bold> Representative western blot of samples of recombinant sVegfr-2 (rsVegfr-2) incubated with recombinant Vegf-c (rVegf-c) and immunoprecipitated with either anti-Vegfr-2 (3<sup>rd</sup> lane from the left) antibody or isotype control IgG (4<sup>th</sup> lane from the left) and immunoblotted with anti-Vegf-c antibody. sVegfr-2 and Vegf-c resolution shown on first two lanes from the left. <bold>(i)</bold> Representative immunoblot of Vegf-c-induced Vegfr-3 phosphorylation of mouse lymphatic endothelial cells. Vegfr-3 re-blot is shown. ϕ, media only. <bold>(j)</bold> Proliferation of human lymphatic microvascular endothelial cells, quantified by BrdU uptake. (<bold>f,j)</bold>, NS, not significant ;* <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, Significance by Mann Whitney U test. Error bars depict s.e.m. Scale bars: (<bold>a,b,d</bold>), 50 μm; (<bold>c</bold>) 500 μm; (<bold>e</bold>) 25 μm; left panel of (<bold>g</bold>), 1 μm; right panel of (<bold>g</bold>), 200 nm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>sVegfr-2 inhibits reparative corneal lymphangiogenesis and rejection of corneal allografts. <bold>(a)</bold> Representative western blot, 5 days after suture placement in <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mouse corneas treated with plasmid coding for Cre recombinase (pCre) or empty vector (pNull) (<italic>n</italic> = 8). Loading control, Gapdh. Bottom panel (arrows) shows Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> vessels-green 14 days after suture placement. <bold>(b)</bold> Real-time PCR of <italic>sVegfr2</italic> in the <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mouse corneas (<italic>n</italic> = 4). <bold>(c)</bold> Quantification of vessel area in corneal flat mounts of <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> and Balb/C wild-type (WT) corneas (<italic>n</italic> = 5-6) and <italic>Vegfr2<sup>loxP/loxP</sup></italic> mice corneas injected with pCre followed by systemic administration of a Vegfr-3 tyrosine kinase inhibitor (R3TKI) (<italic>n</italic> = 8<italic>)</italic>. Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - white bars; Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – black bars. <bold>(d)</bold> Representative corneal flat mounts of C57Bl/6J wild-type mouse corneas. Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - green;Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – red. <bold>(e)</bold> Quantification of vessel area in flat mounts of C57Bl/6J wild-type mouse corneas (<italic>n</italic> = 5). Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - white bars; Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – black bars. <bold>(f)</bold> Kaplan-Meier survival curves showing survival of corneal grafts in BALB/c hosts (<italic>n</italic> = 10–13). <bold>(g)</bold> Representative corneal flat mounts of transplanted mouse corneas. Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - green;Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – red. Limbus, bottom dotted-line; Recipient-donor interface, top dotted-line. <bold>(h)</bold> Quantification of corneal graft vessel area in flat mounts of transplants (<italic>n</italic> = 5). Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - white bars;Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – black bars. (NS, non-significant; *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Significance by Mann Whitney U test). Error bars depict s.e.m. Scale bars: (<bold>a,d,g</bold>), 500 μm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Endogenous Vegf-c and sVegfr-2 selectively modulate corneal lymphangiogenesis. <bold>(a)</bold> Representative color photographs of sutured wild-type mouse corneas (top). Representative flat mounts of sutured corneas. Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - green;Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – red. <bold>(b)</bold> Quantification of corneal vessel area of sutured corneas of wild-type mice (<italic>n</italic> = 8). Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, lymphatic vessel - white bars; Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, blood vessel – black bars. <bold>(c)</bold> ELISA quantification of Vegf-c/VEGF-C in wild-type mouse corneas 2 and 4 days after suture placement or implantation of pellets containing 160 ng recombinant human VEGF-C. <bold>(d)</bold> Immunobloting of sVegfr-2 secreted by transfected human embryonic kidney cells (HEK), Chinese hamster ovary cells (CHO), and mouse corneal epithelial cells (KEPI) under reducing (RED) and non-reducing (NR) conditions. M, marker; lane 1. pNull; lane 2. psVegfr-2 (RED); lane 3. psVegfr-2 (NR). <bold>(e)</bold> Silver staining of polyacrylamide gel loaded with Vegfr-2/Fc and recombinant sVegfr-2 (rsVegfr-2) and resolved under reducing versus non-reducing conditions. Dim, dimer; Mon, monomer; M, marker. <bold>(f)</bold> Corneal area occupied by blood vessels (Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>) following suture injury in wild-type mice. <bold>(g)</bold> Representative immunoblot of phosphorylated Vegfr-2 (phosVegfr-2) of porcine aortic endothelial cells stably transfected with Vegfr-2 (PAE-KDR). Reblotting for total Vegfr-2 and Vinculin are shown. ϕ, no Vegf-a. <bold>(h)</bold> Corneal area occupied by blood vessels (Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>) following pVegf-a injection. NS, not significant; *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Significance by Mann Whitney U test. n = 4–8. Error bars depict s.e.m.(<bold>b,c,f,h</bold>). Scale bar: (<bold>a</bold>), 500μm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0003"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F4" position="float">
      <label>Figure 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Loss of <italic>sVegfr2</italic> in the skin induces lymphatic hyperplasia. <bold>(a) </bold><italic>sVegfr2</italic> mRNA detection (purple-blue) by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in the mouse skin. (<bold>b)</bold> sVegfr-2 immunolocalization (brown) in the mouse skin using AA21127. Cell nuclei stained blue by hematoxylin. (<bold>c)</bold> Immunofluorescence of sVegfr-2 in the skin of newborn mice. Superficial keratin autofluorescence is seen in all instances. Cell nuclei stained with DAPI. Scale bar, 50 μm. <bold>(d)</bold> Representative whole mount of the ventral skin of P0 mice. Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> (green) lymphatic and Cd31<sup>+</sup> (red) Lyve-1<sup>–</sup> blood vessels are shown. <bold>(e)</bold> Skin area occupied by blood vessels (Cd31<sup>+</sup>/Lyve-1<sup>–</sup>, black bars) and lymphatic vessels (Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, white bars) in P0 mice. <bold>(f)</bold> Representative whole mount immunofluorescent image showing Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> (green) and Prox1<sup>+</sup> (red) lymphatic vessels of P0 mice (<italic>n</italic> = 14). <bold>(g)</bold> Lymphatic endothelial cell (LEC) density, quantified by number of Prox1<sup>+</sup> (red) nuclei per 100 μm of lymphatic vessel (Lyve-1<sup>+</sup>, green) length, in P0 mice (<italic>n</italic> = 12). <bold>(h)</bold> Quantitative branch point analysis of Lyve-1<sup>+</sup> lymphatic vessels per unit area (750 μm × 750 μm) is shown (<italic>n</italic> = 8). Scale bar<bold>: (a-d,f)</bold>, 50 μm; (<bold>e,g,h</bold>) NS, not significant; *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Significance by Mann Whitney U test. Error bars depict s.e.m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0004"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F5" position="float">
      <label>Figure 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>sVegfr-2 is produced by blood endothelial cells (BECs) and skin epithelium and circulates in plasma. (<bold>a</bold>) Representative western blots of mouse plasma immunoprecipitated with an antibody against the amino terminus of Vegfr-2 (N) and immunoblotted with either anti-Vegfr-2 (N; left), anti-sVegfr-2 (C; right) and an antibody against the carboxyl terminus of mbVegfr-2 (C; center). (b) PCR amplification of <italic>sVegfr2</italic> mRNA using cDNA derived from mouse lymphatic endothelial cells (LECs) and mouse BECs isolated from the brain (Bend3), Skin (Py4) and pancreas (MS1). Adjacent lane (H2O) shows template negative control. <italic>Gapdh</italic> was loading control (lower band), (<italic>n = 5</italic>). <bold>(c)</bold> ELISA quantification of sVegfr-2 protein in supernatant of blood and lymphatic endothelial cells (<italic>n</italic> = 3). <bold>(d)</bold> Immunofluorescence of sVegfr-2 (red) in the pulmonary microvasculature (Cd31<sup>+</sup> vessel – green). Cell nuclei stained with DAPI. Scale bar, 50 μm. (<bold>e</bold>) ELISA quantification of sVegfr-2 levels in plasma (<italic>n</italic> = 16). *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Significance by Mann Whitney U test. (<bold>c,e</bold>) Error bars depict s.e.m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0005"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F6" position="float">
      <label>Figure 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>sVEGFR-2 exists in humans and inhibits human lymphangioma cell proliferation. <bold>(a)</bold> PCR cloning of open-reading-frame of <italic>VEGFR2</italic> from human umbilical vein endothelial cells. <bold>(b)</bold> sVEGFR-2 immunolocalization (brown) in the human cornea using AA21129. Cell nuclei stained blue by hematoxylin. <bold>(c,d)</bold> Proliferation of lymphatic endothelial cells isolated from two children with lymphangioma, stimulated by VEGF-C and treated with sVEGFR-2 or bovine serum albumin (BSA), quantified by BrdU uptake. (<italic>n</italic> = 6–9); <bold>c</bold>, Patient #1 is a 4-month old child; <bold>d</bold>, Patient #2 is a 10-month-old child. NS, not significant; *, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Significance by Mann Whitney U test. Error bars depict s.e.m.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="nihms-131529-f0006"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>