<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:43:38Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3310843" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3310843</identifier><datestamp>2012-03-28</datestamp><setSpec>plosone</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3310843</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3310843</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3310843</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457725</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22457725</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-23609</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biophysics</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Toxicology</subject>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
            <subject>Chemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Chemical Biology</subject>
            </subj-group>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Polymer Chemistry</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
            <subject>Medicine</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Neurology</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Dementia</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
            <subject>Physics</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Biophysics</subject>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>MRP14 (S100A9) Protein Interacts with Alzheimer Beta-Amyloid Peptide and Induces Its Fibrillization</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Inflammation and Alzheimer's Disease (AD)</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Ce</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Liu</surname>
            <given-names>Yonggang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gilthorpe</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van der Maarel</surname>
            <given-names>Johan R. C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Medical Biochemistry and Biophysics, Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Physics, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Stem Cell and Tissue Engineering, Chongqing Medical University, Chongqing, China</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Umeå Centre for Molecular Medicine (UCMM), Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden</addr-line>
</aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Permyakov</surname>
            <given-names>Eugene A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">Russian Academy of Sciences, Institute for Biological Instrumentation, Russian Federation</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>phyzce@nus.edu.sg</email> (CZ); <email>liuyonggangcq01@yahoo.com</email> (YL)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CZ YgL JG. Performed the experiments: CZ YgL JG. Analyzed the data: CZ YgL JG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CZ YgL JG. Wrote the manuscript: CZ JG JVDM.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Department of Physics, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <elocation-id>e32953</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Zhang et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Increasing evidence supports the contribution of local inflammation to the development of Alzheimer's disease (AD) pathology, although the precise mechanisms are not clear. In this study, we demonstrate that the pro-inflammatory protein S100A9 interacts with the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide and promotes the formation of fibrillar <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e002.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-amyloid structures. This interaction also results in reduced S100A9 cytotoxicity by the binding of S100A9 toxic species to A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e003.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid structures. These results suggest that secretion of S100A9 during inflammation promotes the formation of amyloid plaques. By acting as a sink for toxic species, plaque formation may be the result of a protective response within the brain of AD patients, in part mediated by S100A9.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="7"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Knockdown of S100A9 expression improves cognition function in Alzheimer's disease model mice (Tg2576) and these animals also exhibit reduced amyloid plaque burden <xref rid="pone.0032953-Tae1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. However, a mechanistic link between S100A9 and Alzheimers disease pathology has not been shown. S100A9 protein is a reliable marker of inflammation <xref rid="pone.0032953-vanLent1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Infiltrating macrophages express S100A9 in the event of acute or chronic inflammation <xref rid="pone.0032953-Odink1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Kerkhoff1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. S100A9 and A8 are co-expressed mainly by phagocytes in a variety of inflammatory conditions, including rheumatoid arthritis, allograft rejection, inflammatory bowel, and lung diseases <xref rid="pone.0032953-Goebeler1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Rugtweit1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Inflammatory disorders such as chronic bronchitis, cystic fibrosis, and rheumatoid arthritis are also associated with elevated plasma levels of S100A9 <xref rid="pone.0032953-Roth1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Brun1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p>
      <p>It has been speculated that inflammation is directly related to Alzheimer's disease. Studies performed in transgenic animals suggest that cerebral amyloid deposition is increased in inflammatory conditions <xref rid="pone.0032953-Guo1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In these transgenic animals, amyloid plaques do not develop unless inflammation is induced. Heneka et al. reported that in certain conditions related to chronic stress, astrocytes secreting S100 proteins assemble at the site of amyloid plaques, which may serve to prolong neuroinflammation <xref rid="pone.0032953-Heneka1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. An additional report shows microglial activation in early stages of AD <xref rid="pone.0032953-Cagnin1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. These results indicate that early and local inflammatory events contribute to neuronal dysfunction and the formation of amyloid plaques at this and later stages of AD, respectively.</p>
      <p>To investigate the relationship between S100A9 and amyloid plaques, we have studied the interaction between the main component of the amyloid plaque (A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e004.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40) and S100A9 by exploring the conformational and structural transition of species generated between them by atomic force microscopy (AFM), circular dichorism (CD), polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) and the Thioflovin-T assay (ThT). We observed that, whilst retaining its native structure, S100A9 triggers and promotes the formation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e005.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-amyloid aggregates. To investigate the effect of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e006.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> mixtures on cells of neural origin, we employed the WST-1 assay on the neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cell line. Our results show that freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e007.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 is not toxic to neural cells, whereas S100A9 shows strong cytotoxicity. The addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e008.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 significantly reduces S100A9 cytotoxicity. Our study provides direct physical evidence that S100A9 triggers and accelerates A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e009.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid formation, which indicates that amyloid plaque formation is related to inflammation and may be the result of a protective response.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e010.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 fibrillization induced by S100A9</title>
        <p>A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e011.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40/S100A9 mixtures containing various additions of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e012.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 were examined using atomic force microscopy (AFM). After 1 day (d) of incubation at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e013.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C, massive aggregates were produced in the form of round-shaped oligomers, proto-filaments and elongated thick fibrils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). Randomly distributed on mica surface, the round-shaped oligomers had a diameter of 80 nm and a height of 10 nm. The proto-filaments carried a height of 2.7 nm, a width of 50 nm and an average length of 300 nm. They were dimensionally similar to those observed in the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e014.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> control samples after 3 d of incubation under the same condition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). The thick fibrils were less abundant and had a height of 8 nm, a width of 80 nm and a length in the micrometer range. It is possible that these thick fibrils are formed by the inter-twisting of protofilaments <xref rid="pone.0032953-Jos1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. After incubation for 3 d, there were no obvious transitions in the cross-sectional dimensions of these structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The proto-filaments developed into a more extended form with a width of 50 nm and a height of 2 nm. The filaments inter-connected with each other into network-like structures. The co-localization of protofilaments (2 nm in height) and mature fibrils (5 nm in height) supports our supposition that the fibrillar species are initiated from protofilaments.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g001" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>AFM images of freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e015.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.2 mM) and S100A9 protein (0.02 mM) mixture,</title>
            <p>incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e016.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for (a) 1 d; and (b) 3 d. S100A9 (0.2 mM) with (c) A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e017.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.1 mM) ; (d) A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e018.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.02 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e019.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d. The scale bars denote 1000 nm for Fig. (a), 1200 nm for (b), 600 nm for (c) and 600 nm for (d).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To identify the origin of massive aggregates, S100A9 was titrated with various concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e020.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and incubated at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e021.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). As the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e022.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 concentration was reduced, the quantity of aggregates (fibrils and oligomers) decreased dramatically. Using AFM cross-section measurements, we found that these fibrillar structures shared comparable dimensions (2 nm in height and 30 nm in width). Short proto-filaments carrying a similar cross-sectional dimension were observed for concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e023.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 as low as 0.02 mM. This similarity suggests that these fibrillar aggregates originated from A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e024.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. In conclusion, compared with the amyloid development in A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e025.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 control samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s001">Fig. S1</xref>: It took 3 d for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e026.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 to develop small quantities of amyloid fibrils with a height of 2 nm), the presence of S100A9 promotes the rate of formation and the quantity of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e027.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid species produced.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Kinetics of amyloid formation</title>
        <p>The kinetics of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e028.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid formation was monitored using the ThT-binding assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The specific interaction of ThT with cross-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e029.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet-containing amyloids, leads to an increase in fluorescence emission. The time dependence of amyloid formation depended primarily on the concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e030.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. In contrast to the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e031.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.2 mM) control samples, a sharp increase in ThT intensity was observed with the addition of S100A9 (0.02 mM). After 2 d to 3 d of incubation, the ThT intensity reached its maximum value. A plateau was attained following a decline in the ThT intensity after 7 d to 8 d of incubation. It is possible that the decline in the relative ThT value was induced by the formation of massive aggregates, which is consistent with our AFM observations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). When the concentration of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e032.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> was decreased to 0.1 mM, the relative ThT intensity dropped from 2.0 to 1.6 in spite of the increasing S100A9 concentration (from 0.02 mM to 0.2 mM). The variation in amyloid formation kinetics is consistent with the hypothesis that amyloid formation is largely induced by A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e033.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 rather than by S100A9.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g002" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>ThT and CD spectra of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e034.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.2 mM) complex.</title>
            <p>(a) Kinetics of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e035.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 mixture amyloid formation at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e036.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C monitored by the thioflavin-T assay. Rhombuses correspond to 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e037.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Squares correspond to 0.2 mM S100A9 and 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e038.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Circles correspond to 0.02 mM S100A9 and 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e039.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (b) CD spectra of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e040.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.2 mM), S100A9 (0.02 mM) and their mixture, incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e041.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 1 d.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Transitions in S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e042.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 secondary structures</title>
        <p>The transition in secondary structures during the development of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e043.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 aggregates was monitored using far UV circular dichorism (CD). The CD spectrum of the control sample containing only A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e044.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.2 mM) was dominated by random coil structure and characterized by a pronounced negative peak centered at the wavelength below 200 nm after 1 d of incubation at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e045.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0032953-Greenfield1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. With the addition of trace amount of S100A9 (0.02 mM) under the same conditions, spectra typical of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e046.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structures (centered at 217 nm) were observed. As there was no obvious secondary-structure transition for the samples containing only S100A9 or A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e047.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, we conclude that this evolution is caused by the interaction between these two proteins.</p>
        <p>To explore the effect of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e048.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide on the secondary structure of S100A9, S100A9 protein was incubated with various concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e049.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 for 3 d and 7 d. The CD spectra were characterized by two negative peaks centered at 208 nm and 222 nm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). There was little change in the spectra following the addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e050.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and incubation at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e051.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d and 7 d. The occurrence of S100A9 amyloid formation was excluded by a comparison with S100A9 samples exposed to extreme conditions (pH 3.0 and continuous shaking at 800 rpm). Under these conditions, S100A9 lost its native structure (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e052.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> -helix) and took the form of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e053.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet after 3d of incubation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s004">Fig. S4</xref>). This transition in the secondary structures of S100A9 is consistent with the downward shift of monomer and dimer band positions in SDS PAGE.</p>
        <p>The transition in the secondary structures was exaggerated, when the spectra of S100A9 alone were subtracted from the spectra of the mixtures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). Following incubation for 3 d, the difference spectra of the mixtures showed a negative peak with a minimum below 200nm, which is thought to represent random-coil structure. It is worth noting that the absolute values of the ellipticity were proportional to the input concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e054.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Prolonged incubation of the mixture with lower concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e055.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.002 mM and 0.01 mM) for 7 d resulted in a decrease in the absolute value of the ellipticity from 2 to 1. Such transition could represent a shift from random-coil to orderly structures <xref rid="pone.0032953-Anna1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Unlike other samples, when the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e056.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 concentration reached 0.02 mM, the spectra exhibited a shape that is typical for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e057.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structures. After 7 d of incubation, the negative peak shifted from 206 nm (3 d) to 217 nm. This change denotes the formation of a large quantity of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e058.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structures <xref rid="pone.0032953-Greenfield1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Anna1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Given that the difference CD spectra were obtained by subtracting the S100A9 signal, we believe the transition to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e059.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structure is induced by A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e060.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Considering the lack of transition in the SDS PAGE measurements following the addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e061.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, we believe that the S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e062.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 interaction does not result in any change in S100A9 secondary structures.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g003" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Difference CD spectra of S100A9 (0.2 mM) with the addition of various concentrations A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e063.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.002 mM to 0.1 mM)</title>
            <p>incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e064.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for (a) 3 d; (b) 7 d. The difference CD spectra are obtained by subtracting the ellipticity of the mixture with the ones containing only S100A9 (0.2 mM). (c) Ellipticity of S100A9 (0.2 mM) and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e065.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.2 mM) mixture during 9 d of incubation at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e066.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C. (d) Detailed features of panel c.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>With prolonged incubation (9 d), minor distinctions were observed in the 200 to 230 nm wavelength range (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). The two negative peaks that originate from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e067.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> -helix structures showed a tendency to fuse. After incubation for 1 d, the negative peak that centered at 222 nm nearly disappeared and an enhancement in the amplitude of the peak at 208 nm was observed. After 3 d of incubation, there was a decline in the amplitude of the negative peak and a shift in the peak position to 209 nm. The two negative peaks became even less evident when the samples were maintained at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e068.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 9 d. The distance between peaks decreased from 14 nm (208 nm to 222 nm) to 9 nm (210 nm to 219 nm). Taken together, the results from AFM, ThT and CD analyses suggest that S100A9 retains its secondary structures throughout development, and the conformational and structural changes were caused by amyloid formation from the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e069.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Effect of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e070.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 on S100A9 cytotoxicity</title>
        <p>The effect of S100A9, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e071.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and their aggregates on the viability of SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma cells was assessed using the WST-1 assay. In viable cells, WST-1 undergoes reduction by mitochondrial dehydrogenases (succinate-tetrazolium reductase system) to soluble formazan, which serves as an indicator of the number of metabolically active cells. The effect of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e072.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 on S100A9-induced cytotoxicity was investigated by pre-mixing S100A9 with various concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e073.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and incubating the samples with SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma cells for 1 d to 3 d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). During the first day of incubation, at least 0.04 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e074.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 was required to inhibit the cell cytotoxicity of S100A9 (increasing cell survival to 90% from 70%). After 2 d of incubation, a 50% increase in cell viability (from 30% to 80%) was observed for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e075.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 concentrations exceeding 0.2 mM (0.4 mM and 0.2 mM). Although the cell survival rate for all samples dropped greatly on the third day of incubation, the addition of excessive amounts of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e076.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (0.2 mM and 0.4 mM) increased the cell viability from 10% to 30%. We concluded that the cytotoxicity of S100A9 in SH-SY5Y cells is greatly suppressed by the presence of sufficient amounts of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e077.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (more than 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e078.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 for 0.02 mM S100A9).</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g004" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Measurements of NHSY5Y cell line viability by WST1 assay in the presence of 0.02 mM S100A9 and various S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e079.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 mixtures.</title>
            <p>The S100A9 concentration remained 0.02 mM. The concentration of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e080.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 addition varied from 0.02 mM to 0.4 mM. In control experiments, the cells were incubated in DMEM cell culture buffer alone and the cell viability was equal to 100%.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g004"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Characterization of the interaction between A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e081.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and S100A9</title>
        <p>To explore the interaction between S100A9 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e082.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 during incubation with cells, the mixtures and their corresponding controls (S100A9 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e083.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 only) were analyzed using sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE). No significant shifts in protein band positions were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). According to the bands generated by the control samples (containing only S100A8, A9, or culture media alone), the uppermost band corresponds to components of the media and the lower two bands represent the S100A9 monomer and homodimer, respectively. Because there was no change in the position of the S100A9 bands, it appears that S100A9 maintained its native structure during incubation with the cells. The structural stability of S100A9 was further verified by comparison with the samples exposed to harsh conditions (pH 3.0 and continuous shaking at 800 rpm). After 1 day of shaking at acidic pH, the band position of S100A9 shifted significantly, indicating the formation of more compact, faster migrating structures. A downward shift in band position corresponds to S100A9 amyloid formation, thereforem the absence of changes could indicate an absence of S100A9 amyloid formation during incubation with the cells.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g005" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Electrophoresis of S100A9 incubated with NHSY5Y cells.</title>
            <p>(a) and (c) SDS PAGE; (b) Native PAGE. Panel (a) has the following designations: column 1 corresponds to the ladder; 2 to S100A9 (0.2 mM); 3 to cell culture buffer DMEM; 4 to S100A9 (0.04 mM) with cells in DMEM for 3 d; 5 to S100A9 (0.01 mM) with cells in DMEM. In panel (b), 1 to S100A9 (0.2 mM); 2 to DMEM; 3 to S100A9 (0.04 mM) with cells in DMEM for 3 d. (c) 0.2 mM S100A9 at pH 3.0 and 7.4. The data was obtained by several experiments, and integrated together according to the ladders.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The quantities of S100A9 monomer and homodimer were estimated by integrating the intensities of all bands using Image J software. Based on the SDS PAGE data, the freshly dissolved S100A9 contained 74% monomers and 26% homodimers. After incubation with cells for 3 d, the fraction of homodimer dropped to 8.4%, which suggests that the reduction in the quantity of S100A9 dimers is caused by its interaction with cells. A similar decrease in the S100A9 dimer content was observed when S100A9 was mixed with various concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e084.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Accompanied by a dramatic increase in the quantity of large aggregates at the top of the gel, a declining intensity in the dimer bands was observed for increasing A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e085.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 doses, which indicates the consumption of S100A9 dimers by A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e086.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. The fraction of S100A9 dimers was 30% at 0.002 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e087.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, 18% at 0.01 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e088.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, 14% at 0.02 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e089.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and 10% with 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e090.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Native PAGE revealed a band for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e091.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 monomers when the concentration of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e092.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 exceeded 0.1 mM. Given that S100A9 alone contained 74% monomers and 26% homodimers, 0.2 mM S100A9 solution contains 0.15 mM monomers and 0.025 mM dimers. If A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e093.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 interacts with the S100A9 monomer, the reaction could consume at least 0.15 mM of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e094.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, which is inconsistent with the existence of an A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e095.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 band in the presence of 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e096.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Conversely, 0.025 mM S100A9 dimers could consume 0.02 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e097.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. Considering the decrease in the amount of S100A9 dimers and the absence of an A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e098.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 band for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e099.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 concentrations below 0.02 mM, we believe that there is a specific interaction between the S100A9 dimer and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e100.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 that does not involve S100A9 monomer. Moreover, there was no additional band for S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e101.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 hetero-dimer or any other visible complexes. Thus, it can be assumed that these proteins are not stabilized in low-molecular-weight structures. It is possible that S100A9 can serve at the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e102.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> nucleation or fibrillation stages. The rapid formation of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e103.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid structures contributes to the absence of specific stable complexes between S100A9 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e104.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 in low-molecular-weight forms.</p>
        <fig id="pone-0032953-g006" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Electrophoresis and gas-phase electrophoretic mobility molecular analysis (GEMMA) of S100A9 and S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e105.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 mixture.</title>
            <p>(a) SDS PAGE of S100A9 with (1) 0.002 mM; (2) 0.01 mM; (3) 0.02 mM; (4) 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e106.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and native PAGE of (5) 0.2 mM S100A9 with 0.01 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e107.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40; (6) 0.2 mM S100A9 with 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e108.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40; (7) 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e109.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40; (8) 0.01 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e110.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. The final concentration of S100A9 is 0.2 mM. The data was obtained by several experiments, and integrated together according to the ladders. (b) Size distribution of S100A9 monomer and dimer at pH 7.4 and 3.0 examined by gas-phase electrophoretic mobility molecular analysis (GEMMA). The red columns represent S100A9 at pH 7.4. The blue ones represent S100A9 at pH3.0.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The induction of the S100A9 gene was found in the brains of AD patients and AD animal models, Tg2576 and CT-Tg mice <xref rid="pone.0032953-Tae1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. This observation, together with our results, suggests that S100A9 is responsible for the formation of AD amyloid plaques. The detailed molecular mechanism remains however, unknown. Therefore, we focused our research on the role of S100A9 in A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e111.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid formation and interaction with neuron origin cells.</p>
      <p>The consequences of S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e112.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 interaction were investigated using AFM and CD. When S100A9 was mixed with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e113.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, large quantities of amyloid aggregates (fibrils and oligomers) were formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). The height of the fibrils was 2 nm, which is similar to the values pertaining to mature A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e114.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid fibrils (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s001">Fig. S1</xref>). Conformational variations with different A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e115.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> concentrations identified A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e116.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 as the origin of amyloid formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). In contrast to the lack of transition in the S100A9 secondary structure, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e117.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 is responsible for the small changes seen in CD spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). The possibility of S100A9 amyloid formation was excluded by comparing S100A9 CD spectra in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g003">Fig. 3</xref> with those of S100A9 exposed to harsh conditions (pH 3.0, shaking) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). The formation of S100A9 amyloid structure not only induced the transition to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e118.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structure accompanied by the formation of small filaments (1 nm in height), but also increased cell viability (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s004">Fig. S4</xref>). The reduction in S100A9 cytotoxicity induced by the addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e119.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 was further verified by a luminescent cytotoxicity assay of neuron cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s005">Fig. S5</xref>). Sharing the same protective effect against S100A9 cytotoxicity, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e120.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 monomer was more efficient than A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e121.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 plaques. The higher cell survival rate with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e122.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 monomers compared to the ones of the plaques is consistent with our AFM observation that S100A9 interacted with freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e123.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptides. Possibly, at the same peptide concentration, the pre-formed amyloid plaques decrease A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e124.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 monomer quantity and S100A9 consumption, which was observed as an increased cytotoxicity in the luminescent cytotoxicity assay. The A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e125.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>/S100A9 interaction was further studied using the peptides A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e126.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–16, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e127.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–14 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e128.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s005">Fig. S5</xref>). Similar to the case with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e129.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, S100A9 cytotoxicity was greatly reduced upon addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e130.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–14 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e131.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42. This was accompanied by the formation of large quantities of amyloid aggregates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s006">Fig. S6</xref>). It is worth noting that the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e132.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>/S100A9 interaction did not only inhibit S100A9 cytotoxicity, but also suppressed the toxicity of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e133.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42. In contrast, the addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e134.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–16 brought no effect on S100A9 cytotoxicity and no emergence of amyloid fibrillar structures. As the major difference between A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e135.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–16 and other A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e136.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptides is the absence of a hydrophobic core, we conclude that the hydrophobic core (L17V18F19F20A21) is essential for the S100A9 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e137.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide interaction. In summary, S100A9 interacts with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e138.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and induces A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e139.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid formation whilst retaining its native structures. This specific interaction reduces the quantity of toxic S100A9 species and thus decreases S100A9-mediated cytotoxicity.</p>
      <p>With a constant amount of S100A9 monomers, we observed a great decrease in S100A9 dimer content from 26% to 8% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Such variation reflects the consumption of S100A9 dimers via interaction with cells, which does not involve S100A9 monomers. Since S100A9, apparently via the activity of the dimmer, induces cell death, the reduction in cytotoxicity induced by the addition of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e140.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 could be related to its specific interaction with S100A9 dimers. The hypothesis is supported by titrating S100A9 with different dose of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e141.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. With increasing concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e142.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, amount of S100A9 dimer deceased dramatically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). Additionally, more aggregates are formed as indicated by the increasing band intensity corresponding to the wells. Therefore, it is possible that the interaction between S100A9 dimers and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e143.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 reduces the number of toxic S100A9 dimers, leading to an increase in cell viability.</p>
      <p>S100A9 homodimer is shown to be expressed independently during inflammation <xref rid="pone.0032953-Sunderkotter1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Hessian1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It has the ability to induce neutrophil immobilization and bind both Ca and Zn ions <xref rid="pone.0032953-Sohnle1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Kerkhoff2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Structurally, the S100A9 monomer consists of 4 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e144.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-helices (H1,H2,H3 and H4), a long carboxy-terminal tail and a hinge region between H2 and H3. Through hydrophobic interactions, the C- and N-teminus of helices (H1 and H1';H4 and H4') from two monomers make contact with each other, and form an antiparallel-packed hydrophobic core <xref rid="pone.0032953-Itou11" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Because the electron density of 28 residues in C-terminal tail is low and the residues are mostly hydrophilic, it is believed that the residues do not participate in electrostatic and hydrophobic protein-protein interactions <xref rid="pone.0032953-Itou11" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. As an exposed part of the intra-molecule hydrophobic cluster, the hinge region is identified as a target-binding site for proteins <xref rid="pone.0032953-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The interaction between A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e145.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-40 and S100A9 is possibly initiated by binding to S100A9 hinge region. According to our previous simulation results, the contact of the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e146.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12-24 hydrophobic core (L17V18F19F20A21) leads to the formation of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e147.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-sheet structures, which then act as a seed for further amyloid formation <xref rid="pone.0032953-Bennett1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Besides aggregation, proper stacking (parallel or anti-parallel) is required, which demands a specific residue sequence. The hinge region of S100A9 consists of 11 residues (Leu45-Asn55) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). Similarly to A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e148.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptides, the hinge region has a hydrophobic core (L44Q45N46F47L48), following which K (50, 51, 54) residues are positively charged and E52 is negatively charged. By electrostatic interaction, E22D23 residues pair with K50K51 residues. Such stacking allows A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e149.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide molecules to be aligned in a certain direction. As the anti-parallel stacking is energetically preferred for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e150.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid formation at physiological pH, it is plausible that A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e151.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid formation is initiated by binding of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e152.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide molecules to different sites of S100A9 <xref rid="pone.0032953-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The S100A9 homodimer is formed by anti-parallel stacking of two monomers. Accordingly, the binding of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e153.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptides to the hinge regions of two monomers provides the possibility of anti-parallel stacking. This is consistent with our assumption that the S100A9 homodimer interacts with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e154.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 and our observation of the interactions between S100A9, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e155.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24, and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e156.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 peptide. Similar to A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e157.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e158.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24, and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e159.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 amyloid formation was greatly promoted by S100A9, which emphasizes the importance of the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e160.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> hydrophobic core (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0032953.s006">Fig. S6</xref>). With no hydrophobic core (L17V18F19F20A21), A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e161.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-16 showed no obvious change upon addition of S100A9 in both AFM and Cytotoxicity experiments.</p>
      <fig id="pone-0032953-g007" position="float">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0032953.g007</object-id>
        <label>Figure 7</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Amino acid sequence alignment of S100A9 in the hinge region and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e162.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 peptide.</title>
          <p>The hydrophobic cores of both proteins are marked in red. The charged residues are indicated with their approximate charges. All sequences were obtained from the SWISS-PORT protein database [26].</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.g007"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Overall, the results of this study, combined with those in previous reports, suggest that A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e163.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid production is induced by the pro-inflammatory protein S100A9. The A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e164.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-induced reduction of cytotoxicity indicates that the formation of AD amyloid plaques could be a beneficial response to inflammation. It ameliorates the potentially destructive effects of inflammatory molecules such as S100A9. S100A9-induced A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e165.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid formation also explains the presence of amyloid plaques in normal aged brain <xref rid="pone.0032953-Price1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0032953-Hou1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Further computer simulations will be conducted to elucidate the interaction between S100A9 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e166.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptides.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Sample preparation</title>
        <p>The proteins used in these experiments were recombinant S100A9 (MRP14) and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e167.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-40 obtained from Alexo Tech AB(Umea, Sweden); A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e168.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-42 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e169.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-16 (Innovagen, Sweden). All experiments were performed with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e170.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide concentrations of 0.02 to 0.2 mM and S100A9 concentrations of 0.02 to 0.2 mM. S100A9 protein solutions were prepared in 10 mM Tris-HCl buffer at pH 7.4, and dialyzed to pH 3.0 in 20 mM Glycine buffer using Slide-A-Lyzer Dialysis Cassettes (Thermo Scientific, USA) at 4<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e171.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C. We dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e172.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide at low temperatures (ice water) following a protocol released previously <xref rid="pone.0032953-Muller1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. The chilled A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e173.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> peptide powder was initially dissolved in 10 mM NaOH at a concentration above 1 mg/ml and sonicated in an ice water bath for 1 min. Finally, a trace amount of 1 M <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e174.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> buffer was added to adjust the sample to pH7.4 and 3.0. All other chemicals were purchased from Sigma unless mentioned differently.</p>
        <sec id="s4a1">
          <title>Amyloid kinetics Assay</title>
          <p>A ThT stock solution was made by dissolving 2.5 mM Thioflavin-T (Merck-Schuchardt) in phosphate buffer (10 mM phosphate, 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.4) and filtered before use. This stock solution was diluted 50-fold in the phosphate buffer to generate the working solution. Protein samples of 10 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e175.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>L of protein sample was taken added to 300 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e176.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>L of the working solution, and was allowed to bind the ThT for 1 min. ThT Fluorescence was measured using a FluoroMax-2 spectrofluorometer (Jobin Yvon/Psex Instruments) with excitation and emission wavelengths of 440 and 48 5nm, respectively, and a slit width of 5 nm. The ThT fluorescence intensities were normalized to the fluorescence of the free dye in solution.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a2">
          <title>CD spectroscopy</title>
          <p>CD spectra were recorded with a JASCO J-720 spectropolarimeter equipped with a PTC-343 temperature controller. For each sample, 3 spectra were acquired and averaged in the range of 190 nm to 250 nm, using a 5 nm/min scan speed, and 1 nm resolution. The quartz cells had a 1 mm optical path. The contribution from the buffer was subtracted, and the results are presented in relative ellipticity. The difference ellipticity in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g003">Fig. 3</xref> was obtained by subtracting the ellipticity of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e177.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1-40 peptide (0.002 to 0.1 mM) and S100A9 (0.2 mM) complex with the ones from 0.2 mM S100A9.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a3">
          <title>Electrophoresis</title>
          <p>SDS and native polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) was carried out on 15% Tris gels. 5 volume of protein sample was mixed with 1 volume of loading buffer (1.6 ml Tris-HCl (1 M), 4 ml SDS (10%), 2 ml glycerol (100%), 1 ml <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e178.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-mercaptoethanol, 1.4 ml water and 4 mg Bromophenol blue; SDS and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e179.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-mercaptoethanol are excluded for native-PAGE). The electrophoretic separation was conducted in a Mini Protean II Electrophoresis system (Biorad, USA) with a running buffer (25 mM Tris and 192 mM glycine at pH 8.3; 0.3% SDS was added for SDS PAGE). The standard protein ladder was purchased from BioRad. Coomassie brilliant blue B7920 (Biorad, USA) (0.125 g Coomassie Brilliant Blue R-250 in 200 ml methanol, 35 ml acetic acid and 265 ml water, filtered before use) was used for staining, and the following destaining step was performed by using destaining agent (50% methanol, 10% acitic acid and 40% water) for around 2 hours with gentle agitation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a4">
          <title>Gas-phase electrophoretic mobility molecular analysis (GEMMA)</title>
          <p>The operation procedure of GEMMA instrument was as published previously <xref rid="pone.0032953-Bairoch1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. S100A9 samples at pH 7.4 and 3.0 were exchanged against 20 mM ammonium acetate buffer (pH 7.4) by centrifugal ultrafiltration in Spin-X Centrifuge Tubes (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) before loading into the capillary tube. The operation current and voltage were approximately 300 nA and 2 kV respectively.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a5">
          <title>Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM)</title>
          <p>AFM measurements were obtained with a PicoPlus AFM (Agilent) in tapping mode using a 100 nm scanner in ambient conditions. Acoustically driven cantilevers with etched silicon probes of the TESP model (diameters of 10nm and less) (Digital Instruments) were used. We applied a resonance frequency in the 170 kHz to 190 kHz range, a scan rate of 1 Hz or less, and a resolution of 512 pixels×512 pixels. Height, amplitude and phase data were collected simultaneously in trace and retrace modes to avoid scan artifacts. Amyloid samples were deposited on the surface of freshly cleaved mica (GoodFellow) for 5 min, washed 3 times with 200 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e180.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>l of DI water and dried in air at room temperature.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a6">
          <title>Cell culture</title>
          <p>SH-SY5Y (ATCC CRL-2266) were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium supplemented with 10%(v/v) FBS. Mixed cortical neuron cultures were prepared from embryonic day 16.5 rat embryos. Animals used in this study were maintained in strict accordance with the approval granted by Ume<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e181.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> Ethical Committee for Animal Experimentation (Permit Number: A107–08). The cortical hemi-spheres were quickly dissected in ice-cold phosphate saline buffers (PBS, pH 7.2) with 10 mM D-glucose. Cortices from 6–8 embryos were pooled and neurons were isolated using the Papain Dissociation System (Worthington Biochemical Corp). Viable cells were counted following staining with 0.2% (w/v) trypan blue (Gibco/Invitrogen) and plated at a density of 10,000 cells per well (100,000 cells/ml) in a 96-well black-walled imaging plate (BD Falcon). Neurons were cultured for 72 h in Neurobasal medium (Invitrogen) containing 2% (v/v) NS21 supplement (Chen et al. 2008), 0.5 mM L-glutamine, 100 units/ml penicillin and 100 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e182.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>g/ml streptomycin in a humidified incubator (37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e183.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C/5% (v/v) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e184.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4a7">
          <title>WST1 cell viability assay</title>
          <p>To evaluate cell viability, 10 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e185.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>l of WST-1 reagent was added per 100 <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e186.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>l of cell culture and samples were incubated at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e187.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 4 h. The absorbance was measured with an ELISA plate reader (Labsystem Multiscan RC) at 450 nm. Cell viability was expressed as a percentage of the absorbance in wells containing cells treated with amyloid compared to the control cells.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e188.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.2 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e189.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C</bold> for (a) 1 d; (b) 3 d. The scale bars denote 600 nm and 2000 nm, respectively. The insertions show the cross-section profile of the fibrils corresponding to the marked positions. After 1 d incubation, proto-fibrils with a height of 0.5 nm were observed. After 3 d, the surface was dominated by fibrils with a height of 2 nm, which is typical for amyloid mature fibrils. As the fibrils observed upon the addition of S100A9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032953-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) carried a height of 2 nm and the protofibrils are not necessarily related with amyloid formation, it is reasonable to conclude that the presence of S100A9 promotes the rate of formation and the quantity of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e190.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 amyloid species produced.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s001.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>CD septra</bold> (a) The transition in the secondary structures of (a) S100A9 (0.2 mM); (b) A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e191.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.2 mM). Ellipticity of S100A9 (0.2 mM) with the addition of various concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e192.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 peptide (0.002 mM to 0.1 mM), incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e193.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for (c) 3 d; (d) 7 d. The insertions denote the curves of 0.1 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e194.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 in panel (c) and (d).</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s002.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>AFM height images of S100A9 (0.2 mM)</bold> (a) incubated at pH 3.0 and 57<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e195.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C with continuous shaking at 800 rpm for 3 d; (b) incubated at pH 3.0 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e196.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d; (c) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e197.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d. The scale bars represent 500 nm, 1000 nm and 500 nm, respectively. (d) CD spectra of the corresponding samples shown in AFM: black squares correspond to Fig. (a); blue triangles correspond to Fig. (b); red circles correspond to Fig. (c).</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s003.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>Measurements of NHSY5Y cell line viability by WST1 assay in the presence of</bold> (a): freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e198.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 at pH 7.4. Different colors denote different concentrations of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e199.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40. (b): 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e200.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 fibrils, 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e201.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 fibrils and 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e202.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 plaque. A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e203.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 plaques were formed by incubation at pH 3.0 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e204.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d. To avoid pH effect, pre-formed A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e205.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> plaques were carefully dialyzed to pH 7.4. A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e206.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e207.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 fibrils were formed by incubation at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e208.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for over 10 d. (c) The relationship between the kinetics of S100A9 amyloid formation (Relative ThT: left Y axis) at pH 3.0 and the effects of S100A9 (0.02 mM) on NHSY5Y cell viability (WST1 assay: right Y axis). Before mixing with cells, S100A9 was incubated at pH 3.0 and 4<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e209.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for up to 70 d. Aliquots were taken for measurements of ThT and cytotoxicity at different time during incubation. The columns in each group correspond to 1 to 3 d of incubation with cells (In day 6 aliquots, S100A9 samples were incubated with cell for up to 2 d). (d) Measurements of NHSY5Y cell line viability by WST1 assay in the presence of S100A9 (0.02 mM) at pH 7.4 and 3.0. Different colors denote 1 d to 3 d of incubation with cells.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s004.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s005">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>(a) Luminescent cytotoxicity assay of neuron cells in presence of 0.02 mM S100A9 and S100A9/A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e210.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 mixture. S100A9 and the mixture were incubated at 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e211.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3, 6, 12 and 24 h before mixing with cells. A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e212.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–40 plaques were formed by incubation at pH 3.0 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e213.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d. To avoid pH effect, pre-formed A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e214.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> plaques were carefully dialyzed to pH 7.4 before mixing with S100A9. Utilizing cortical neuron cells, the CytoTox-Glo Cytotoxicity assay uses a luminogenic peptide substrate, the AAF-Glo, to measure the activity of dead-cell protease, which is released from cells that have lost membrane integrity. The AAF-Glo substrate cannot cross intact cell membranes and does not generate any appreciable signal from the live-cell population. (b) Measurements of NHSY5Y cell line viability by WST1 assay in the presence of freshly dissolved (1) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e215.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24; (2) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e216.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 and 0.02 mM S100A9 mixture; (3) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e217.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–16; (4) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e218.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–16 and 0.02 mM S100A9 mixture; (5) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e219.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42; (6) 0.2 mM A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e220.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 and 0.02 mM S100A9 mixture.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s005.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0032953.s006">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<bold>AFM images of</bold> (a) A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e221.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 peptide (0.2 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e222.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d; (b) the mixture of freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e223.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 peptide (0.2 mM) and S100A9 protein (0.02 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e224.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d; (c) A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e225.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 peptide (0.2 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e226.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d; (d) the mixture of freshly dissolved A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e227.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>1–42 peptide (0.2 mM) and S100A9 protein (0.02 mM) incubated at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e228.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C for 3 d. In fig. a and b, the scale bars denote 100 nm in the figure, and 1000 nm in the insertion, respectively. The scale bars denote 200 nm in fig. c and 500 nm in fig. d. With the addition of S100A9, large quantities of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e229.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 amyloid fibrils (2 nm in height) were formed, which is similar in size with the mature A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e230.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> fibrils. In contrast, only protofibrils (0.5 nm in height) were observed with A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e231.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 control samples under the same conditions (panel a). Similarly, A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e232.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> fibrils were only formed in the presence of S100A9 after 3 d incubation at pH 7.4 and 37<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e233.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>C. The average height of the fibrils in fig. d is 2 nm, which is close to the reported value for A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e234.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> amyloid fibrils.</p>
          <p>(TIF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="pone.0032953.s006.tif">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
        <p><bold>Funding: </bold>There are no current external funding sources for this study.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Tae1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tae</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Keun</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong A</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hye</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Seonghan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>S100a9 knockdown decreases the memory impairment and the neuropathology in Tg2576 mice, AD animal model.</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e8840</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20098622</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-vanLent1">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Lent</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Grevers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloetjes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mort</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Myeloid-related proteins S100A8/S100A9 regulate joint inflammation and cartilage destruction during antigen-induced arthritis.</article-title>
<source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>1750</fpage>
<lpage>1758</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055478</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Odink1">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerletti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerc</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarcsay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Two calcium-binding proteins in infiltrate macrophages of rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>330</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>82</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3313057</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Kerkhoff1">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klempt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Novel insights into structure and function of MRP8 (S100A8) and MRP14 (S100A9).</article-title>
<source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1448</volume>
<fpage>200</fpage>
<lpage>211</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920411</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Goebeler1">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goebeler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burwinkel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vollmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Expression and complex formation of S100-like proteins MRP8 and MRP14 by macrophages during renal allograft rejection.</article-title>
<source>Transplantation</source>
<volume>58</volume>
<fpage>355</fpage>
<lpage>361</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7519798</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Rugtweit1">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rugtweit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandtzaeg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Halstensen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fausa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Increased macrophage subset in inflammatory bowel disease: apparent recruitment from peripheral blood monocytes.</article-title>
<source>Gut</source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>669</fpage>
<lpage>674</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8200563</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Roth1">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teigelkamp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tummler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Complex pattern of the myelo-monocytic differentiation antigens MRP8 and MRP14 during chronic airway inflammation.</article-title>
<source>Immunobiology</source>
<volume>186</volume>
<fpage>304</fpage>
<lpage>314</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1490735</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Brun1">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haga</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Measurement of plasma calprotectin as an indicator of arthritis and disease activity in patients with inflammatory rheumatic diseases.</article-title>
<source>J Rheumatol</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>733</fpage>
<lpage>738</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8035402</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Guo1">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grass</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>de Beer</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindy</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Inflammation-dependent cerebral deposition of serum amyloid a protein in a mouse model of amyloidosis.</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>5900</fpage>
<lpage>5909</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12122052</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Heneka1">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heneka</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesinger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumitrescu</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Neuronal and glial coexpression of argininosuccinate synthetase and inducible nitric oxide synthase in Alzheimer disease.</article-title>
<source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>906</fpage>
<lpage>916</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556547</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Cagnin1">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cagnin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>In-vivo measurement of activated microglia in dementia.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>358</volume>
<fpage>461</fpage>
<lpage>467</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11513911</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Jos1">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Josè</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewan</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mario</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carol</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Helen</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The protofilament structure of insulin amyloid fibrils.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>9196</fpage>
<lpage>9201</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12093917</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Greenfield1">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasman</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1969</year>
<article-title>Computed Circular Dichroism Spectra for the Evaluation of Protein Conformation.</article-title>
<source>Biochemistry</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>4108</fpage>
<lpage>4116</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5346390</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Anna1">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anna</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Loic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Alex</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Juri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Astrid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Secondary structure conversions of Alzheimer's A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e235.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>(1–40) peptide induced by membrane-mimicking infiltrate macrophages of rheumatoid arthritis.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>330</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<lpage>82</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3313057</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Sunderkotter1">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunderkotter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beil</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Cellular events associated with inflammatory angiogenesis in the mouse cornea.</article-title>
<source>Am J Pathol</source>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>931</fpage>
<lpage>939</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1707239</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Hessian1">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hessian</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The S100 family protein MRP-14 (S100A9) has homology with the contact domain of high molecular weight kininogen.</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett</source>
<volume>371</volume>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7556608</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Sohnle1">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohnle</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Colin-lech</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiessner</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>The zinc-reversible antimicrobial activity of neutrophil lysates and abscess fluid supernatants.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>164</volume>
<fpage>137</fpage>
<lpage>142</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2056200</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Kerkhoff2">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerkhoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Klempt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Novel insights into structure and function of MRP8(S100A8 and MRP14(S100A9).</article-title>
<source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1448</volume>
<fpage>200</fpage>
<lpage>211</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9920411</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Itou11">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itou1</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The Crystal Structure of Human MRP14 (S100A9), a Ca(2+)-dependent Regulator Protein in Inflammatory Process.</article-title>
<source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>316</volume>
<fpage>265</fpage>
<lpage>276</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851337</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Xu1">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Astrid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludmilla</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Intrinsic Determinants of A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e236.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>12–24 pH-Dependent Self-Assembly Revealed by Combined Computational and Experimental Studies.</article-title>
<source>PLOS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>e24329</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21957446</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Bennett1">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arvanitakis</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Neuropathology of older persons without cognitive impairment from two community-based studies.</article-title>
<source>Neurology</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>1837</fpage>
<lpage>1844</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801647</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Price1">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeel DW</surname><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Buckles</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Neuropathology of nondemented aging: presumptive evidence for preclinical Alzheimer disease.</article-title>
<source>Neurobiol Aging</source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1026</fpage>
<lpage>1036</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19376612</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Hou1">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Solution NMR Studies of the A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e237.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>(1–40) and A<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0032953.e238.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>(1–42) Peptides Establish that the Met35 Oxidation State Affects the Mechanism of Amyloid Formation.</article-title>
<source>J Am Chem Soc</source>
<volume>126</volume>
<fpage>1992</fpage>
<lpage>2005</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14971932</pub-id></element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Muller1">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Allmaier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Determination of Molecular Weight, Particle Size, and Density of High Number Generation PAMAM Dendrimers Using MALDITOFMS and nESGEMMA.</article-title>
<source>Macromolecules</source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>5599</fpage>
<lpage>5605</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="pone.0032953-Bairoch1">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The SWISS-PROT protein sequence database and its supplement TrEMBL in 2000. Nucl.</article-title>
<source>Acids Res</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>48</lpage>
</element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>