<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:44:58Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3386896" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3386896</identifier><datestamp>2013-01-01</datestamp><setSpec>wtpa</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec><setSpec>manuscript</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9216904</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2419</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Genet</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Genet.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature genetics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1061-4036</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1546-1718</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3386896</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386896</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3386896</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22634753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2299</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">wtpa48043</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Mutations in Nicotinamide Nucleotide Transhydrogenase (NNT) cause familial glucocorticoid deficiency</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Meimaridou</surname>
            <given-names>Eirini</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kowalczyk</surname>
            <given-names>Julia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Guasti</surname>
            <given-names>Leonardo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>Claire R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wagner</surname>
            <given-names>Florian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Frommolt</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nürnberg</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mann</surname>
            <given-names>Nicholas P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Banerjee</surname>
            <given-names>Ritwik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saka</surname>
            <given-names>H. Nurcin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chapple</surname>
            <given-names>J. Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Clark</surname>
            <given-names>Adrian J.L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Metherell</surname>
            <given-names>Louise A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Queen Mary University of London, Centre for Endocrinology, William Harvey Research Institute, Barts and the London School of Medicine and Dentistry, London, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>ATLAS Biolabs GmbH Friedrichstraße 147 10117 Berlin, Germany
</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Cologne Center for Genomics (CCG), University of Cologne, Weyertal 115b, 50931 Köln, Germany
</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Royal Berkshire Hospital, London Road, Reading, Berkshire UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology, Luton and Dunstable Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, Luton, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A6"><label>6</label>İstanbul University, Istanbul Faculty of Medicine, Department of Pediatrics, Pediatric Endocrinology Unit, Istanbul, Turkey
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="CR1">Correspondence and reprint requests: Professor Adrian J.L Clark, Centre for Endocrinology, First Floor North, John Vane Science Centre, Charterhouse Square, London EC1M 6BQ, UK, Tel; + 44-20-7882-6202, Fax; +44-20-7882-6197, <email>a.j.clark@qmul.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>44</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>740</fpage>
      <lpage>742</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <license>
          <license-p>Users may view, print, copy, download and text and data- mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p id="P1">Using targeted exome sequencing we identified mutations in <italic>NNT</italic>, an antioxidant defence gene, in patients with familial glucocorticoid deficiency. In mice with <italic>Nnt</italic> loss, higher levels of adrenocortical cell apoptosis and impaired glucocorticoid production were observed. NNT knockdown in a human adrenocortical cell line resulted in impaired redox potential and increased ROS levels. Our results suggest that NNT may have a role in ROS detoxification in human adrenal glands.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>adrenal insufficiency</kwd>
        <kwd>oxidative stress</kwd>
        <kwd>reactive oxygen species</kwd>
        <kwd>familial glucocorticoid deficiency</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="United Kingdom">Medical Research Council : </funding-source>
          <award-id>G0901980(93842) || MRC_</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="United Kingdom">Medical Research Council : </funding-source>
          <award-id>G0801265(87957) || MRC_</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="United Kingdom">Medical Research Council : </funding-source>
          <award-id>G0700767(82255) || MRC_</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="P2">Familial Glucocorticoid Deficiency (FGD;OMIM 202200) is a rare autosomal recessive disorder characterized by an inability of the adrenal cortex to produce cortisol in response to stimulation by adrenocorticotropin hormone (ACTH). Patients typically present within the first few months of life with symptoms related to cortisol deficiency including recurrent illnesses/infections, hypoglycaemia, convulsions, failure to thrive and shock. The disease is life-threatening if untreated. 50% of FGD cases are caused by mutations in one of three genes; <italic>MC2R, MRAP</italic> or <italic>STAR</italic>, all encoding components of the ACTH signaling - steroidogenic pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>].</p>
    <p id="P3">To search for further causal genes in FGD we carried out SNP array genotyping using the GeneChip Human Mapping 10K Array <italic>Xba142</italic> (Affymetrix) in 9 probands from consanguineous families with FGD of unknown aetiology. Data analysis identified a candidate region, 5p13-q12 with linkage to 3 families (maximum HLOD score of 2.34). Genotyping of microsatellite markers confirmed homozygosity in this region only in affected family members and not in parents or unaffected siblings. Targeted exome sequencing of the proband from one kindred with chromosome 5-linkage identified 717 variants from the Feb. 2009 (NCBI37/hg19) human reference sequence assembly. Application of a filtration strategy (see methods) reduced the number of variants for validation to 5 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Only 1 variant, (c.1598C&gt;T;p.Ala533Val) in nicotinamide nucleotide transhydrogenase (<italic>NNT</italic>) was homozygous in the affected patient, heterozygous in his parents and absent in controls (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1A</xref>). Homozygous <italic>NNT</italic> mutations, c.600-1delG at the splice junction of intron 4/exon 5 (predicted consequence p.Tyr201PhefsX2) and c.2930T&gt;C; p.Leu977Pro within exon 20, were discovered in the two other chromosome 5-linked families (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1B</xref>). 18 further mutations in 12 kindreds were found in homozygosity or compound heterozygosity on sequencing of 100 patients with FGD of unknown cause (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary Figures 1[C&amp;D] and 2</xref>). These mutations were spread throughout the gene and included abolition of the initiating methionine, two further splice mutations and many mis- and nonsense changes. No <italic>NNT</italic> mutations have previously been described in humans and none of the reported variants have been annotated in any SNP or mutation database including the 1000 genomes project and the NHLBI grand opportunity exome sequencing project in which &gt;5,000 exomes have been sequenced [see <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">URLs</xref>].</p>
    <p id="P4">Mutation of the initiating methionine is of unknown consequence as the next methionine is at residue 132, and initiation of translation from this codon would result in a protein lacking the whole mitochondrial targeting presequence. Many of the described mutations are nonsense/frameshift and will lead to premature truncation of the protein. The remaining missense mutations, with the exception of the H365P substitution, are predicted to cause disruption to vital, highly conserved eukaryotic protein domains.</p>
    <p id="P5"><italic>NNT</italic>, a highly conserved gene, encodes an integral protein of the inner mitochondrial membrane. Under most physiological conditions, this enzyme uses energy from the mitochondrial proton gradient to produce high concentrations of NADPH. Detoxification in mitochondria of reactive oxygen species (ROS) by glutathione peroxidases depends on this NADPH for regeneration of reduced glutathione (GSH) from oxidized glutathione (GSSG) to maintain a high GSH/GSSG ratio (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). Arkblad <italic>et al</italic>. showed that <italic>C. elegans</italic> lacking <italic>nnt-1</italic> either through mutation or RNAi knockdown are more susceptible to oxidative stress (OS) because of a lowered GSH/GSSG ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. Certain sub-strains of C57BL/6J mice contain a spontaneous <italic>Nnt</italic> mutation (an in-frame 5 exon deletion), and have been reported to display glucose intolerance and reduced insulin secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. Knockdown of <italic>NNT</italic> in human PC12 phaeochromocytoma cells results in decreased cellular NADPH, decreased GSH/GSSG ratios, increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels and hence impaired redox homeostasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>].</p>
    <p id="P6">Adrenals from 3 month C57BL6/J mice carrying the <italic>Nnt</italic> mutation had slightly disorganized zonae fasciculata with higher levels of apoptosis than wild-type, C57BL6/NHsd, mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1A &amp; B</xref>). There were no observable differences between levels of the steroidogenic enzymes CYP11A1 and CYP11B1 between the two substrains however the mutant mice did have lower basal and stimulated levels of corticosterone than their wild-type counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A &amp; C</xref>). Knockdown of <italic>NNT</italic> in the human adrenocortical H295R cell line by shRNA not only increased levels of mitochondrial ROS and apoptosis but also lowered the GSH/GSSG ratio (29.95±4.77 vs 18.82±8.75 in scrambled vs knockdown cells; p&lt;0.001) implying these cells also have an impaired redox potential (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D-G</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary Figure 4</xref>). We found <italic>NNT</italic> to be widely expressed and most readily detectable in human adrenal, heart, kidney, thyroid and adipose tissue (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>) similar to murine expression profiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>].</p>
    <p id="P7">These findings suggest that the impairment of adrenal steroidogenesis and development of FGD is due to defective OS responses. OS has been implicated in the pathogenesis of many disease conditions. Of particular relevance to our patients is Triple A syndrome (OMIM 231550) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. In this condition mutations in <italic>AAAS</italic> lead to deficiency or mislocalization of the nuclear-pore protein ALADIN resulting in impairment of the nuclear import of DNA repair and antioxidant proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>] thereby rendering the patients cells more susceptible to OS. <italic>AAAS<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mice however show no such phenotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. <italic>Nnt</italic> loss in mice has been reported to lead to impaired insulin secretion and glucose-intolerance because of OS in pancreatic beta cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. Although no adrenal phenotype has previously been documented in these mice, our studies hint at a mild deficit in adrenal steroidogenesis. In conclusion our results suggest that, at least in humans, NNT is of primary importance for ROS detoxification in adrenocortical cells, highlighting the susceptibility of the adrenal cortex to this type of pathological damage. Over time patients may develop other organ pathologies related to impaired anti-oxidant defence and will therefore need careful monitoring.</p>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
        <label>1</label>
        <media xlink:href="NIHMS48043-supplement-1.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e392" position="anchor" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="S1">
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We would like to thank Janine Altmüller for running the sample on GAIIx, Gudrun Nürnberg for doing the linkage analysis, the NHLBI GO Exome Sequencing Project and its ongoing studies which produced and provided exome variant calls for comparison: the Lung GO Sequencing Project (HL-102923), the WHI Sequencing Project (HL-102924), the Broad GO Sequencing Project (HL-102925), the Seattle GO Sequencing Project (HL-102926) and the Heart GO Sequencing Project (HL-103010).</p>
      <p>This work has been supported by the Medical Research Council UK (New Investigator Research Grant G0801265 to LAM, Clinical Research Training Fellowship Grant G0901980 to CRH and project grant G0700767 to PK).</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1">
        <p id="P8"><bold>Disclosure statement:</bold> The authors have nothing to disclose.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="FN2">
        <p id="P9">URLs</p>
        <p id="P10">1000 Genomes, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.1000genomes.org/">http://www.1000genomes.org/</ext-link></p>
        <p id="P11">Exome Variant Server, NHLBI Exome Sequencing Project (ESP), Seattle, WA (URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evs.gs.washington.edu/EVS/">http://evs.gs.washington.edu/EVS/</ext-link>) [January 2012 accessed].</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Best Pract. Res. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>159</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19500760</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Metherell</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>166</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15654338</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Metherell</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>3865</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19773404</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arkblad</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Free Radic. Biol. Med</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1518</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toye</surname>
              <given-names>A.a.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>675</fpage>
          <lpage>686</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729571</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Freeman</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>806</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17052203</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fei</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>1817</volume>
          <fpage>410</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22226918</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dezso</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>BMC Biol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>AI</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>4465</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11904358</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Walker</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>742</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15060018</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooray</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Endocr Dev</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18493136</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hirano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>2298</fpage>
          <lpage>303</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467144</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Storr</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Mol. Endocrinol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>2086</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855093</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huebner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1879</fpage>
          <lpage>87</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Knockout or knockdown of NNT increases levels of mitochondrial ROS and apoptosis. <bold>A</bold> Adrenal zonation and steroidogenesis in 6NHsd and 6J mice. Wt and Nnt mutant mice showed similar patterns of CYP11A1 (red) and -B1 (green) staining, indicating no significant differences in zonation or steroidogenic capacity. The ZF cells in 6J mice however are slightly hyperplastic and disorganised being more densely packed and lacking the linear architecture seen in wt ZF. 40× magnification. <bold>B</bold> Increased apoptosis in 6J mice. Adrenals from 6J showed a higher number of caspase 3 positive cells (red) in zona fasciculata than 6NHsd. <bold>C</bold> Corticosterone levels in 6NHsd and 6J mouse serum stimulated with ACTH. Radioimmunoassay results revealed both basal and stimulated corticosterone levels were lower in 6J (p&lt; 0.05). <bold>D</bold> Stable NNT knockdown (NNT-KD) in H295R cells. RT-PCR (i) and western blot analysis (ii) confirmed knockdown of NNT mRNA (71%) and protein (78%) levels in KD compared to SCR. <bold>E</bold> Detection of superoxide production by Mitosox. Quantitative analysis showed a significant increase (p&lt;0.005) in superoxide production in NNT-KD relative to SCR cells. <bold>F</bold> Densitometric analysis showed a significant (p&lt;0.001) increase in cleaved PARP between SCR and NNT-KD cells. Values are intensities of cleaved PARP relative to actin, n=12. <bold>G</bold> The GSH/GSSG ratio was lower in NNT-KD vs SCR cells (p&lt;0.001). OS induced by the addition of 40μM menadione to the SCR cells reduced the ratio to 0.69±0.67.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="ukmss-48043-f0001"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="landscape">
      <?legal?>
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title><italic>NNT</italic> mutations in 15 kindreds with Familial Glucocorticoid Deficiency</title>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleotide change</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein change</th>
            <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon (intron)</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein domain and/or consequence</th>
            <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zygosity</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN2">b</xref></sup></td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1598C&gt;T];[1598C&gt;T]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Ala533Val];[Ala533Val]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11;11</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">a</xref></sup></td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[600-1delG];[600-1delG]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Tyr201LysfsX1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">*</xref>];[Tyr201LysfsX1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">*</xref>]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intron4/exon5</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">premature truncation aa 202</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">a</xref></sup></td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[2930T&gt;C];[2930T&gt;C]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Leu977Pro];[Leu977Pro]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20;20</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleotide binding</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1310C&gt;T];[1669C&gt;T]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Pro437Leu];[Gln557X]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10;12</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane;truncation aa 557</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound het</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1147C&gt;T];[1147C&gt;T]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Gln383X];[Gln383X]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9;9</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">premature truncation aa 383</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1094A&gt;C];[1094A&gt;C]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[His365Pro];[His365Pro]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8;9</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial matrix</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[2032G&gt;A];[2585G&gt;A]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Gly678Arg];[Gly862Asp]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14;17</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane;transmembrane</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound het</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1A&gt;G];[1A&gt;G]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Met1?];[Met1?]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2;2</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">initiating Met&gt;Val</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1107-1110delTCAC];[3027T&gt;G]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[His370X];[Asn1009Lys]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9;19</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">premature truncation aa 370;nucleotide binding</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1355delA];[1355delA]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Gln452ArgfsX44];[Gln452ArgfsX44</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10;10</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fs &amp; premature truncation aa 496</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[578G&gt;A];[578G&gt;A]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Ser193Asn];[Ser193Asn]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4;4</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial matrix</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[63delG];[1864-1G&gt;T]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Ser22ProfsX6];[Ile622AspfsX1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">*</xref>]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2;14</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fs &amp; premature truncations aa 28 &amp; 623</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound het</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1069A&gt;G];[2637delA]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Thr357Ala];[Met880X]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7;18</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial matrix;premature truncation aa 880</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound het</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[3022G&gt;C];[3022G&gt;C]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Ala1008Pro];[Ala1008Pro]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21;21</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleotide binding</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">homo</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.[1990G&gt;A];[2293+1G&gt;A]</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.[Gly664Arg];[Thr689LeufsX320<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">*</xref>]</td>
            <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14;15</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmembrane;fs &amp; premature truncation aa 984</td>
            <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound het</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="TFN1">
          <label>a</label>
          <p id="P12">kindreds 1,2 and 3 had linkage to 5p13-q12</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="TFN2">
          <label>b</label>
          <p id="P13">the proband from kindred 1 was subjected to targeted exome sequencing</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="TFN3">
          <label>*</label>
          <p id="P14">predicted result if exon skipped, fs=frameshift, aa=amino acid, homo=homozygous mutation, compound het=compound heterozygous mutations.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>