<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:46:52Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3531731" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3531731</identifier><datestamp>2012-12-28</datestamp><setSpec>jbc</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Biol. Chem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jbc</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBC</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>9650 Rockville Pike, Bethesda, MD 20814, U.S.A.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3531731</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3531731</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3531731</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23144454</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">M112.372540</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.372540</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Membrane Biology</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cortactin Controls Surface Expression of the Voltage-gated Potassium Channel K<sub>V</sub>10.1</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="short">Cortactin Controls K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Functional Expression</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Herrmann</surname>
            <given-names>Solveig</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>‡</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ninkovic</surname>
            <given-names>Milena</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>§</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kohl</surname>
            <given-names>Tobias</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>§</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lörinczi</surname>
            <given-names>Éva</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>§</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pardo</surname>
            <given-names>Luis A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>‡</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1">From the <label>‡</label>Oncophysiology Group and </aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>§</label>Department of Molecular Biology of Neuronal Signals, Max-Planck Institute of Experimental Medicine, Hermann-Rein-Str. 3, 37075 Göttingen, Germany</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>4</label> To whom correspondence should be addressed: <addr-line>AG Onkophysiologie, Max-Planck-Institut für experimentelle Medizin, Hermann-Rein-Str. 3, 37975 Göttingen, Germany.</addr-line> Tel.: <phone>49-551-3899-646</phone>; Fax: <fax>49-551-3899644</fax>; E-mail: <email>pardo@em.mpg.de</email>.</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="supported-by" id="FN1">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>Present address: Dept. of Neurosurgery, Georg August University Medical Center, Göttingen, Germany.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="supported-by" id="FN2">
          <label>2</label>
          <p>Present address: Dept. of Cardiology &amp; Pneumology, Translational Cardiology, Georg August University Medical Center, Göttingen, Germany.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="supported-by" id="FN3">
          <label>3</label>
          <p>Present address: Dept. of Cell Physiology and Pharmacology, University of Leicester, Leicester, UK.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
      <volume>287</volume>
      <issue>53</issue>
      <fpage>44151</fpage>
      <lpage>44163</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2012 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <license-p><italic>Author's Choice</italic>—Final version full access.</license-p>
          <license-p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author Choice Articles</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zbc05312044151.pdf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
        <p><bold>Background:</bold> K<sub>V</sub>10.1 is a potassium channel expressed in the brain and important for non-neural tumorigenesis.</p>
        <p><bold>Results:</bold> An interaction between the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and the proline-rich domain of cortactin stabilizes the channel at the plasma membrane.</p>
        <p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> Cortactin interacts with K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and controls surface expression of the channel.</p>
        <p><bold>Significance:</bold> Our findings provide a functional and mechanistic link between the functions of two oncology-relevant proteins.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>K<sub>V</sub>10.1 is a voltage-gated potassium channel aberrantly expressed in many cases of cancer, and participates in cancer initiation and tumor progression. Its action as an oncoprotein can be inhibited by a functional monoclonal antibody, indicating a role for channels located at the plasma membrane, accessible to the antibody. Cortactin is an actin-interacting protein implicated in cytoskeletal architecture and often amplified in several types of cancer. In this study, we describe a physical and functional interaction between cortactin and K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Binding of these two proteins occurs between the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and the proline-rich domain of cortactin, regions targeted by many post-translational modifications. This interaction is specific for K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and does not occur with K<sub>V</sub>10.2. Cortactin controls the abundance of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the plasma membrane and is required for functional expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 channels.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Ion Channels</kwd>
        <kwd>Membrane Proteins</kwd>
        <kwd>Potassium Channels</kwd>
        <kwd>Protein Assembly</kwd>
        <kwd>Protein-Protein Interactions</kwd>
        <kwd>Trafficking</kwd>
        <kwd>Cortactin</kwd>
        <kwd>K<sub>V</sub>10.1</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Actin cytoskeleton remodeling is crucial for many cellular processes such as migration, invasion, endocytosis, or cell cycle progression. Cortactin (CTTN)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN4"><sup>5</sup></xref> therefore plays a central role in these processes, because it interacts with the cortical actin network and is able to alter it (see for example, Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). To fulfill this role, CTTN requires the interplay of several functional domains and different binding partners as well as post-translational modifications. CTTN binds F-actin through the actin binding repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) and regulates its polymerization via binding and activation of the Arp2/3 complex at the CTTN N-terminal acidic domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). This region is followed by an α-helical domain including a calpain cleavage site and a proline-rich region, which harbors multiple tyrosine, threonine, and serine phosphorylation sites. Many kinases, including Src, are reported to act on these sites to control CTTN function in response to intracellular signaling cascades. Therefore, CTTN is thought to act as a key regulator transmitting kinase signaling toward actin remodeling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). At its extreme C terminus, CTTN possesses a Src homology 3 domain (SH3), where binding of several interacting partners is observed, linking CTTN to several additional cell signaling pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>Lately, CTTN has been reported to affect the voltage-gated potassium channel K<sub>V</sub>1.2 and the large conductance calcium- and voltage-activated potassium channel, K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 (BK, <italic>KCNMA1</italic>), by altering their surface expression or conducting properties, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). It has been proposed that these processes are due to a CTTN-mediated linkage of these ion channels with the cytoskeleton. At least for K<sub>V</sub>1.2, this seems to be a phosphorylation-dependent process, which influences receptor-mediated endocytosis of this channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>).</p>
      <p>The voltage-gated potassium channel K<sub>V</sub>10.1 has attracted particular interest for its ability to transform cells and its resulting oncological relevance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). This behavior has been partially attributed to the role of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in cell cycle control downstream of p53 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Blocking K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in MCF-7 cells arrests them in the G<sub>1</sub> phase of the cell cycle and inhibits expression of cell cycle-related genes such as cyclin D1 (<italic>CCND1</italic>) and E (<italic>CCNE</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). On the other hand, K<sub>V</sub>10.1 itself is regulated during the cell cycle and it shows altered conductive properties and reduced current in the M phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). This regulation process is thought to be induced by alterations of the interaction of the ion channel with the cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this study, we identified CTTN as an interaction partner of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 <italic>in vivo</italic> and confirmed this with different approaches. Our results clearly show that CTTN expression is essential for the surface expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and it dramatically influences the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current by regulating its membrane localization. Given that CTTN is often overexpressed in cancer (being part of the well described 11q3 amplicon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>)) and linked to tumor invasiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>), CTTN and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 could have a synergistic effect on their transforming properties. CTTN might serve to connect K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and central signaling pathways in the cell, for example, during the cell cycle.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title>
      <sec>
        <title/>
        <sec>
          <title/>
          <sec>
            <title>Yeast Two-hybrid</title>
            <p>The yeast reporter strain L40 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) (<italic>MATa, trp1, leu2, his3, LYS</italic>::<italic>lexA-HIS3, URA3::lexA-lacZ</italic>) was transformed with pLexN-K<sub>V</sub>10.1 by the lithium acetate method and grown on synthetic medium lacking tryptophan. Following further transformation with plasmid pVP16-3-cDNA (postnatal 8 rat brain cDNA library, kindly provided by Nils Brose), double transformants were plated on synthetic medium lacking histidine, leucine, uracil, lysine, and tryptophan and in the presence of the competitive inhibitor of the HIS3 protein 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole. Positive colonies were picked after 4–6 days and tested for β-galactosidase activity using the plate assay. Plasmids from positive clones were rescued and transformed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain HB101. <italic>E. coli</italic> cells were plated on leucine-lacking medium. Positive clones were further analyzed by yeast retransformation and DNA sequencing.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Expression and Purification of GST-tagged Proteins</title>
            <p>Full-length CTTN (accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_005231.3">NM 005231.3</ext-link>) or fragments N-term (residues 1–329), N-term-H (residues 1–400), HP (residues 360–495) and SH3 (residues 475–551) were cloned into pGEX-4T-1 (GE Healthcare) expression vector to introduce an N-terminal GST tag. Expression was performed in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(D3) after induction with 0.05 m<sc>m</sc> isopropyl 1-thio-β-<sc>d</sc>-galactopyranoside for 3 h at 37 °C. Cells were harvested and resuspended in 10 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 1 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA. After treatment with 0.1 mg/ml of lysozyme on ice, cells were sonicated (Sonotrode TT13). The soluble fraction was supplemented with protease inhibitors and used for further purification with glutathione-agarose beads (Sigma) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Quality and quantity of purified proteins was checked using SDS-PAGE.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Cell Culture and Transfection</title>
            <p>HeLa cells were cultured in minimal essential medium + GlutaMax (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FCS (PAA), HEK293 cells in DMEM/F-12 + GlutaMax (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FCS and Zeocin (Cayla; 300 μg/ml) in the case of the stable cell line HEK293/K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS (HEK-BBS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>)) at 10% CO<sub>2</sub> and 37 °C. Proliferation was determined with alamarBlue as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>).</p>
            <p>Transfection was performed using Lipofectamine 2000 or Lipofectamine (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Knockdown of CTTN was induced by transfection with siRNA against human CTTN (Dharmacon), “all stars” negative control siRNA (Qiagen) was used to control for off-target effects. For the expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.x-BBS and CTTN (with or without fusion to Venus), sequence coding for these proteins were cloned in pcDNA3 or pECFP-N1 vectors. Empty vectors were used as controls.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Fractional Labeling, Quantification, and Purification of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS</title>
            <p>K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS is a tagged K<sub>V</sub>10.1 channel that carries the bungarotoxin-binding site from the acetylcholine receptor inserted in the extracellular loop between transmembrane segments 3 and 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Labeling of whole cell K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was performed in cell lysates in buffer LP (20 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 5 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1% Nonidet P-40, protease inhibitors (Roche Applied Science)) with α-bungarotoxin-biotin (α-BTX-biotin) conjugate (Invitrogen) at a final concentration of 0.2 μg/ml for 30 min on ice. To detect membrane and/or internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, living cells (HEK-BBS) were incubated in media supplemented with α-BTX-biotin conjugate at a final concentration of 2.5 μg/ml and kept at room temperature for 10 min (membrane) or at 37 °C for 1 h (internalized). For internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, cells were washed with ice-cold acid wash buffer (150 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, pH 3.0) for 3 min to remove membrane labeling of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. Twice washing with cold PBS removed the residual α-BTX-biotin conjugate. Cells were then harvested and lysed with LP buffer for 20 min on ice. The insoluble fraction was removed by centrifugation at 18,000 × <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C, and the supernatant was used for ELISA or pull-down experiments. K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes injected with the corresponding cRNA was processed in the same way as that from HEK-BBS cells.</p>
            <p>For pulldown approaches, labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was bound to streptavidin-coated magnetic beads (T1, Invitrogen) for at least 30 min at 4 °C. Unbound protein was removed by washing twice with a stringent series of four washing buffers (1, LP; 2, 1% dioxane, 0.5% Nonidet P-40, 300 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 5 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA; 3, 10% dioxane, 0.1% Nonidet P-40, 1 <sc>m</sc> NaCl, 50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 5 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA; and 4, TBS).</p>
            <p>Quantification of the amount of labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was performed by ELISA. After labeling, total cell lysates (30 and 150 μg of protein), were immobilized on streptavidin-coated plates (Pierce) and detected using a C-terminal monoclonal anti-K<sub>V</sub>10.1 antibody (Ab33, 5 μg/ml) and a polyclonal anti-mouse secondary antibody (Pierce, 1:500) coupled to peroxidase. ABTS (Invitrogen) was used as a substrate for development and detected in a Wallac Victor2 reader at 405 nm (reference 490 nm). Experiments were performed in duplicate.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Pull-down Experiments</title>
            <p>For immunoprecipitation, rat brain lysates (800 μg of total protein) were incubated overnight at 4 °C with 2–5 μg of antibody (anti-K<sub>V</sub>10.1 33/62 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>); anti-CTTN (Millipore); or nonspecific mouse IgG κ2b) in buffer A (0.5% Triton X-100, 25 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 75 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 2.5 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA and protease inhibitors (Roche Applied Science)). Pull down was performed by adding 20 μl of Protein G/A-coated Sepharose beads (Calbiochem) for 2 h at 4 °C under rotation. After washing five times with buffer A, bound protein was eluted at 70 °C for 10 min using LDS sample buffer containing reducing agent (Invitrogen) and analyzed by SDS-PAGE (Invitrogen) and Western blotting.</p>
            <p>To test binding to CTTN (full-length or partial domains), the GST-tagged constructs were incubated with K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS immobilized on streptavidin-coated beads (Invitrogen), in PBS supplemented with protease inhibitors (Roche Applied Science) overnight at 4 °C. Unbound protein was washed away in five washing steps (PBS) before eluting specifically bound proteins by incubation at 70 °C for 10 min using LDS sample buffer containing reducing agent (Invitrogen). Eluted proteins were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (Invitrogen) and Western blotting.</p>
            <p>All pull-down and immunoprecipitation experiments were performed at least three times independently with essentially identical results. The figures show representative examples.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Electrophysiology</title>
            <p>Recordings on <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes were performed as described in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref> using a Turbo TEC-10CD amplifier (NPI electronics). cRNA was synthesized using the mMessage mMachine kit (Ambion) according to the manufacturer's instructions. 0.1–1 ng of cRNA per oocyte were microinjected 1–3 days prior to recording. When not otherwise indicated, 5 ng of the phosphorothioate antisense oligodeoxynucleotide (PTO; CAGTCGTCTGTCTCATCTG; Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) was injected to deplete CTTN. The sense oligodeoxynucleotide served as control. Cells were kept at 18 °C in ND 96 solution (96 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 2 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 0.2 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 m<sc>m</sc> Hepes/NaOH, pH 7.5) supplemented with theophylline (0.5 m<sc>m</sc>) to avoid maturation of the oocytes. For voltage clamp recordings, pipettes had resistances ranging from 0.5 to 1.2 <sc>m</sc>Ω when filled with 2 <sc>m</sc> KCl. External solution (NFR) contained 115 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 2.5 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 1.8 m<sc>m</sc> CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 m<sc>m</sc> Hepes/NaOH (pH 7.2). Current was digitized at 5 kHz and filtered at 1 kHz. Where relevant, voltage pulse protocols are described in the figure legends. Current amplitudes were compared by non-paired Student's <italic>t</italic> test. <italic>p</italic> values below 0.05 were considered statistically significant. Asterisks in the figures indicate <italic>p</italic> values (*, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.005).</p>
            <p>Non-stationary noise analysis was carried out using an EPC9 patch clamp amplifier (HEKA Electronics) in the outside-out configuration on macropatches of <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Intracellular solution contained 100 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> EGTA, 10 m<sc>m</sc> Hepes/KOH (pH 7.2). NFR was used as external measuring solution. Patches were held at a holding potential of −80 mV. Average currents were determined from at least 300 consecutive identical test pulses to +40 mV, and variance was calculated with PulseTools software (HEKA Electronics). Number of channels (N) and single channel currents (i) were determined from the variance (σ<sup>2</sup>) <italic>versus</italic> amplitude (<italic>I</italic>) plot using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Equation 1</xref>,
<disp-formula id="FD1"><graphic xlink:href="zbc05312-3530-m01"/></disp-formula> where σ<sub>0</sub><sup>2</sup> represents the baseline variance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>).</p>
            <p>Data acquisition and analysis was performed with Pulse-PulseFit, PulseTools (HEKA Electronics), and IgorPro (WaveMetrics). All experiments were performed on oocytes from at least two different animals. The number of individual recordings is indicated in the figures.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Microscopy</title>
            <p>HEK293 cells were plated in Nunc chambers (LabTek Chamber Slides 177399) and transfected with BBS-tagged constructs of K<sub>V</sub>10.x using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Labeling was performed 24 h after transfection for 1 h at 37 °C by adding Alexa Fluor 555-BTX conjugate (2 μg/ml, Invitrogen) to the culture medium. After five washing steps with ice-cold PBS, live cell imaging was performed on a Zeiss Axiovert 200M microscope.</p>
            <p>For confocal microscopy, HeLa cells were grown on glass coverslips, transfected, and fixed 24 h after transfection in 4% paraformaldehyde in PBS for 10 min at room temperature. Permeabilization was performed using 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS for 10 min at room temperature. Nonspecific binding sites were blocked with 0.5% gelatin in PBS for 30 min at room temperature. To visualize K<sub>V</sub>10.x-BBS, permeabilized cells were treated with Alexa 555-BTX conjugate (0.5 μg/ml, Invitrogen) for 1 h, washed thoroughly with PBS, and mounted with ProLong Gold Antifade Reagent (Invitrogen). To detect focal adhesion kinase (FAK) a mouse anti-FAK (BD Biosciences) antibody was used according to the manufacturer's instructions, with a secondary antibody conjugated to Alexa Fluor 555 (Invitrogen). Image acquisition was performed using a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta confocal microscope, and analysis was carried out with Fiji.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec>
        <title/>
        <sec>
          <title/>
          <sec>
            <title>K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN Interact Directly in Vitro via the Proline-rich Region of CTTN</title>
            <p>To identify interacting partners of K<sub>V</sub>10.1, we performed yeast two-hybrid screens using a rat brain expression library. Full-length K<sub>V</sub>10.1 fused to the DNA binding domain of the bacterial LexA transcription factor was used as bait to screen a rat brain cDNA library fused to the activation domain of the VP16 transcription factor. Of 2 million screened clones, eight were positive for the <italic>HIS3</italic> marker. After sequencing, one of the clones was found to contain the coding sequence for CTTN. Co-immunoprecipitation studies on native tissue confirmed the interaction of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN. Immunoprecipitation of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 co-precipitated CTTN and, in the converse experiment, antibodies against CTTN precipitated K<sub>V</sub>10.1 from rat brain lysates, indicating that physical interaction between CTTN and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 occurs <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 1.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Co-immunoprecipitation of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN from rat brain lysates.</bold> Protein extract from rat brain was subjected to immunoprecipitation using Sepharose-linked antibodies against K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (Ab 62/33), CTTN or isotype control IgG (<italic>IgG</italic>κ<italic>2b</italic>). Protein A/G-Sepharose beads alone served as an additional negative control (<italic>blank</italic>). The immunoprecipitated materials were then analyzed subsequently by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting with either (<italic>A</italic>) rabbit anti-K<sub>V</sub>10.1 or (<italic>B</italic>) mouse anti-CTTN antibodies.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300001"/>
            </fig>
            <p>To study the determinants for interaction, we generated tagged proteins for pull-down assays: an N-terminal GST-CTTN fusion protein (purified from bacteria) and an BTX-binding site (BBS)-labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1. The labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1 construct was generated by inserting BBS between transmembrane segments 3 and 4. This construct has been confirmed to elicit currents similar to wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and been exposed to the extracellular milieu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was stably expressed in HEK 293 cells and pulled down using streptavidin-coated beads. The resulting purified K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was able to precipitate the GST-CTTN fusion protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>) but not GST alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>), confirming the interaction between these two tagged proteins. In this type of experiment, we also observed some co-precipitation when using K<sub>V</sub>10.2, the closest relative to K<sub>V</sub>10.1, but the specific signal was much weaker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>A</italic>).</p>
            <fig id="F2" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 2.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>K<sub>V</sub>10.1 is able to pull down CTTN <italic>in vitro</italic>.</bold> K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS or K<sub>V</sub>10.2-BBS were labeled with BTX-biotin (+Bb) in lysates of HEK293 cells expressing either K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS or K<sub>V</sub>10.2-BBS, pulled down, and washed rigorously using streptavidin-coated beads. The streptavidin-precipitated proteins were then used in pull-down experiments with various GST-CTTN fusion proteins that were then analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by immunoblotting using an anti-GST antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic>, and <italic>D</italic>) or Coomassie staining (<italic>E</italic>). Unlabeled cell lysates served as a negative control (−Bb). Both K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and K<sub>V</sub>10.2 were able to precipitate the full-length GST-CTTN (<italic>A</italic>) but not GST alone (<italic>B</italic>). <italic>C,</italic> schematic representation of the various CTTN domain GST-tagged proteins using pull-down assays with K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. Of these CTTN-domain containing fusions only the HP region was precipitated by K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS (<italic>D</italic>). Specific pull down of GST-HP-region of CTTN by K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was also confirmed in Coomassie stained gels (<italic>E</italic>).</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300002"/>
            </fig>
            <p>To narrow down the region responsible for mediating the interaction between these proteins, we constructed fragments of CTTN based on the functional domains described for this protein: the N-terminal acidic domain and the neighboring actin binding repeats responsible for actin binding and polymerization, and the proline-rich region, which is flanked by a helical and a classical SH3 domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Thus, we designed four CTTN fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>C</italic>): -N-term (residues 1–329), spanning the N-terminal acidic domain and the actin repeats; -N-term-H (residues 1–400), which adds the helical region to N-term; -HP (residues 360–495), corresponding to the helical and proline-rich regions; and -SH3 (residues 475–551), namely the classical SH3 domain of CTTN.</p>
            <p>Three of these constructs (N-term, HP, and SH3) were cloned in the pLexN vector and tested in the yeast two-hybrid system for interaction with K<sub>V</sub>10.1 domains in pVP16–4: N terminus, (residues 1–220), C terminus, (residues 478–963), or full-length K<sub>V</sub>10.1. We did not detect interactions with the N-term or HP constructs. In this approach, the SH3 domain could not be evaluated because it showed autoactivation activity.</p>
            <p>We then tested the ability of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 to pull down the purified GST-tagged CTTN domains. Only GST-HP clearly showed interaction to K<sub>V</sub>10.1, whereas no or only a very weak signal was detected in GST-N-term, GST-N-term-H, or GST-SH3 pull-down (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>D</italic>). We were also able to detect binding of the HP region to K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in a large scale pull-down followed by Coomassie stain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>E</italic>). This result strongly suggests that the interaction between K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN interaction occurs through the proline-rich region of CTTN.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>CTTN Influences K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated Current</title>
            <p>Having established that CTTN and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 interact directly, we asked next if there is a functional consequence associated with this interaction. CTTN is known to regulate the current through K<sub>V</sub>2.1 (by altering its surface expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>)) and K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 (BK, by changing its interaction with the actin cytoskeletal and thereby the open probability of the channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>)).</p>
            <p>To test whether the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current was affected, we manipulated the levels of CTTN in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1. To increase CTTN levels, we injected cRNA encoding human CTTN; to reduce the endogenous CTTN, we injected a specific PTO previously reported to deplete CTTN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). We then measured the current mediated by K<sub>V</sub>10.1 channels.</p>
            <p>In these experiments, the macroscopic K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current amplitude depended on the presence of CTTN, but K<sub>V</sub>10.1 currents in CTTN-depleted or overexpressing oocytes did not differ in kinetics or voltage dependence from those obtained in untreated oocytes. K<sub>V</sub>10.1 produced slowly activating, outward rectifying currents, which did not inactivate; a slight inward rectification was observed with strong depolarizations compatible with block by intracellular sodium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>A</italic>). The current-voltage relationships were also unchanged by CTTN depletion or overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>B</italic>). A defining feature of the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current is the dependence of the time constant of activation on the holding potential in such a way that the current activates slower the more negative the prepulse potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). This property was also not affected by CTTN depletion or overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>C</italic>).</p>
            <fig id="F3" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 3.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Effect of CTTN depletion and overexpression on K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current.</bold> Representative current traces of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes under control conditions (<italic>Control</italic>), depleted (<italic>PTO</italic>; via injection of an antisense oligonucleotide) or increased (<italic>CTTN</italic>; via overexpression) CTTN levels are shown. Test pulses were applied ranging from the holding potential of −100 to +80 mV in 20-mV increments evoked whole cell currents. To determine the current-voltage relationship, the steady state current (<italic>I</italic>) was measured at the end of each pulse and normalized to the recorded current at +80 mV (<italic>I</italic><sub>max</sub>). Increased or decreased levels of CTTN (<italic>PTO</italic> or <italic>CTTN</italic>, respectively) do not have any effect on the general characteristic current appearance (<italic>A</italic>) or on current-voltage relationships (<italic>B</italic>). <italic>C,</italic> K<sub>V</sub>10.1 currents were evoked with a test pulse to +40 mV starting from either a holding potential of −100 or −70 mV. As expected for K<sub>V</sub>10.1, the activation of current depended on the prepulse potential independent of CTTN expression levels. <italic>D</italic> and <italic>E,</italic> depletion of CTTN (<italic>PTO</italic>) significantly decreased current amplitudes at a test pulse of +80 mV in comparison to control levels. This effect was dependent on the amount of PTO injected (<italic>D</italic>). Overexpression of human CTTN was not able to increase current amplitudes over control levels significantly, but partially restored current amplitudes in PTO injected oocytes (<italic>E</italic>). <italic>F,</italic> incubation for 24 h with the Arp2/3 inhibitor CK-666 (50 μ<sc>m</sc>) did not alter the current amplitude in oocytes expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Current amplitude was determined at the end of a depolarization to +60 mV.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300003"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Depletion of CTTN by PTO injection reduced or even abolished the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>D</italic>). We subsequently used injections of 5 ng of PTO per oocyte as a working concentration because it led to a current reduction of more than 80% (to 18 ± 6%) but still allowed quantification of the remaining current (<italic>n</italic> = 12, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>D</italic>). A similar behavior was observed when HEK293 cells expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1 were treated with siRNA against CTTN. K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was measured in randomly chosen cells of each group, and the mean current density (pA/pF) was determined. Although the overall current values were not significantly different (210 ± 36 pA/pF in the controls and 179 ± 33 pA/pF in the siRNA-treated cells, <italic>p</italic> = 0.5), 11 of 28 treated cells (40%) showed current densities below 50 pA/pF, <italic>versus</italic> 4/23 (17%) in the controls, compatible with the expectation of an effect on current density only in a subset of cells successfully transfected with siRNA.</p>
            <p>Increasing CTTN over physiological levels did not further enhance K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated currents (117 ± 16%, <italic>n</italic> = 11, <italic>p</italic> = 0.6, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>E</italic>). This was not due to a saturation of the translation/processing systems of the oocyte, as injection of larger amounts of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 cRNA leads to an increase in current amplitudes (not shown). PTO does not hybridize to human CTTN (the best match spans only 8 bases). Therefore, co-injection of the human cRNA should be able to replace the depleted CTTN of oocytes. This replacement restored K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current amplitudes to 60 ± 10%, <italic>n</italic> = 17 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>E</italic>).</p>
            <p>As CTTN is known to play important roles in cytoskeletal organization, it is possible that the effects observed are the result of interference rather than a direct effect on K<sub>V</sub>10.1. To test this, we used the Arp2/3 complex inhibitor CK666 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current amplitude was determined in oocytes incubated with 50 μ<sc>m</sc> CK666 over 24 h (the entire incubation period after RNA injection). No differences were observed as compared with oocytes treated with vehicle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref><italic>F</italic>), indicating that the effect of CTTN knockdown is independent of its role as an Arp2/3 activator. Taken together, these observations strongly indicate that CTTN regulates the amplitude of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated currents.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Regulation by CTTN Is Specific to K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and Depends on Its C Terminus</title>
            <p>As K<sub>V</sub>10.2 was able to bind CTTN in <italic>in vitro</italic> pull-down assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref><italic>B</italic>), we next examined the possible functional effects of CTTN depletion on K<sub>V</sub>10.2 currents in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. We found that currents evoked by this channel were not significantly affected by depletion of CTTN levels (133 ± 21% of control levels, <italic>n</italic> = 30, <italic>p</italic> = 0.2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>A</italic>). Overexpression of CTTN also did not have an effect on K<sub>V</sub>10.2-mediated currents (100 ± 17% of control levels, <italic>n</italic> = 10, <italic>p</italic> = 0.99; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>a</italic>). The kinetic properties of the macroscopic currents of K<sub>V</sub>10.2 were also unaffected.</p>
            <fig id="F4" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 4.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Regulating effect of the CTTN expression level depends on C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1.</bold>
<italic>A,</italic> varying CTTN levels by depletion (PTO, <italic>left panel</italic>) or overexpression (CTTN, <italic>right panel</italic>) in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes did not influence whole cell current amplitudes of K<sub>V</sub>10.2 in comparison to control levels. <italic>B,</italic> exchanging C termini between K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and K<sub>V</sub>10.2 transfers current dependence to CTTN levels. Current amplitudes of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 bearing the K<sub>V</sub>10.2 C terminus (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>panel a</italic>) were no longer sensitive to CTTN depletion in contrast to currents mediated by K<sub>V</sub>10.2 bearing the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 C terminus (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>panel b</italic>), which were significantly affected by CTTN reduction with injection of PTO. Current traces <italic>above the bar</italic> diagrams show typical responses elicited by the respective chimeras in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes (see legend to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). <italic>Scale bars</italic>: 5 μA, 200 ms. <italic>C,</italic> effect of partial deletion of the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 C terminus on current amplitudes. Partial deletions of the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 were generated and expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. Current amplitudes of deletions K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3, Δ4, Δ5, Δ6, and Δ8 were significantly reduced compared with the wild type.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300004"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Although both channels are very similar in sequence and structure, they differ widely in their expression patterns and functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) and it is formally possible that they are regulated by different mechanisms. K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and K<sub>V</sub>10.2 share high sequence homology and the differences between them are concentrated in the C terminus, so we next tested the effect of CTTN depletion on K<sub>V</sub>10 chimeras with exchanged C termini. Both chimeric channels expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes were functional, showing robust currents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>) with kinetics and voltage dependence very similar to wild-type currents. Current amplitudes of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 bearing the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.2 were no longer sensitive to CTTN depletion (145 ± 15% of control levels, <italic>n</italic> = 23, <italic>p</italic> = 0.11), whereas those of K<sub>V</sub>10.2 with the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 showed a prominent reduction upon PTO injection (22 ± 3% of control levels, <italic>n</italic> = 16, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0005, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>B</italic>). This supports the idea that the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 mediates the functional interaction of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN.</p>
            <p>To further map the binding site of CTTN within the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1, we constructed mutated channels with various C-terminal deletions (K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ1–8, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>C</italic>). Deletions were chosen in those regions that differ most between K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and K<sub>V</sub>10.2. As depletion of endogenous CTTN greatly reduced the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current, we expected the deletion of the CTTN binding site to have the same effect. Indeed, we found that five of the eight deletion mutants produced reduced current amplitudes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>C</italic>). One group of deletions, namely K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ4-Δ6 showed only moderate reduction of current amplitude, which was further decreased by depletion of CTTN (not shown). This indicates that these regions are not implicated in the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-CTTN interaction. Deletion of amino acid residues 705–755 (K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3) or the extreme C terminus (K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8) led to a reduction of current amplitudes by more than 90% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref><italic>C</italic>), so we concentrated on these two constructs for further analysis.</p>
            <p>To check if depletion of CTTN has any effect on current amplitudes of the mutants we increased the amount of cRNA injected to obtain quantifiable currents, and then measured the effect of CTTN knockdown on current amplitudes in experiments equivalent to those performed on wild-type channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref><italic>E</italic>). Current amplitudes for K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 were reduced to 49 ± 8% (<italic>n</italic> = 19, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) by co-injection of the PTO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>A</italic>). However, the effect of PTO injection was significantly weaker than in wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>B</italic>). Restoration of CTTN expression levels by co-injection of human CTTN could not rescue current amplitudes of this mutant (52 ± 9%, <italic>n</italic> = 15, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>). We were not able to record any currents for K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8, as reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) unless we used RNA concentrations in the range of 5000 times greater than those used for wild-type, and then only in very few cells.</p>
            <fig id="F5" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 5.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Deleting amino acids 705–755 of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 changes its distribution as well as its ability to bind CTTN.</bold>
<italic>A,</italic> depletion of CTTN by co-injection of the PTO oligonucleotide was able to reduce current amplitudes of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 (del705–755) in voltage clamp oocyte recordings as determined by a depolarization step to +80 mV. Restoration of CTTN levels by injection of human CTTN did not rescue the effect of PTO on this mutant. <italic>B,</italic> the effect of PTO-mediated CTTN depletion on K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 was weaker (reducing current amplitude by 50%) than that observed in full-length K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (that reduced current by 80%). Current amplitude of the mutant K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 after CTTN depletion was not rescued by additional expression of human CTTN, in contrast to wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1. <italic>C,</italic> membrane K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was labeled using a BTX-Alexa 555 conjugate and allowed for internalization for 1 h. Washed cells were analyzed by wide field microscopy. K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS as well as K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ8 (del933–962) showed prominent membranous labeling of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, whereas nearly no membrane-bound K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ3 was observed. <italic>Scale bar</italic>, 10 μm. <italic>D</italic>, K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS and K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ8 successfully precipitated GST-CTTN, K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ3 showed much weaker co-precipitation of the full-length CTTN. Mutants K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ3, K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ8, or wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS were transiently expressed in HEK 293 cells. Lysates were labeled with BTX-biotin (<italic>Bb</italic>) to pull down K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS using streptavidin-coated beads, unlabeled lysates served as negative control. Subsequent GST-CTTN was added and analyzed for co-precipitation using SDS-PAGE followed by Western blotting using a GST antibody.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300005"/>
            </fig>
            <p>A reduction of current amplitude can be due to a change in the electrophysiological properties of K<sub>V</sub>10.1, or in the number of available channels at the surface. To distinguish between these two possibilities, we measured the expression at the plasma membrane in a cell culture system by adding the BBS tag to the deletion mutants. Living HEK 293 cells expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS, or K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8-BBS were labeled with a BTX-Alexa Fluor conjugate to visualize membrane and internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). A clear membrane staining as well as internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was seen independently of the presence of the extreme C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>, K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8-BBS). Despite robust expression levels of all three constructs, only K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS showed reduced labeling; internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was stained, but there was minimal signal at the membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>). With our experimental protocol, only surface BBS can be detected. Therefore, there is probably a population of channels at the surface, but we were not able to detect it. Close-ups of the regions indicated by a white rectangle are shown in the lower panel. Peripheral staining was prominent in K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, whereas only punctate structures could be detected in K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS. K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8-BBS showed an intermediate profile with clear staining of cellular processes, compatible with plasma membrane together with abundant punctate staining.</p>
            <p>Precipitation studies with GST-CTTN using K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS Δ3 or Δ8, as described above, revealed, that K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ8 is able to bind GST-CTTN with an efficiency comparable with wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1, whereas K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 showed reduced binding capability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>D</italic>), although co-precipitation of the HP-region of CTTN was observed for K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3 (not shown). We therefore conclude that amino acid residues 705–755 of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 contribute to the functional interaction with CTTN, but it is likely that other unidentified regions also participate in CTTN binding.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>CTTN Does Not Influence the Biophysical Properties of K<sub>V</sub>10.1</title>
            <p>Total current through an ion channel results from the combination of three parameters: the unitary current through a single channel (<italic>i</italic>), the total number of available channels (<italic>N</italic>), and the probability of a channel being open (<italic>P<sub>o</sub></italic>).</p>
            <disp-formula id="FD2">
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc05312-3530-m02"/>
            </disp-formula>
            <p>Thus, a change in <italic>I</italic> can be caused by altering channel surface expression (varying <italic>N</italic>) or eliciting a change in single channel conductance or open probability. Each of these possibilities is conceivable in the case of CTTN and K<sub>V</sub>10.1. The cytoskeleton is known to play an important role in regulating the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>) and CTTN is reportedly involved in the regulation of the surface expression of some ion channels and receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>); it can also alter the conducting properties of K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 channels by regulating its interactions with the actin cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). To distinguish between these possibilities, we used electrophysiological and biochemical techniques.</p>
            <p>To determine electrophysiologically which of the above parameters is altered, we used non-stationary noise analysis, a technique that allows an estimation of <italic>I</italic>, <italic>N</italic>, and <italic>P<sub>o</sub></italic> from macroscopic currents based on the variance observed in the current trace. Variance is minimal both when all channels are either closed or open (see “Experimental Procedures”). We performed such analysis on excised <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte macropatches in the outside-out configuration. We averaged 300 depolarizing stimuli and determined point by point the variance of each trace with respect to the average trace. Fitting a parabola function (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Equation 1</xref>) to the current <italic>versus</italic> the variance data, the slope of the initial, pseudolinear segment of the distribution corresponds to the single channel current (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The result of the fitting gave similar single channel currents in the presence (884 ± 64 fA) and absence (789 ± 68 fA, <italic>p</italic> = 0.4) of CTTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref><italic>A</italic>). When normalized to compensate for the smaller currents in patches from PTO-treated oocytes, the variance <italic>versus</italic> current plots overlapped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref><italic>A</italic>, <italic>inset</italic>). Under the experimental conditions, the maximal open probability reached was similar in the presence or absence of CTTN (0.58 ± 0.03 <italic>versus</italic> 0.57 ± 0.04, <italic>p</italic> = 0.4; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref><italic>C</italic>). Therefore, the parameter that is most likely influenced by CTTN knockdown is the number of available channels. These data strengthen the idea that CTTN influences the number of functional K<sub>V</sub>10.1 channels at the plasma membrane.</p>
            <fig id="F6" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 6.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>CTTN influences surface expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1.</bold>
<italic>A,</italic> non-stationary noise analysis of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current in control and CTTN-depleted <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. Representative plots of the variance against the mean current with the corresponding fitting parabola for patches derived from control untreated (<italic>squares</italic>) or CTTN-depleted (<italic>circles</italic>) oocytes. The same plots are shown with independent scales in the <italic>inset</italic>. The slope of the initial segment of the function (representing single channel current) did not change upon CTTN depletion. <italic>B,</italic> depletion of CTTN reduced surface levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes was analyzed by Western blot (<italic>WB</italic>) using anti-K<sub>V</sub>10.1 antibodies. No difference of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 expression was found in whole oocyte lysates in response to CTTN depletion with the PTO (<italic>left panel</italic>), whereas surface levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 obtained from pull-down assays of membrane bound K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS were clearly reduced in the presence of the PTO (<italic>right panel</italic>).</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300006"/>
            </fig>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>Surface Expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Depends on the Presence of CTTN</title>
            <p>We next analyzed the expression levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the plasma membrane with biochemical techniques. Insertion of a BBS at the extracellular part of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 allows specific labeling of membranous K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS in intact cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>); cRNA encoding these modified proteins was injected into oocytes. Exposed K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was labeled in the intact oocyte with BTX-biotin. Oocytes were then lysed, and labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS was pulled down using streptavidin. In agreement with the electrophysiological data, CTTN-depleted cells showed a clear reduction in labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, indicating less protein at the cell surface in three independent experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref><italic>B</italic>). Importantly, the total protein level of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in whole oocyte lysates was independent of CTTN levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref><italic>B</italic>, <italic>right panel</italic>), arguing against the possibility of reduced surface expression due to a reduction in the protein in the cell. Taken together, these results strongly suggest that CTTN regulates surface expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes.</p>
            <p>We then asked if observations made in oocytes could be translated to mammalian expression systems more suitable for studying trafficking processes. For this purpose, we first examined if alterations in CTTN expression levels induce changes in the cellular localization of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in mammalian cells. Cells with normal, reduced, or increased levels of CTTN were transfected with a fluorescent K<sub>V</sub>10.1-Venus fusion protein and analyzed by confocal microscopy. Overexpression of a CFP-tagged CTTN showed good co-localization with K<sub>V</sub>10.1-Venus throughout the cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>; thresholded Manders coefficient; tM, 0.73 ± 0.02) and at the membrane, especially at locations compatible with focal adhesions (tM, 0.77 ± 0.01).</p>
            <fig id="F7" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 7.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>CTTN and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 co-localize <italic>in vivo</italic>.</bold>
<italic>A</italic>, transiently transfected HeLa cells were analyzed for the co-localization of CFP-CTTN with different K<sub>V</sub>10.x-BBS constructs by confocal microscopy. K<sub>V</sub>10.x-BBS constructs were visualized by labeling with a BTX-Alexa fluorophore after fixation and permeabilization of the cells. K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS showed typical distribution in the cells, co-localizing with CFP-CTTN mostly at the periphery of the cell (<italic>arrows</italic>). K<sub>V</sub>10.2-BBS as well as K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS did not co-localize with CFP-CTTN, both having a completely different distribution compared with K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. Deletion of amino acids 705–755 (K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS) dramatically changed the intracellular localization of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 to a diffuse staining mainly around the nucleus. <italic>B,</italic> co-staining with FAK revealed that the interaction between Venus-tagged K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CFP-CTTN occurs preferentially at focal adhesions. <italic>C,</italic> the cellular localization of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 depends on the presence of CTTN. CTTN levels were manipulated in HeLa cells by siRNA-mediated knockdown or overexpression of CFP-CTTN. Fluorescent Venus-tagged K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was expressed in these cells and analyzed for its cellular distribution using confocal microscopy. Control cells and cells overexpressing CTTN showed enrichment of the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 signal in focal adhesions. This distribution was lost upon CTTN knockdown. <italic>Scale bars</italic>, 20 μm.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300007"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Co-staining for FAK showed that co-localization between K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and CTTN occurs at focal adhesions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Co-localization of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-Venus and FAK can also be observed in cells with endogenous levels of CTTN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>B</italic>). Depletion of CTTN by siRNA clearly changed the localization of K<sub>V</sub>10.1; it was essentially absent from the cell margins, but there was a diffuse staining mainly around the cell nucleus. This manipulation also abolished the co-localization with FAK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>C</italic>).</p>
            <p>Depletion of CTTN had a very similar effect to deletion of amino acids 705–755 in the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 C terminus (K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>A</italic>). CFP-CTTN showed weak co-localization with K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS (tM, 0.29 ± 0.03, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) or K<sub>V</sub>10.2-BBS (tM, 0.31 ± 0.09). At the membrane or presumptive focal adhesions, no co-localization of these two proteins was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref><italic>A</italic>), again indicating that CTTN interacts with neither K<sub>V</sub>10.2 nor K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3-BBS <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
            <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
              <label>TABLE 1</label>
              <caption>
                <p>
                  <bold>Quantification of co-localization with CTTN</bold>
                </p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead valign="bottom">
                  <tr>
                    <th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/>
                    <th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Location</th>
                    <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Thresholded Manders coefficient<hr/></th>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th>
                    <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody valign="top">
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>V</sub>10.1</td>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cell</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 ± 0.02 (87)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 ± 0.02 (87)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adhesions</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.01 (79)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 ± 0.01 (79)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>V</sub>10.2</td>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cell</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 ± 0.09 (12)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ± 0.07 (12)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adhesions</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.02 (35)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 ± 0.03 (35)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>V</sub>10.1 Δ3</td>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole cell</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 ± 0.05 (17)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 ± 0.06 (17)</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                    <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adhesions</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 ± 0.03 (40)</td>
                    <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 ± 0.03 (40)</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>We also labeled and tracked K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS in living cells using fluorescently labeled BTX. HEK 293 cells stably expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS were transfected either with control (scrRNA) or siRNA directed against CTTN. Reduced CTTN levels to about 50% (as revealed by Western blot analysis, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>A</italic>) lowered surface staining by BTX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>B</italic>). To quantify this effect, we performed ELISA on BTX-coated plates (by immobilization of BTX-biotin on streptavidin-coated plates). Labeled cell extracts were incubated on these plates and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was detected using a C-terminal antibody. Different labeling protocols enabled us to distinguish between different fractions of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. Incubating with BTX after cell lysis labels total K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and not just the exposed fraction. Quantification showed that changing the CTTN expression levels did not have any effect on the total K<sub>V</sub>10.1 content (siRNA mediated knock-down: 105 ± 5% of the control, overexpression: 97 ± 5% of control; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>C</italic>), indicating that, like in oocytes, CTTN does not affect the expression levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1.</p>
            <fig id="F8" position="float">
              <label>FIGURE 8.</label>
              <caption>
                <p><bold>Effect of altered CTTN expression on K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in HEK 293 cells stably expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS.</bold>
<italic>A,</italic> CTTN levels were influenced by either overexpression of a CFP-CTTN fusion protein or knockdown of CTTN by using siRNA as verified by immunoblotting against CTTN in HEK 293 cells stably expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. <italic>B</italic>, surface K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS labeled with a BTX-Alexa 555 conjugate was rarely observed in cells treated with siRNA against CTTN, whereas it was clearly seen in control cells (<italic>control</italic>) as well as in CFP-CTTN overexpressing cells (<italic>CTTN</italic>). Wide field microscopy on living cells, <italic>scale bars</italic>, 10 μm. The <italic>areas indicated by a white square</italic> are shown at a higher magnification on the <italic>lower panel. C</italic>, quantification of surface K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS by ELISA revealed a clear reduction in response to CTTN depletion, whereas overexpression of CTTN did not change the amount of membrane-bound K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS significantly. Whole cell expression levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS were independent of the modulated CTTN levels. To measure internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, cells were incubated with BTX-biotin for 1 h at physiological temperature to allow internalization. Subsequently, membrane labeling was removed by an acid wash. Overexpression of CTTN reduced internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS in the given time, whereas depletion of CTTN did not have an effect. <italic>D,</italic> reduction of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current amplitude in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes was only observed when CTTN depletion was achieved when PTO was injected before or simultaneously with K<sub>V</sub>10.1, but not if it was injected 24 h later. <italic>E,</italic> growth of HeLa cells was stimulated by CTTN transfection (<italic>circles</italic>) as compared with transfection with empty vector (<italic>triangles</italic>). The <italic>inset</italic> shows that knockdown of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 does not impair proliferation of CTTN-overexpressing cells.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="zbc0041335300008"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Selective labeling and detection of membrane-bound K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS can be achieved by incubating living cells with the conjugate at room temperature for a short time to avoid internalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Comparable with the findings in oocytes, overexpression of CTTN did not increase the membrane fraction of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS (112 ± 21% of control), whereas siRNA-mediated knockdown of CTTN (to ∼50%, as determined for every individual experiment) significantly reduced surface levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS (57 ± 5% of the control, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>C</italic>). Taken together, these results point to a CTTN-mediated regulation of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 surface expression.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec>
            <title>CTTN Stabilizes K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the Cell Membrane</title>
            <p>As the amount of total K<sub>V</sub>10.1 does not change in response to alterations in CTTN expression, two mechanisms to vary K<sub>V</sub>10.1 membrane expression are conceivable. If CTTN is involved in trafficking processes of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 toward the membrane, less K<sub>V</sub>10.1 may reach the membrane when CTTN is missing. Alternatively, in the absence of CTTN, K<sub>V</sub>10.1 that had reached the membrane would remain there for a shorter time, thus reducing the steady-state level.</p>
            <p>If a trafficking process is involved, one would expect that depletion of CTTN prior to K<sub>V</sub>10.1 expression would reduce the membrane expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1. To test this, sequential injection of the PTO and K<sub>V</sub>10.1 cRNA was therefore performed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes. When K<sub>V</sub>10.1 cRNA was injected 24 h before CTTN levels were lowered by PTO, K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated currents were significantly reduced to 51 ± 11% of control levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>D</italic>). In contrast, when PTO injection was performed before K<sub>V</sub>10.1 injection, there was no reduction of the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current with respect to the control (92 ± 9% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>D</italic>)). This observation argues against involvement of CTTN in trafficking processes, but instead indicates a role in stabilizing K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the plasma membrane.</p>
            <p>We therefore tested internalization processes in mammalian cells using ELISA experiments similar to those described previously. Living HEK293 cells stably expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS were incubated with a BTX-biotin conjugate for 1 h at physiological temperature to allow internalization of labeled K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS. Non-internalized BTX was then removed by acid wash. Quantification revealed that although K<sub>V</sub>10.1 was clearly reduced at the membrane in response to CTTN depletion, the amount of internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1 within 1 h was not changed (98 ± 9% of the control, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>C</italic>). CTTN overexpression on the other hand reduced the amount of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 internalized in this time (70 ± 6% of the control, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>C</italic>). These data are compatible with the proposed involvement of CTTN in stabilizing K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in the plasma membrane. We therefore conclude that CTTN is probably involved in processes stabilizing the presence of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the membrane.</p>
            <p>If more K<sub>V</sub>10.1 is available at the plasma membrane, the downstream effects of channel expression could also be enhanced. To test if this is the case, we overexpressed CTTN in HeLa cells, which have a relatively high endogenous expression of K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Channel knockdown in HeLa cells strongly reduces proliferation, indicating that the channel plays a role in this process. Transient transfection with CTTN increased proliferation rates of HeLa cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>E</italic>). Additionally, when a stable cell line overexpressing CTTN (by ∼25% at the protein level, as estimated by Western blot and densitometry) was treated with siRNA against K<sub>V</sub>10.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), proliferation was not reduced (<italic>inset</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref><italic>E</italic>). These observations are compatible with enhanced levels of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the cell surface in the presence of excess CTTN.</p>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <p>In this study we report that CTTN is an interaction partner of the voltage-gated potassium channel K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Our results indicate that this interaction is direct as precipitation with purified proteins did not require the addition of any bridging factor. Different pulldown assay formats allowed us to identify the proline-rich region of CTTN as responsible for binding to K<sub>V</sub>10.1. This region appears to be a major substrate for post-translational modifications in CTTN, bearing several well known phosphorylation sites. We have not examined possible post-translational regulation of the CTTN interaction with K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and this does represent an area for further work.</p>
      <p>We also observed co-localization of CTTN with K<sub>V</sub>10.1 <italic>in vivo</italic> and in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes we identified CTTN expression as a requirement for the K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current, as complete depletion of CTTN abolished current responses. The abundance of CTTN, however, does not appear to be a limiting factor for K<sub>V</sub>10.1 functional expression, as overexpression of CTTN could not further enhance current amplitudes in oocytes, but it did accelerate proliferation of HeLa cells, a phenomenon that has been related to K<sub>V</sub>10.1 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). This effect is specific for K<sub>V</sub>10.1, because its closest relative, K<sub>V</sub>10.2, did not co-localize with CTTN <italic>in vivo</italic>, nor is K<sub>V</sub>10.2-mediated current affected by CTTN knockdown.</p>
      <p>The known role of CTTN in actin cytoskeleton rearrangements (reviewed in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>) is unlikely to be responsible for its effects on K<sub>V</sub>10.1 reported here; the effect was highly specific and did not apply to K<sub>V</sub>10.2-mediated current. In addition, interference with actin cytoskeleton rearrangement through Arp2/3 inhibition did not mimic the effect of CTTN knockdown.</p>
      <p>Exchanging the C termini of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and K<sub>V</sub>10.2 transferred the regulatory effect of CTTN to the latter, indicating that the specific functional interaction depends on the C terminus of K<sub>V</sub>10.1. Deletion of residues 705–755 mimics the effects of CTTN depletion on K<sub>V</sub>10.1, indicating that this segment is implicated in the interaction with CTTN. Chen and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) examined truncation mutants of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and found that several deletions removing the tetramerizing coiled-coil at the distal C terminus of the channel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) did show functional expression of currents. Interestingly, mutations deleting the domain identified here as the CTTN-interacting domain always produced non-functional channels. More recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>), a crystal structure of the proximal C-domain and the putative cyclic nucleotide binding domain (<italic>i.e.</italic> the protein domain spanning between the last transmembrane segment S6 and the end of the CNBD) of a K<sub>V</sub>10.1 family member revealed that it is able to form dimers, and that it would therefore potentially be implicated in the formation of multimeric channels. Our Δ8 construct (deletion of the TCC) failed to produce any currents, but apparently did generate proteins able to reach the membrane (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref><italic>C</italic>) because we could detect internalized BTX in cells expressing this mutant. Additionally, the N terminus of the protein has also been implicated in tetramerization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) in K<sub>V</sub>11 channels. Altogether, these observations point to a scenario where the multimeric assembly occurs co-translationally with multiple interaction domains (N terminus, S6, proximal domain, and finally TCC “locking” and stabilizing the mature structure). The mature protein is then targeted to the plasma membrane and CTTN would stabilize it there. Nevertheless, residues 705–755 are probably not the only determinants of interaction with CTTN, because we still observed binding of the HP region to the deletion mutant as well as a residual effect on current amplitudes by CTTN depletion in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes, pointing toward additional requirements for CTTN interaction.</p>
      <p>CTTN can direct K<sub>V</sub>10.1 to focal adhesions. These structures play a role in cancer via signaling cascades involving integrins as well as the FAK, a non-receptor tyrosine kinase mainly restricted to focal adhesions. These proteins seem to be key regulators in cancer progression (reviewed in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). Again, a close relative of K<sub>V</sub>10.1, HERG, (K<sub>V</sub>11.1) is directly linked to β1 integrin signaling pathways, where it modulates downstream signaling elicited by integrin activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). K<sub>V</sub>10.1, in addition to its presence at focal adhesions shown here seems to adopt a function in adhesion processes: its expression clearly influences adhesion of cells and the extracellular matrix is also able to modulate the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current, although a direct interaction with β1 integrin has not been shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). The strong association of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 with the actin cytoskeleton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) might explain this behavior, and CTTN could serve to modulate interaction.</p>
      <p>Other ion channels such as K<sub>V</sub>1.2 and the large conductance calcium- and voltage-activated potassium channel K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 have been reported to bind to and to be influenced by CTTN via effects on affecting membrane expression or changes in open probability, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). In the latter, CTTN was suggested to bridge K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 channels to actin filaments, a process dependent on the phosphorylation state of CTTN and linkage of K<sub>Ca</sub>1.1 channels to intracellular signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). K<sub>V</sub>10.1 has been shown to be associated with actin fibers in CHO cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) and the K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current is influenced by interactions with the cytoskeleton as disruption of the actin cytoskeleton by cytochalasin B dramatically increases K<sub>V</sub>10.1 current density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>).</p>
      <p>In our study, examination of the biophysical properties of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 revealed that CTTN expression levels do not influence the single channel conductance or the open probability of this channel. Together with the fact that CTTN depletion clearly reduced membrane-located K<sub>V</sub>10.1 in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes as well as in HEK 293 cells stably expressing K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS, we conclude that CTTN has a regulatory effect on channel synthesis, maintenance, or transport. As CTTN depletion resulted in no detectable change in the amount of total whole cell K<sub>V</sub>10.1, it is unlikely that CTTN affects channel synthesis or degradation. Sequential injection in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 and the PTO affecting CTTN suggests that K<sub>V</sub>10.1 transport toward the membrane is not affected by CTTN depletion. In line with this, the same amount of K<sub>V</sub>10.1-BBS seems to reach the membrane in a given time span in ELISA experiments on CTTN-depleted HEK 293 cells. Therefore, we propose that CTTN is involved in K<sub>V</sub>10.1 endocytotic processes or in their regulation.</p>
      <p>Consistent with this hypothesis, CTTN depletion is known to reduce endocytosis over clathrin-coated pits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). However, in our system, CTTN depletion affects K<sub>V</sub>10.1 surface expression, leading to clearly reduced membrane-resident protein. A similar effect is reported for K<sub>V</sub>1.2 and interpreted to be the result of stabilization of the channel at the membrane as well as favoring its endocytosis in a phosphorylation-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). As the amount of internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1 is not altered by depletion of CTTN, but overexpression of CTTN does reduce the amount of internalized K<sub>V</sub>10.1, we believe that CTTN plays a minor role in events of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 internalization under basal conditions. Instead, we postulate a model whereby CTTN stabilizes K<sub>V</sub>10.1 at the membrane; in the absence of CTTN, this would lead to a reduced membrane-residency time of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 via faster internalization. Mechanistically, CTTN may connect K<sub>V</sub>10.1 to the cytoskeleton by directing and stabilizing it at the desired locations and its ability to bind and induce polymerization of actin (reviewed by Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Additionally, CTTN has been linked to angiotensin II-induced tissue repair in smooth muscle cells, influencing proliferation and migration in an insulin-like growth factor-1 receptor and Src dependent way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). Within this process, CTTN is phosphorylated and subsequently translocated to the membrane, especially to focal adhesions. The K<sub>V</sub>10.1-mediated current has been reported to be up-regulated in MCF-7 cells following stimulation with insulin-like growth factor-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), and the pro-proliferative effects of this growth factor are dependent on K<sub>V</sub>10.1. K<sub>V</sub>10.1 overexpression alone has also been reported to increase proliferation rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>); this increase requires functional ion channels at the plasma membrane because blockade by an extracellular antibody reduced this effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>), but does not depend strictly on potassium permeation, because a point mutant unable to permeate K<sup>+</sup> recapitulates many of the effects of wild-type K<sub>V</sub>10.1, although less efficiently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). In good agreement with these observations, we found that overexpression of CTTN in HeLa cells increased proliferation, and rendered the cells no longer sensitive to K<sub>V</sub>10.1 knockdown.</p>
      <p>Overall, our observations would be compatible with a model where signaling pathways such as insulin-like growth factor-1R/Akt or Src induce CTTN-mediated alteration of K<sub>V</sub>10.1 expression at the cell surface. In this way CTTN activity could be translated into cell cycle progression. Further work will be necessary to determine whether this is the case.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group content-type="abbreviations">
      <fn id="FN4">
        <label>5</label>
        <p>The abbreviations used are:
<def-list><def-item><term id="G1">CTTN</term><def><p>cortactin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">SH3</term><def><p>Src homology 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">BBS</term><def><p>bungarotoxin-binding site</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">BTX</term><def><p>bungarotoxin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">PTO</term><def><p>phosphorothioate antisense oligodeoxynucleotide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6">FAK</term><def><p>focal adhesion kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7">N-term</term><def><p>N-terminal.</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Prof. Nils Brose for the gift of the cDNA library used in the yeast two-hybrid screen. We thank Victor Díaz, Sabine Klöppner, Tanja Nilsson, and Annett Sporning for excellent technical support.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammer</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weed</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cortactin branches out. Roles in regulating protrusive actin dynamics</article-title>. <source>Cell. Motil. Cytoskeleton</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>687</fpage>–<lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18615630</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuser</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karginov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Interaction of cortactin and N-WASp with Arp2/3 complex</article-title>. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1270</fpage>–<lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12176354</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weed</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karginov</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinley</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cortactin localization to sites of actin assembly in lamellipodia requires interactions with F-actin and the Arp2/3 complex</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lua</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cortactin phosphorylation as a switch for actin cytoskeletal network and cell dynamics control</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>579</volume>, <fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15670811</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hattan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cachero</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morielli</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Tyrosine phosphorylation of Kv1.2 modulates its interaction with the actin-binding protein cortactin</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>277</volume>, <fpage>38596</fpage>–<lpage>38606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151401</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClafferty</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knaus</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipston</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A noncanonical SH3 domain binding motif links BK channels to the actin cytoskeleton via the SH3 adapter cortactin</article-title>. <source>FASEB J.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2588</fpage>–<lpage>2590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065230</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClafferty</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipston</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Reversible tyrosine protein phosphorylation regulates large conductance voltage- and calcium-activated potassium channels via cortactin</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>283</volume>, <fpage>3067</fpage>–<lpage>3076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markey</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doczi</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morielli</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>An essential role for cortactin in the modulation of the potassium channel Kv1.2</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>17412</fpage>–<lpage>17417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17959782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>del Camino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brüggemann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Oncogenic potential of EAG K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>5540</fpage>–<lpage>5547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10523298</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wulff</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Voltage-gated potassium channels as therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>982</fpage>–<lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19949402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Transcriptional and post-transcriptional mechanisms for oncogenic overexpression of ether à go-go K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e20362</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21655246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouadid-Ahidouch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bourhis</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roudbaraki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toillon</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delcourt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prevarskaya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Changes in the K<sup>+</sup> current-density of MCF-7 cells during progression through the cell cycle. Possible involvement of a h-ether-a-gogo K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>. <source>Recept. Channels</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>–<lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11697078</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borowiec</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hague</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harir</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guénin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerineau</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouilleux</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roudbaraki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassoued</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouadid-Ahidouch</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>IGF-1 activates hEAG K<sup>+</sup> channels through an Akt-dependent signaling pathway in breast cancer cells. Role in cell proliferation</article-title>. <source>J. Cell. Physiol.</source>
<volume>212</volume>, <fpage>690</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17520698</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brüggemann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Cell cycle-related changes in the conducting properties of r-eag K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>143</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>–<lpage>775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9813096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cytoskeletal interactions determine the electrophysiological properties of human EAG potassium channels</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch. Eur. J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>441</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11211100</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuuring</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooi</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalides</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Identification and cloning of two overexpressed genes, U21B31/PRAD1 and EMS1, within the amplified chromosome 11q13 region in human carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1532244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cortactin in tumor invasiveness</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source>
<volume>265</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18406052</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vojtek</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollenberg</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Mammalian Ras interacts directly with the serine/threonine kinase Raf</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8334704</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lörinczi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Rapid internalization of the oncogenic K<sup>+</sup> channel KV10.1</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e26329</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22022602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griesinger</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The potassium channel Ether a go-go is a novel prognostic factor with functional relevance in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cancer</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20105281</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmerlein</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weseloh</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello de Queiroz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knötgen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliephacke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinz-Joachim-Radzun</surname></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of Eag1 potassium channels in clinical tumours</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cancer</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17022810</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Electrophysiologic recordings from <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>293</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9711614</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Nonstationary noise analysis and application to patch clamp recordings</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>207</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1326701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terlau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunder</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brüggemann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongs</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Functional expression of a rat homologue of the voltage-gated either a go-go potassium channel reveals differences in selectivity and activation kinetics between the <italic>Drosophila</italic> channel and its mammalian counterpart</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>4451</fpage>–<lpage>4458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7925287</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nolen</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasevic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakowicz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of two classes of small molecule inhibitors of Arp2/3 complex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>460</volume>, <fpage>1031</fpage>–<lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648907</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weseloh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karschin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Netzer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stansfeld</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pongs</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cloning and functional expression of rat eag2, a new member of the ether-à-go-go family of potassium channels and comparison of its distribution with that of eag1</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882483</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular identification and characterization of the human eag2 potassium channel</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>524</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135768</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schönherr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gessner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Löber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Functional distinction of human EAG1 and EAG2 potassium channels</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>514</volume>, <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11943152</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monje</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weseloh</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>C-terminal domains implicated in the functional surface expression of potassium channels</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554641</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNiven</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>SRC-mediated phosphorylation of dynamin and cortactin regulates the “constitutive” endocytosis of transferrin</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995918</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello de Queiroz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukow</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Silencing the activity and proliferative properties of the human Eag1 potassium channel by RNAi</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>281</volume>, <fpage>13030</fpage>–<lpage>13037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jow</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeng</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Distal end of carboxyl terminus is not essential for the assembly of rat Eag1 potassium channels</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>27183</fpage>–<lpage>27196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21646358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brelidze</surname><given-names>T. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankaran</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagotta</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Structure of the carboxyl-terminal region of a KCNH channel</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>481</volume>, <fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230959</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phartiyal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Heteromeric assembly of human ether-à-go-go-related gene (hERG) 1a/1b channels occurs cotranslationally via N-terminal interactions</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>282</volume>, <fpage>9874</fpage>–<lpage>9882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17272276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Focal adhesion kinase: a prominent determinant in breast cancer initiation, progression and metastasis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source>
<volume>289</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19643531</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becchetti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crociani</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Defilippi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guasti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillozzi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Physical and functional interaction between integrins and hERG potassium channels</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>826</fpage>–<lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15494025</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillozzi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guasti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crociani</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Stefano</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Becchetti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Defilippi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wymore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Human ether-a-go-go-related gene 1 channels are physically linked to β1 integrins and modulate adhesion-dependent signaling</article-title>. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2972</fpage>–<lpage>2983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernabei</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crociani</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guasti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillozzi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lastraioli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polvani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolozzi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solazzo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gragnani</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Defilippi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>HERG K<sup>+</sup> channels activation during β<sub>1</sub> integrin-mediated adhesion to fibronectin induces an up-regulation of α<sub>v</sub>β<sub>3</sub> integrin in the preosteoclastic leukemia cell line FLG 29.1</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>, <fpage>4923</fpage>–<lpage>4931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080495</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toral</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendoza-Garrido</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azorín</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández-Gallegos</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomora</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgadillo</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano-Agama</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Effect of extracellular matrix on adhesion, viability, actin cytoskeleton, and K<sup>+</sup> currents of cells expressing human ether a go-go channels</article-title>. <source>Life Sci.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586530</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuser</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McNiven</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cortactin is a component of clathrin-coated pits and participates in receptor-mediated endocytosis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2162</fpage>–<lpage>2170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Roles of cortactin, an actin polymerization mediator, in cell endocytosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Biochim. Biophys. Sin.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16474900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zahradka</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Storie</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>IGF-1 receptor transactivation mediates Src-dependent cortactin phosphorylation in response to angiotensin II</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Physiol. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>805</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19898563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gómez-Varela</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwick-Wallasch</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knötgen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ossipov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weseloh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras-Jurado</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Monoclonal antibody blockade of the human Eag1 potassium channel function exerts antitumor activity</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>7343</fpage>–<lpage>7349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17671204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knötgen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras-Jurado</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gymnopoulos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stühmer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Eag1 expression interferes with hypoxia homeostasis and induces angiogenesis in tumors</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>283</volume>, <fpage>36234</fpage>–<lpage>36240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927085</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>