<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:39:59Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3060158" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3060158</identifier><datestamp>2011-03-18</datestamp><setSpec>molvis</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Vis</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MV</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Molecular Vision</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1090-0535</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Molecular Vision</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3060158</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3060158</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3060158</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21423869</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">79</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2010MOLVIS0441</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Mutation screening and genotype phenotype correlation of α-crystallin, γ-crystallin and GJA8 gene in congenital cataract</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Manoj</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Agarwal</surname>
            <given-names>Tushar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Khokhar</surname>
            <given-names>Sudarshan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kumar</surname>
            <given-names>Manoj</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kaur</surname>
            <given-names>Punit</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roy</surname>
            <given-names>Tara Sankar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Dada</surname>
            <given-names>Rima</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Laboratory for Molecular Reproduction and Genetics, Department of Anatomy, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Dr. Rajendra Prasad Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biophysics, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Anatomy, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to: Dr. Rima Dada, Associate Professor, Laboratory for Molecular Reproduction and Genetics, Department of Anatomy, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi-110029, India; Phone: +91 11 26543517; FAX: +91 11 26588663; email: <email xlink:href="rima.dadarima@gmail.com">rima.dadarima@gmail.com</email> or <email xlink:href="rima_dada@rediffmail.com">rima_dada@rediffmail.com</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <fpage>693</fpage>
      <lpage>707</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>07</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2011 Molecular Vision.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
        Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
        distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
        work is properly cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Purpose</title>
          <p>To screen α-crystallin (<italic>CRYAB</italic>), γ-crystallin (<italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>CRYGD</italic>), and Connexin 50 (Cx-50 or <italic>GJA8</italic>) genes in congenital cataract patients and controls.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Thirty clinically diagnosed congenital cataract cases below 3 years of age from northern India, presenting at Dr. R. P. Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences (AIIMS, New Delhi, India) were enrolled in this study. Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood, all coding and exon/intron regions were amplified using PCR and direct sequencing was performed to detect any nucleotide variation. ProtScale and Discovery Studio programs were used for insilico and structural analysis of non-synonymous mutations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>DNA sequencing analysis of <italic>CRYAB, CRYGC, CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic> showed a total of six variations of which two were novel (<italic>CRYGC</italic>:p.R48H and <italic>GJA8</italic>:p.L281C) and four have been previously reported (<italic>CRYAB</italic>: rs11603779T&gt;G, <italic>GJA8</italic>: p.L268L, <italic>CRYGD</italic>: p.R95R, and c.T564C). Both the novel changes, in <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>GJA8</italic> were found in 16.6% of the patients. Previously reported nucleotide alterations (<italic>CRYGD</italic>:p.R95R and c.T564C) were found in 90% of the patients. Insilico and structural analysis data suggested that two novel non-synonymous mutations altered the stability and solvent accessibility of γC-crystallin and Cx-50 proteins which may lead to lens opacification.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>We observed two novel nonsynonymous variations and four reported variations in <italic>CRYAB, CRYGC, CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic>. The p.R48H variation in γC-crystallin may disrupt the normal structure of lens and can cause cataract. Cx50 is responsible for joining the lens cells into a functional syncytium and a mutation (p.L281C) in <italic>GJA8</italic> may lead to lens opacification resulting in cataract formation. This study further expands the mutation spectrum of congenital cataract and help understanding how mutant proteins lead to opacification of lens.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>GalleyStatus</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Export to XML</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>corr-author</meta-name>
          <meta-value>Dada</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Cataract is an opacification of the lens resulting from alterations in lens cellular architecture or in lens proteins, or both. Congenital cataract is a clinically and genetically heterogeneous lens disease responsible for a significant proportion of visual impairment and blindness in childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">2</xref>]. The prevalence of congenital cataract is estimated to vary from 0.6 to 6 per 10,000 live births with an incidence of 2.2–2.49 per 10,000 live births [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">3</xref>]. It is estimated that globally, 20 million children under the age of 16 years suffer from cataract, and among these, 200,000 (15%) are severely visually impaired or blind [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">5</xref>]. Pediatric cataracts are responsible for 7.4% to 15.3% of childhood blindness in developing countries like india [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">8</xref>]. The prevalence of blindness in children ranges from approximately 0.3/1000 children in affluent regions to 1.5/1000 in the poorest communities. The population of India in 2001 was estimated to be 1.03 billion, approximately 420 million of whom are children under 16 years of age (40.9%). Overall, there are probably 280,000–320,000 blind children in India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">9</xref>]. Cataract is responsible for ~12% of childhood blindness in India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref>]. The occurrence of congenital cataract varies in different parts of India as it is 5.25% in northen India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">7</xref>], 8.5% in northeast states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>], 7.25% in western India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref>] and 11.4% in south India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>].</p>
      <p>Currently there are ~60 loci implicated in non-syndromic congenital cataract, among these, over 22 have been associated with mutations in specific genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref>] including 10 crystallin genes: αA-crystallin (<italic>CRYAA</italic>), αB-crystallin (<italic>CRYAB</italic>), βA1-crystallin (<italic>CRYBA1</italic>), βA4-crystallin (<italic>CRYBA4</italic>), βB1-crystallin (<italic>CRYBB1</italic>), βB2-crystallin (<italic>CRYBB2</italic>), βB3-crystallin (<italic>CRYBB3</italic>), γC-crystallin (<italic>CRYGC</italic>), γD-crystallin (<italic>CRYGD</italic>), γS-crystallin (<italic>CRYGS</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>], two cytoskeletal protein genes: beaded filament structural protein 1, filensin (<italic>BFSP1</italic>), beaded filament structural protein 2, phakinin (<italic>BFSP2</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>], four membrane protein genes: gap junction protein (alpha 3, <italic>GJA3</italic>), gap junction protein (alpha 8, <italic>GJA8</italic>), major intrinsic protein of lens fiber (<italic>MIP</italic>), and lens intrinsic membrane protein 2 gene (<italic>LIM2</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref>], three growth and transcription factor genes: heat shock transcription factor 4 (<italic>HSF4</italic>), paired-like homeodomain 3 (<italic>PITX3</italic>), Maf-like protein (<italic>MAF</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">27</xref>], and chromatin modifying protein-4B (<italic>CHMP4B</italic>), Ephrin receptor EphA2 (<italic>EPHA2</italic>), and Nance-Horan syndrome (<italic>NHS</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">27</xref>].</p>
      <p>As crystallin genes account for nearly 90% of the water soluble proteins in lens and the encoded proteins account for around 30% of lens mass, these proteins play an essential roles in maintaining the lens transparency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r28">28</xref>] and are good candidate genes for screening in congenital cataract patients. Crystallin mutations accounts for about 50% of the non syndromic cataract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref>]. Since the lens is an avascular structure, the crystallins are retained in soluble form through the maintenance of ionic balance by the actions of gap junction proteins which allow the metabolically active epithelium to regulate the precise inter-cellular communication and transport between the lens periphery and its interior. Gap junction proteins (alpha 3 and alpha 8) are expressed in the lens vesicle and mutations in these genes have been reported to lead to cataract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r31">31</xref>].</p>
      <p>Congenital cataract is the most important treatable cause of pediatric blindness in developing countries like India. In this pilot study, we screened 30 cases of congenital cataract for sequence variations in <italic>CRYAB</italic>, <italic>CRYGC</italic>, <italic>CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic>. Upon sequence analysis we detected six sequence variations. Out of six, two novel mutations were found in <italic>CRYGC</italic> (R48H) and <italic>GJA8</italic> (L281C). The probable pathogenicity of the mutations found in this study as disease causing is discussed in light of earlier studies.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Clinical examination and selection of cases</title>
        <p>After receiving ethical approval from the institutional review board (IRB#00006862; All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Delhi, India), 30 clinically diagnosed consecutive congenital cataract cases below 3 years of age from northern India, presenting at the Dr. R. P. Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences (AIIMS, New Delhi, India) were enrolled in this study. These congenital cataract cases had no other ocular or systemic abnormalities. Detailed history was taken from parents regarding high fever, TORCHES ([<italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>; <italic>T</italic>. <italic>gondii</italic>], rubella virus [RV], cytomegalovirus [CMV], herpes simplex virus [HSV], syphilis [caused by <italic>Treponema pallidum</italic>]) infection, tuberculosis, exposure to radiation, and drug intake during gestation period. Metabolic tests like serum biochemistry for levels of blood glucose, calcium and phosphorous evaluations, RBC transferase and galactokinase levels and urine test for reducing sugars (galactosemia) and for amino acids (Lowe syndrome) were also done. Cases with known cause of congenital cataract were excluded from the study. Affected status was determined by a history of cataract extraction or ophthalmologic examination. A total of 30 ethnically and age-matched normal individuals without any history of ocular or systemic disorders were enrolled as controls. They had no metabolic, genetic, or ocular disorder on examination by a ophthalmologist and an extensive history was taken regarding family, occupation of parents, any medical problem, and drug intake by parents. Informed consent in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki was obtained from all participants or their parents and controls.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>DNA isolation, PCR amplification and sequence analysis</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from whole blood samples of all cases and controls, using organic method as described by Sambrook et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r32">32</xref>] with some modifications. Briefly, 5 ml blood was incubated in 15 ml of Red Cell Lysis Buffer (RCLB) at 4 °C and then centrifuged at 6,861× g for 15 min at 4 °C. Supernatant was discarded and pellet was given repeated washes with RCLB till the pellet became white. The white pellet was re-suspended in 5 ml of DNA extraction buffer, 40 µl of proteinase-K (40 µg/ml) and 300 µl of sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS). The cocktail was incubated at 55 °C for 2-3 h. The digested proteins were precipitated by adding equal volumes of saturated phenol and chloroform:isoamylalcohol (24:1). The mixture was gently mixed on rotor-mixer for 15-20 min and then centrifuge at 6,861× g for 15 min at 4 °C. In upper viscous layer equal amount of chloroform:isoamylalcohol (24:1) solution was added and again mixed for 15 min in rotor-mixer. The aqueous layer containing the genomic DNA was carefully collected. Then DNA was precipitated with chilled ethanol and centrifugation at 1,461.6× g for 15 min. DNA pellet was washed with 70% ethanol and dissolved in TE buffer. The exon-intron regions of <italic>CRYAB</italic>, <italic>CRYGC</italic>, <italic>CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic> were amplified in congenital cataract patients and controls. PCR amplifications for all primer sets (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>) were performed in a 40 μl volume containing 1.0 μl of 20 mM stock solution for each primer (Eurofins Genomics India pvt Ltd, Bangalore, India), 100 ng of genomic DNA, 1 unit of Taq polymerase (Banglore Genei, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India), 0.1 mM of each deoxynucleotide triphosphate (dNTP), and 4 μl of 10× PCR buffer (with 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>). Amplified PCR products were purified using a gel/PCR DNA fragments extraction kit (Geneaid Biotech Ltd., Sijhih City, Taiwan). Purified PCR products were sent for sequencing to Molecular Cloning Laboratories (South San Francisco, CA). All fragments were sequenced in both forward and reverse directions for confirmation of any nucleotide variation in congenital cataract patients and controls and compared to the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene">Human Genome Reference Sequence</ext-link> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/1420">NC_000002.11</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/2703">NC_000001.10</ext-link>) provided by the National Center for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/guide/">NCBI</ext-link>), using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/">ClustalW2</ext-link> (multiple sequence alignment program for DNA; European Bioinformatics Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton, Cambridge, UK).</p>
        <table-wrap id="t1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Oligonucleotides used as primers for PCR amplification of <italic>CRYAB</italic>, <italic>CRYGC</italic>, <italic>CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic> and their annealing temperatures.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="81" span="1"/>
            <col width="185" span="1"/>
            <col width="186" span="1"/>
            <col width="113" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Gene (exon)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Forward primer (5′→3′)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Reverse primer (5′→3′)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Temperature (°C)</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYAB</italic> (1)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCTGACATCACCATTCCAGA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGCAGGGTAGGAAAGGAAA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYAB</italic> (2)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGCAGAATAAGACAGCACCTG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAGCCTCCAAAGCTGATAG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYAB</italic> (3)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGTTGTCATGGCATTTGGTC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCATTCACTGGTGGGGAAA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGC</italic> (1,2)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGCCATCCTGCTATATAG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGCATGATGGAAATCTAG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGC</italic> (3)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTTGGACAAATTCTGGAA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCACAATGAAAGAATGAC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic> (1)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGAACACGAAAATGCCCTTG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTCTCACAGGCCTGCTCCT<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic> (2)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGCTTCCTCCATCGC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCTGGGTCCTGACTTGA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic> (3)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTGGACTGCCTAACAATGC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACATCTTGGTTGCCATTTG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic> (1)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TATGGGCGACTGGAGTTTCCT<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCCATGCGGACGTAGTGCAC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic> (2)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCTGGGTGCTGCAGATCATC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACAGAGGCCACAGACAACAT<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic> (3)<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACTACTTCCTGTACGGGTTC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCTTGGTAGCCCCGGGACAA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic> (4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTCTCCTCCATCCAGAAAGCC</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCATACGGTTAGATCGTCTGA</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Computational assessment of missense mutations</title>
        <p>We used an evolutionary model to predict the functional consequence of genetic variation in the ATP-binding cassette, sub-family A (<italic>ABC1</italic>), member 1 gene and tested these predictions through in vitro assessments of protein function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r33">33</xref>]. We predicted the functional consequence of each variant using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org/">PANTHER</ext-link>. The probability that a given coding variant will cause a deleterious functional change is estimated by the substitution position-specific evolutionary conservation (sub-PSEC) score. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link> (Sorting Intolerant From Tolerant) analysis tool was also used to predict the functional impact of missense changes identified in this study. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link> is a sequence homology based tool that sorts intolerant from tolerant amino acid substitutions and predicts whether an amino acid substitution in a protein will have a phenotypic effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r34">34</xref>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link> is based on the premise that protein evolution is correlated with protein function. Positions with normalized probabilities less than 0.05 are predicted to be deleterious and, those greater than or equal to 0.05 are predicted to be tolerated in case of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link>. We have also used an improved splice site predictor tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">35</xref>] to predict whether a nucleotide change is likely to create a splice site.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Protein modeling</title>
        <p>The normal and mutant proteins were analyzed for their structure. Prediction of structure differences between wild and mutant were performed using Discovery Studio (DS) 2.0 (Accelrys Inc., San Diego, CA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r36">36</xref>]. The first step in homology modeling method was to find suitable homologus structure (template). Comparative modeling for GJA8 was not possible as the homology model has only 21% sequence identity whereas homology model for human γC-crystallin has 84% sequence identity, thus the comparative modeling for human γC-crystallin was possible using homology model.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Comparative modeling of human γC-crystallin</title>
        <p>The best available template for the modeling of 3-D structure of the human γC-crystallin was a high resolution (1.9 Å) crystal structure of mouse γC-crystallin (PDB ID=<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein?term=2V2U">2V2U</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r37">37</xref>]. The sequence identity and similarity between human and mouse γC-crystallin was found to be 84% and 91%, respectively. This template was used to build the homology model of human γC-crystallin using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://salilab.org/modeller/">MODELER 9.2</ext-link> program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>] available in Discovery Studio (DS) 2.0 (Accelrys Inc., San Diego, CA), a software package for molecular modeling and simulation. The model with the lowest energy among all the generated models was taken and its stereochemistry checked using the Ramachandran plot. The native model was solvated and further minimized using the available molecular dynamics (MD) simulation protocols to ensure the stability of the generated model. The 3-D model structure of human γC-crystallin mutant (Arg48His) was developed taking the model structure of wild type human γC-crystallin by using the “Build Mutant” protocol and altering the corresponding residue from Arg to His. The built model of mutant was optimized similar to the wild-type human γC-crystallin. The explicit solvent MD simulation was also performed similar to the wild type human γC-crystallin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The correlation coefficient between mutations in crystallin and gap junction protein genes and parameters like degree of opacification, morphology of congenital cataract, and visual acuity were calculated by spearman's test. p-value less than 0.05 is considered as significant. Statistical analyses were performed using graphpad software (GraphPad Software, Inc., La Jolla, CA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Clinical findings</title>
        <p>A total of 30 congenital cataract patients below 3 years of age were enrolled in this study. The mean age of the patients was 1.75±0.19 years (one month to 3 years). The age of onset was recorded as the age at which the disease was first noticed by the parents or first documented by a clinician. All cases were sporadic and were enrolled consecutively as they presented to Dr. R.P. Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences. In this study 20 cases were males and 10 were females. None of the cases were product of consanguineous marriage and all cases had bilateral congenital cataract. The cataract phenotype varied among patients as 66.66% (20/30) of patients had nuclear cataract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1A</xref>), 23.33% (7/30) had zonular/lamellar type cataract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1B</xref>), 6.66% (2/30) had anterior polar cataract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1C</xref>), and 3.3% (1/30) had total cataract (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1D</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). In this study 93% cases were detected with one or the other nucleotide alterations in <italic>CRYAB, CRYGC</italic>, <italic>CRYGD</italic>, and <italic>GJA8.</italic> Six nucleotide variations were detected in patients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). 66% nucleotide changes were found in crystallin genes (<italic>CRYAB</italic>, <italic>CYRGC</italic>, and <italic>CRYGD</italic>) and 44% were detected in connexin (<italic>GJA8</italic>). Of the six mutations identified, two were novel and four have been reported.</p>
        <fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Different types of cataract. <bold>A</bold>: Nuclear cataract: The eye picture shows opacity of both lenses in one of the patient. <bold>B</bold>: Zonular/lamellar cataract: The zonular/lamellar cataract in one of the patient. <bold>C</bold>: Polar Cataract: Anterior polar cataract phenotype shown by one of the patient. <bold>D</bold>: Total Cataract: total cataract phenotype found in one patient.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f1"/>
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="t2" position="float">
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Mutations detected and the associated phenotype seen in patients. (Abbrevations: OD-Right eye, OS-Left eye, N/A-Not applicable, mm-millimeter).</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="54" span="1"/>
            <col width="50" span="1"/>
            <col width="82" span="1"/>
            <col width="66" span="1"/>
            <col width="62" span="1"/>
            <col width="37" span="1"/>
            <col width="73" span="1"/>
            <col width="78" span="1"/>
            <col width="118" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">
                  <bold>Axial length (mm)</bold>
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hr/>
                </th>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Case number</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Age/sex (years)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Age of onset (years)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Cataract phenotype</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Corneal diameter (mm)</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>OD</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>OS</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Visual acuity (decimal) binocular</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Mutation detected</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC1<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pulverulent Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGC:p.R48H, CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC2<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dense Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.50<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar cataract with nystagmus<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC4<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.50<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC5<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 years<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar pulverulent<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC6<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.80<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC7<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progressive lamellar cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.70<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYAB:rs11603779T&gt;G<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC8<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.70<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYAB:rs11603779T&gt;G<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC9<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pulverulent Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.50<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.60<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC11<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC12<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior polar cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.60<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GJA8:p.L268L, CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC13<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar cataract with nystagmus<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.50<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC14<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.60<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC15<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dense Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYAB:rs11603779T&gt;G<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC16<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC17<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC18<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 years<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract with nystagmus<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.80<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGC:p.R48H, CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC19<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.60<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGC:p.R48H, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar cataract with nystagmus<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGC:p.R48H, GJA8: p.L281C, CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC21<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC22<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.90<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYAB:rs11603779T&gt;G<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC23<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pulverulent Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.50<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC24<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior polar cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.80<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.20<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC26<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC27<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC28<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11/M<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract pulverulent<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">09.4<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.40<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC29<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1/F<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">since birth<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.30<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.90<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC30</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/F</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 year</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract with nystagmus</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.10</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.50</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD:p.R95R, CRYGD: c.T564C</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="t3" position="float">
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Nucleotide variations found in congenital Cataract patients.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="51" span="1"/>
            <col width="95" span="1"/>
            <col width="52" span="1"/>
            <col width="69" span="1"/>
            <col width="72" span="1"/>
            <col width="57" span="1"/>
            <col width="99" span="1"/>
            <col width="65" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Sample number</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Nucleotide change</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Locus</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Codon change</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Amino acid change</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Type of mutation</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>PANTHER/SIFT score</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Frequency</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rs11603779T&gt;G^<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYAB<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">intronic<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.G181A*<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGT&gt;CAT<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R48H<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.72/1.00<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.33%<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.T564C^<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3′UTR<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.66%<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.A313G^<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRYGD<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGA&gt;AGG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R95R<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYN<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33%<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.C857T^<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GJA8<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTC&gt;CTT<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L268L<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYN<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3%<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.T905C*</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GJA8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTG&gt;TCG</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L281C</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.97/0.00</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3%</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <p> (Abbrevations: *Novel variations, ^Reported- <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org">ensembl</ext-link>, SYN-synonymous, NS-Non-synonymous, N/A-Not applicable).</p>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Summary of mutations in α-crystallin genes</title>
        <p>The α-crystallin gene family consists of two similar genes coding for αA-crystallin (<italic>CRYAA</italic> located on chromosome 21q22.3) and αB-crystallin (<italic>CRYAB</italic> on chromosome 11q22.1) sharing 57% sequence identity. <italic>CRYAB</italic> contains 3 exons which encodes a 175 amino acid protein. Direct sequencing of the coding regions and of the flanking intronic sequences of <italic>CRYAB</italic> revealed one nucleotide change (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp?term=rs11603779">rs11603779</ext-link>T&gt;G) in the intronic region between exon 2 and 3 of <italic>CRYAB</italic>. The variation was found in 13.33% (4/30) case of congenital cataract. No nucleotide changes were found in controls. Improved splice site prediction for <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp?term=rs11603779">rs11603779</ext-link>T&gt;G showed that this location is not present at splice site and may not create a splicing error in <italic>CRYAB.</italic></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Summary of mutations in γ-crystallin genes</title>
        <p>The γ-crystallin gene family is mainly located in a cluster of six highly related genes (<italic>CRYGA-CRYGF</italic>) on human chromosome 2q33–35 and the seventh <italic>CRYG</italic> gene (<italic>CRYGS</italic>) on human chromosome 3. Mutations in <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>CRYGD</italic> have been associated with congenital and hereditary cataract (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>). Direct sequencing of the coding region and of the flanking intronic sequences of <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>CRYGD</italic> revealed three sequence variations. One heterozygous nucleotide change (c.G181A) was detected in exon 2 of <italic>CRYGC</italic>, resulting in the substitution of Arg to His at codon 48 (p.R48H; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>) and was found in 13.33% (4/30) cases of congenital cataract. The multiple sequence alignments generated using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/sss/fasta/genomes.html">FASTA3</ext-link> (version 3 at the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/">EBI</ext-link>) software showed that the Arg at position 48 of human <italic>CRYGC</italic> is highly conserved in <italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>, <italic>Canis lupus</italic>, <italic>Bos taurus</italic>, <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>, <italic>Mus musculus</italic>, and <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). Nucleotide change p.R48H was found to be non-pathogenic on insilico analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org/">PANTHER</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). However as this change was in a highly conserved domain it may adversely affect protein function. None of the nucleotide changes were detected in control group. Two nucleotide changes in <italic>CRYGD</italic>; c.A313G in exon 3, resulting in synonymous change (p.R95R; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp?term=rs2305430">rs2305430</ext-link>) and c.T564C (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp?term=rs2305429">rs2305429</ext-link>) in the 3′UTR region, were also observed in 28 and 23 patients, respectively.</p>
        <table-wrap id="t4" position="float">
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Summary of the mutations identified in <italic>CRYGD</italic>, <italic>CRYGC</italic>, and <italic>GJA8</italic> with different congenital cataract phenotypes belonging to different ethnic groups.</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="50" span="1"/>
            <col width="93" span="1"/>
            <col width="99" span="1"/>
            <col width="106" span="1"/>
            <col width="70" span="1"/>
            <col width="62" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Gene</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Nucleotide</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Amino acid</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Phenotype</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Ethnicity</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Reference</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.43C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg15Cys<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Punctate cataract, juvenile progressive, Coralliform/nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caucasian, Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r70">70</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.43C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg15Ser<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coralliform<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r71">71</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.70C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro24Thr<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar, Cerulean Coral-shaped- coralliform, Flaky-silica-like nuclear cataract, Fasciculiform<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian, Moroccan, Caucasian, Australian, Chinese, Saudi Arabian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r72">72</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.109C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg37Ser<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">with protein crystallization, Nuclear golden crystal<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czech boy, Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r73">73</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.168C&gt;G<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr56Stop<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazilian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r74">74</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.176G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg59His<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aculeiform<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macedonian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.181G&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly61Cys<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coralliform<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r75">75</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.320A&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Glu107Ala<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r76">76</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.403C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Tyr134Stop<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No data<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danish<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r69">69</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.418C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg140Stop<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">41</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.470G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Trp157Stop<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">46</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.494delG<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly165fs<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r72">72</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGD</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.229C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg77Ser<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior polar, Coronary<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r77">77</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGC</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.13A&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Thr5Pro<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coppock-like<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">----<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGC</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.123insGCGGC<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Gly41delinsGlyfsX62<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular pulverulent<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">----<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r45">45</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGC</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.502C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg168Trp<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamellar/nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">----<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">46</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGC</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.327C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Cys109X<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r47">47</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>CRYGC</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c. 181G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg48His<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular and nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present study<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.68G&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg23Thr<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Progressive dense nuclear<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iranian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.92T&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile31Thr<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.131T&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Val44Glu<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cataract and microcornea<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r68">68</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.134G&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Trp45Ser<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jellyfish-like cataract and microcornea<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.139G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asp47Asn<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear pulverulent cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">English<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r57">57</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.139G&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Asp47Tyr<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r58">58</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.142G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Glu48Lys<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular nuclear pulverulent<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pakistani<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r59">59</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.191T&gt;G<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Val64Gly<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r60">60</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.235G&gt;C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Val79Leu<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full moon like with Y-sutural opacities<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r61">61</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.262C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro88Ser<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular pulverulent<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">English<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r62">62</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.262C&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro88Gln<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Balloon-like”cataract with Y-sutural opacities<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">English, Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r63">63</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.565C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Pro189Leu<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuclear cataract and microcornea<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Danish<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r69">69</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.593G&gt;A<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Arg198Gln<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior subcapsular cataract and microcornea<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r68">68</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.670insA<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fs<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total cataract and nystagmus<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r64">64</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.741T&gt;G<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ile247Met<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular pulverulent cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russian<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r65">65</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ins776G<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fs<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triangular nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">German<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r66">66</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                  <hr/>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c.827C&gt;T<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Ser276Phe<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulverulent nuclear cataract<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chinese<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r67">67</xref>]<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>GJA8</italic>
                </td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">c. 905T&gt;C</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p.Leu281Cys</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zonular Cataract</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Indian</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present study</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <fig id="f2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic>CRYGC</italic> DNA sequence in an affected and an unaffected individual. <bold>A</bold>: DNA sequence electropherogram of an unaffected individual showing wild type G at position 181. <bold>B</bold>: DNA sequence electropherogram showing the heterozygous 181G&gt;A substitution that replaces Arginine by Histidine at codon 48 in the affected individual. The position of mutated (G&gt;A) and wild type nucleotide G in an affected and an unaffected individual is indicated in box.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f2"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f3" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Multiple sequence alignment of the fourth Greek key motif of CRYGC is shown from <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (codons 1–62), <italic>Macaca mulatta, Canis lupus, Bos Taurus, Rattus norvegicus, Mus musculus</italic>, and <italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>. The Arg48 residue is highly conserved.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f3"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Summary of mutations in the <italic>GJA8</italic> (Connexin-50) gene</title>
        <p>Direct sequencing of the amplified fragments of <italic>GJA8</italic> in congenital cataract patients identified two single base alterations (p.L268L and p.L281C). The change p.L268L was found in 3.33% (1/30) case of congenital cataract with anterior polar cataract whereas p.L281C (heterozygous) also found in 3.33% (1/30) cases. This case had lamellar/zonular form of cataract with nystagmoid movement. Both the nucleotide alterations (c.C857T and c.T905C) were in the second exon of <italic>GJA8</italic>. The nucleotide alteration c.T905C resulted in a novel amino acid substitution of leucine to cysteine at codon 281 (p.L281C; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>) whereas the c.C857T nucleotide alteration leads to a synonymous amino acid substitution. GJA8 family protein sequences were obtained from NCBI website and multiple-sequence alignments of GJA8 family proteins from various species were obtained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>) using <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/sss/fasta/genomes.html">FASTA</ext-link> (version 3 at the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/">EBI</ext-link>). This changed a phylogenetically conserved leucine to cysteine at codon 281 (p.L281C). Computational analysis (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org/">PANTHER</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link>) of p.L281C predicted this nucleotide change as a pathogenic variant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). The remainder of the <italic>GJA8</italic> coding sequence showed no change. In addition, these nucleotide changes were not detected in 30 normal unrelated individuals from the same ethnic background.</p>
        <fig id="f4" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic>GJA8</italic> DNA sequence in an affected and an unaffected individual. <bold>A</bold>: DNA sequence electropherogram of an unaffected individual showing wild type T at position 905. <bold>B</bold>: DNA sequence electropherogram showing the heterozygous 905T&gt;C substitution that replaces Leucine by Cysteine at codon 281 in the affected individual. The position of mutated (T&gt;C) and wild type nucleotide G in an affected and an unaffected individual is indicated in the box.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f4"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f5" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Multiple sequence alignment of the fourth Greek key motif of GJA8 is shown from <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (codons 243–290), <italic>Pan troglodytes, Canis lupus, Bos Taurus, Mus musculus</italic>, <italic>Gallus gallus</italic> and <italic>Danio rerio</italic>. The Lys281 residue is highly conserved.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f5"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Comparative modeling study of γC-crystallin</title>
        <p>Since the sequence identity between target (human γC-crystallin) and template (mouse γC-crystallin) was 84% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>), the structural reliability of the generated 3-dimensional homology model was high. The stability of the modeled wild-type and mutant (Arg48His) human γC-crystallin was checked by performing molecular dynamics simulation. These results indicated that the structures were stable. Both the wild type and mutant had very similar conformation with good geometry. The structure of wild type as well as mutant human γC-crystallin consisted of three small helices (each helix contains four residues), four anti-parallel β-strands and connecting loops (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="f6" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Sequence alignment of wild type human γC-crystallin and mouse γC-crystallin (PDB ID: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein?term=2V2U">2V2U</ext-link>).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f6"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f7" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Change in conformation of loop3 in wild type (in magenta) and mutant (in orange) of human γC-crystallin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f7"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>In-silico analysis</title>
        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org/">PANTHER</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link> online tools were used for potential functional prediction of mutant proteins. After input the amino acid sequences of the wild-type CRYGC and GJA8 protein and their mutants, the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pantherdb.org/">PANTHER</ext-link> scores were −2.72 and −3.97, respectively, whereas the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org/">SIFT</ext-link> scores were 1.00 and 0.00, respectively, which meant that the variant (CRYGC:p.R48H) was predicted as “non-pathogenic” and the variant (GJA8:p.L281C) was predicted as “pathogenic” with high confidence. In comparison with the wild-type CRYGC and GJA8 protein, the hydrophobicity of the mutants CRYGC and GJA8 were dramatically increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8</xref>). The secondary structure of mutant and wild type amino acid sequences of <italic>GJA8</italic> were analyzed by Antheprot 2000ver. 6.0 software (IBCP, Lyon,France) which showed that the mutation p.L281C lead to the replacement of random coil with extended loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9">Figure 9</xref>). This replacement may be sufficient to change the secondary structure of the protein resulting in lens opacification.</p>
        <fig id="f8" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Hydrophobicity analysis. <bold>A</bold>: Comparision of hydrophobicity between wild type and mutant CRYGC. The protscale online software predict the effect of substitution on CRYGC protein hydrophobicity. Hydrophobicity of mutant protein increases around mutation point (R48H). <bold>B</bold>: Comparision of hydrophobicity between wild type and mutant GJA8. The protscale online software predict the effect of substitution on GJA8 protein hydrophobicity. Hydrophobicity of mutant protein increases around mutation point (L281C).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f8"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="f9" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <p>The predicted secondary structure of the mutant and wild type amino acid sequences. Target sequences are shown by red box which indicate that random coil has been replaced by the exented loop.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f9"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Genotype-phenotypes correlation</title>
        <p>The genotype-phenotype correlation with the different morphological types of congenital cataract, their severity, visual acuity and different mutations have been tabulated (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t5">Table 5</xref>). The genotype and phenotype correlation coefficient (r value) between parameters like Degree of opacification, morphology of congenital cataract, visual acuity and mutations, showed no significance and hence no association between mutations and different parameters. Therefore no particular type of cataract was found to be associated with any particular mutant phenotype.</p>
        <table-wrap id="t5" position="float">
          <label>Table 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Correlation coefficient and p value between crystallins and gap junction protein gene mutations and visual parameters (degree of opacification and visual acuity).</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="147" span="1"/>
            <col width="147" span="1"/>
            <col width="147" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Mutations</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Degree of opacification</bold>
                </th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Visual acuity</bold>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGC</italic>:p.R48H<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.1903, p=0.3139<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.0747, p=0.6945<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic>:p.R95R<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.0808, p=0.6711<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.0490, p=0.7969<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic>:T564C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.0955, p=0.6154<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.04662, p=0.8067<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CRYGD</italic>:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/snp?term=rs11603779">rs11603779</ext-link>T&gt;G<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.0951, p=0.6170<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.0753, p=0.6922<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic>:p.L268L<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.2252, p=0.2315<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.1110, p=0.5594<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>GJA8</italic>:p.L281C<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.2252, p=0.2315<hr/></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=-0.2336, p=0.2394<hr/></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visual acuity</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r=0.1915, p=0.3100</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The transparency and high refractive index of the lens are achieved by the precise architecture of the fiber cells and the homeostasis of the lens proteins in terms of their concentration, stability, and supramolecular organization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r40">40</xref>]. In this pilot study we identified six nucleotide variations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). Crystallin specific mutations (16.6%) were identified which is similar to the mutations detected in south Indian population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">41</xref>]. We also detected 16.6% <italic>GJA8</italic> specific variations in congenital cataract cases. We identified two non-synonymous novel mutations, p.R48H(4/30) and p.L281C(1/30) in <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>GJA8</italic>, respectively. Crystallins (α-, β-, and γ-crystallin) encode the major proportion of water soluble structural proteins of the lens fiber cells and are ubiquitous lens proteins. Functional changes and alteration of crystallin molecular properties could cause the breakdown of the lens microstructure and result in changes in the refractive index and increased light scattering.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Description of mutations in <italic>CRYGC</italic> and associated phenotypes</title>
        <p>It is reported that self aggregation or quaternary structural alteration of γ-crystallin is responsible for the phenotypic association with lens opacification as well as cataractogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, four mutations in <italic>CRYGC</italic> have been reported in the literature (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r47">47</xref>]. The mutation p.R48H involves substitution of highly basic and polar charged Arginine with a neutral and less polar Histidine which may cause conformational changes. Arginine has well spread electron density enabling high solubility. It is a hydrophilic amino acid with a positive charge and lies within the extended strand on the surface of the molecule, interacting with water. Arginine is replaced by histidine, a hydrophobic amino acid compared to arginine. It has been reported that changing the solvation property of an amino acid residue on the surface of the γ-crystallin protein diminishes its solubility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>]. The distorted γC-crystallin may change its folding properties as shown in a study where the COOH-terminal domain folds before and nucleates the folding of the NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal domain in human γD-crystallin refolding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r49">49</xref>]. The relatively loose or partially unfolded structure of mutant γC-crystallin may be susceptible to aggregation and insolubilization, which leads to cataract formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r50">50</xref>]. Another possible consequence of the R48H mutation may be related to the disturbances of the interactions between γC-crystallin and other crystallins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r51">51</xref>].</p>
        <p>The overall conformation, secondary structure elements and geometry of the conformers of wild-type and mutant human γC-crystallin were mainly similar. The most significant variation was observed in the conformation of the loop 3 region involving residues 47–54 which houses the mutation (Arg48His; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>). The mutant has substitution of the longer and basic Arginine by a shorter Histidine possessing an imidazole ring. Thus this mutation alters the characteristic of this residue in both nature and length which is reflected in the difference in its interactions with neighboring amino acid residues The Arg48 in the wild type interacts with its adjacent acidic residue Glu47 which in turn forms a hydrogen bond with Gln54 thus stabilizing the loop 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10">Figure 10A</xref>). Thus the interaction of Glu47 with both residues Arg48 and Gln54 imparts an orientation to loop3. In the case of the mutant the shorter Histidine is no longer able to interact with Glu47 but instead interacts with Gln52 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10">Figure 10B</xref>). This loss of the stabilizing interaction enables Glu47 to adopt a different orientation and it in turn interacts with Arg77 while maintaining its interaction with Gln54. This alteration in the orientation of Glu47 and subsequently its interacting residues in the mutant, results in the modification of the relative orientation of the loop 3 comprising residues 47 to 54.</p>
        <fig id="f10" fig-type="figure" position="float">
          <label>Figure 10</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Hydrogen bond interactions. <bold>A</bold>: Conformation of loop3 (in magenta) in wild type human γC-crystallin. <bold>B</bold>: Conformation of loop3 (in orange) in mutant (R48H) human γC-crystallin.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="mv-v17-693-f10"/>
        </fig>
        <p>γ-Crystallins are long lived proteins of the lens and are generally characterized by both high stability and solubility. A key feature of γ-crystallins is that their surfaces are covered in ion pairs. The Arg head groups are most accessible to solvent water and therefore have a profound effect on the surrounding water, particularly important in lens. Since sequences of γ-crystallins are optimized for high solubility and minor changes to the surface can dramatically alter solution interaction properties. So the changes in protein conformations can decrease in solubility and stability of native protein which could result in aggregation of protein and thus opacification of lens. The R48H mutation interferes with the formation of two COOH-terminal Greek key motifs. Although the function of the Greek key motifs has not been elaborated in detail, computer-based analysis suggests that it may be responsible for particular protein–protein interactions in the lens, and it is postulated to be critical in the maintenance of lens transparency. The possible influence of the mutation on the structure as well as the function of γC-crystallin requires further investigation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Description of mutations in <italic>GJA8</italic> and associated phenotypes</title>
        <p><italic>GJA8</italic> is located on chromosome 1q21.1 and encodes a 50 kDa protein (connexin 50; Cx50). Cx-50 is a member of the connexin family of proteins that are important in the formation of gap junction channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>] in human lens which are responsible for direct intercellular transfer of ions and molecules between adjacent cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r53">53</xref>]. Since the eye lens is an avascular structure, it relies heavily on an intercellular communication system constructed of gap junctions for preservation of tissue homeostasis and transparency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>]. Cx50 contains four transmembrane domains (M1, M2, M3, and M4) linked by two extracellular loops (E1 and E2), as well as an intracellular loop (CL), and intra-cytoplasmic NH<sub>2</sub>- and COOH-termini [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>]. Mutant connexins are unable to participate in gap junction formation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>] and inhibit channel formation. To date, 22 mutations have been detected in <italic>GJA8</italic> in association with congenital cataract (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r69">69</xref>]. We identified a novel missense mutation, p.L281C, in GJA8 in cases with congenital cataract (zonular/lamellar cataract with nystagmus). Different mutations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t4">Table 4</xref>) in the connexin gene are often associated pulverulent nuclear opacities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r69">69</xref>]. However some studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r63">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r67">67</xref>] have detected mutations in <italic>GJA8</italic> which were associated with zonular/lamellar cataract phenotype as we found in this study. Insilico analysis of p.L281C mutation showed that the hydrophobicity of the mutant protein increased while the hydrophobic moment decreased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f8">Figure 8</xref>). The predicted new characteristics of the mutant protein, which include altered interactions with other proteins, altered regulation activities of <italic>GJA8</italic>, and altered assemblies, may be the cause of the disease.</p>
        <p>Our findings further expand the mutation spectrum of <italic>GJA8</italic> and <italic>CRYGC</italic> in congenital cataract. In summary, this study identified variations in 28 of 30 congenital cataract patients in north Indian population. Crystallin family (α- and γ-crystallin) accounts for 66% of the variations whereas connexins accounts for 44% of the total variations. It is notable that only two variations (<italic>CRYGC</italic>:p.R48H and <italic>GJA8</italic>:p.L281C) in <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>GJA8</italic> detected in this study were predicted to be pathogenic which may cause congenital cataract. This study further confirms that <italic>CRYGC</italic> and <italic>GJA8</italic> play a major role in the maintenance of lens transparency and expands the mutation spectrum of both the genes in congenital cataract.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank all patients and their family members who participated in this study. This study was financially supported by the ICMR (Indian Council of Medical Research, New Delhi, India). Manoj Kumar is a Senior Research Fellow (SRF) of ICMR and gratefully acknowledges ICMR for its financial support.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="r1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wozencraft</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reuter</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parks</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaiser-Kupfer</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Autosomal dominant congenital cataract. Interocular phenotypic variability.</article-title>
          <source>Ophthalmology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>866</fpage>
          <lpage>71.8190472</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8190472</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genetics of cataract: our vision becomes clearer.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>520</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9497271</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular genetic basis of inherited cataract and associated phenotypes.</article-title>
          <source>Surv Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>300</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110667</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Johnson GJ, editor. The epidemiology of eye disease. 2nd ed. London: Arnold; 2003.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foster</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rahi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology of cataract in childhood: a global perspective.</article-title>
          <source>J Cataract Refract Surg</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>601</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278811</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Das</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borah</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guha</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gogate</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purukayastha</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Causes of childhood blindness in the northeastern states of India.</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974521</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Titiyal</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pal</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murthy</surname>
              <given-names>GV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tandon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vajpayee</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilbert</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Causes and temporal trends of blindness and severe visual impairment in children in schools for the blind in North India.</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>941</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12881329</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dandona</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rao</surname>
              <given-names>GN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population-based assessment of childhood blindness in southern India.</article-title>
          <source>Arch Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>116</volume>
          <fpage>545</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9565065</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">[REMOVED IF= FIELD]Census of India 2001. India: Registrar General and Census Commissioner, 2001. </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santhiya</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sudhakar</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klopp</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Illig</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Söker</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groth</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Platzer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gopinath</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular analysis of cataract families in India: new mutations in the CRYBB2 and GJA3 genes and rare polymorphisms.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1837</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21031021</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johar</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savalia</surname>
              <given-names>NK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasavada</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology based etiological study of pediatric cataract in western India.</article-title>
          <source>Indian J Med Sci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051906</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gogate</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalua</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Courtright</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blindness in childhood in developing countries: time for a reassessment?</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>e1000177</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19997501</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Congenital cataract and their molecular genetics.</article-title>
          <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>134</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18035564</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shiels</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cat-Map: putting cataract on the map.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>2007</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21042563</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mouse models of cataract.</article-title>
          <source>J Genet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>469</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20090208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reddy</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collyer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vithana</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MacKay</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dawson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carey</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinlan</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alpha-B crystallin gene (CRYAB) mutation causes dominant congenital posterior polar cataract in humans.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>1141</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11577372</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jing</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decreasing the homodimer interaction: a common mechanism shared by the deltaG91 mutation and deamidation in betaA3-crystallin.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>438</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20300566</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A missense mutation in CRYBA4 associated with congenital cataract and microcornea.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1019</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20577656</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Billingsley</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santhiya</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paterson</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogata</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wodak</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hosseini</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Manisastry</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gopinath</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CRYBA4, a novel human cataract gene, is also involved in microphthalmia.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>702</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16960806</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Riazuddin</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yasmeen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sergeev</surname>
              <given-names>YV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zulfiqar</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riaz</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riazuddin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in betaB3-crystallin associated with autosomal recessive cataract in two Pakistani families.</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>2100</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914629</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gamma-S crystallin gene (CRYGS) mutation causes dominant progressive cortical cataract in humans.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>706</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16141006</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Song</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Landsbury</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahm</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinlan</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functions of the intermediate filament cytoskeleton in the eye lens.</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>1837</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19587458</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation analysis of congenital cataract in a Chinese family identified a novel missense mutation in the connexin 46 gene (GJA3).</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>713</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaushal</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Missense mutations in MIP underlie autosomal dominant 'polymorphic' and lamellar cataracts linked to 12q.</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>15</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802646</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pras</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levy-Nissenbaum</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bakhan</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lahat</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Assia</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geffen-Carmi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frydman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldman</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pras</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A missense mutation in the LIM2 gene is associated with autosomal recessive presenile cataract in an inbred IraqiJewish family.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>1363</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917274</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cui</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weng</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Removal of Hsf4 leads to cataract development in mice through down-regulation of gamma S-crystallin and Bfsp expression.</article-title>
          <source>BMC Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>10</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19224648</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r27">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>SQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Progress in pathogenic genes and their functions of congenital cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Zhonghua Yan Ke Za Zhi</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>280</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20450675</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r28">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wistow</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piatigorsky</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lens crystallins: the evolution and expression of proteins for a highly specialized tissue.</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>479</fpage>
          <lpage>504</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3052280</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r29">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fletcher</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Connexin mediated cataract prevention in mice.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>e12624</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20844585</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r30">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel mutation in GJA8 causing congenital cataract-microcornea syndrome in a Chinese pedigree.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1585</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20806042</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r31">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>SQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel connexin 50 (GJA8) mutation in a Chinese family with a dominant congenital pulverulent nuclear cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>418</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334966</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Sambrook J, Fritsch EF, Maniatus T. Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual, second ed., Cold Spring Harbour Labortory Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r33">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brunham</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singaraja</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pape</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kejariwal</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayden</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accurate prediction of the functional significance of single nucleotide polymorphisms and mutations in the ABCA1 gene.</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>e83</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16429166</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r34">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ng</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henikoff</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SIFT: Predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function.</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>3812</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r35">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reese</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eeckman</surname>
              <given-names>FH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kulp</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haussler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improved splice site detection in Genie.</article-title>
          <source>J Comput Biol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>311</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <comment>.9278062</comment>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278062</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Discovery Studio 2.0.</collab></person-group>Molecular modeling program package. Accelrys Software Inc; San Diego, CA USA<year>2006</year></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r37">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Purkiss</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bateman</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wyatt</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilmarth</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>David</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wistow</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slingsby</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biophysical Properties of? C-Crystallin in Human and Mouse Eye Lens: The Role of Molecular Dipoles.</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>372</volume>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17659303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r38">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sali</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blundell</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative protein modelling by satisfaction of spatial restraints.</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>234</volume>
          <fpage>779</fpage>
          <lpage>815</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8254673</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r39">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sali</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pottertone</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuan</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Vlijmen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karplus</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of comparative protein modeling by MODELLER.</article-title>
          <source>Proteins</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>318</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710825</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r40">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cataract mutations and lens development.</article-title>
          <source>Prog Retin Eye Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9932285</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r41">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devi</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sergeev</surname>
              <given-names>YV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sundaresan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystallin gene mutations in Indian families with inherited pediatric cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1157</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18587492</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r42">
        <label>42</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pande</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pande</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asherie</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lomakin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogun</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lubsen</surname>
              <given-names>NH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walton</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benedek</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular basis of a progressive juvenile-onset hereditary cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>1993</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688888</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r43">
        <label>43</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pande</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pande</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asherie</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lomakin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogun</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benedek</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal cataract: human genetic cataract caused by protein crystallization.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>6116</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371638</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r44">
        <label>44</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Devi</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel mutations in GJA8 associated with autosomal dominant congenital cataract and microcornea.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>190</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16604058</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r45">
        <label>45</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hansen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eiberg</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kjaer</surname>
              <given-names>KW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baggesen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenberg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic heterogeneity in microcornea-cataract: five novel mutations in CRYAA, CRYGD, and GJA8.</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>3937</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724170</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r46">
        <label>46</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Héon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Priston</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schorderet</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billingsley</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Girard</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lubsen</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munier</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The? -crystallins and human cataracts: a puzzle made clearer.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>1261</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10521291</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r47">
        <label>47</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roshan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijaya</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lavanya</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shama</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Santhiya</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gopinath</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satyamoorthy</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel human CRYGD mutation in a juvenile autosomal dominant cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>887</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20508808</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r48">
        <label>48</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wyatt</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wistow</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bateman</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wallace</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slingsby</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The P23T cataract mutation causes loss of solubility of folded gammaD-crystallin.</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>343</volume>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15451671</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r49">
        <label>49</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flaugh</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosinski-Collins</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interdomain sidechain interactions in human gammaD crystallin influencing folding and stability.</article-title>
          <source>Protein Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>2030</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046626</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r50">
        <label>50</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Talla</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Narayanan</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Srinivasan</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation causing self-aggregation in human gammaC-crystallin leading to congenital cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>5212</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122105</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r51">
        <label>51</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liang</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of protein-protein interactions among lens crystallins in a mammalian two-hybrid system assay.</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <fpage>4255</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11700327</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r52">
        <label>52</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berthoud</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minogue</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williamson</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebohara</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beyer</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Loss of function and impaired degradation of a cataract-associated mutant connexin 50.</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12800976</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r53">
        <label>53</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bakthavachalu</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalanke</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galande</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramanamurthy</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parab</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohale</surname>
              <given-names>KN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seshadri</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dense cataract and microphthalmia (dcm) in BALB/c mice is caused by mutations in the GJA8 locus.</article-title>
          <source>J Genet</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20861565</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r54">
        <label>54</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Willoughby</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arab</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gandhi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeinali</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arab</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luk</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billingsley</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Munier</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heon</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel GJA8 mutation in an Iranian family with progressive autosomal dominant congenital nuclear cataract.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>e124</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14627691</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r55">
        <label>55</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yun</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suo</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel GJA8 mutation (p.I31T) causing autosomal dominant congenital cataract in a Chinese family.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2813</fpage>
          <lpage>20</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r56">
        <label>56</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanita</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperling</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel mutation in GJA8 associated with jellyfish-like cataract in a family of Indian origin.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>323</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334946</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r57">
        <label>57</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arora</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minogue</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Addison</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Russel-Eggitt</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webster</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebihara</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beyer</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berthoud</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel connexin50 mutation associated with congenital nuclear pulverulent cataracts.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>155</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006672</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r58">
        <label>58</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>NN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>YC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>XQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>ZL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel GJA8 mutation in a Chinese family with autosomal dominant congenital cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Yi Chuan Xue Za Zhi</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18247306</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r59">
        <label>59</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackay</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khaliq</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hameed</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anwar</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehdi</surname>
              <given-names>SQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newbold</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ionides</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shiels</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Connexin 50 mutation in a family with congenital “zonular nuclear” pulverulent cataract of Pakistani origin.</article-title>
          <source>Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10480374</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r60">
        <label>60</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>JQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>ZW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A heterozygous transversion of connexin 50 in a family with congential nuclear cataract in the northeast of China.</article-title>
          <source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Yi Chuan Xue Za Zhi</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>76</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15696487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r61">
        <label>61</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanita</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hennies</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nürnberg</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperling</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel mutation in GJA8 associated with autosomal dominant congenital cataract in a family of Indian origin.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1217</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110920</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r62">
        <label>62</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shiels</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackay</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ionides</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berry</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharya</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A missense mutation in the human connexin50 gene (GJA8) underlies autosomal dominant “zonular pulverulent” cataract, on chromosome 1q.</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>526</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9497259</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r63">
        <label>63</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanita</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperling</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A mutation in GJA8 (p.P88Q) is associated with “balloon-like” cataract with Y-sutural opacities in a family of Indian origin.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1171</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18587493</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r64">
        <label>64</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ponnam</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramesha</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tejwani</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramamurthy</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kannabiran</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation of the gap junction protein alpha 8 (GJA8) gene causes autosomal recessive cataract.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>e85</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17601931</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r65">
        <label>65</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Polyakov</surname>
              <given-names>AV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shagina</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khlebnikova</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Evgrafov</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation in the connexin 50 gene (GJA8) in a Russian family with zonular pulverulent cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Clin Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>476</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846744</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r66">
        <label>66</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klopp</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Illig</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel GJA8 mutation causing a recessive triangular cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>851</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18483562</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r67">
        <label>67</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xiong</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>SQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel connexin 50 (GJA8) mutation in a Chinese family with a dominant congenital pulverulent nuclear cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>418</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334966</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r68">
        <label>68</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation G61C in the CRYGD gene causing autosomal dominant congenital coralliform cataracts.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>378</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334953</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r69">
        <label>69</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gillanders</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderveen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freas-Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wistow</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baxevanis</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Auken</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quesenberry</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey-Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juo</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trent</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brownstein</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Progressive juvenile-onset punctuate cataracts caused by mutation of the gD-crystallin gene.</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>1008</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927684</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r70">
        <label>70</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Messina-Baas</surname>
              <given-names>OM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez-Huerta</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cuevas-Covarrubias</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two affected siblings with nuclear cataract associated with a novel missense mutation in the CRYGD gene.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>995</fpage>
          <lpage>1000</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16943771</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r71">
        <label>71</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santhiya</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shyam Manohar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rawlley</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijayalakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Namperumalsamy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gopinath</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loster</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graw</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel mutations in the gamma-crystallin genes cause autosomal dominant congenital cataracts.</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>352</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011157</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r72">
        <label>72</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kmoch</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brynda</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asfaw</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bezouska</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novák</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rezácová</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ondrová</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Filipec</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sedlácek</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elleder</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Link between a novel human? D-crystallin allele and a unique cataract phenotype explained by protein crystallography.</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>1779</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10915766</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r73">
        <label>73</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tong</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiang</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lou</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lam</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yam</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pang</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel gammaD-crystallin mutation causes mild changes in protein properties but leads to congenital coralliform cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1521</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19668596</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r74">
        <label>74</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santana</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waiswol</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arcieri</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabral de Vasconcellos</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barbosa de Melo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation analysis of CRYAA, CRYGC, and CRYGD associated with autosomal dominant congenital cataract in Brazilian families.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>793</fpage>
          <lpage>800</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390652</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r75">
        <label>75</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yam</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tam</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lam</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pang</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel deletion variant of gammaD-crystallin responsible for congenital nuclear cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>2096</fpage>
          <lpage>104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079686</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r76">
        <label>76</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ren</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shastry</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padma</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayyagari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parks</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaiser-Kupfer</surname>
              <given-names>MI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hejtmancik</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A 5-base insertion in the gammaC-crystallin gene is associated with autosomal dominant variable zonular pulverulent cataract.</article-title>
          <source>Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10914683</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="r77">
        <label>77</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yao</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shentu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A nonsense mutation in CRYGC associated with autosomal dominant congenital nuclear cataract in a Chinese family.</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1272</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18618005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>