<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:42:01Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3185831" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:3185831</identifier><datestamp>2011-11-02</datestamp><setSpec>actamyol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Myol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Myologica</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1128-2460</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1128-2460</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pacini Editore SpA</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC3185831</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3185831</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">3185831</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21842594</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21842594</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Pacini</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title xml:lang="en">Desmin A213V substitution represents
a rare polymorphism but not a mutation
and is more prevalent in patients
with heart dilation of various origins</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>KOSTAREVA</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SJOBERG</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>GUDKOVA</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SMOLINA</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SEMERNIN</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SHLYAKHTO</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>SEJERSEN</surname>
            <given-names>T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Woman and Child Health, and Centre for Molecular Medicine, Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden;</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label> Almazov Federal Centre of Heart, Blood and Endocrinology, St. Petersburg, Russia</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1">Address for correspondence: Anna Kostareva, Department of Woman and Child Health, Center for Molecular Medicine, Karolinska
Institute, L8:02, 17176 Stockholm, Sweden. Tel. +46 851 773920. Fax +46 851 773620. E-mail <email xlink:href="anna.kostareva@ki.se">anna.kostareva@ki.se</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>30</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>42</fpage>
      <lpage>45</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>The journal and the individual contributions contained in it are protected by the copyright of Gaetano Conte Academy, Naples, Italy
</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">
          <license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several desmin mutations have been described in patients with cardiomyopathies and distal myopathies. Among them, A213V substitution has been associated with three completely different clinical phenotypes: restrictive cardiomyopathy, dilated cardiomyopathy and isolated distal myopathy. However, the identification of this substitution also in control subjects has highlighted the question if the A213V shift represents a conditional mutation, giving rise to cardiomyopathy only in the presence of other predisposing factors. The aim of the present work was to study the potential role of this substitution in predisposing to heart dilation.</p>
        <p>Methods and results. We screened 108 patients with heart dilation due to ischemic heart disease, alcoholic cardiomyopathy or viral myocarditis, and 300 healthy controls for the presence of A213V substitution by direct sequencing and confirmed the results by site-specific restriction. In the control group A213V substitution was identified in 3 out of 300 patients, representing a rare polymorphism with a frequency of approximately 1%, which corresponds to the earlier reported frequency. In the study group A213V substitution was found in 5 out of 108 cases, corresponding to approximately 4.6% (p &lt; 0.035). Therefore we conclude that A213V desmin substitution represents a conditional mutation, i.e. a rare polymorphism that plays a role as a predisposing factor resulting in maladaptive heart remodelling in the presence of other pathological factors.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Key words</title>
        <kwd>Desmin</kwd>
        <kwd>polymorphisms</kwd>
        <kwd>heart dilation</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="S1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Desmin is a chief intermediate filament of muscle cells. It is highly expressed postnatally in all types of muscle tissue where it contributes to the structural and mechanical integrity of the skeletal and cardiac myocytes as well as smooth muscle cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>). It connects to the sarcomere at the level of the Z-discs, and serves as a linker between neighboring myofibrils, thus, providing their simultaneous and effective contraction. It is also involved in proper mitochondrial positioning, ensuring mitochondrial membrane stability and proper mitochondrial function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>). Recently, besides just structural functions, desmin along with some other Z-disk associated proteins has been shown to play an important role in mechanosensing and mechanotransduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>Desmin mutations have been associated with cardiac disorders, such as cardiomyopathies (dilated, restrictive or hypertrophic), and with skeletal myopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>). More than 40 different desmin mutations have been described up to date with most of them giving rise to combined cardiac and skeletal muscle phenotype. In terms of the prevalence, desmin mutations have been shown to be a rare cause of dilated cardiomyopathy (1-2%), whereas it is found in a considerably larger proportion of restrictive cardiomyopathies in association with intracellular aggregates and conduction defects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>). Recently A213V desmin substitution has been described in seven unrelated patients with three different phenotypes; distal skeletal myopathy, restrictive cardiomyopathy, and dilated cardiomyopathy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). However, this substitution has been found also in control groups with a frequency of approximately 1%, and has also been described in a familial case of dilated cardiomyopathy where it did not segregate with the disease phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>). Therefore, it was suggested that A213V substitution represents a rare polymorphism rather than a true disease-causing mutation. Our group has previously described this substitution in a patient with late onset and rapid progression of heart dilation, no signs of coronary artery disease or previous myocardial infarction, but with a long history of arterial hypertension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>). We therefore hypothesize that A213V substitution can play a predisposing role in heart dilation in presence of other provocative and unfavorable factors. This hypothesis of A213V constituting a conditional mutation was here tested by comparing the frequency of the desmin A213V substitution in a group of patients with heart dilation due to various factors to the frequency in a healthy control group.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="S2a">
        <title>Patient cohort</title>
        <p>The study group included patients with sings of heart failure (NYHA class II-IV) and enlarged left ventricle dimensions (LVEDD &gt; 56 mm) with preserved of decreased contractile function due to various etiologies: ischemic heart disease, arterial hypertension, metabolic syndrome, alcoholic cardiomyopathy and inflammatory cardiomyopathy. They patients with genetic dilated cardiomyopathy (familial or sporadic forms) were excluded from the study. Totally, 108 patients with heart failure and cardiac dilation were included in the study group. Of these 70 (65%) were due to ischemic heart disease, including 19 (17.5%) post MI, 14 (13%) with metabolic syndrome and arterial hypertension, 10 (9%) with alcoholic cardiomyopathy and 14 (13,%) with inflammatory cardiomyopathy. Clinical data and case history were obtained by direct physical examination during patient's visit and from medical records. Echocardiography was performed according to standard protocol. Written informed consent was obtained prior to patient enrollment and was approved by the local ethical committees of Almazov Federal Centre, St.Petersburg and Stockholm. The control group included 300 healthy donors with the same Caucasian background.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S2b">
        <title>Sequencing of the desmin gene</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood using a phenol-chlorophorm purification method. Exon 2 of the desmin gene (DES) including exon-intron boundaries was amplified by PCR followed by direct DNA sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>). In all cases A213V substitution has been confirmed by restriction enzyme analysis, since A213V substitution introduces a restriction site for AccBsI, thus, cutting the original 384 bp PCR product to 103+281 fragments.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S3">
      <title>Statistical analysis</title>
      <p>Echocardiography data were analyzed using a Student's t-test and expressed as mean ± SD. The difference in the distribution of genotypes between the study group and controls was statistically analyzed by means of the Fisher's exact test to obtain a <italic>P</italic> value. A <italic>P</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered significant. Odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI) were calculated to express the strength of the association between a polymorphism and the disease.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S4">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Direct sequencing of <italic>DES</italic> exon 2 revealed A213V substitution in 5 patients from the study group, and in 3 cases from control group (4.6% and 1% respectively, P &lt; 0.035, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). There was no significant difference in mean echocardiography values between patients with and without A213V substitution in the study group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The major cause of heart failure in a patient 1 was ischemic heart disease without arterial hypertension or metabolic syndrome, complicated with ST-myocardial infarction 7 years prior to examination. Patients 2 and 3 both had metabolic syndrome including arterial hypertension, dyslipidemia and diabetes mellitus. Patient 4 was a young man suffering from chronic post-viral myocarditis confirmed by Dallas criteria after endomyocardial biopsy 4 yeas prior to examination. In patient 5 dilated cardiomyopathy was observed in combination with arterial hypertension and Marfan-like connective tissue disorder phenotype.</p>
      <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
        <label>Table 1.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Direct sequencing of <italic>DES</italic> exon 2.</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study group (n = 108)</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control group (n = 300)</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A213A</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (95.5%)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297 (99%)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A213V</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.6%)</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (1%)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn id="FN1">
            <p>P &lt; 0.035 CI – 1.1-20.0 OR 4.7</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <table-wrap id="T2" position="float">
        <label>Table 2.</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Mean echocardiography values observed in patients with and without A213V substitution.</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVEDD</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVESD</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVEDD</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVPWd</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LVPWs</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVSd</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVSs</th>
              <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EF</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pat.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.8</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.42</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pat.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pat.3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pat.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.9</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pat.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean      A213V group</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2 ± 5.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45      ± 10.8</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2 ± 7.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.7 ± 5.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 ± 2.8</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 ± 2.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 ± 1.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 ± 2.4</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 ± 12.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean study group</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.2 ± 6.6</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.2 ± 11.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 ± 6.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5 ± 8.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 ± 2.0</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1 ± 3.2</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,7 ± 2.9</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 ± 3.1</td>
              <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7 ± 14.9</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </sec>
    <sec id="S5">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Desmin A213V substitution has previously been described in different cardiac/muscle phenotypes. The first patient, described in Holland, had skeletal distal myopathy and no cardiac phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>). In spite of concomitant double-mutation in the alpha–glucosidase gene, skeletal muscle biopsy with desmin and αB crystalline -positive protein aggregates and with no evidence of glycogen or phosphatase-positive vacuoles strongly suggested the A213V desmin shift to be disease causing. The second A213V substitution was described in a familial case of restrictive cardiomyopathy without signs of skeletal muscle affection, where A213V substitution segregated with the disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). Further, our group previously described this substitution in a patient with late-onset dilated cardiomyopathy, first degree AV block and left bundle branch block. However, findings from Taylor et al. put a directly causative role of the A213V substitution at question. The substitution was found in one large pedigree with familial DCMP out of 116 families studied, as well as in 6 out of 306 non-familial cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>). While absence of clinical symptoms in several A213V carriers from this study could be explained by low penetrance, absence of this substitution in one affected family member almost ultimately excludes its exclusive primary disease-causing nature. However the possibility that A213V is a rare allelic variant, predisposing to malign cardiac remodeling as a conditional mutation has not previously been analyzed.</p>
      <p>In our study the frequency of A213V substitution in control group correspond to the earlier reports and constitutes approximately 1% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>). However, overrepresentation of A213V in the group with cardiac dilation strongly supports that this substitution may have an unfavorable impact on cardiac remodeling under various stress conditions. If so, it is particular interesting to unravel a mechanism, by which structural polymorphism of desmin influences a pattern of cardiac remodeling. In our study we did not see any overt gross alterations of desmin or vimentin filament network in A213V desmin transfected HeLa cells. A213V desmin is able to participate in fine filamentous network and does not appear, at the light microscope level, to interfere with vimentin filaments. This corresponds to the earlier data from our as well as other groups, obtained on different cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>). However, it does cause aberrant IF assembly as monitored by viscometer analysis, a very sensitive tool to assess filament aggregation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). Further, it has been found that pathological effect of mutant desmin does not completely correlate with the ability of aggregate formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>). Kreplack et. al showed severe alteration of nanomechanical properties of two C-terminal desmin rod domain mutations in spite of their ability to form filamentous network and absence of desmin aggregates in transfected cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). If this is true also for A213V substitution, altered biophysical properties of A213V desmin can predispose to cardiac vulnerability under certain stress conditions.</p>
      <p>Recently, Z-disks were shown to be an important element of mechanical stretch sensing machine. Several desmin and Z-disk associated proteins as well as desmin itself have been shown to play an important role in development of cardiac hypertrophy induced by various stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). In this context, modified properties of A213V desmin can predispose to altered adaptation of muscle cells to external and internal stress factors, such as pressure overload, ischemia or impaired metabolism. This could be a case, for example, in a patient with alpha- glucosidase gene deficiency in skeletal muscles, in patients with impaired glucose metabolism or in patient with connective tissue disorders. This substitution is likely to be of less importance in familial cases of DCMP, where genetic origin of the disorder due to severe alterations in myocyte proteins by itself is sufficient to cause a clinical phenotype. However, in non-genetic DCMP and in patients with heart dilation due to other acquired causes where many other factors besides genetic play a pivotal role this substitution can make sense as a conditional mutuation. It is interesting to note that another rare polymorphism of cardiomyocyte structural protein nebulette has been shown to associate with non-familial DCMP, but not with familial cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). Therefore it could be particular important to study rare gene variants and their impact on cardiac remodeling, since genome-wide approach, generally accepted now for searching new disease-causing and disease-modifying genes, usually does not cover rare polymorphisms with a frequency 5% and less.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we have shown that the A213V substitution represents a rare polymorphism with a population frequency of approximately 1%, that is overrepresented in patients with heart dilation of various origins (4,6%). This makes it most likely that the A213V shift constitutes a conditional mutation predisposing to malign cardiac remodeling under other stressful conditions. More studies A213V desmin biomechanical properties can shed light on the detailed mechanisms, involved in cardiac maladaptation in A213V patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the Swedish Heart-Lung
foundation, Stiftelsen Frimurare Barnhuset, King Gustav V and
Queen Victoria foundation, Sällskapet Barnavård, Stiftelsen Samariten,
Ronald MacDonald Child Fund, Sunnerdahls Handikappfond,
Swedish Research Council and United Mitochondrial
Disease Foundation as well as Russian Federal program "Scientific
and Educational recourses of in Russian Innovation".</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lazarides</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intermediate filaments: a chemically heterogeneous,
developmentally regulated class of proteins</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6180679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fountoulakis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soumaka</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapti</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alterations in the heart
mitochondrial proteome in a desmin null heart failure model</article-title>
          <source>J Mol
Cell Cardiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>461</fpage>
          <lpage>474</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733906</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensing stretch is fundamental</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12553903</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frank</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuhn</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katus</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The sarcomeric Z-disc: a nodal
point in signalling and disease</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Med</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>446</fpage>
          <lpage>468</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16416311</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldfarb</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vicart</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goebel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desmin myopathy</article-title>
          <source>Brain</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>127</volume>
          <fpage>723</fpage>
          <lpage>734</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14724127</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slavov</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ku</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of desmin mutations in
dilated cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>1244</fpage>
          <lpage>1251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17325244</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tesson</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sylvius</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pilotto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Epidemiology of desmin and
cardiac actin gene mutations in a european population of dilated
cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>1872</fpage>
          <lpage>1876</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11052860</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kostareva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gudkova</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sjoberg</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desmin mutations in a St. Petersburg cohort of cardiomyopathies</article-title>
          <source>Acta Myol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>115</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R09">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arbustini</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasotti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pilotto</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desmin accumulation restrictive
cardiomyopathy and atrioventricular block associated with
desmin gene defects</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Heart Failure</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>477</fpage>
          <lpage>483</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goudeau</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodrigues-Lima</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fischer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ariable pathogenic
potentials of mutations located in the desmin alpha-helical
domain</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>906</fpage>
          <lpage>913</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16865695</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bowles</surname>
              <given-names>NJS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vatta</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chrisco</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Familial restrictive cardiomyopathy
caused by missense mutation in the desmin gene</article-title>
          <source>Pediatric
Research</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51 Suppl 2</volume>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mucke</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kostareva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Severe muscle disease-causing
desmin mutations interfere with in vitro filament assembly at distinct
stages</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>15099</fpage>
          <lpage>15104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16217025</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kostareva</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sjoberg</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Forced expression of desmin
and desmin mutants in cultured cells: impact of myopathic missense
mutations in the central coiled-coil domain on network formation</article-title>
          <source>Exp Cell Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>312</volume>
          <fpage>1554</fpage>
          <lpage>1565</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16519886</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krplak</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Severe myopathy mutations modify the nanomechanics
of desmin intermediate filaments</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>385</volume>
          <fpage>1043</fpage>
          <lpage>1051</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026658</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakagami</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kikuchi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katsuya</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gene polymorphism of
myospryn (cardiomyopathy-associated 5) is associated with left
ventricular wall thickness in patients with hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Hypertens
Res</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>1239</fpage>
          <lpage>1246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344630</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheikh</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raskin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An FHL1-containing complex
within the cardiomyocyte sarcomere mediates hypertrophic biomechanical
stress responses in mice</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>3870</fpage>
          <lpage>3880</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033658</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Monreal</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cytoskeletal remodeling
of desmin is a more accurate measure of cardiac dysfunction than
fibrosis or myocyte hypertrophy</article-title>
          <source>Life Sci</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <fpage>786</fpage>
          <lpage>794</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955067</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kong</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shelton</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rothermel</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cardiac-specific LIM protein
FHL2 modifies the hypertrophic response to beta-adrenergic
stimulation</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>2731</fpage>
          <lpage>2738</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390345</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arimura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hiroi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of the human
nebulette gene: a polymorphism in an actin-binding motif is
associated with nonfamilial idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy</article-title>
          <source>Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>440</fpage>
          <lpage>451</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11140941</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>