<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:54:09Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4141364" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4141364</identifier><datestamp>2015-09-01</datestamp><setSpec>diabetes</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">diabetes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">diabetes</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Diabetes</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Diabetes</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0012-1797</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1939-327X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American Diabetes Association</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4141364</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4141364</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4141364</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24740569</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1607</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db13-1607</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Islet Studies</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>ADCY5 Couples Glucose to Insulin Secretion in Human Islets</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hodson</surname>
            <given-names>David J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mitchell</surname>
            <given-names>Ryan K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marselli</surname>
            <given-names>Lorella</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pullen</surname>
            <given-names>Timothy J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gimeno Brias</surname>
            <given-names>Silvia</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Semplici</surname>
            <given-names>Francesca</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Everett</surname>
            <given-names>Katy L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cooper</surname>
            <given-names>Dermot M.F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bugliani</surname>
            <given-names>Marco</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marchetti</surname>
            <given-names>Piero</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lavallard</surname>
            <given-names>Vanessa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bosco</surname>
            <given-names>Domenico</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Piemonti</surname>
            <given-names>Lorenzo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            <given-names>Paul R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hughes</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">
            <sup>8</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Daliang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Wen-Hong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">
            <sup>9</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shapiro</surname>
            <given-names>A.M. James</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Rutter</surname>
            <given-names>Guy A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup>Section of Cell Biology, Division of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Medicine, Imperial College London, London, U.K.</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Endocrinology and Metabolism, University of Pisa, Pisa, Italy</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Pharmacology, University of Cambridge, Cambridge,<bold/>U.K.</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup>Cell Isolation and Transplantation Center, Department of Surgery, Geneva University Hospitals and University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland</aff>
        <aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup>Diabetes Research Institute, San Raffaele Scientific Institute, Milan, Italy</aff>
        <aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup>Nuffield Department of Surgical Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, U.K.</aff>
        <aff id="aff7"><sup>7</sup>Oxford Centre for Diabetes, Endocrinology, and Metabolism, University of Oxford, Oxford, U.K.</aff>
        <aff id="aff8"><sup>8</sup>National Institute of Health Research Oxford Biomedical Research Centre, Churchill Hospital, Oxford, U.K.</aff>
        <aff id="aff9"><sup>9</sup>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX</aff>
        <aff id="aff10"><sup>10</sup>Clinical Islet Laboratory and Clinical Islet Transplant Program, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author: David J. Hodson, <email>d.hodson@imperial.ac.uk</email>, or Guy A. Rutter, <email>g.rutter@imperial.ac.uk</email>.</corresp>
        <fn>
          <p>D.J.H. and R.K.M. made equal contributions to this study.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>16</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>63</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <fpage>3009</fpage>
      <lpage>3021</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2014 by the American Diabetes Association. Readers may use this article as long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, and the work is not altered.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="3009.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) within the <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene, encoding adenylate cyclase 5, are associated with elevated fasting glucose and increased type 2 diabetes (T2D) risk. Despite this, the mechanisms underlying the effects of these polymorphic variants at the level of pancreatic β-cells remain unclear. Here, we show firstly that <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA expression in islets is lowered by the possession of risk alleles at rs11708067. Next, we demonstrate that ADCY5 is indispensable for coupling glucose, but not GLP-1, to insulin secretion in human islets. Assessed by in situ imaging of recombinant probes, ADCY5 silencing impaired glucose-induced cAMP increases and blocked glucose metabolism toward ATP at concentrations of the sugar &gt;8 mmol/L. However, calcium transient generation and functional connectivity between individual human β-cells were sharply inhibited at all glucose concentrations tested, implying additional, metabolism-independent roles for ADCY5. In contrast, calcium rises were unaffected in ADCY5-depleted islets exposed to GLP-1. Alterations in β-cell ADCY5 expression and impaired glucose signaling thus provide a likely route through which <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene polymorphisms influence fasting glucose levels and T2D risk, while exerting more minor effects on incretin action.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="13"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Type 2 diabetes (T2D) is one of the foremost health challenges currently facing developed societies. This metabolic disease, which affects ∼8.3% of the adult population worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), usually reflects a failure of the β-cell mass to adapt output to increased peripheral insulin resistance. The resulting hyperglycemia and dyslipidemia lead to debilitating complications, ranging from kidney failure and blindness to cardiovascular disease and cancer (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Although the maintenance of an adequate functional β-cell mass is critical for avoiding the development of diabetes (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), the molecular basis of β-cell failure is still poorly understood (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>The mechanisms underlying glucose-stimulated insulin secretion from single β-cells involve uptake of the sugar via specific glucose transporters (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), enhanced ATP synthesis (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), and closure of ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> (K<sub>ATP</sub>) channels (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The consequent plasma membrane depolarization leads to Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and exocytosis from secretory granules (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), both of which are further potentiated by “K<sub>ATP</sub>-independent” amplifying signals (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In addition, incretin hormones such as glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic peptide, released in response to food transit through the gut, potentiate insulin secretion in a glucose-dependent manner (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Cognate receptor activation engages adenylate cyclases (ADCYs), enzymes that catalyze the generation of cAMP, a key intra- and intercellular signaling effector in the β-cell. Through its downstream interactions with protein kinase A and exchange protein activated by cAMP (Epac), cAMP drives changes including Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> mobilization (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), and the enhanced fusion competence of secretory granules (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). By contrast, glucose evokes more modest increases in intracellular cAMP (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), possibly via the stimulation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated ADCYs such as ADCY1 and ADCY10 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>Both genetic (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and environmental (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) risk factors conspire to determine the rate and extent of loss of insulin secretory capacity in T2D. Thus, the majority of genetic risk loci (∼70) currently identified by genome-wide association (GWAS) or familial studies alter functional β-cell mass while exerting little, or occasionally a beneficial, effect on insulin sensitivity (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Of note, recent genetic studies have provided evidence that several pathways converging on β-cell cAMP signaling may influence T2D risk. For example, carriers of the major A-allele at rs11708067, or the C-allele at the neighboring single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) rs2877716, lying on chromosome 3 in intron 3 of the <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene, have an increased odds ratio of developing T2D (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). ADCY5 is a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-inhibited type III adenylate cyclase (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and risk allele carriers present with elevated fasting glucose (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) but not impaired insulinogenic index or area under the curve (AUC)<sub>insulin/glucose</sub> 2-h postoral glucose load (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). These data strongly imply that ADCY5 activity may be required for normal insulin release in response to glucose but not incretin, the latter largely accounting for the effects of oral glucose (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Whether and how SNPs exert control over β-cell function by influencing ADCY5 expression remain, nonetheless, unclear.</p><p>Therefore, the aims of the current study were to <italic>1</italic>) establish a link between genotype and <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA levels, <italic>2</italic>) silence ADCY5 expression in human islets using specific short hairpin (sh)RNAs, and <italic>3</italic>) use in situ imaging approaches and hormone release assays to establish the role of the cyclase in regulating β-cell responsiveness to glucose and incretin.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Research Design and Methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Human Islet Isolation</title><p>Human islets were isolated from deceased heart-beating donors at transplantation facilities in Oxford, Geneva, Pisa, Edmonton, and Milan, with the relevant national and local ethics permissions, including consent from next of kin where required, and cultured as described (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). All studies involving human tissue were approved by the National Research Ethics Committee (NRES) London (Fulham), Research Ethics Committee no. 07/H0711/114.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Mouse Islet Isolation</title><p>Male and female C57BL/6 mice, 8–12 weeks of age, were killed by cervical dislocation and pancreatic islets isolated by collagenase digestion as previously described (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Animal procedures were approved by the home office according to the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986 of the United Kingdom (PPL 70/7349).</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><italic>ADCY5</italic> Genotyping</title><p>DNA samples were genotyped for the SNP rs11708067 by restriction fragment length polymorphism analysis, as the G allele generated an <italic>Hha</italic>I site. A 250-bp region flanking the locus was amplified by PCR using Phire polymerase (Thermo) with the following primers: TCCGGAAGGCAAACACAGCA and AGCCAGGCTGCACCCAAGTG. The products were digested with <italic>Hha</italic>I and resolved by agarose gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Lentiviral Delivery of shRNA</title><p>Lentiviral particles carrying shRNA expression constructs against human <italic>ADCY5</italic> were acquired from Sigma-Aldrich (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>). Multiplicity of infection was calculated using Turbo-GFP particles on the same backbone (TRC 1.5; Sigma-Aldrich). Specificity of <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene silencing was confirmed in both dissociated and intact islets, assuming 1,000–2,000 cells/islet for the latter. In all cases, lentiviral particles containing scrambled shRNA were used as controls (Con) and islets infected for 48–72 h.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Generation of Adenoviral Epac2-camps</title><p>cDNA encoding the cAMP sensor citrine/cerulean-Epac2-camps (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) was cloned into pShuttleCMV via <italic>Hin</italic>dIII and <italic>Xho</italic>1 sites before recombination with pAdEasy1 and virus production as described (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Real-Time PCR</title><p>Relative mRNA abundance was quantified by quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) using SYBR green (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>) were designed using PerlPrimer (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), specificity validated using a dissociation curve, and amplification efficiency was determined using a dilution series. Expression of each gene was normalized to cylcophilin A (<italic>Ppia</italic>) and <italic>N</italic>-fold change in mRNA expression versus Con calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup>.</p><p><italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA levels were measured for expression quantitative trait locus analysis by qRT-PCR of RNA from isolated human islets as described earlier (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The expression level of <italic>ADCY5</italic> relative to TATA box–binding protein (<italic>TBP</italic>) was determined by qRT-PCR using Taqman primers and reagents (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link>) and the comparative Ct method (2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup>) used for subsequent calculations.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>Islets were fixed overnight at 4°C in paraformaldehyde before application of primary antibodies against ADCY5/6 (cat. no. ab66037; Abcam) (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and either guinea pig anti-insulin 1:200 or mouse anti-glucagon 1:1,000 (both DAKO). Revelation was performed with goat anti-rabbit Alexa-Fluor 488 and either goat anti–guinea pig Alexa-Fluor 568 or goat anti-mouse Alexa-Fluor 568 antibodies (both 1:500, Invitrogen). Images were acquired as previously described (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Measurements of Insulin Secretion From Isolated Islets</title><p>Insulin secretion was measured from groups of five to six islets per well, incubated for 30 min in 0.5 mL Krebs-HEPES-bicarbonate (KHB) solution (130 mmol/L NaCl, 3.6 mmol/L KCl, 1.5 mmol/L CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 mmol/L MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 mmol/L NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 2 mmol/L NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 10 mmol/L HEPES, and 0.1% [w/v] BSA, pH 7.4) at 37°C containing the indicated glucose and GLP-1 (7-36 human amide fragment) (Cambridge Bioscience) concentrations (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Total islet proinsulin and insulin were measured after acid ethanol extraction and sonication using specific radioimmunoassays (EMD Millipore).</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Live:dead and TUNEL Assays</title><p>Islets were incubated with 3 μmol/L calcein-AM (Life Technologies) and 2.5 μmol/L propidium iodide (Sigma-Aldrich) before detection of absorbance/emission at 491/525 nm and 561/620 nm, respectively. The islet area occupied by dead cells was expressed as a unitary ratio versus that occupied by live cells. Apoptosis was assessed using a TUNEL staining kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, and islets were counterstained against insulin before detection of absorbance/emission at 491/525 nm and 561/620 nm, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Calcium, ATP/ADP, and cAMP Imaging</title><p>Isolated islets were incubated (37°C, 95% O<sub>2</sub>/5% CO<sub>2</sub>) for 1 h in fluo2-AM (10 μmol/L) diluted in a bicarbonate buffer solution (120 mmol/L NaCl, 4.8 mmol/L KCl, 1.25 mmol/L NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 24 mmol/L NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 2.5 mmol/L CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.2 mmol/L MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 3 mmol/L <sc>d</sc>-glucose; all Sigma-Aldrich). Functional multicellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> imaging was performed using a Nipkow spinning-disk head and the resulting traces were normalized to minimum fluorescence (<italic>F</italic>min) (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). A near-identical distribution of Fluo-2 intensity was detected in Con and ADCY5 shRNA-treated islets under resting (3 mmol/L glucose) conditions, indicating that basal Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels were likely unaffected by gene knockdown, assuming similar dye loading (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1</ext-link>).</p><p>For imaging of cytosolic ATP/ADP with Perceval (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) or cAMP with Epac2-camps, islets were infected for 48 h with adenoviruses at multiplicity of infection 10–100, giving infection of the first 2–3 islet cell layers. Cells were imaged using a HEPES-bicarbonate buffer (120 mmol/L NaCl, 4.8 mmol/L KCl, 24 mmol/L NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 0.5 mmol/L Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 5 mmol/L HEPES, 2.5 mmol/L CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1.2 mmol/L MgCl<sub>2</sub>). For Perceval, absorbance/emission was 491/525 nm. For the Epac2-camps probe, excitation was delivered at 440 nm and emitted signals captured using cerulean (530 nm) and citrine (470 nm) filters. Förster resonance energy transfer (FRET) was calculated as the ratio of cerulean:citrine fluorescence and, for each experiment, expressed as a percentage of that obtained after maximal stimulation with 50 μmol/L forskolin (FSK). No differences in probe responses to FSK were detected in Con and ADCY5 shRNA-treated tissue (<italic>F</italic>/<italic>F</italic>min = 1.07 ± 0.01 vs. 1.06 ± 0.01 arbitrary units [AU], Con vs. ADCY5, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>ZIMIR Imaging</title><p>ZIMIR, a membrane-bound probe that fluoresces upon binding of zinc (Zn<sup>2+</sup>) coreleased with insulin from granules, was used to dynamically monitor insulin secretion as previously described (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Briefly, islets were incubated with 10 μmol/L ZIMIR for 2 h and imaged in bicarbonate buffer supplemented with 1 μmol/L EGTA. After acquisition (absorbance/emission = 491/525 nm), islets were divided into 20 subregions before extraction of intensity over time traces and analysis of amplitude and AUC.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Total Internal Reflection of Fluorescence Microscopy</title><p>Insulin-stained PFA-fixed islets were subjected to total internal reflection of fluorescence imaging to capture a superresolution snapshot of submembrane insulin granule distribution. The evanescent field was produced using a 561-nm laser (CrystaLaser) and a 100× 1.6 NA objective (Zeiss). Insulin granule density was expressed as a unitary ratio versus the total membrane area, the latter being clearly visible between adjacent cells.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Correlation and Frequency Analysis</title><p>Correlation and frequency analyses were performed as previously detailed (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Briefly, intensity over time traces were extracted for each fluo-2–loaded cell using a region of interest before manual triage for glucose responsiveness based on rises above a 25% threshold. The Pearson product moment correlation was performed for all possible cell pair combinations and significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) calculated versus the expected <italic>t</italic> distribution of independent <italic>R</italic> values. Functional connectivity maps showing the location of significantly correlated cell pairs were then constructed based upon correlation strength and position within the imaged field (<italic>x</italic>–<italic>y</italic>). Phase maps were compiled by converting the normalized intensity of each cell to a value between 1 and 100% and assigning this to a color using a light-dark ramp. Ca<sup>2+</sup>-spiking frequency was measured using the fast Fourier transform.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data distribution was determined using D’Agostino omnibus or Shapiro-Wilk tests. Nonmultifactorial pairwise comparisons were made using Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test or Student unpaired and paired <italic>t</italic> tests. Two-way ANOVA was used to assess interactions between multiple treatments (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and pairwise comparisons were performed using Bonferonni posttests. Expression quantitative trait locus data were stratified according to genotype, BMI, age, and sex. Factors included in the model were selected using the Akaike Information Criterion, resulting in the exclusion of age and BMI, as these were uninformative with regard to <italic>ADCY5</italic> expression. To account for any prediction error, linear regression analyses were performed separately for both excluded variables, yielding nonsignificant relationships (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Owing to a significant interaction between sex and genotype in donors 22–70 years of age (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0476; two-way ANOVA), effects of genotype on mRNA abundance were assessed within sex group using one-way ANOVA. In all cases, analysis was performed using R (R Project), GraphPad Prism (GraphPad Software), IgorPro (Wavemetrics), and MATLAB (Mathworks), and results were considered significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s17"><title>Results</title><sec id="s18"><title>ADCY5 Is Expressed in Human Islets at the mRNA and Protein Level</title><p>We sought firstly to characterize ADCY5 expression in tissue isolated from human and murine donors. Confirming previously published microarray data (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), SYBR Green qRT-PCR analyses revealed that <italic>ADCY5</italic> and <italic>ADCY6</italic> transcript levels were similar in human but not mouse islets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). Immunohistochemistry using an antibody against ADCY5, and with some reported cross-reactivity against ADCY6, demonstrated the localization of both enzymes in the cytoplasm of insulin and glucagon immunopositive cells throughout individual human islets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>ADCY5 is expressed in isolated human islets and affected by T2D risk alleles. <italic>A</italic>: <italic>ADCY5</italic> and <italic>ADCY6</italic> are expressed at similar levels in human islets (<italic>n</italic> = 4 donors). Conversely, <italic>Adcy6</italic> mRNA expression is ∼40-fold more abundant than that of <italic>Adcy5</italic>, which is barely detectable in mouse islets (<italic>n</italic> = 3 female and 3 male animals; **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs.<italic> ADCY5</italic>, Student <italic>t</italic> test). <italic>B</italic>: Immunostaining using an anti-ADCY5 immunoglobulin, with some reported cross-reactivity to ADCY6, reveals the cytoplasmic distribution of both proteins throughout the human α- and β-cell populations (DAPI, blue; scale bar, 60 µm). <italic>C</italic>: Scatter plot showing reduced <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA abundance in islets from males &lt;70 years of age who are carriers of the AA risk allele at rs11708067 (*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.043 vs. AG; one-way ANOVA; <italic>n</italic> = 7 donors for each allele). Values represent mean ± SEM. <italic>D</italic>: Age of donors is not significantly correlated with <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA expression (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.21 and <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.01 for AG and AA, respectively; linear regression) (<italic>P</italic> values shown on graph). <italic>E</italic>: As for <italic>D</italic>, but BMI (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.23 and <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.003, AG vs. AA, respectively; linear regression) (<italic>P</italic> values shown on graph).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig1"/></fig></sec><sec id="s19"><title><italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA Levels Are Influenced by Genotype</title><p>While GWAS provides statistically powerful information concerning associations between SNPs and T2D risk, it is unable to report on how the expression of genes at variant <italic>loci</italic> is altered in tissues implicated in glucose homeostasis. Since the elevated glucose levels associated with T2D may influence <italic>ADCY5</italic> expression, we attempted to correlate genotype at SNP rs11708067 with <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA abundance using tissue from a catalog of healthy donors. Allele frequency was close to that expected from previous studies (∼75% A) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and Taqman qRT-PCR analysis of RNA from isolated islets revealed approximately twofold lower mean <italic>ADCY5</italic> expression in male AA versus AG carriers &lt;70 years of age (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 4</ext-link>). When considered separately, neither age nor BMI significantly influenced ADCY5 expression for either genotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>D</italic> and <italic>E</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>ADCY5 Is Required for Glucose-Stimulated Insulin Secretion</title><p>Given the above association between <italic>ADCY5</italic> expression and fasting glucose levels and genotype in man, we next explored a role for this gene in human β-cell stimulus-secretion coupling. shRNAs directed against various sequences of the <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene were delivered into dispersed cells or islets using replication-incompetent lentiviruses (<italic>n</italic> = 26 separate normoglycemic donors) (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 5</ext-link>). Gene silencing efficiency was determined using qRT-PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>), and effects were confirmed at the protein level using immunohistochemistry and an antiserum raised against ADCY5/6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>). Although mRNA levels were less affected by shRNA in intact than dissociated islets, this was most likely due to limited penetration of virus into the islet core (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>); cells within the imaged layers were nevertheless typified by the near-complete absence of ADCY5 immunoreactivity. <italic>ADCY6</italic> mRNA abundance was not altered by <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing, suggesting that the action of the shRNA on immunoreactivity was largely due to loss of the latter mRNA message (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>D</italic></xref>). Cell viability and apoptosis indices were normal, excluding any effects of impaired cAMP signaling on β-cell survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>ADCY5 silencing inhibits glucose- but not GLP-1–stimulated insulin secretion. <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>: Lentivirus harboring shRNA against <italic>ADCY5</italic> reduces expression by &gt;50% in both dispersed and intact islets (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Student paired <italic>t</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 3–4 donors). <italic>C</italic>: ADCY5/6 protein expression is markedly reduced in the first few cell layers of intact islets, as determined using confocal imaging (<italic>n</italic> = 6 islets from two donors). <italic>D</italic>: <italic>ADCY6</italic> mRNA expression is unaffected by <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Student paired <italic>t</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 4 donors). <italic>E</italic>: Dead:live cell ratio is similar in Con and shRNA-treated islets (positive Con, Triton X-100; NS, nonsignificant vs.; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 10–11 islets from three donors). <italic>F</italic>: As for <italic>E</italic>, but TUNEL assay for apoptosis (<italic>n</italic> = 9 islets from three donors). The proportion of apoptotic β-cells was expressed as a fraction area versus nonapoptotic insulin-positive cell mass (Vv). <italic>G</italic>: <italic>ADCY5</italic> knockdown suppresses glucose-induced insulin secretory dynamics, as shown by bar graphs of AUC and amplitude of ZIMIR responses (mean traces, <italic>left panel</italic>; <italic>n</italic> = 8–9 islets from four donors) (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). <italic>H</italic>: GLP-1–stimulated insulin secretory dynamics are subtly improved after ADCY5 depletion (mean traces, <italic>left panel</italic>; AUC and amplitude, <italic>right panel</italic>; <italic>n</italic> = 7 islets from three donors) (NS, nonsignificant). <italic>I</italic>: Glucose-stimulated insulin release into static culture is impaired in shRNA-treated islets, as determined using radioimmunoassay (G3 and G16.7, 3 mmol/L and 16.7 mmol/L glucose, respectively) (<italic>n</italic> = 4–8 donors). KCl 30 mmol/L was added as a Con. <italic>J</italic>: As for <italic>I</italic>, but stimulation index vs. 3 mmol/L glucose to better account for the variation between islet preparations (*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.02 vs. Con at 16.7 mmol/L glucose; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). <italic>K</italic>: As for <italic>J</italic>, but vs. 16.7 mmol/L glucose (G16.7) (*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. 16.7 mmol/L glucose for each group; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). Values represent mean ± SEM. hr, hour.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig2"/></fig><p>The impact of <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing on glucose- or incretin-stimulated insulin secretory dynamics was subsequently assessed using Nipkow spinning-disk microscopy (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) to image Zn<sup>2+</sup> coreleased from insulin-containing granules within individual ZIMIR-stained islets (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The amplitude and AUC of glucose (11 mmol/L)-stimulated insulin release were markedly impaired in islets silenced for <italic>ADCY5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>G</italic></xref>). By contrast, insulin-release dynamics in response to GLP-1 were subtly improved in tissue depleted for ADCY5, suggesting the presence of an intact incretin axis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>H</italic></xref>). The observations with ZIMIR were confirmed using conventional static incubation techniques followed by radioimmunoassay of supernatant, and we further detected no significant effect of gene silencing on KCl-stimulated insulin release (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2<italic>I</italic>–<italic>K</italic></xref>). Donor variability was largely accounted for by a paired experimental design, and this was further supported by linear regression analyses, which revealed no relationship between age, BMI, and the magnitude suppression of glucose-stimulated insulin release in ADCY5-silenced islets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>). Insulin content was similar in Con and ADCY5 shRNA-treated islets, although there was a tendency toward an increased proinsulin-to-insulin ratio in the latter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), as expected from studies in patients harboring SNPs in or near the <italic>ADCY5</italic> locus (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Lastly, and in line with the secretory measures, total internal reflection of fluorescence imaging of insulin-stained islets confirmed that ADCY5 knockdown did not alter the distribution of granules located in the vicinity of the plasma membrane (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 3<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Insulin and proinsulin content in Con and ADCY5 shRNA-treated islets (<italic>n</italic> = 4 donors)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Con</th><th align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">shRNA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proinsulin content (ng/islet)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 ± 0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 ± 0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin content (ng/islet)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8 ± 3.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 ± 3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proinsulin:insulin (%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6 ± 0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 ± 1.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means ± SEM.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s21"><title>ADCY5 Couples Glucose to cAMP Generation, Ca<sup>2+</sup> Rises, and β-Cell Connectivity</title><p>Using Epac2-camps (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) to measure cAMP rises in β-cells (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 4</ext-link>), almost a threefold reduction in glucose- but not FSK-stimulated cAMP generation could be detected in ADCY5-silenced islets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). Since cAMP elevations are linked to enhanced electrotonic coupling (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), the effects of ADCY5 depletion on the cell-cell communication processes underlying the intraislet regulation of insulin secretion were next investigated. Cytosolic free Ca<sup>2+</sup> levels were thus used as a proxy to measure the electrical dynamics known to orchestrate Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent hormone secretion from the hundreds of cells residing within the first few microorgan layers; under the conditions used, Ca<sup>2+</sup> changes chiefly reflect those within β-cells (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In line with its dramatic effects on secretion, <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing suppressed both the amplitude and AUC of glucose-evoked Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises throughout the imaged population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Movies 1 and 2</ext-link>) (<italic>n</italic> = 3 donors; BMI range = 25.4–27.4; age range = 52–76 years). Furthermore, connectivity between individual β-cells, analyzed by large-scale mapping of long-term (∼30 min) evolutions in correlated cell-cell interactivity (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) and recently shown to be a key element in the insulin secretory response (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), was also reduced in <italic>ADCY5</italic>-silenced islets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic>F</italic> and <italic>G</italic></xref>). Neither the number of responsive cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic>H</italic></xref>) nor the frequency of [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> oscillations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3<italic>I</italic></xref>) was affected by <italic>ADCY5</italic> knockdown, suggesting that the absence of the cyclase was unlikely to impair insulin release by targeting the rhythmicity of a β-cell subpopulation. Implying that the effects of silencing were unlikely to reflect a long-term consequence of ADCY5 depletion, a similar degree of suppression of glucose-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises was obtained using 20 μmol/L NKY80, a relatively selective chemical inhibitor of the enzyme (IC<sub>50</sub> = 8.3 μmol/L, 132 μmol/L, and 1.7 mmol/L for ADCY5, 3, and 2, respectively) (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 5<italic>A</italic></ext-link>). Demonstrating the specificity of both shRNA and NKY80, the inhibitory actions of the drug were lost after <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></ext-link>).</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>ADCY5 depletion suppresses glucose-induced increases in cytosolic free Ca<sup>2+</sup><italic>.</italic>
<italic>A</italic>: ADCY5 silencing decreases cystosolic cAMP levels, as determined using the recombinant probe Epac2-camps (representative traces shown; gray/black, smoothed; red, raw). <italic>B</italic>: As for <italic>A</italic>, but summary data showing a reduction in measured FRET signal versus maximal stimulation with FSK (%), as well as decreased AUC (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Student <italic>t</italic> test; <italic>n =</italic> 12 recordings from three donors). <italic>C</italic>: ADCY5 knockdown suppresses 11 mmol/L glucose (G11)-evoked cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises (<italic>left panel</italic>: mean traces) (<italic>right panel</italic>: zoom-in of Ca<sup>2+</sup> oscillations). <italic>D</italic>: AUC and amplitude of Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises are reduced in shRNA-treated islets (<italic>right panel</italic>, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 10 islets from three donors). <italic>E</italic>: Pseudocolored Con and shRNA-treated human islets during exposure to 11 mmol/L glucose (recording time = 40 min; image cropped to display a single islet). <italic>F</italic>: ADCY5 is required for long-term evolutions in coordinated cell activity after exposure to elevated glucose (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 9–10 islets from three donors) (correlation calculated over 20–30 min; sig, significantly). <italic>G</italic>: Representative functional connectivity map depicting location, number, and strength (color-coded; 0 [blue] = lowest, 1 [red] = highest) of significantly correlated cell pairs (Pearson <italic>R</italic> coefficient, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Note that ADCY5 silencing decreases both the number and strength of correlations. <italic>H</italic>: Gene silencing does not significantly alter the percentage (%) of glucose (11 mmol/L)-responsive cells (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). <italic>I</italic>: The cumulative distribution of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-spiking frequencies remains similar in Con and shRNA-treated islets. Values represent mean ± SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig3"/></fig></sec><sec id="s22"><title>GLP-1–Stimulated β-Cell Activity Does Not Involve ADCY5</title><p>Consistent with the lack of effect of gene silencing on GLP-1–induced insulin release, loss of ADCY5 failed to impact Ca<sup>2+</sup> changes and even appeared to augment Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases in response to the incretin without modulating the proportion of responsive cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Movies 3 and 4</ext-link>). Furthermore, GLP-1–mediated increases in β-cell–β-cell connectivity, critical for generating the acute (5–10 min) bursts in coordinated activity that underlie incretin potentiation of glucose-stimulated insulin secretion (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), were unchanged after treatment with anti-ADCY5 shRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic>C</italic>–<italic>E</italic></xref>). In line with this, <italic>GLP-1R</italic> mRNA expression levels were unaffected by <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4<italic>F</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>ADCY5 does not mediate GLP-1–stimulated cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases. <italic>A</italic>: ADCY5 knockdown subtly improves GLP-1 responses (<italic>left panel</italic>: mean traces), as evidenced by increased AUC and amplitude of cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises in shRNA-treated islets (<italic>right panel</italic>) (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 10 islets from three donors). <italic>B</italic>: The proportion of GLP-1–responsive cells is similar in Con and shRNA-treated islets (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). <italic>C</italic>: ADCY5 silencing does not affect coordinated β-cell responses to 11 mmol/L glucose plus GLP-1 (representative Ca<sup>2+</sup> traces [<italic>top panel</italic>]; gray, smoothed; red, raw) (heat map depicting minimum–maximum for each cell [<italic>bottom panel</italic>]) (<italic>n</italic> = 10 islets from three donors; correlation measured using 5-min windows). <italic>D</italic>: Histogram showing mean % significantly correlated cell pairs in Con and shRNA-treated islets before, during, and after GLP-1 application (NS, nonsignificant; two-way ANOVA). <italic>E</italic>: Representative weighted graphs demonstrating large increases in β-cell connectivity after exposure to GLP-1 in both normal and ADCY5-depleted islets (scale bar, 50 µm). <italic>F</italic>: Gene silencing does not alter <italic>GLP-1R</italic> mRNA expression (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Student paired <italic>t</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 3 donors). Values represent mean ± SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig4"/></fig></sec><sec id="s23"><title>Glucose Still Increases Cytosolic ATP-to-ADP Ratio After ADCY5 Silencing</title><p>We wondered whether the substantial reductions in glucose-induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises and insulin release, detected in <italic>ADCY5</italic>-silenced islets, were accompanied by fulminant changes to β-cell glucose metabolism. To allow the real time recording of ATP dynamics specifically in β-cells, the expression of the recombinant probe Perceval was directed in human islets using an adenoviral vector (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Confirming tropism of the virus for β-cells, as previously described in rodent islets (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), green fluorescent protein fluorescence was restricted to insulin-immunopositive cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic>A</italic></xref>). In response to increasing glucose concentrations (3–17 mmol/L), β-cells responded with large, coordinated, and nonoscillatory elevations in ATP-to-ADP ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic>B</italic></xref>). Although significantly reduced, a glucose-induced increase in ATP-to-ADP ratio could still be detected after <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic>C</italic></xref>). Further excluding a role for cAMP-independent effects on K<sub>ATP</sub> or voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel (VDCC) activity, <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing did not alter Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises induced by KCl applied in the absence and presence of the K<sub>ATP</sub> channel opener, diazoxide (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 6<italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></ext-link>). Consistent with our previous findings in MIN6 β-cells (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), GLP-1 was able to provoke significant rises in ATP-to-ADP ratio under both low (3 mmol/L) and high (16.7 mmol/L) glucose conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic>D</italic>–<italic>F</italic></xref>), as well as in the presence of ADCY5 silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5<italic>G</italic> and <italic>H</italic></xref>). Hence, an action of glucose to accelerate oxidative metabolism toward ATP synthesis is not a prerequisite for GLP-1 signaling.</p><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>ADCY5 alters β-cell energetics. <italic>A</italic>: Expression of the ATP/ADP probe Perceval is predominantly restricted to β-cells, as shown using immunohistochemistry with antibodies against insulin and glucagon (scale bar, 25 µm [<italic>top panels</italic>] and 20 µm [<italic>bottom panels</italic>]). <italic>B</italic>: Glucose (17 mmol/L) (G17) still induces increases in ATP-to-ADP ratio after ADCY5 silencing (representative traces shown; gray/black, smoothed; red, raw). <italic>C</italic>: Bar graph showing a significant effect of shRNA treatment on the amplitude of cytosolic (cyt) ATP/ADP rises in response to 17 mmol/L glucose (*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 9–10 islets from three donors). <italic>D</italic>: GLP-1 increases ATP/ADP in the presence of permissive (17 mmol/L) glucose concentrations (representative traces shown; gray/black, smoothed; red, raw). <italic>E</italic>: As for <italic>D</italic>, but in the presence of nonpermissive (3 mmol/L) glucose concentrations. <italic>F</italic>: Summary statistics demonstrate similar effects of GLP-1 on ATP/ADP in islets exposed to 3 or 17 mmol/L glucose (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 10–13 recordings from five donors). <italic>G</italic>: ATP/ADP responses to GLP-1 are similar in Con and ADCY5 shRNA-treated islets (representative traces shown; gray/black, smoothed; red, raw). <italic>H</italic>: Summary statistics demonstrate no significant effect of gene silencing on GLP-1–induced ATP/ADP rises (NS, nonsignificant vs. Con; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 6 recordings from two donors). Values represent mean ± SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig5"/></fig><p>To determine the relative contribution of metabolism to ADCY5-regulated β-cell function, ATP-to-ADP dynamics were imaged after exposure to increasing glucose concentrations. Whereas both Con and <italic>ADCY5</italic>-silenced islets responded normally to 5 and 8 mmol/L glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic>A</italic></xref>), the latter failed to respond to further elevation of the sugar, and this deficit could be rescued using FSK to elevate cAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>). Cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses to 8 mmol/L glucose, however, remained suppressed after <italic>ADCY5</italic> knockdown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic>C</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F6" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>ADCY5 targets nonmetabolic processes to alter Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses. <italic>A</italic>: Impaired ATP/ADP responses are only present in ADCY5-silenced islets at glucose concentrations of ≥11 mmol/L (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. Con; two-way ANOVA; <italic>n</italic> = 9 recordings from three donors). <italic>B</italic>: Elevation of cAMP using FSK rescues ATP/ADP rises in ADCY5-silenced islets after transition from 3 mmol/L to 17 mmol/L glucose (G3-G17) (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. shRNA; one-way ANOVA; <italic>n</italic> = 9 recordings from three donors; <italic>n</italic> = 4–5 recordings). <italic>C</italic>: ADCY5 knockdown suppresses β-cell Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses after transition from 3 mmol/L to 8 mmol/L glucose (G3-G8) (representative traces [<italic>left panel</italic>]; gray/black, smoothed; red, raw]), as evidenced by reduced amplitude (<italic>right panel</italic>) (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. shRNA; Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test; <italic>n</italic> = 8–9 recordings from three donors).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s24"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of the current study was to explore the role of <italic>ADCY5</italic> in the regulation of insulin secretion from human islets. We show that ADCY5 is required to link glucose-derived signals to the intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises that principally drive insulin granule exocytosis. By contrast, incretins such as GLP-1 remain competent to evoke insulin release in the face of ADCY5 silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Providing compelling evidence that defective ADCY5 action may contribute to impaired fasting glucose were the observations that mRNA expression was reduced in islets from subjects harboring risk alleles at rs11708067. Interestingly, <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA levels were also reduced in β-cells from (ungenotyped) patients with T2D versus healthy donors (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), providing a further link with disease status.</p><fig id="F7" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Schematic of ADCY5 function in human β-cells. Glucose-stimulated insulin secretion relies on K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent and -independent signals. The latter include cAMP generation, and this likely requires ADCY5 activation by the sugar to increase ATP generation, Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, and exocytosis (<italic>left panel</italic>). By contrast, incretins such as GLP-1, believed primarily to engage cAMP-signaling pathways, may potentiate insulin secretion via other ADCY isoforms (<italic>right panel</italic>). PKA, protein kinase A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="3009fig7"/></fig><p>Assessed by next-generation sequencing (RNA-Seq), <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA occupies the top 13th centile of all mRNAs in human islets (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) and is the most strongly expressed member of the ADCY family in this tissue, with mRNA levels approximately twofold higher than those of <italic>ADCY1</italic>, the next most abundant isoform, and 50% higher than <italic>ADCY6</italic> mRNA. Assuming similar levels of <italic>PPIA</italic> mRNA, our qRT-PCR results in isolated human islets are broadly consistent with this observation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>). Of note, however, analysis of laser-capture–dissected β-cells (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) (Gene Expression Omnibus public repository, accession no. GSE20966) and a β-cell–enriched fraction from human islets (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) revealed lower levels of <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA (∼50th and ∼65th centiles, respectively), being in each case ∼50% of those of <italic>ADCY6</italic>. Intriguingly, in the current study, <italic>Adcy5</italic> mRNA was barely detectable in mouse islets, being expressed at a level ∼40-fold lower than <italic>Adcy6</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). A similar, though less marked (approximately eightfold), preponderance of <italic>ADCY6</italic> over <italic>ADCY5</italic> mRNA also exists for rat islets (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), demonstrating marked species variability in the relative abundance of ADCY isoforms within this tissue. Since these variations do not appear to reflect the greater proportion of α-cells in human (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) versus rodent (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) islets, ADCY5 may serve a nonconserved function between mammalian species.</p><p>Levels of mRNA encoding ADCY8, previously reported to be regulated by glucose in rat and human islets (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), were recently shown to be much lower in human islets than either <italic>ADCY5</italic> or <italic>-6</italic> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Confirming these findings, <italic>ADCY8</italic> mRNA was undetectable in four out of the five independent repeats that we conducted in human islets, and in the single experiment in which an amplicon was present, C<sub>t</sub> values were incompatible with accurate quantification (37.05 ± 0.49 cycles).</p><p>Of other genes lying 250 kb on either side of rs2877716 and rs11708067, which might also conceivably mediate the observed effects on diabetes risk, <italic>MYLK</italic> transcripts are barely detectable in human islets (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>SEC22A, PDIA</italic>, and <italic>PTPLB</italic> are each detectably expressed and so may contribute. Nonetheless, our observations on the effects of <italic>ADCY5</italic> silencing are entirely consistent with the observed phenotype of subjects possessing risk alleles (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>The strong dependence of glucose-stimulated insulin secretion upon ADCY5 expression in human islets is surprising given the abundant presence of ADCY6 and the redundancies inherent to the cAMP signaling cassette (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Although the above differences at the mRNA level are not necessarily reflective of protein quantity or enzymatic activity, the observed sensitivity to ADCY5 depletion may reflect either microcompartmentalization of ADCY5-containing complexes in proximity to Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and release sites (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) or a requirement for ADCY5 in cAMP-independent signaling processes. Thus, while our data indicate that ADCY5 couples glucose to insulin secretion by translating a glucose signal into cAMP generation (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), GLP-1 receptors may engage alternative ADCY family members to modify cAMP dynamics. Further studies will be required to explore the latter possibility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Of note, global deletion of ADCY5 in mice leads to longevity and the resistance of cardiomyocytes to oxidative stress via the upregulation of Ras-MAPK signaling (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). A similar mechanism might therefore contribute to the small but significant enhancement of GLP-1 signaling observed here in human β-cells after ADCY5 silencing.</p><p>Although ADCY5 is Ca<sup>2+</sup> inhibited in vitro (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), the range of Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations over which inhibition occurs (&gt;10 μmol/L) comfortably exceeds normal intracellular concentrations of these ions in β-cells (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Whether ADCY5 is therefore a direct target for activation by intracellular signals generated by glucose (ATP, etc.) or is, rather, a passive but essential element of a glucose-activated signaling pathway leading to Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and insulin release remains to be established.</p><p>Recent studies have shown that the intraislet regulation of cell-cell communication is critical for the proper generation of hormone release after secretagogue challenge (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Providing further evidence that the islet context is an important player in insulin secretion was the observation in the current study that β-cell responses to glucose were less coordinated in islets depleted of ADCY5. While the mechanisms underlying this phenomenon remain obscure, cAMP has been shown to alter β-cell gap junction conductance (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), and the resultant enhanced intercellular coupling may contribute to the insulin-raising actions of cAMP-elevating agents such as glucose and incretins. Whereas we recently showed that knockdown of connexin 36 markedly reduced coordinated cell responses to incretin, more modest effects on glucose action were observed (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The impact of cAMP on glucose-induced cell connectivity may therefore also stem from perturbed paracrine signaling circuits between β-, α-, and other cell types, in addition to enhanced electrotonic coupling. Likewise, an intriguing possibility is that <italic>ADCY5</italic> suppression may also affect glucagon and, potentially, GLP-1 (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) secretion from neighboring α-cells to affect β-cell “glucose competence.” In any case, ADCY5-depleted islets still displayed impaired Ca<sup>2+</sup> responses even when metabolic dysfunction was accounted for (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6<italic>B</italic></xref>), supporting the view that other downstream processes, including cell-cell communication, are targeted by cAMP signaling.</p><p>Remarkably, GLP-1 evoked Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises and hormone release even when glucose-stimulated insulin secretion was abolished by ADCY5 silencing. This implies that GLP-1 signaling—generally believed to hinge on increased intracellular cAMP levels (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>)—is sufficient under these conditions to elicit closure of K<sub>ATP</sub> and induce Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx and exocytosis. Indeed, studies by Miki et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) have demonstrated that GLP-1 is still able to evoke insulin secretion in the complete absence of K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. Thus, the glucose dependency of GLP-1–induced insulin secretion is unlikely solely to reflect the effects of the sugar on oxidative metabolism and, hence, the closure of K<sub>ATP</sub> channels, especially in light of data showing the absence of GLP-1–induced Ca<sup>2+</sup> rises in human islets incubated at nonpermissive glucose concentrations (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Rather than a simple summation of glucose and GLP-1–derived Ca<sup>2+</sup> signals, the ATP/ADP responses to the latter, readily detectable at low glucose concentrations, may instead be converted into a depolarizing stimulus through a complex interplay between K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent and -independent pathways (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>In summary, we describe here a novel role for the GWAS-identified gene <italic>ADCY5</italic> in the normal regulation of insulin secretion from human islets of Langerhans. Thus, we elucidate a pathway that converts <italic>ADCY5</italic> gene polymorphisms into defective β-cell function. Since β-cell decompensation is a hallmark of T2D pathogenesis irrespective of genotype, ADCY5 may provide a useful target for the restoration of insulin release in man.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_63_9_3009__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_db13-1607_DB131607SupplementaryData.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1" fn-type="supplementary-material">
        <p>This article contains Supplementary Data online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1">http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.2337/db13-1607/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Article Information</title>
      <p><bold>Acknowledgments.</bold> The authors thank Drs. Tatsuya Kin and Doug O'Gorman from the Clinical Islet Isolation Laboratory in Edmonton for providing human islets for this study.</p>
      <p><bold>Funding.</bold> These studies were supported by a Diabetes UK R.D. Lawrence Research Fellowship (12/0004431) to D.J.H. and by a Wellcome Trust Senior Investigator award (WT098424AIA), a Medical Research Council Programme award (MR/J0003042/1), a Diabetes UK Project grant (11/0004210), and a Royal Society Wolfson Research Merit award to G.A.R. Isolation of human islets was supported by JDRF awards (31-2008-416) to D.B. and (31-2008-413) to L.P. (European Consortium for Islet Transplantation). P.R.J. and S.J.H. were supported by grants from the National Institute for Health Research Biomedical Research Centre, Oxford. W.-H.L. was supported by grants from the JDRF (37-2011-21) and National Institutes of Health (R01-GM-077593). The work leading to this publication has received support from the Innovative Medicines Initiative Joint Undertaking under grant 155005, resources of which are composed of financial contribution from the European Union's Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013), and European Federation of Pharmaceutical Industries and Associations companies’ in-kind contribution to G.A.R.</p>
      <p><bold>Duality of Interest.</bold> No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article were reported.</p>
      <p><bold>Author Contributions.</bold> D.J.H. supervised the research, conceived and designed the study, performed the experiments, performed analysis, and wrote the manuscript with input from all authors. R.K.M. performed the experiments and analysis and conceived and designed the study. L.M. and T.J.P. performed the experiments and analysis. S.G.B. and F.S. performed the experiments. K.L.E., D.M.F.C., D.L., and W.-H.L. provided reagents. M.B., P.M., V.L., D.B., L.P., P.R.J., S.J.H., and A.M.J.S. isolated and provided human islets. G.A.R. jointly supervised the research, conceived and designed the study, performed analysis, and wrote the manuscript with input from all the authors. G.A.R. is the guarantor of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p>
      <p><bold>Prior Presentation.</bold> Parts of this study were presented in abstract form at the 73rd Scientific Sessions of the American Diabetes Association, Chicago, IL, 21–25 June 2013.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diabetes in numbers</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>485</volume>:<fpage>S2</fpage>–<lpage>S3</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22616094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22616094</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cancer and diabetes: are we ready for prime time?</article-title>
<source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1541</fpage>–<lpage>1544</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20549181?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20549181</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">DeFronzo RA, Abdul-Ghani MA. Preservation of β-cell function: the key to diabetes prevention. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 2011;96:2354–2366</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The beta-cell in type 2 diabetes and in obesity</article-title>. <source>Front Horm Res</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18230899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18230899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Bunt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frayn</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gloyn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>GLUT2 (SLC2A2) is not the principal glucose transporter in human pancreatic beta cells: implications for understanding genetic association signals at this locus</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Metab</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>653</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21920790?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21920790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarasov</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Semplici</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The mitochondrial Ca2+ uniporter MCU is essential for glucose-induced ATP increases in pancreatic β-cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e39722</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22829870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829870</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rorsman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>ATP-sensitive K+ channels: a link between B-cell metabolism and insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Biochem Soc Trans</source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2185070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2185070</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grapengiesser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gylfe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dual effect of glucose on cytoplasmic Ca2+ in single pancreatic beta-cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>1988</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3276310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3276310</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuboi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Multiple forms of “kiss-and-run” exocytosis revealed by evanescent wave microscopy</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>563</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12676086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henquin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of insulin secretion: a matter of phase control and amplitude modulation</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>751</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19288076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19288076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacology, physiology, and mechanisms of incretin hormone action</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>837</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23684623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23684623</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuboi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva Xavier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Holz</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouaville</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glucagon-like peptide-1 mobilizes intracellular Ca2+ and stimulates mitochondrial ATP synthesis in pancreatic MIN6 beta-cells</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>369</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12410638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12410638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunaga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Interaction of ATP sensor, cAMP sensor, Ca2+ sensor, and voltage-dependent Ca2+ channel in insulin granule exocytosis</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>:<fpage>7956</fpage>–<lpage>7961</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14660679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14660679</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawecki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pictet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grodsky</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Insulin secretion. Interrelationships of glucose, cyclic adenosine 3:5-monophosphate, and calcium</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>1975</year>;<volume>250</volume>:<fpage>6134</fpage>–<lpage>6140</lpage><?supplied-pmid 168208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">168208</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zippin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamenetsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glucose and GLP-1 stimulate cAMP production via distinct adenylyl cyclases in INS-1E insulinoma cells</article-title>. <source>J Gen Physiol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18695009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18695009</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Genomics, type 2 diabetes, and obesity</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>363</volume>:<fpage>2339</fpage>–<lpage>2350</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21142536?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21142536</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">da Silva Xavier G, Bellomo EA, McGinty JA, French PM, Rutter GA. Animal models of GWAS-identified type 2 diabetes genes. J Diabetes Res 2013;2013:906590</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokopenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>DIAGRAM Consortium; GIANT Consortium; Global BPgen Consortium; Anders Hamsten on behalf of Procardis Consortium; MAGIC investigators</collab>. <article-title>New genetic loci implicated in fasting glucose homeostasis and their impact on type 2 diabetes risk</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20081858?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20081858</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cloning and expression of a Ca(2+)-inhibitable adenylyl cyclase from NCB-20 cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1992</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>6716</fpage>–<lpage>6720</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1379717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1379717</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Type 5 adenylyl cyclase disruption increases longevity and protects against stress</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>130</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17662940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17662940</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boesgaard</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Grarup</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Borch-Johnsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>; <collab>Meta-Analysis of Glucose and Insulin-Related Trait Consortium (MAGIC)</collab>. <article-title>Variants at DGKB/TMEM195, ADRA2A, GLIS3 and C2CD4B loci are associated with reduced glucose-stimulated beta cell function in middle-aged Danish people</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1647</fpage>–<lpage>1655</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20419449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20419449</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hivert</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>; <collab>GIANT consortium; MAGIC investigators</collab>. <article-title>Genetic variation in GIPR influences the glucose and insulin responses to an oral glucose challenge</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20081857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20081857</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windholz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tönjes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of genetic variants in ADCY5, GIPR, GCKR and VPS13C on early impairment of glucose and insulin metabolism in children</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e22101</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21789219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21789219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hydrie</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Hare</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of 16 genetic variants on fasting glucose and type 2 diabetes in South Asians: ADCY5 and GLIS3 variants may predispose to type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e24710</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21949744?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949744</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudziak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzberg-Schäfer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Glucose-raising genetic variants in MADD and ADCY5 impair conversion of proinsulin to insulin</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e23639</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21887289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21887289</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nauck</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Homberger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Incretin effects of increasing glucose loads in man calculated from venous insulin and C-peptide responses</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>1986</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3522621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3522621</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lipotoxicity disrupts incretin-regulated human β cell connectivity</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>4182</fpage>–<lpage>4194</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24018562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24018562</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Isolation and culture of mouse pancreatic islets for ex vivo imaging studies with trappable or recombinant fluorescent probes</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>633</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20204627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20204627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DMF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An improved targeted cAMP sensor to study the regulation of adenylyl cyclase 8 by Ca2+ entry through voltage-gated channels</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e75942</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24086669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinzler</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A simplified system for generating recombinant adenoviruses</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>2509</fpage>–<lpage>2514</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9482916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482916</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva Xavier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Loder</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>TCF7L2 regulates late events in insulin secretion from pancreatic islet beta-cells</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>894</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19168596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19168596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>PerlPrimer: cross-platform, graphical primer design for standard, bisulphite and real-time PCR</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2471</fpage>–<lpage>2472</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15073005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15073005</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marselli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gene expression profiles of Beta-cell enriched tissue obtained by laser capture microdissection from subjects with type 2 diabetes</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e11499</fpage><?supplied-pmid 20644627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644627</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>del Puerto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Díaz-Hernández</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenylate cyclase 5 coordinates the action of ADP, P2Y1, P2Y13 and ATP-gated P2X7 receptors on axonal elongation</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>188</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22250198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22250198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glucose or insulin, but not zinc ions, inhibit glucagon secretion from mouse pancreatic alpha-cells</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1789</fpage>–<lpage>1797</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15919801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919801</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Imaging dynamic insulin release using a fluorescent zinc indicator for monitoring induced exocytotic release (ZIMIR)</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>21063</fpage>–<lpage>21068</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22160693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Cardenas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontanaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pituitary growth hormone network responses are sexually dimorphic and regulated by gonadal steroids in adulthood</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>21878</fpage>–<lpage>21883</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21098290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098290</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diraison</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Over-expression of sterol response element binding protein-1c or culture with 5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide ribonucleoside induces lipogenesis and decresaes glucose-stimulated insulin secretion from rat pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>Diabet Med</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>A77</fpage></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B39">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mears</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>NF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Atwater</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Magnitude and modulation of pancreatic beta-cell gap junction electrical conductance in situ</article-title>. <source>J Membr Biol</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7473686?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7473686</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B40">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanò</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Existence of long-lasting experience-dependent plasticity in endocrine cell networks</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1612.:605<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms1612.:605</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22215080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22215080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B41">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stožer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolenšek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Functional connectivity in islets of Langerhans from mouse pancreas tissue slices</article-title>. <source>PLOS Comput Biol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1002923</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23468610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23468610</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B42">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Type-specific regulation of adenylyl cyclase. Selective pharmacological stimulation and inhibition of adenylyl cyclase isoforms</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>276</volume>:<fpage>47785</fpage>–<lpage>47793</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11602596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11602596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B43">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yellen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A genetically encoded fluorescent reporter of ATP:ADP ratio</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19122669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19122669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B44">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diraison</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferré</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Over-expression of sterol-regulatory-element-binding protein-1c (SREBP1c) in rat pancreatic islets induces lipogenesis and decreases glucose-stimulated insulin release: modulation by 5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide ribonucleoside (AICAR)</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>378</volume>:<fpage>769</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14690455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14690455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B45">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eizirik</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sammeth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouckenooghe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The human pancreatic islet transcriptome: expression of candidate genes for type 1 diabetes and the impact of pro-inflammatory cytokines</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1002552</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22412385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22412385</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B46">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bramswig</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schug</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Epigenomic plasticity enables human pancreatic α to β cell reprogramming</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>123</volume>:<fpage>1275</fpage>–<lpage>1284</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23434589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B47">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Limited role for SREBP-1c in defective glucose-induced insulin secretion from Zucker diabetic fatty rat islets: a functional and gene profiling analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>291</volume>:<fpage>E982</fpage>–<lpage>E994</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16772326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16772326</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B48">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Armanet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Unique arrangement of alpha- and beta-cells in human islets of Langerhans</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1202</fpage>–<lpage>1210</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20185817?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20185817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B49">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elayat</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>el-Naggar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An immunocytochemical and morphometric study of the rat pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>J Anat</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>–<lpage>637</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7559135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7559135</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B50">
        <label>50</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Adenylyl cyclase 8 is central to glucagon-like peptide 1 signalling and effects of chronically elevated glucose in rat and human pancreatic beta cells</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21046358?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21046358</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B51">
        <label>51</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Organization and Ca2+ regulation of adenylyl cyclases in cAMP microdomains</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>965</fpage>–<lpage>1010</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17615394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615394</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B52">
        <label>52</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuboi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravier</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> microdomains and the control of insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Cell Calcium</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>551</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17030367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B53">
        <label>53</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyachok</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Isakov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sågetorp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tengholm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oscillations of cyclic AMP in hormone-stimulated insulin-secreting beta-cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>439</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>352</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16421574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421574</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B54">
        <label>54</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugliani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A local glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) system in human pancreatic islets</article-title>. <source>Diabetologia</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>3262</fpage>–<lpage>3272</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22965295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22965295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B55">
        <label>55</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holz</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Epac: A new cAMP-binding protein in support of glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor-mediated signal transduction in the pancreatic beta-cell</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14693691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14693691</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B56">
        <label>56</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Minami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Distinct effects of glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide and glucagon-like peptide-1 on insulin secretion and gut motility</article-title>. <source>Diabetes</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>1063</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15793244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15793244</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>