<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:59:39Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:471550" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:471550</identifier><datestamp>2004-07-17</datestamp><setSpec>bmcgeno</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/2.3/ https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/2.3/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id>
      <journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC471550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC471550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">471550</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238157</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-5-43</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15238157</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-5-43</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Synaptotagmin gene content of the sequenced genomes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Craxton</surname>
            <given-names>Molly</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref>
          <email>molly@mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Medical Research Council, Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Hills Road, Cambridge, CB2 2QH, UK</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <fpage>43</fpage>
      <lpage>43</lpage>
      <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/5/43"/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2004</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2004 Craxton; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Craxton; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article's original URL.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Synaptotagmins exist as a large gene family in mammals. There is much interest in the function of certain family members which act crucially in the regulated synaptic vesicle exocytosis required for efficient neurotransmission. Knowledge of the functions of other family members is relatively poor and the presence of Synaptotagmin genes in plants indicates a role for the family as a whole which is wider than neurotransmission. Identification of the Synaptotagmin genes within completely sequenced genomes can provide the entire Synaptotagmin gene complement of each sequenced organism. Defining the detailed structures of all the Synaptotagmin genes and their encoded products can provide a useful resource for functional studies and a deeper understanding of the evolution of the gene family. The current rapid increase in the number of sequenced genomes from different branches of the tree of life, together with the public deposition of evolutionarily diverse transcript sequences make such studies worthwhile.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>I have compiled a detailed list of the Synaptotagmin genes of <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>, <italic>Anopheles</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, <italic>Ciona</italic>, <italic>Danio</italic>, <italic>Fugu</italic>, <italic>Mus</italic>, <italic>Homo</italic>, <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>and <italic>Oryza </italic>by examining genomic and transcript sequences from public sequence databases together with some transcript sequences obtained by cDNA library screening and RT-PCR. I have compared all of the genes and investigated the relationship between plant Synaptotagmins and their non-Synaptotagmin counterparts.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>I have identified and compared 98 Synaptotagmin genes from 10 sequenced genomes. Detailed comparison of transcript sequences reveals abundant and complex variation in Synaptotagmin gene expression and indicates the presence of Synaptotagmin genes in all animals and land plants. Amino acid sequence comparisons indicate patterns of conservation and diversity in function. Phylogenetic analysis shows the origin of Synaptotagmins in multicellular eukaryotes and their great diversification in animals. Synaptotagmins occur in land plants and animals in combinations of 4–16 in different species. The detailed delineation of the Synaptotagmin genes presented here, will allow easier identification of Synaptotagmins in future. Since the functional roles of many of these genes are unknown, this gene collection provides a useful resource for future studies.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>Synaptotagmin (Syt) 1 was initially found as a protein component of synaptic vesicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. New members of the <italic>Syt </italic>gene family have subsequently been discovered by DNA sequence similarity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. <italic>Syts </italic>encode proteins which share a common structure: an N-terminal transmembrane sequence joined to a variable length linker, followed by two tandemly arranged, distinct C2 domains, C2A and C2B. At present, a great deal more is known about Syt1 than the other Syts because it functions crucially in synaptic vesicle trafficking in the nervous systems of animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Other Syts are implicated in trafficking events in the nervous system as well as in various other tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Certain <italic>Syts </italic>are known to express alternatively spliced transcripts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and RNA editing of <italic>Drosophila Syt1 </italic>has been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Little is known however, about the details of the variations in expression of different Syts.</p>
      <p>Public sequence database resources are becoming quite comprehensive, including vast numbers of transcript sequences from a wide variety of organisms as well as a number of relatively complete genome sequences. Systematic identification of <italic>Syts </italic>by database searching makes it possible to begin to address questions such as: what is the evolutionary extent of this gene family? where do these genes appear on the tree of life? and how many of these genes does an organism need?</p>
      <p>Building on my previous effort to extract the <italic>Syt </italic>content of the sequenced genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] I have now collected information for 98 <italic>Syts </italic>from organisms with sequenced genomes. Transcript sequences reveal abundant variation in <italic>Syt </italic>expression and indicate the presence of <italic>Syts </italic>in all land plants and all animals.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Identification of Syts</title>
        <p>Previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] I used a 44 amino acid sequence probe, representing the most highly conserved stretch of all the known Syts, and lying within a single exon in the C2B region, to search the sequence databases. This probe detected all the loci within the available genomes which could harbour <italic>Syts</italic>, but in order to confirm that these loci did indeed encode Syts it was necessary to ascertain that all the relevant parts were present (N-terminal transmembrane sequence, variable length linker, C2A and C2B). Whilst some regions (C2A and C2B) are well conserved, there is great variation in the sequences of other regions. It is difficult to predict exons accurately from genomic sequence unless a good degree of sequence similarity is present. Transcript sequences can reveal the true gene structure but few transcripts were available at that time, so although I could locate the already known <italic>Syts </italic>in <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>, <italic>Drosophila </italic>and <italic>Homo</italic>, it was clear that there were more potential <italic>Syts </italic>in each of these genomes and that <italic>Syt </italic>relatives may even be present in plants, which would indicate a general function for this gene family, not restricted to the operation of nervous systems.</p>
        <p>Recently, more genomes have been sequenced and some very good transcript resources have become available. I have also carried out cDNA library screening and RT-PCR to investigate the <italic>Arabidopsis Syts</italic>, the novel <italic>Homo Syts </italic>and the alternative splicing of <italic>Rattus Syt1 </italic>(accession numbers aj617615-aj617630). I used tblastn and blastn to search sequences at NCBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], EBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], Ensembl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] and JGI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. I assembled transcript sequences into gap4 databases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and used Spin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and Align [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] to compare transcripts with genomic sequence. I have compiled a list of 98 <italic>Syts </italic>from the genomes of <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>, <italic>Anopheles</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, <italic>Ciona</italic>, <italic>Danio</italic>, <italic>Fugu</italic>, <italic>Mus</italic>, <italic>Homo</italic>, <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>and <italic>Oryza </italic>([see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional File 1</xref>] entries 1–98). This list summarizes the results of the database searches and includes genomic locations, amino acid sequences, exon structures and alternative splicing patterns. The identities of all the sequences examined here are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Where <italic>Syt </italic>synonyms exist, I have chosen the human gene names used by Ensembl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] but have also indicated synonyms within parentheses.</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" id="T1">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of sequence identities</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Number</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Organism</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Names</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Number</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Organism</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Names</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Number</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Organism</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>Names</bold>
                </td>
                <td align="left">
                  <bold>C2 domains</bold>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">1</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">43</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt6 Frsyt6</td>
                <td align="left">85</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytB</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">2</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">44</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt6.1 Drsyt6.1</td>
                <td align="left">86</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytA</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">3</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">45</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt6.2 Drsyt6.2</td>
                <td align="left">87</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytC</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">4</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Cesyt1</td>
                <td align="left">46</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt12 Frsyt12</td>
                <td align="left">88</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">5</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">47</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt13 Drsyt13</td>
                <td align="left">89</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">6</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td align="left">syt7 Cesyt7</td>
                <td align="left">48</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Frsyt16</td>
                <td align="left">90</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">7</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Cesyt4</td>
                <td align="left">49</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Drsyt16</td>
                <td align="left">91</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td align="left">OssytB</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">8</td>
                <td align="left">Anopheles</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Agsyt1</td>
                <td align="left">50</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt14 Drsyt14</td>
                <td align="left">92</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td align="left">OssytC</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">9</td>
                <td align="left">Anopheles</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Agsyt4</td>
                <td align="left">51</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt14.1 Frsyt14.1</td>
                <td align="left">93</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytD</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">10</td>
                <td align="left">Anopheles</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">52</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt14 Frsyt14</td>
                <td align="left">94</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytE</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">11</td>
                <td align="left">Anopheles</td>
                <td align="left">syt13 Agsyt13</td>
                <td align="left">53</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Mmsyt1</td>
                <td align="left">95</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">12</td>
                <td align="left">Anopheles</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Agsyt16</td>
                <td align="left">54</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt2 Mmsyt2</td>
                <td align="left">96</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">13</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Dmsyt1</td>
                <td align="left">55</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt3 Mmsyt3</td>
                <td align="left">97</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">AtsytF</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">14</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Dmsyt4</td>
                <td align="left">56</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Mmsyt4</td>
                <td align="left">98</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td align="left">OssytF</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">15</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt7 Dmsyt7</td>
                <td align="left">57</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt5 Mmsyt5 (syt9)</td>
                <td align="left">99</td>
                <td align="left">Ceratopteris</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">16</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">58</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt6 Mmsyt6</td>
                <td align="left">100</td>
                <td align="left">Physcomitrella</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">17</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt13 Dmsyt13</td>
                <td align="left">59</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt7 Mmsyt7</td>
                <td align="left">101</td>
                <td align="left">Physcomitrella</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">18</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt12 Dmsyt12</td>
                <td align="left">60</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt8 Mmsyt8</td>
                <td align="left">102</td>
                <td align="left">Pinus</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">19</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Dmsyt16</td>
                <td align="left">61</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt9 Mmsyt9 (syt5)</td>
                <td align="left">103</td>
                <td align="left">Pinus</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">20</td>
                <td align="left">Ciona</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Cisyt1</td>
                <td align="left">62</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt10 Mmsyt10</td>
                <td align="left">104</td>
                <td align="left">Pinus</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">21</td>
                <td align="left">Ciona</td>
                <td align="left">syt7 Cisyt7</td>
                <td align="left">63</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt12 Mmsyt12 (syt11)</td>
                <td align="left">105</td>
                <td align="left">Pinus</td>
                <td/>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">22</td>
                <td align="left">Ciona</td>
                <td align="left">syt15 Cisyt15</td>
                <td align="left">64</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt11 Mmsyt11 (syt12)</td>
                <td align="left">106</td>
                <td align="left">Physcomitrella</td>
                <td align="left">PpsytF</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">23</td>
                <td align="left">Ciona</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Cisyt16</td>
                <td align="left">65</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt13 Mmsyt13</td>
                <td align="left">107</td>
                <td align="left">Ceratopteris</td>
                <td align="left">CrsytF</td>
                <td/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">24</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Drsyt1</td>
                <td align="left">66</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt14 Mmsyt14</td>
                <td align="left">108</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td align="left">CaLB</td>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">25</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Frsyt1</td>
                <td align="left">67</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Mmsyt16 (syt14r)</td>
                <td align="left">109</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">26</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt5.1 Drsyt5.1</td>
                <td align="left">68</td>
                <td align="left">Mus</td>
                <td align="left">syt15 Mmsyt15</td>
                <td align="left">110</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">27</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt5.1 Frsyt5.1</td>
                <td align="left">69</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt1 Hssyt1</td>
                <td align="left">111</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">28</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt5.2 Drsyt5.2</td>
                <td align="left">70</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt2 Hssyt2</td>
                <td align="left">112</td>
                <td align="left">Arabidopsis</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">29</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt2 Drsyt2</td>
                <td align="left">71</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt3 Hssyt3</td>
                <td align="left">113</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">30</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt5.2 Frsyt5.2</td>
                <td align="left">72</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Hssyt4</td>
                <td align="left">114</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">31</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt8 Frsyt8</td>
                <td align="left">73</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt5 Hssyt5 (syt9)</td>
                <td align="left">115</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">32</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Drsyt4</td>
                <td align="left">74</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt6 Hssyt6</td>
                <td align="left">116</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">33</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt4 Frsyt4</td>
                <td align="left">75</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt7 Hssyt7</td>
                <td align="left">117</td>
                <td align="left">Oryza</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">34</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt11.2 Drsyt11.2</td>
                <td align="left">76</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt8 Hssyt8</td>
                <td align="left">118</td>
                <td align="left">Caenorhabditis</td>
                <td align="left">MBC2</td>
                <td align="left">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">35</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt11.1 Drsyt11.1</td>
                <td align="left">77</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt9 Hssyt9 (syt5)</td>
                <td align="left">119</td>
                <td align="left">Drosophila</td>
                <td align="left">CG6643</td>
                <td align="left">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">36</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt11 Frsyt11</td>
                <td align="left">78</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt10 Hssyt10</td>
                <td align="left">120</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">KIAA0747</td>
                <td align="left">&gt;3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">37</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt9.2 Drsyt9.2</td>
                <td align="left">79</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt12 Hssyt12 (syt11)</td>
                <td align="left">121</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">CHR3SYT</td>
                <td align="left">&gt;2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">38</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt9.2 Frsyt9.2</td>
                <td align="left">80</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt11 Hssyt11 (syt12)</td>
                <td align="left">122</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">KIAA1228</td>
                <td align="left">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">39</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt9.1 Drsyt9.1</td>
                <td align="left">81</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt13 Hssyt13</td>
                <td align="left">123</td>
                <td align="left">Saccharomyces</td>
                <td align="left">Tricalbin3</td>
                <td align="left">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">40</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt9.1 Frsyt9.1</td>
                <td align="left">82</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt14 Hssyt14</td>
                <td align="left">124</td>
                <td align="left">Saccharomyces</td>
                <td align="left">Tricalbin2</td>
                <td align="left">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">41</td>
                <td align="left">Fugu</td>
                <td align="left">syt10 Frsyt10</td>
                <td align="left">83</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt16 Hssyt16 (syt14r)</td>
                <td align="left">125</td>
                <td align="left">Saccharomyces</td>
                <td align="left">Tricalbin1</td>
                <td align="left">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td align="left">42</td>
                <td align="left">Danio</td>
                <td align="left">syt10 Drsyt10</td>
                <td align="left">84</td>
                <td align="left">Homo</td>
                <td align="left">syt15 Hssyt15</td>
                <td align="left">126</td>
                <td align="left">Trypanosoma</td>
                <td/>
                <td align="left">1</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the chromosomal locations of <italic>Homo </italic>and <italic>Mus Syts</italic>. <italic>Syt2 </italic>and <italic>Syt14</italic>, <italic>Syt6 </italic>and <italic>Syt11</italic>, <italic>Syt8 </italic>and <italic>Syt9</italic>, <italic>Syt3 </italic>and <italic>Syt5</italic>, and <italic>Syt7 </italic>and <italic>Syt12</italic>, are linked in both <italic>Homo </italic>and <italic>Mus</italic>. <italic>Syt4</italic>, <italic>Syt15</italic>, and <italic>Syt16 </italic>are each solitary in both <italic>Homo </italic>and <italic>Mus</italic>. Linkage of <italic>Syt1</italic>, <italic>Syt10 </italic>and <italic>Syt13 </italic>is different in <italic>Homo </italic>and <italic>Mus</italic>. Different <italic>Homo </italic>(<italic>Syt9</italic>) and <italic>Mus </italic>(<italic>Syt4</italic>, <italic>Syt12</italic>) <italic>Syts </italic>are associated with overlapping antisense transcripts.</p>
        <fig position="float" id="F1">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Chromosomal locations of <italic>Homo </italic>and <italic>Mus Syts </italic></bold>I have labelled ideograms produced from blast search results at Ensembl [25] with the locations of <italic>Syt1-Syt16</italic>. (A) <italic>Homo</italic>. (B) <italic>Mus</italic>. Asterisks indicate loci with overlapping antisense transcription.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-1"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Syt comparisons</title>
        <p>I used clustalw at EBI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>] to compare all 98 Syts (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) and Multalin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>] followed by manual editing to produce mulitple alignments (figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Where alternative splicing produces complex sequence variation, I chose one representative sequence. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> shows the clustalw cladogram tree of relationships between the Syts. The multiple alignments are arranged in the same way, with N-terminus and linker regions in figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and C2A to C-terminus regions in figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>. Intron positions, alternative splicing and RNA-edited positions are indicated.</p>
        <fig position="float" id="F2">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>Cladogram tree of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the right. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are identified with names and are bracketed. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are identified with names, following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14].</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-2"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F3">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>N-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Putative transmembrane regions are indicated with a yellow background. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. A motif common to Syt 15, Syt9, Syt10, Syt6 and Syt3 is indicated in blue in fig. 4.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-3"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F4">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>N-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Putative transmembrane regions are indicated with a yellow background. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. A motif common to Syt 15, Syt9, Syt10, Syt6 and Syt3 is indicated in blue in fig. 4.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-4"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F5">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>N-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Putative transmembrane regions are indicated with a yellow background. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. A motif common to Syt 15, Syt9, Syt10, Syt6 and Syt3 is indicated in blue in fig. 4.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-5"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F6">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>C2A to C-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. The calcium coordinating positions of Syt1 and Syt3 [37,38] are indicated by a yellow background. Positions with greater than 90% conservation are indicated with a purple background.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-6"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F7">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>C2A to C-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. The calcium coordinating positions of Syt1 and Syt3 [37,38] are indicated by a yellow background. Positions with greater than 90% conservation are indicated with a purple background.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-7"/>
        </fig>
        <fig position="float" id="F8">
          <label>Figure 8</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>C2A to C-terminal regions of Syts </bold>Syts are identified on the left. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are are bracketed and named. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Amino acid sequence length is indicated on top. Intron positions are indicated by red vertical lines. Regions of alternative splicing or RNA editing are enclosed by red boxes. The main branches of Syts are separated by horizontal blue lines. Similarity between members of a main branch is indicated with a coloured background. The calcium coordinating positions of Syt1 and Syt3 [37,38] are indicated by a yellow background. Positions with greater than 90% conservation are indicated with a purple background.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-8"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Animal <italic>Syts </italic>are distributed over more than 7 main branches of the cladogram tree while plant <italic>Syts </italic>occupy a separate main branch. Groups of orthologues and paralogues appear on closely linked sub-branches. A group of orthologues includes genes from different species for example, all <italic>Syt1 </italic>genes. Paralogues are multiple versions of one gene within the same species. The paralogues of <italic>Syt1 </italic>in <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>are <italic>Syt2</italic>, <italic>Syt5 </italic>and <italic>Syt8</italic>. I have used the tree and multiple alignment information to give provisional names to as many <italic>Syts </italic>as possible (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p>
        <p>The 6 <italic>Arabidopsis Syts </italic>and 8 <italic>Oryza Syts </italic>are each found on three sub-branches. The <italic>Oryza </italic>genome is polyploid so one would expect multiple copies of many genes, and since the genome sequence is incomplete, further <italic>Oryza Syts </italic>may yet be found. Searches of plant transcript sequences, reveal the presence of <italic>Syts </italic>in all the land plants. Sequences from <italic>Pinus</italic>, <italic>Physcomitrella </italic>and <italic>Ceratopteris </italic>([see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional File 1</xref>] entries 99–107) demonstrate the presence of plant <italic>Syts </italic>across the whole evolutionary range of land plants.</p>
        <p>Animals have a more diverse array: 7 <italic>Syts </italic>in <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>, 5 or more in <italic>Anopheles </italic>(incomplete genome sequence), 7 in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, 4 or more in <italic>Ciona </italic>(a surprisingly small number perhaps, but an incomplete genome sequence), 13–14 in <italic>Danio </italic>and <italic>Fugu </italic>(incomplete genome sequences) and 16 in <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo</italic>. Bearing in mind that some of the genome sequences are incomplete, the overall picture appears to reflect both acquisition and loss of different types of <italic>Syt</italic>, with different animals bearing different arrays of <italic>Syts</italic>. I have highlighted a motif (G X X X P E L Y) in the linker region of the <italic>Syt15 </italic>orthologues (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>) which is shared with the otherwise unrelated, vertebrate specific branch of <italic>Syts </italic>which includes <italic>Syt9</italic>, <italic>Syt10</italic>, <italic>Syt6 </italic>and <italic>Syt3</italic>. Such a conserved motif probably indicates the specification of a common function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Expression of variant Syts</title>
        <p>Alternative splicing (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional File 1</xref>) adds a further level of diversity to <italic>Syts</italic>. The large numbers of <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>transcripts in particular, show abundant alternative splicing which involves coding regions as well as both upstream and downstream regions. There are common patterns of alternative splicing in <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>as well as species specific patterns. For example, both <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo Syt11 </italic>transcripts, use atypical GC intron donors in the final intron, rather than the typical GT donors which are present, to specify a change in the second calcium coordinating position in the C2B region (fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). In fish, the same sequence is encoded via typical intron donors. Another such example is <italic>Syt16 </italic>where both <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>use atypical GC intron donors in the final intron preceding the C2A region, but <italic>Fugu Syt16 </italic>does not. There are numerous examples of differences in the patterns of alternative splicing between <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo</italic>. Certain regions of the coding sequences are altered in specific <italic>Syts </italic>but overall, these regions range from N-terminus to C-terminus indicating a sophisticated control of many functions.</p>
        <p>Examples of common patterns of sequence variation in certain <italic>Syts </italic>include the alternative splicing of the short linker of <italic>Syt1 </italic>in <italic>Anopheles</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>(fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The functional consequences of this alternative splicing have recently been investigated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In <italic>Syt1</italic>, the C2B region undergoes alternative splicing in <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>and RNA editing in <italic>Anopheles </italic>and <italic>Drosophila</italic>. Alternative splicing equivalent to that of <italic>Caenorhabditis </italic>has just also been described in <italic>Aplysia </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. There is no evidence for equivalent alteration of <italic>Ciona</italic>, <italic>Danio</italic>, <italic>Fugu</italic>, <italic>Mus </italic>or <italic>Homo Syt1</italic>. It is intriguing to note that this region in the most abundantly expressed <italic>Arabidopsis Syt </italic>is also encoded by alternative exons. Alterations of the N-terminal end of <italic>Syt6 </italic>and the C-terminal ends of many <italic>Syts </italic>in the same vertebrate specific branch, as well as variable insertions into the linker region of <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo Syt7 </italic>(although nothing similar is found in other <italic>Syt7 </italic>orthologues) and insertions into the C2B region of the <italic>Syt14 </italic>homologues are further examples of common patterns of sequence variation in certain <italic>Syts</italic>. The true complexity of <italic>Syt </italic>alternative splicing needs to be examined systematically in detail.</p>
        <p>It is fortunate that the transcript sequencing projects in <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>have generated sequences from many different cell types at different stages of development, as it is likely that the production of variant <italic>Syts </italic>is under cell type and temporal control. Alternative splicing of exons in the 5' untranslated (UTS) region of <italic>Syt1 </italic>in mammals (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional File 1</xref> and accession numbers aj617615-aj617619 for alternative splicing in <italic>Homo</italic>, <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Rattus</italic>) seems to be particularly complex and is the likely explanation for the described variations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. This was not seen in the original 5' mapping work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>] but RNase protection (RPA) analysis in <italic>R. norvegicus </italic>and <italic>R. rattus </italic>(fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>) confirms the evidence of complex, species specific alternative splicing in this region of <italic>Syt1 </italic>in the sequence databases. Alternative splicing of this region is also evident in <italic>Ciona Syt1 </italic>and a functional analysis of this region in the related organism <italic>Halocynthia </italic>has recently been carried out [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Insufficient transcript evidence is currently available from other organisms to establish the universality of <italic>Syt1 </italic>5'UTS alternative splicing.</p>
        <fig position="float" id="F9">
          <label>Figure 9</label>
          <caption>
            <p><bold>RNase protection analysis of 5'UTS region of <italic>Rattus Syt1 </italic></bold>(A) 5'UTS probe aj617620. (B) 5'UTS probe aj617621. (C) 5'UTS probe aj617622. Lane 1: <italic>Rattus norvegicus </italic>brain mRNA. Lane 2: <italic>Rattus rattus </italic>brain mRNA. The uppermost bands are full-length products from mRNA transcripts which match the input probe across its whole length. Shorter products result from partially matching mRNA transcripts.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-9"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>I have described more than 98 <italic>Syts </italic>from a broad range of animals and plants. Much remains to be done to understand the control of the expression and location of the range of variants produced by each <italic>Syt</italic>. There is no evidence of <italic>Syts </italic>in single cell organisms or those with the most simple forms of multicellularity (algae, fungi, slime moulds) leading one to speculate that these genes may be necessary for communication in more differentiated cell systems. Although C2 domains are present in the simpler eukaryotes, the distinctly conserved C2A-C2B arrangement is unique to <italic>Syts</italic>. All of the plant <italic>Syts </italic>share the transmembrane-linker-C2A region with a family of genes which encode proteins with variable numbers of C2 domains. This family has members in yeast, fungi, metazoa, land plants and trypanosoma, but there is no evidence of family members in other eukaryotes at present. The first functional analysis of the yeast members (tricalbins) has just been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] but the family is poorly characterized otherwise. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional File 1</xref> entries 108–126 describe the non-<italic>Syt </italic>members of this gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Oryza</italic>, <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, <italic>Homo</italic>, <italic>Saccharomyces </italic>and <italic>Trypanosoma</italic>. The analogous situation is not found in animals, where the relation between <italic>Syts </italic>and other gene families is restricted to C2 domain sequence similarity. The clustalw cladogram tree of all the sequences described in this paper is shown in fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>.</p>
      <fig position="float" id="F10">
        <label>Figure 10</label>
        <caption>
          <p><bold>Cladogram tree of all sequences </bold>Sequences are identified on the right. <italic>Mus </italic>and <italic>Homo </italic>Syts are named and bracketed. <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>Syts are named following the nomenclature of Fukuda [14]. Yeast tricalbins are named and bracketed.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-10"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The advantages of performing an evolutionary analysis of <italic>Syts </italic>and attempting to understand their origins and diversity include the possibility of exhaustively defining the functions of a minimal set in a model organism (eg. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Ciona</italic>). Comparative analysis of subgroups of <italic>Syts </italic>from a range of evolutionary lineages helps to define exactly which sequences are required to maintain function and which are able to diversify (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] for a structural evolutionary analysis of the C2 domains of Syts). The patterns of alternative splicing displayed by certain groups of <italic>Syts </italic>indicate enormous functional diversity that is only beginning to be understood. It will be fascinating to discover what it is about certain animal <italic>Syts </italic>that distinguishes them as essential players in neurotransmission.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>RT-PCR and cDNA library screening</title>
        <p>RT-PCR from <italic>Rattus </italic>brain mRNA was carried out with Pfu-turbo polymerase. A <italic>Homo </italic>brain cDNA library (Clontech) was screened with probes for the 6 novel human loci identified in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] (accession numbers aj303363-aj303368). An <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>whole plant cDNA library (Stratagene) was screened with probes for the loci identified in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The probes were produced by PCR from genomic DNA which was a gift from Ian Furner (Cambridge University department of Genetics).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>RNase protection analysis</title>
        <p>RNase protection analysis (RPA) analysis was carried out as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. <italic>Rattus rattus </italic>brain was a gift from S.Redrobe at Bristol Zoo. Brain mRNA was prepared from <italic>Rattus rattus </italic>and from <italic>Rattus norvegicus </italic>(Sprague-Dawley) by guanidine isothiocyanate followed by polyA selection with oligo-dT cellulose. Regions of the 5' untranslated (5'UTS) portion of sequence accession x52772 (<italic>Rattus rattus Syt1) </italic>were cloned using RT-PCR with <italic>Rattus </italic>brain mRNA. RPA probes were produced using the Maxiscript kit (Ambion) from pBSIIKS- clones containing insert sequences aj617620-aj617622.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Additional File 1</title>
          <p>This text file describes the detailed features of all 98 <italic>Syts </italic>as well as information about a further 28 related genes mentioned in this paper.</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="1471-2164-5-43-S1.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for file</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <sec>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <p>I wish to thank Nicola Ramsey for galvanising discussions.</p>
      </sec>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Perin</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fried</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mignery</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jahn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phospholipid binding by a synaptic vesicle protein homologous to the regulatory region of protein kinase C</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>345</volume>
          <fpage>260</fpage>
          <lpage>263</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2333096</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/345260a0</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geppert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Archer</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
              <suffix>III</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin II a novel differentially distributed form of synaptotagmin</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>266</volume>
          <fpage>13548</fpage>
          <lpage>13552</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1856191</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mizuta</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inagaki</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nemoto</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsukura</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seino</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin III is a novel isoform of rat synaptotagmin expressed in endocrine and neuronal cells</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>269</volume>
          <fpage>11675</fpage>
          <lpage>11678</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8163462</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hillbush</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A third synaptotagmin gene, <italic>Syt3</italic>, in the mouse</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>8195</fpage>
          <lpage>8199</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8058779</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Craxton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goedert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin V: a novel synaptotagmin isoform expressed in rat brain</article-title>
          <source>FEBS Lett</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>361</volume>
          <fpage>196</fpage>
          <lpage>200</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7698322</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(95)00176-A</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hudson</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification of a nonneuronal isoform of synaptotagmin</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>5895</fpage>
          <lpage>5899</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7597049</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ullrich</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>JZ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>RGW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brose</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent and -independent activities of neural and non-neural synaptotagmins</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>375</volume>
          <fpage>594</fpage>
          <lpage>599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7791877</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/375594a0</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Babity</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plumier</surname>
              <given-names>J-CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Currie</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel seizure-induced synaptotagmin gene identified by differential display</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>2638</fpage>
          <lpage>2641</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9122248</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.6.2638</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thyroid hormone-responsive genes in developing cerebellum include a novel synaptotagmin and a <italic>hairless </italic>homolog</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>7832</fpage>
          <lpage>7840</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8987811</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>von Poser</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ichtchenko</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shao</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rizo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The evolutionary pressure to inactivate a subclass of synaptotagmins with an amino acid substitution that abolishes Ca<sup>2+ </sup>binding</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>272</volume>
          <fpage>14314</fpage>
          <lpage>14319</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9162066</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.22.14314</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>von Poser</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin 13: structure and expression of a novel synaptotagmin</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11211934</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mikoshiba</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of KIAA1427 protein as an atypical synaptotagmin (SytXIII)</article-title>
          <source>Biochem J</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>354</volume>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171101</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0264-6021:3540249</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Craxton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genomic analysis of synaptotagmin genes</article-title>
          <source>Genomics</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11543631</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/geno.2001.6619</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular cloning, expression, and characterization of a novel class of synaptotagmin (SytXIV) conserved from <italic>Drosophila </italic>to humans</article-title>
          <source>J Biochem</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>641</fpage>
          <lpage>649</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12801916</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jb/mvg082</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of human, rat, and mouse synaptotagmin XV</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>306</volume>
          <fpage>64</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12788067</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(03)00911-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geppert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goda</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammer</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosahl</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stevens</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin I: a major Ca<sup>2+ </sup>sensor for transmitter release at a central synapse</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>717</fpage>
          <lpage>727</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7954835</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmins: why so many?</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <fpage>7629</fpage>
          <lpage>7632</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739399</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.R100052200</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tucker</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chapman</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of synaptotagmin in Ca<sup>2+ </sup>-triggered exocytosis</article-title>
          <source>Biochem J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>366</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12047220</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mikoshiba</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel alternatively spliced variant of synaptotagmin VI lacking a transmembrane domain</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>274</volume>
          <fpage>31428</fpage>
          <lpage>31434</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10531344</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.44.31428</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Craxton</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goedert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alternative splicing of synaptotagmins involving transmembrane exon skipping</article-title>
          <source>FEBS Lett</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>460</volume>
          <fpage>417</fpage>
          <lpage>422</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10556508</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(99)01382-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sugita</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Butz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez-Chacon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lao</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synaptotagmin VII as a plasma membrane Ca<sup>2+ </sup>sensor in exocytosis</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>473</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11395007</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(01)00290-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoopengardner</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhalla</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staber</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reenan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nervous system targets of RNA editing identified by comparative genomics</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>301</volume>
          <fpage>832</fpage>
          <lpage>836</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12907802</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1086763</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <citation citation-type="other">
          <article-title>National Center for Biotechnology Information</article-title>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov"/>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <citation citation-type="other">
          <article-title>European Bioinformatics Institue</article-title>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk"/>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <citation citation-type="other">
          <article-title>Ensembl Genome Browser</article-title>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org"/>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <citation citation-type="other">
          <article-title>Joint Genome Initiative Ciona intestinalis v1.0</article-title>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/ciona4/ciona4.home.html"/>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <citation citation-type="other">
          <article-title>Staden Package WWW site</article-title>
          <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk/pubseq/staden_home.html"/>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pearson</surname>
              <given-names>WR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Griffin AM, Griffin HG</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>In Methods in Molecular Biology, Computer analysis of sequence data, PartII</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <publisher-name>New Jersey: Humana Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>389</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corpet</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering</article-title>
          <source>Nuc Acids Res</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>10881</fpage>
          <lpage>10890</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakhost</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houeland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castelluci</surname>
              <given-names>VF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sossin</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential regulation of transmitter release by alternatively spliced froms of synaptotagmin 1</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>6238</fpage>
          <lpage>6244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867508</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakhost</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Houeland</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blandford</surname>
              <given-names>VE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castelluci</surname>
              <given-names>VF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sossin</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of a novel C2B splice variant of synaptotagmin I</article-title>
          <source>J Neurochem</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15056279</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B32">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bagalá</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolev</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mandinova</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soldi</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mouta</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graziani</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prudovsky</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macaig</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The alternative translation of synaptotagmin 1 mediates the non-classical release of FGF1</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>1041</fpage>
          <lpage>1047</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14559220</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2003.09.119</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B33">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Perin</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brose</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jahn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Domain structure of synaptotagmin (p65)</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>266</volume>
          <fpage>623</fpage>
          <lpage>629</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1985919</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B34">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katsuyama</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsumoto</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okada</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohtsuka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okado</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okamura</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of synaptotagmin gene expression during ascidian embryogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Dev Biol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>244</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11944938</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.2002.0584</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B35">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schulz</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creutz</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The tricalbin C2 domains: lipid-binding properties of a novel, synaptotagmin-like yeast protein family</article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>3987</fpage>
          <lpage>3995</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15049706</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi036082w</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B36">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiménez</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Contreras-Moreira</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sgouros</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meunier</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bates</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schiavo</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional recycling of C2 domains throughout evolution: A comparative study of synaptotagmin, protein kinase C and phospholipase C by sequence, structural and modelling approaches</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>333</volume>
          <fpage>621</fpage>
          <lpage>639</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14556749</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2003.08.052</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B37">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davletov</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berghuis</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Südhof</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sprang</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structure of the first C2 domain of synaptotagmin I: a novel Ca<sup>2+</sup>/phospholipid-binding fold</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>929</fpage>
          <lpage>938</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7697723</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B38">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ernst</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brunger</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal structure of the cytosolic C2A-C2B domains of synaptotagmin III. Implications for Ca(+2)-independent snare complex interaction</article-title>
          <source>J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>589</fpage>
          <lpage>598</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10545502</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.147.3.589</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>