<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:54:05Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4131753" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4131753</identifier><datestamp>2014-08-14</datestamp><setSpec>wtpa</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec><setSpec>manuscript</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">9216904</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">2419</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Genet</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat. Genet.</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Nature genetics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1061-4036</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1546-1718</issn>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4131753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4131753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4131753</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24212882</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24212882</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2826</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">ems55280</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Recessive mutations in a distal <italic>PTF1A</italic> enhancer cause isolated pancreatic agenesis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Weedon</surname>
            <given-names>Michael N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Cebola</surname>
            <given-names>Ines</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Patch</surname>
            <given-names>Ann-Marie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Flanagan</surname>
            <given-names>Sarah E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Franco</surname>
            <given-names>Elisa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Caswell</surname>
            <given-names>Richard</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rodríguez-Seguí</surname>
            <given-names>Santiago A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shaw-Smith</surname>
            <given-names>Charles</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cho</surname>
            <given-names>Candy H-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Allen</surname>
            <given-names>Hana Lango</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Houghton</surname>
            <given-names>Jayne AL.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Roth</surname>
            <given-names>Christian L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chen</surname>
            <given-names>Rongrong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hussain</surname>
            <given-names>Khalid</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Marsh</surname>
            <given-names>Phil</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vallier</surname>
            <given-names>Ludovic</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Murray</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <collab>International Pancreatic Agenesis Consortium</collab>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN1">11</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ellard</surname>
            <given-names>Sian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Ferrer</surname>
            <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">12</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hattersley</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Biomedical and Clinical Science, University of Exeter Medical School, Exeter, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Genomic Regulation of Pancreatic Beta-Cells Laboratory, Institut d’Investigacions Biomèdiques August Pi I Sunyer, Spain
</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>CIBER de Diabetes y Enfermedades Metabólicas, 08036 Barcelona, Spain
</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Instituto de Fisiología, Biología Molecular y Neurociencias (IFIBYNE)-Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Ciudad Universitaria, Buenos Aires, Argentina
</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Wellcome Trust–Medical Research Council Cambridge Stem Cell Institute, Anne McLaren Laboratory for Regenerative Medicine, West Forvie Site, Robinson Way, Cambridge, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Seattle Children’s Hospital Research Institute, Seattle, WA 98101, USA
</aff>
      <aff id="A7"><label>7</label>School of Biomedical Science, Waterloo Campus, King’s College London, London, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A8"><label>8</label>London Centre for Paediatric Endocrinology and Metabolism, in partnership with the Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children National Health Service Trust, London, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Institute of Child Health, University College London, London, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Diabetes Research Group, Diabetes and Nutritional Sciences Division, School of Medicine, King’s College London, London, UK
</aff>
      <aff id="A11"><label>12</label>Department of Medicine, Imperial College, London, UK
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="CR1">Corresponding Authors: Andrew Hattersley (<email>A.T.Hattersley@exeter.ac.uk</email>) and Jorge Ferrer (<email>j.ferrer@imperial.ac.uk</email>)</corresp>
        <fn id="FN1">
          <label>11</label>
          <p id="P1">Full lists of members and affiliations appear in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note</xref>.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="FN3">
          <p id="P2"><bold>Author Contributions: </bold>MNW, SE, JF and ATH designed the study. MNW, AMP, JH and HLA performed bioinformatic analyses. IC, SARS, CC, AM, LV and JF performed the functional studies. AMP, JH, EDF, RC, SEF, SE performed the Sanger sequencing or deletion analysis and interpreted the results. SEF, CSS, KH, CLR, PM and ATH analysed the clinical data. MNW, IC, AMP, SE, JF and ATH prepared the draft manuscript. All authors contributed to the discussion of the results and the manuscript preparation.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
        <day>7</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>46</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>61</fpage>
      <lpage>64</lpage>
      <!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1038/ng.2826-->
      <permissions>
        <license>
          <license-p>Users may view, print, copy, download and text and data- mine the content in such documents, for the purposes of academic research, subject always to the full Conditions of use:
<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms">http://www.nature.com/authors/editorial_policies/license.html#terms</uri></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p id="P4">The contribution of <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory mutations to human disease remains poorly understood. Whole genome sequencing can identify all non-coding variants, yet discrimination of causal regulatory mutations represents a formidable challenge. We used epigenomic annotation in hESC-derived embryonic pancreatic progenitor cells to guide the interpretation of whole genome sequences from patients with isolated pancreatic agenesis. This uncovered six different recessive mutations in a previously uncharacterized ~400bp sequence located 25kb downstream of <italic>PTF1A (pancreas-specific transcription factor 1a)</italic> in ten families with pancreatic agenesis. We show that this region acts as a developmental enhancer of <italic>PTF1A</italic> and that the mutations abolish enhancer activity. These mutations are the most common cause of isolated pancreatic agenesis. Integrating genome sequencing and epigenomic annotation in a disease-relevant cell type can uncover novel non-coding elements underlying human development and disease.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="P5">Most patients with syndromic pancreatic agenesis have heterozygous dominant mutations in <italic>GATA6<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></italic>. Extra-pancreatic features in these individuals include cardiac malformations, biliary tract defects, gut and other endocrine abnormalities. Four families have been reported with syndromic pancreatic agenesis with severe neurological features and cerebellar agenesis caused by recessive coding mutations in <italic>PTF1A</italic><sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Most cases of isolated, non-syndromic pancreatic agenesis remain unexplained with the only cause described being recessive coding mutations in <italic>PDX1</italic> that have been reported in two families<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. We previously noted that individuals with unexplained pancreatic agenesis were often born to consanguineous parents and rarely had extra-pancreatic features<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. This suggested an autosomal recessive defect underlying isolated pancreatic agenesis.</p>
    <p id="P6">To identify recessive mutations causing isolated pancreatic agenesis we used linkage and whole genome sequencing. Initially we performed homozygosity mapping in 6 affected and 1 unaffected subject from 3 unrelated consanguineous families (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). This highlighted a single shared locus on chromosome 10 that included <italic>PTF1A</italic>, but mutations in coding and promoter sequences of <italic>PTF1A</italic> and the coding sequences of 24 other genes in the region were excluded by Sanger sequencing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). We next performed whole genome sequencing on probands from the two families with multiple affected individuals. We first looked for homozygous coding mutations in the exomes of the two whole genome sequenced patients. Each patient had ~ 3.6 million variants, from which we filtered out any that were present in 81 control genomes or that were present at &gt;1% frequency in the 1000 Genomes Project<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. This left a total of 2,868 and 3,188 rare or novel homozygous SNVs and indels per patient. Of these, 8 and 19 were annotated as missense, nonsense, frameshift or essential splice site (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). However, these coding variants either did not co-segregate with the disease or were not considered plausible candidates for a role in pancreas development (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>).</p>
    <p id="P7">We next searched for non-coding disease-causing mutations among the remaining candidate homozygous variants. We reasoned that any causal variants should disrupt a non-coding genomic element that is active in cells that are relevant to this disease. As isolated pancreatic agenesis must be the result of a defect in early pancreas development, we determined if any of the rare or novel homozygous variants in these patients mapped to active regulatory regions from pancreatic endoderm cells derived from human embryonic stem cells (hESC) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>). We thus defined 6,109 embryonic pancreatic progenitor putative transcriptional enhancers that were enriched in H3K4me1, a post-translational histone modification that is associated with enhancer regions, and were also bound by two or more pancreatic developmental transcription factors that are known to be essential for early pancreas development. Seven homozygous variants from each patient occurred in one of these annotated non-coding regions. However, only one of the 6,109 regulatory regions contained a variant in both sequenced individuals, and it was the same variant in the two unrelated patients (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). This variant, chr10:23508437A&gt;G, was located ~25kb downstream of <italic>PTF1A</italic>, in the region previously identified by homozygosity mapping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The novel variant occurred in a short (~400bp) evolutionary conserved region that showed enrichment for enhancer marks (H3K4me1 and H3K27Ac), and was bound by the transcription factors FOXA2 and PDX1 in hESC-derived pancreatic progenitor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>). Remarkably, this region lacked active chromatin features in 68 embryonic and adult cell types from the Epigenome RoadMap project and in 125 cell types from the ENCODE project (which includes an adult pancreatic exocrine cell line) indicating that it is specifically active in pancreatic embryonic progenitors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). A combination of whole genome sequencing and <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory annotations therefore identified a recessive mutation that mapped to a putative stage- and lineage-restricted transcriptional enhancer.</p>
    <p id="P8">We sequenced this putative pancreatic developmental enhancer in 19 additional probands with pancreatic agenesis of unknown aetiology (9 with extra-pancreatic features and 10 isolated cases) and identified recessive mutations in 7 of the 10 patients with non-syndromic pancreatic agenesis. We also identified a homozygous mutation in one patient with pancreatic agenesis and intrahepatic cholestatic failure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). Of the 10 probands with mutations in this element, 6 had the same chr10:23508437A&gt;G mutation as part of a shared extended haplotype (minimal shared haplotype of 1.2Mb; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). Three of the remaining probands had different base substitution mutations: a homozygous chr10:23508363A&gt;G mutation, a homozygous chr10:23508305A&gt;G mutation and compound heterozygous chr10:23508365A&gt;G/chr10:23508446A&gt;C mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In the tenth family a 7.6kb deletion was identified by long range PCR, and sequence analysis showed that the deleted region (chr10:23502416-23510031) included the entire putative enhancer (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>).</p>
    <p id="P9">Testing of parents and siblings demonstrated co-segregation of the mutations with diabetes and exocrine insufficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). None of the mutations were present in 1092 individuals from the 1000 genomes project<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> or in dbSNP137, and Sanger sequencing of 299 controls did not detect any of these variants. The deletion was not observed in the Database of Genomic Variants<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. There is very little diversity in humans within this element; the only 3 variants reported in dbSNP137 or the 1000 genomes project are rare (&lt;0.2% allele frequency). These results provide overwhelming genetic evidence that we have identified mutations causing non-syndromic pancreatic agenesis in a non-coding genomic region that is likely to be a transcriptional enhancer during pancreas development.</p>
    <p id="P10">We next tested whether this previously uncharacterized non-coding element acts as a developmental enhancer of <italic>PTF1A</italic>. We linked the wild type sequence to a minimal promoter and performed luciferase assays in human pancreatic progenitor cells, which demonstrated lineage-specific enhancer activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). The enhancer was not active in adult exocrine pancreatic cell lines, consistent with a stage-specific regulatory function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). To assess if this enhancer truly targets <italic>PTF1A</italic>, we performed chromatin conformation capture (3C) experiments. This demonstrated that the enhancer region establishes direct interactions with the <italic>PTF1A</italic> promoter in human pancreatic progenitor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>).</p>
    <p id="P11">We next demonstrated that the five base-substitution mutations prevent enhancer activity by abolishing transcription factor binding. We noted that three of the mutations disrupt binding sites for FOXA2 and a fourth disrupts a binding site for PDX1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). FOXA2 and PDX1 are essential transcription factors for pancreatic development<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Electrophoretic mobility shift assays confirmed that these four mutations abolished binding of FOXA2 or PDX1, as predicted, whereas the remaining point mutation disrupted the affinity of an uncharacterized sequence-specific DNA-binding protein present in mouse pancreatic progenitors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 8</xref>). Importantly, all five mutations disrupted the enhancer activity of this region in hESC-derived human pancreatic progenitors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). Collectively, these findings show that multiple mutations causing isolated pancreas agenesis disrupt the function of a previously unrecognized enhancer that targets <italic>PTF1A</italic> in human embryonic pancreatic progenitor cells.</p>
    <p id="P12">The contribution of non-coding variants to human disease remains poorly understood. There are examples of mutations in distal regulatory elements causing monogenic disease<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>-<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>, but the number is small compared to coding mutations. Although whole genome sequencing technologies can potentially solve this problem, the discrimination of functional non-coding causal variants amongst millions of non-coding variants present in each individual remains a formidable challenge. The ENCODE project has recently uncovered functional elements throughout the non-coding genome, leading to expectations that these can be integrated with genome sequencing to discover causal non-coding mutations<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Our study now provides an example that validates this expectation, and shows that recessively inherited distal <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory mutations in a novel developmental enhancer are the most common cause of a rare Mendelian disease. The fact that the mutated regulatory element was exclusive to embryonic pancreatic progenitors among a broad panel of adult and embryonic tissues highlights the importance of analyzing disease-relevant genomic annotations. Our results support efforts to identify novel regulatory element mutations in monogenic disorders by integrating genome sequencing data with functional annotation from projects such as ENCODE<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and the Epigenome Roadmap<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. These findings may also be relevant for future efforts to discover causal alleles in common non-Mendelian diseases, where many susceptibility variants appear to lie outside coding regions<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>.</p>
    <p id="P13">In summary, we have demonstrated that mutation of a novel, distal, developmental enhancer of <italic>PTF1A</italic> is a common cause of isolated pancreatic agenesis in humans and demonstrate the potential of integrating genome sequencing with epigenomics to identify mutations in novel regulatory elements that cause disease.</p>
    <sec sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only" id="S1">
      <title>Online Methods</title>
      <sec sec-type="subjects" id="S2">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p id="P14">Pancreatic agenesis was defined as a) pancreatic beta-cell failure indicated by neonatal diabetes requiring insulin treatment and b) exocrine pancreatic insufficiency requiring enzyme replacement therapy, as previously described<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Isolated disease was defined as pancreatic agenesis with normal development and no neurological or other major clinical features. Clinical details of the patients are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3</xref>. Subjects with pancreatic agenesis were recruited by their clinicians for molecular genetic analysis in the Exeter Molecular Genetics Laboratory. The study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and all subjects or their parents gave informed consent for genetic testing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S3">
        <title>Whole genome sequencing</title>
        <p id="P15">Whole genome sequencing of probands from families 1 and 2 was performed at Complete Genomics (Mountain View, CA, USA). The method has been described previously<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Complete Genomics software version 1.8.0.30 was used to align reads to the hg19 genome and call SNVs and indels. A total of 222 and 190Gb of bases were mapped with an average coverage of 73× and 63×. Ninety-five percent of hg19 bases had sufficient coverage to be fully called. 3,197,771 and 3,182,809 SNVs were called per sample with a Ti/Tv ratio of 2.15 and 2.14, and a novel (dbSNP131) SNP rate of 4.7 and 4.8%, respectively. 445,141 and 440,357 indels were called per sample with a dbSNP131 novelty rate of 22.4 and 22.8%.</p>
        <p id="P16">For filtering SNVs and indels we used 69 publically available whole genomes provided by Complete Genomics<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> and 12 additional whole genomes that had also been sequenced by Complete Genomics for a non-overlapping disease. We also filtered out variants present at &gt;1% minor allele frequency in the 1000 genomes project<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S4">
        <title>Differentiation of pancreatic endoderm from human embryonic stem cells</title>
        <p id="P17">Human ESCs (H9 from WiCell, Maddison, WI, USA) were imported under the guidelines of the UK Stem Cell Bank Steering Committee (authorisation SCSC10-44). Cells were maintained and differentiated into artificial pancreatic progenitors using a previously fully described protocol<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. These artificial pancreatic progenitors express a constellation of pancreatic endoderm markers including PDX1, HLXB9, NKX6.1, SOX9, HNF6, and PTF1A<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. In brief, definitive endoderm (DE) was induced by growing hESCs in CDM-PVA + Activin-A (100ng/mL), BMP4 (10ng/mL), bFGF (20ng/mL) and LY (10 μM) (AFBLy). The CDM-PVA AFBLy cocktail was replenished daily, and daily media changes were made during the entire differentiation protocol. After the DE stage (days 1-3), cells were cultured in Advanced DMEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with SB-431542 (10 μM; Tocris), FGF10 (50 ng/ml; AutogenBioclear), all-trans retinoic acid (RA, 2 μM; Sigma) and Noggin (150 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) for 3 days (days 4-6). For the next stage (days 7-10), the cells were cultured in Advanced DMEM supplemented with human FGF10 (50 ng/ml; AutogenBioclear), all-trans retinoic acid (RA, 2 uM; Sigma), KAAD-cyclopamine (0.25 μM; Toronto Research Chemicals) and Noggin (150 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) for 3 days. For the last stage (days 10-12), the cells were cultured in human FGF10 (50 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) for 3 days. For maturation of pancreatic progenitors (day 15 and day 18 artificial pMPCs), cells were grown in Advanced DMEM + 1% vol/vol B27 and DAPT (1 mM) for 3 days and for 3 additional days in Advanced DMEM + 1% vol/vol B27.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S5">
        <title>ChIP-Seq maps of pancreatic progenitor regulatory elements</title>
        <p id="P18">Chromatin immunoprecipitations (ChIPs) for H3K4me1 (Abcam ab-8895; n=2), FOXA2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-6554, n=2), GATA6 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-9055X; n=1), HNF1β (Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-22840-X, n=1), ONECUT1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-13050, n=1) and PDX1 (BCBC AB2027; n=1) were performed essentially as described<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>, using ~10 million artificially derived pancreatic progenitors for each experiment. These transcription factors were chosen because they are known to be essential regulators of early pancreas development<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>-<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>, and because of the availability of antibodies that recognize human epitopes in chromatin immunoprecipitation experiments. Sequencing of ChIPs and input DNA was performed on an IlluminaHiSeq2000 platform. Transcription factor enrichment sites were detected with MACS v1.4.0beta<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and H3K4me1-enriched regions were defined with SICER v1.03<sup><xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. We identified genomic regions that showed H3K4me1 enrichment in duplicate samples, and then defined H3K4me1-enriched regions bound by at least two transcription factors that were not located within 1 Kb from the transcriptional start sites of RefSeq genes. We then defined the limits of remaining regions as the outer limits of the transcription factor binding sites that cluster in each H3K4me1-enriched region. This resulted in 6,109 putative enhancer regions. ChIP-seq analysis of pancreatic progenitors, as well as global integrative and functional analysis of these regulatory maps is described elsewhere (SRS, CHC, IC, LV, JF, unpublished).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S6">
        <title>H3K27Ac ChIP</title>
        <p id="P19">Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) for H3K27ac (Abcam ab-4729: n=2) was performed as previously described<sup><xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>, using ~10 million artificially derived pancreatic progenitors. Fold enrichment was calculated using <italic>NANOG</italic> TSS as negative control. The oligonucleotides used in this analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S7">
        <title>Homozygosity Mapping</title>
        <p id="P20">Genome wide single nucleotide polymorphism genotyping was performed using the Affymetrix Mapping 10K Xba SNP genotyping chip by Medical Solutions, Nottingham (formerly GeneService; Nottingham, UK) with an average call rate of &gt;96%. Runs of homozygous SNP calls that exceeded 3cM from at least 20 consecutive probes were identified in the 6 affected probands and one unaffected sibling from 3 families. Common genomic regions of homozygosity were sought across the affected patients, excluding any shared with the unaffected sibling (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). The coding exons of all 25 RefSeq genes contained within the single shared region of homozygosity on chromosome 10 and the promoter and upstream conserved region of <italic>PTF1A</italic> were sequenced using capillary sequencing on the Applied BioSystems 3730xl DNA Analyzer (Life Technologies). Primers were designed to cover −50 to plus 10 base pairs of each exon in overlapping fragments if required (Primer designs are available on request). There was no evidence to support any causative variants within these genes</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S8">
        <title>Conservation analysis</title>
        <p id="P21">Eighty percent of bases between positions chr10:23508149 to chr10:23508510 were classified as being part of a vertebrate conserved element by PhastCons<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> (LOD&gt;17). Multiz alignment from the UCSC genome browser<sup><xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> shows that there is conservation of the entire element down to Chicken, and that over half the element is conserved down to X. Tropicalis. All mutated bases are highly conserved with all having GERP<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> scores of 5.65.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S9">
        <title>Sanger sequencing of the PTF1A element</title>
        <p id="P22">We amplified the conserved ~400bp element using primers in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>. PCR products were sequenced on an ABI3730 capillary machine (Applied Biosystems, Warrington, UK) and analyzed using Mutation Surveyor v3.98 (SoftGenetics, Pennsylvania, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S10">
        <title>Shared haplotype analysis and cryptic relatedness testing</title>
        <p id="P23">We first tested for a shared haplotype from the individuals in whom whole genome sequencing was undertaken. We only used SNPs where both alleles in both samples were fully called. There were 1,234 consecutive SNP calls between chr10:21314935 to 24693292 that were identical between the two samples, except for 4 discrepancies (which is within the expected genotyping error rate). For shared haplotype analyses of additional families with the 437A&gt;G mutation we also included 3 patients genotyped on the Affymetrix Genome-wide Human SNP 5.0 or 6.0, and extracted genotypes from these SNPs for the two individuals who underwent genome sequencing. Sample 6-1 was not included in this analysis because of a lack of dense genotyping data. Any SNP that was not called for at least one sample was excluded from the analysis. One discrepancy per 50 SNPs was tolerated to allow for genotyping error. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref> presents a graphical representation of the shared haplotype.</p>
        <p id="P24">To test whether the shared haplotype could be explained by cryptic relatedness between families we used KING<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> to estimate relatedness between probands from each of the families with the 437A&gt;G mutation. We only used SNPs that were present on both the Affymetrix Genome-wide Human SNP 5.0 or 6.0. All pairs of probands had a kinship coefficient &lt; 0.022 consistent with them being “unrelated”<sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S11">
        <title>Deletion analysis</title>
        <p id="P25">The genomic region chr10:23501386-23512912 was amplified in patients 7-4 and 7-8 by long-range PCR using the SequalPrep Long PCR kit (Life Technologies). PCR products were sheared by sonication (Diagenode Bioruptor), and fragments in the size range of 200–300 bp were isolated for library preparation with NextFlex adapters with a 6 base index sequence tag. Individual libraries were enriched by 6 cycles of PCR amplification and were then pooled in equimolar quantities for 100 bp paired-end sequencing on an Illumina HiSeq2000 sequencer. We used BWA (v0.6.2)<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> to align sequence reads to the hg19 reference genome and then visualized the breakpoints using the Integrative Genomics Viewer<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> which demonstrated that the deletion breakpoints occurred at chr10:23502416 and chr10:23510031 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>). The deletion mutation was investigated in all available members of family 7 using a junction fragment PCR assay (primer sequences available on request).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S12">
        <title>Sanger sequencing of the PTF1A enhancer in control samples</title>
        <p id="P26">We sequenced the putative <italic>PTF1A</italic> enhancer element in 150 healthy controls of European descent from the Exeter Family Study of Childhood health<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and 149 individuals from Turkey using Sanger sequencing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). No variants were identified.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S13">
        <title>Transcription factor binding motif analysis</title>
        <p id="P27">Motif discovery over the point mutation sites comparing wild type and mutation-containing sequences was performed using HOMER<sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S14">
        <title>Electrophoretic mobility-shift assays</title>
        <p id="P28">Mouse pancreatic buds were dissected from E11.5 and E12.5 C57Bl/6J mouse embryos as described<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Nuclear extracts were purified as described<sup><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>. Binding of nuclear extracts from embryonic pancreas and MIN6 β-cells to <sup>32</sup>P-labeled oligonucleotides that contained either wild type or the mutation-containing sequence was performed as described previously<sup><xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. The oligonucleotide sequences used are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>. Assay specificity was assessed by preincubation of the nuclear lysates with 30- and 100-fold excess of unlabelled wild type, mutant or consensus double-stranded oligonucleotides. Supershifts were performed using 2 μl of goat polyclonal serum anti-FOXA2 (sc-6554), anti-PDX1 (sc-14662) or control IgG (sc-2028; Santa Cruz Biotechnologies).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S15">
        <title>Chromosome conformation capture assay</title>
        <p id="P29">Approximately 10<sup>7</sup> artificial pancreatic progenitors were fixed for 20 minutes at 4°C in 4% paraformaldehyde, washed three times in PBS and lysed (10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 10 mM NaCl, 0.3% IGEPAL CA-630 (Sigma-Aldrich, Cat. No. I8896), 1× protease inhibitor cocktail (Complete, Roche). Nuclei were digested with HindIII endonuclease (New England Biolabs). DNA was then ligated with T4 DNA ligase (Promega). Locus specific primers were designed with Primer3 v. 0.4.0<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> as described previously<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. Relative enrichment of each ligation product was measured by real time quantitative PCR. The primer specific to <italic>PTF1A</italic> enhancer (3C-E) was considered fixed and interaction with <italic>PTF1A</italic> promoter was tested using primers close either to the promoter (3C-P) or to adjacent control regions (3C-Crt1, 3C-Crt2 and 3C-Crt3). A primer specific to the <italic>XBP1</italic> promoter was used as an unrelated locus control (3C-XBP1). All primers are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>. Amplimers were compared with parallel amplifications of serial dilutions of control bacterial artificial chromosomes (BAC) that encompass the genomic region of interest (RP11-938O7) and the XBP1 control locus (RP11-594I15), which were processed identically to the pancreatic progenitor chromatin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="S16">
        <title>PTF1A enhancer cloning and luciferase reporter assays</title>
        <p id="P30"><italic>PTF1A</italic> enhancer wild type and mutant sequences were PCR amplified from genomic DNA of a control individual and patients carrying the mutations, respectively, with Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (New England Biolabs) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref> for primer sequences) and cloned into pENTR/D-TOPO (Invitrogen). The enhancers were then shuttled into a pGL4.23[<italic>luc2</italic>/minP] Vector backbone (Promega) previously adapted for Gateway cloning pGL4.23-GW (Pasquali L, unpublished), using Gateway LR Clonase II Enzyme Mix (Invitrogen). Correct cloning was assessed by Sanger sequencing and restriction enzyme digestion.</p>
        <p id="P31">DNA was prepared with PureYieldTM Plasmid Maxiprep System (Promega). At day 10 of differentiation the artificial pancreatic progenitors were transfected in 24-well plates with 400ng of pGL4.23-GW-PTF1A_Enhancer vectors and 4ng Renilla normalizer control using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) Opti-MEM (Gibco) according to manufacturer’s instructions. Panc-1 (human pancreatic ductal), 266-6 (mouse pancreatic acinar), AR42J (rat pancreatic acinar) and HeLa cells were transfected in 96-well plates using Lipofectamine 2000 and Opti-MEM (Gibco) at a density of 4×10<sup>4</sup> of cells per well, according to manufacturer’s instructions for this format. 48 hours after transfection, luciferase activity was measured with Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega). Firefly luciferase activity was normalized to Renilla luciferase activity and then to the pGL4.23[<italic>luc2</italic>/minP] Vector backbone. Statistical significance was determined by comparing firefly/renilla luciferase values of each mutant to the wild type construct using a two-sided T-test. All DNA preparations were transfected in triplicate.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
        <label>Supplementary Information</label>
        <media xlink:href="NIHMS55280-supplement-1.docx" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e815" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack id="S17">
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>SE and ATH are supported by Wellcome Trust Senior Investigator awards. MNW is supported by the Wellcome Trust as part of the WT Biomedical Informatics Hub funding. EDF is funded by the BOLD grant (European Community’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agreement number FP7-PEOPLE-ITN-2008 (Marie Curie Initial Training Networks, Biology of Liver and Pancreatic Development and Disease). The authors thank Michael Day, Annet Damhuis and Javier Garcia-Hurtado, for technical assistance, and Rick Tearle (Complete Genomics), Juan Tena and José Luís Skarmeta (Centro Andaluz de Biologia del Desarrollo) for advice. This work was supported by NIHR Exeter Clinical Research Facility through funding for SE and ATH and general infrastructure, and Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (SAF2011-27086, PLE2009-0162 to JF). The views expressed in this paper are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN4">
        <p id="P33"><bold>Competing Financial Interests: </bold>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lango Allen</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GATA6 haploinsufficiency causes pancreatic agenesis in humans</article-title>
          <source>Nature genetics</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22158542</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Franco</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GATA6 Mutations Cause a Broad Phenotypic Spectrum of Diabetes From Pancreatic Agenesis to Adult-Onset Diabetes Without Exocrine Insufficiency</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>993</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23223019</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sellick</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutations in PTF1A cause pancreatic and cerebellar agenesis</article-title>
          <source>Nature genetics</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>1301</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15543146</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tutak</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A Turkish newborn infant with cerebellar agenesis/neonatal diabetes mellitus and PTF1A mutation</article-title>
          <source>Genetic counseling</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>147</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19650412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Shammari</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Husain</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Kharfy</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alkuraya</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel PTF1A mutation in a patient with severe pancreatic and cerebellar involvement</article-title>
          <source>Clinical genetics</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>196</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21749365</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stoffers</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zinkin</surname>
              <given-names>NT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanojevic</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Habener</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pancreatic agenesis attributable to a single nucleotide deletion in the human IPF1 gene coding sequence</article-title>
          <source>Nature genetics</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>106</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8988180</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwitzgebel</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Agenesis of human pancreas due to decreased half-life of insulin promoter factor 1</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of clinical endocrinology and metabolism</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>4398</fpage>
          <lpage>406</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970316</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Abecasis</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomes</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>491</volume>
          <fpage>56</fpage>
          <lpage>65</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23128226</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iafrate</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of large-scale variation in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>949</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15286789</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dynamic regulation of Pdx1 enhancers by Foxa1 and Foxa2 is essential for pancreas development</article-title>
          <source>Genes and development</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>3435</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19141476</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genes, mutations, and human inherited disease at the dawn of the age of personalized genomics</article-title>
          <source>Human mutation</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>631</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20506564</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smemo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulatory variation in a TBX5 enhancer leads to isolated congenital heart disease</article-title>
          <source>Human molecular genetics</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>3255</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22543974</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spielmann</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Homeotic arm-to-leg transformation associated with genomic rearrangements at the PITX1 locus</article-title>
          <source>American journal of human genetics</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23022097</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sankaran</surname>
              <given-names>VG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A functional element necessary for fetal hemoglobin silencing</article-title>
          <source>The New England journal of medicine</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>365</volume>
          <fpage>807</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21879898</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>ENCODE Project Consortium</collab>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>489</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955616</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bernstein</surname>
              <given-names>BE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The NIH Roadmap Epigenomics Mapping Consortium</article-title>
          <source>Nature biotechnology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maurano</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Systematic localization of common disease-associated variation in regulatory DNA</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>337</volume>
          <fpage>1190</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955828</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Drmanac</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human genome sequencing using unchained base reads on self-assembling DNA nanoarrays</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>327</volume>
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19892942</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cho</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inhibition of activin/nodal signalling is necessary for pancreatic differentiation of human pluripotent stem cells</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>3284</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23011350</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moran</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human beta cell transcriptome analysis uncovers lncRNAs that are tissue-specific, dynamically regulated, and abnormally expressed in type 2 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Cell metabolism</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>435</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23040067</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carrasco</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delgado</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soria</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rojas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GATA4 and GATA6 control mouse pancreas organogenesis</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>3504</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23006330</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xuan</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pancreas-specific deletion of mouse Gata4 and Gata6 causes pancreatic agenesis</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>3516</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23006325</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haumaitre</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lack of TCF2/vHNF1 in mice leads to pancreas agenesis</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>1490</fpage>
          <lpage>5</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668393</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jacquemin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transcription factor hepatocyte nuclear factor 6 regulates pancreatic endocrine cell differentiation and controls expression of the proendocrine gene ngn3</article-title>
          <source>Molecular and cellular biology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>4445</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10825208</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Offield</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PDX-1 is required for pancreatic outgrowth and differentiation of the rostral duodenum</article-title>
          <source>Development</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <fpage>983</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Model-based analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS)</article-title>
          <source>Genome biology</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>R137</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18798982</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R27">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A clustering approach for identification of enriched domains from histone modification ChIP-Seq data</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1952</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505939</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R28">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Arensbergen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Derepression of Polycomb targets during pancreatic organogenesis allows insulin-producing beta-cells to adopt a neural gene activity program</article-title>
          <source>Genome research</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>722</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20395405</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R29">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siepel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolutionarily conserved elements in vertebrate, insect, worm, and yeast genomes</article-title>
          <source>Genome research</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1034</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16024819</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R30">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The UCSC Genome Browser database: extensions and updates 2013</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic acids research</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>D64</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23155063</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R31">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davydov</surname>
              <given-names>EV</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identifying a high fraction of the human genome to be under selective constraint using GERP++</article-title>
          <source>PLoS computational biology</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>e1001025</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21152010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R32">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manichaikul</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robust relationship inference in genome-wide association studies</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>2867</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926424</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R33">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Durbin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fast and accurate short read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1754</fpage>
          <lpage>60</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19451168</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R34">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Integrative genomics viewer</article-title>
          <source>Nature biotechnology</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R35">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Knight</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hattersley</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Exeter Family Study of Childhood Health (EFSOCH): study protocol and methodology</article-title>
          <source>Paediatric And Perinatal Epidemiology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>172</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16466435</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R36">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heinz</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Simple combinations of lineage-determining transcription factors prime cis-regulatory elements required for macrophage and B cell identities</article-title>
          <source>Molecular cell</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>576</fpage>
          <lpage>89</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513432</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R37">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>van Arensbergen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ring1b bookmarks genes in pancreatic embryonic progenitors for repression in adult beta cells</article-title>
          <source>Genes and development</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23271347</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R38">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maestro</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hnf6 and Tcf2 (MODY5) are linked in a gene network operating in a precursor cell domain of the embryonic pancreas</article-title>
          <source>Human molecular genetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>3307</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14570708</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R39">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boj</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parrizas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maestro</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrer</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A transcription factor regulatory circuit in differentiated pancreatic cells</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>14481</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11717395</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R40">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rozen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skaletsky</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title>
          <source>Methods in molecular biology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>86</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10547847</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R41">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tena</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An evolutionarily conserved three-dimensional structure in the vertebrate Irx clusters facilitates enhancer sharing and coregulation</article-title>
          <source>Nature communications</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>310</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Epigenome annotation of variants from genome sequencing identifies a shared variant in a putative enhancer element</title>
        <p>Variant identified by whole genome sequencing, plus an additional five variants in patients with pancreatic agenesis map to a 25 Kb region downstream of <italic>PTF1A</italic>, which contains a single candidate pancreatic progenitor-specific enhancer within a highly conserved 400bp element. The top panel depicts ChIP-seq density plots for the enhancer mark H3K4me1, the second and third show occupancy for FOXA2 and PDX1. A broad panel of embryonic and adult human tissues do not show active chromatin marks in this region (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). Vertebrate Conservation and mammalian conservation tracks (as measured by the GERP Score) tracks illustrate the high conservation of this element. The red line depicts the approximate location of a 7.6 kb deletion in this region, and red arrows indicate point mutations, using the final 3 digits from the hg19 coordinates as labels (referring to positions 23508305A&gt;G, 23508363A&gt;G, 23508365A&gt;G, 23508437A&gt;G and 23508446A&gt;C on chromosome 10 respectively).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="emss-55280-f0001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Families with mutations in the <italic>PTF1A</italic> enhancer.</title>
        <p>Black filled individuals have isolated pancreatic agenesis. Striped filled individual had pancreatic agenesis with intrahepatic cholestatic failure from which he died. Dark grey symbols are patients with exocrine insufficiency and young onset diabetes (age at diagnosis &lt; 22 years). * Whole genome sequenced individual. DNA from the parents in family 2, 5, 6 and 8 was not available.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="emss-55280-f0002"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption>
        <title>Pancreas agenesis mutations disrupt the function of a transcriptional enhancer that is specifically active in pancreatic progenitors</title>
        <p>(<bold>A</bold>) Reporter assays for the novel enhancer in hESC-derived pancreatic endoderm progenitors, several adult pancreatic exocrine transformed cells (Panc-1, 266-6, AR42J) and HeLa cells. Transcriptional enhancer activity was only observed in hESC-derived pancreatic progenitor cells, and it was disrupted by all 5 mutations. Asterisks indicate Student’s t test P&lt;0.05 for comparisons of mutant vs. wild type enhancers in progenitors. (<bold>B</bold>) Chromosome conformation capture shows that the newly identified enhancer interacts directly with <italic>PTF1A</italic> promoter in hES cell-derived pancreatic progenitor cells. The viewpoint at <italic>PTF1A</italic> is signaled with an arrow, and the approximate regions that were tested for interaction with the viewpoint (C1, C2, C3, and P, for <italic>PTF1A</italic> promoter) are shown in (<bold>C</bold>). C4 represents a control region in an unrelated locus. (<bold>C</bold>) Pancreas agenesis mutations target critical residues in predicted binding sites for pancreatic regulators FOXA2 and PDX1. (<bold>D</bold>) Electrophoretic mobility shift assay showing high affinity, sequence-specific interaction of FOXA2 with a double stranded oligonucleotide containing the wild type (WT) sequence, but not the 363 A&gt;G mutation (MUT). The retardation signal was suppressed by unlabelled consensus high-affinity binding site for FOXA2, and supershifted with antibodies recognizing FOXA2. Black triangles represent competition gradients of 30 and 100-fold cold probe excess. Binding activity is shown for MIN6 cells and dissected pancreatic buds from e12.5 mouse embryos. Probe refers to the radioactively labelled probed used in binding assays. (<bold>E</bold>) Electrophoretic mobility shift assay showing sequence-specific interaction of PDX1 with oligonucleotide containing the wild type (WT) sequence, but not the 446 A&gt;C mutation (MUT). The retardation signal was suppressed by unlabelled consensus high-affinity binding site for PDX1, and supershifted with antibodies recognizing PDX1. Competition was performed with 100-fold cold probe excess. Binding activity is shown for MIN6 cells and pancreatic buds from e11.5 mouse embryos.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="emss-55280-f0003"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>