<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:57:05Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4461289" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4461289</identifier><datestamp>2016-05-21</datestamp><setSpec>acssd</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochemistry</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochemistry</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bi</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="coden">bichaw</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biochemistry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-2960</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1520-4995</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American
Chemical Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4461289</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4461289</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4461289</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25996083</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00302</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Characterization of Novel Ribosome-Associated Endoribonuclease
SLFN14 from Rabbit Reticulocytes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath1">
          <name>
            <surname>Pisareva</surname>
            <given-names>Vera P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="cor2" ref-type="other">*</xref>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2">
          <name>
            <surname>Muslimov</surname>
            <given-names>Ilham A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3">
          <name>
            <surname>Tcherepanov</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath4">
          <name>
            <surname>Pisarev</surname>
            <given-names>Andrey V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><sup>†</sup>Department of Cell Biology and <sup>‡</sup>Department of Physiology and Pharmacology, <institution>SUNY Downstate Medical Center</institution>, 450 Clarkson Avenue, Brooklyn, New York 11203, <country>United States</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Department of Cell Biology, SUNY
Downstate Medical Center, 450 Clarkson Ave., Box 44, Brooklyn, NY
11203. E-mail: <email>andrey.pisarev@downstate.edu</email>. Telephone: <phone>(718) 270-1143</phone>. Fax: <fax>(718) 270-2656</fax>.</corresp>
        <corresp id="cor2"><label>*</label>Department of Cell Biology, SUNY
Downstate Medical Center, 450 Clarkson Ave., Box 44, Brooklyn, NY
11203. E-mail: <email>vera.pisarev@downstate.edu</email>. Telephone: <phone>(718) 270-1143</phone>. Fax: <fax>(718) 270-2656</fax>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>05</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>05</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>02</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>54</volume>
      <issue>21</issue>
      <fpage>3286</fpage>
      <lpage>3301</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>05</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 American Chemical
Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>American Chemical
Society</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This is an open access article published under an ACS AuthorChoice <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/page/policy/authorchoice_termsofuse.html">License</ext-link>, which permits copying and redistribution of the article or any adaptations for non-commercial purposes.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p content-type="toc-graphic">
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0008" id="ab-tgr1"/>
        </p>
        <p>Turnover
of mRNA is a critical step that allows cells to control gene expression.
Endoribonucleases, enzymes cleaving RNA molecules internally, are
some of the key components of the degradation process. Here we provide
a detailed characterization of novel endoribonuclease SLFN14 purified
from rabbit reticulocyte lysate. Schlafen genes encode a family of
proteins limited to mammals. Their cellular function is unknown or
incompletely understood. In reticulocytes, SLFN14 is strongly overexpressed,
represented exclusively by the short form, all tethered to ribosomes,
and appears to be one of the major ribosome-associated proteins. SLFN14
binds to ribosomes and ribosomal subunits in the low part of the body
and cleaves RNA but preferentially rRNA and ribosome-associated mRNA.
This results in the degradation of ribosomal subunits. This process
is strictly Mg<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-dependent, NTP-independent,
and sequence nonspecific. However, in other cell types, SLFN14 is
a full-length solely nuclear
protein, which lacks ribosomal binding and nuclease activities. Mutational
analysis revealed the ribosomal binding site and the aspartate essential
for the endonucleolytic activity of protein. Only few endoribonucleases
participating in ribosome-mediated processes have been characterized
to date. Moreover, none of them are shown to be directly associated
with the ribosome. Therefore, our findings expand the general knowledge
of endoribonucleases involved in mammalian translation control.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name>
          <meta-value>bi5b00302</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name>
          <meta-value>bi-2015-00302y</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name>
          <meta-value/>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="sec1">Eukaryotic
cells have created
multiple highly regulated and complex mechanisms to control the level
of particular cytoplasmic messenger RNA (mRNA) molecules, ensuring
their functionality and providing their
degradation in the case of incorrect transcript maturation, some stress
stimuli, or the accomplishment of cellular function. mRNA degradation
is mediated through several pathways. RNA quality control starts in
the nucleus and covers the transcription and processing stages. Aberrant
mRNAs, which escaped into the cytoplasm, are identified on the basis
of the translation process and destroyed by different surveillance
machineries depending on the type of abnormality. The concentration
of fully matured mRNAs is, in turn, regulated by the RNA interference
mechanism in addition to the general mRNA turnover process. Although
mRNA degradation in prokaryotes is initiated by endoribonucleases,
it was widely accepted that eukaryotes employ for the decay mostly
exoribonucleases, enzymes hydrolyzing the RNA molecule from 5′-
and 3′-ends. Currently, the growing number of reports of identified
and suggested endoribonucleases assigns a key role in various degradation
pathways to these enzymes. According to current opinion, the mRNA
molecule after the initial internal cleavage is subsequently degraded
by exoribonucleases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Endoribonucleases reveal
a great variety in the organization of
the active center and, therefore, are structurally diverse. Only some
of them (for example, RNase L and IRE1) share the similar nuclease
domain composition and catalytic mechanisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup> Moreover, the nuclease domains of many known endoribonucleases
(for example, PMR1, APE1, and adolase C) have yet to be identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> As a result, it is very difficult to predict
novel endoribonucleases
based on the primary sequence comparative analysis. Thus, the enzymes
responsible for many processes relying on the internal cleavage of
RNA (for example, no-go decay and 18S nonfunctional rRNA decay) are
still unknown.</p>
    <p>The intracellular distribution of endoribonucleases
is one of the
options for controlling RNA target specificity. Endoplasmic reticulum
(ER)-anchored IRE1 is a good example for providing such localized
degradation activity. After the response of the unfolded protein,
which is a cellular response associated with the accumulation of unfolded
or misfolded proteins in the lumen of the ER, IRE1 initiates the cleavage
of ER-localized mRNAs to cease the translation and, therefore, mediates
the recovery from stress.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> Interestingly,
the vast majority of endoribonucleases
seems to act in the cytoplasm, because they are found to be enriched
in such cytoplasmic components as stress granules (sites for mRNA
storage and degradation), exosomes (RNA degradation protein machineries),
RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC, part of the RNA interference
pathway), and polysomes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> Importantly, some of
them become redistributed in the cytoplasm to
mediate the response of the cell to different stimuli. For example,
PMR1 endoribonuclease is found to be associated with polysomes, but
it is transferred to stress granules upon arsenite treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Another significant characteristic of endoribonucleases is
their
specificity for mRNA targets. Some enzymes are involved in the general
degradation mechanism such as RNA interference (Dicer and AGO2) and
mRNA surveillance (SMG6) pathways, where they cut mRNAs in a nonspecific
manner. Others cleave particular mRNAs and, therefore, play an essential
role in their metabolism. For instance, Ard-1, G3BP, and APE1 endoribonucleases
have been shown to regulate c-myc mRNA, which encodes the transcription
factor and whose turnover should be tightly controlled.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup></p>
    <p>In our laboratory, we investigate the mammalian translation
process
by reconstituting it <italic>in vitro</italic> from purified components.
Although the mechanism of canonical stages (initiation, elongation,
termination, and ribosomal recycling) has been well-studied, the details
of numerous regulation steps remain unknown. Recently, we became interested
in mRNA surveillance pathways, which take place in the cytoplasm and
absolutely depend on the translation cycle. These pathways aim to
destroy mRNAs, which cannot be correctly translated: nonsense-mediated
decay (NMD) targets mRNAs with a premature termination codon, no-go
decay (NGD) eliminates transcripts containing the elements in the
open reading frame arresting the ribosome during the elongation step,
and nonstop decay (NSD) degrades mRNAs without a termination codon.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> Genetic experiments in yeast revealed the endonucleolytic
cleavage of mRNA in the proximity of a structured barrier during NGD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> To determine the unknown endoribonuclease involved
in
NGD, we employed an <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstitution approach
for assembling the stalled ribosomal elongation complex on a model
mRNA coupled with the rabbit reticulocyte lysate (RRL) fractionation.
The purified enzyme was identified as SLFN14, a member of the Schlafen
protein family that is limited to mammals. Although SLFN14 introduced
the endonucleolytic cleavage to mRNA downstream of the P site of the
ribosome, its abundance in RRL resulting in the complete rRNA degradation
and independence of catalytic activity from translation
machinery raise the question of the authentic role of SLFN14 in the
cell. It was found that the expression level of <italic>Slfn1</italic>, which was the first member of the Schlafen family discovered, has
a profound effect on cell growth and progression through the cell
cycle. In particular, overexpression of <italic>Slfn1</italic> resulted
in a cell cycle arrest at the G<sub>0</sub>/G<sub>1</sub> stage. Therefore,
the family had been named <italic>Schlafen</italic>, which is translated
from German as “to sleep”.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> Consistently, with the aforementioned diversity among
members of this class of enzymes, it is not surprising that SLFN14
does not share sequence and structural homology with any described
eukaryotic endoribonucleases. However, the detailed biochemical characterization
of protein and mutational analysis unambiguously confirmed that SLFN14
is a bona fide endoribonuclease with yet-to-be-identified cellular
function.</p>
    <sec id="sec2">
      <title>Materials and
Methods</title>
      <sec id="sec2.1">
        <title>Antibodies</title>
        <p>SLFN14, GAPDH, HDAC2, and eIF2α antibodies
were from Abcam.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.2">
        <title>Purification of Translation Factors, Ribosomal
Subunits, and
Aminoacylation of tRNA</title>
        <p>Native 40S and 60S subunits, DHX29,
ABCE1, eIF 2, 3, 4F, and 5B, eEF 1H and 2, recombinant eIF 1, 1A,
3j, 4A, 4B, and 5, and eRF 1 and 3 were purified as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Rabbit aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases were purified, and <italic>in
vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA<sub>i</sub><sup>Met</sup>, tRNA<sup>Val</sup>,
and rabbit native total tRNAs (Promega) were aminoacylated as appropriate,
as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.3">
        <title>SLFN14 Purification</title>
        <p>Native rabbit SLFN14 was purified
from RRL on the basis of endonucleolytic cleavage of HBBmod mRNA in
assembled <italic>in vitro</italic> stalled EC. Native murine SLFN14
was purified from Krebs ascites cell lysate on the basis of chasing
the protein by immunoblotting. Purification of both forms involved
preparation of ribosomal salt wash, fractionation by ammonium sulfate
precipitation, chromatography on DEAE cellulose and phosphocellulose,
and FPLC on MonoS/MiniS, MonoQ, and hydroxyapatite columns, as appropriate.
Recombinant rabbit and murine forms of SLFN14–65kDa were expressed
in <italic>Escherichia
coli</italic> and isolated by affinity chromatography on Ni-NTA agarose
followed by affinity purification on 80S ribosomes via SDG centrifugation.
Recombinant rabbit SLFN14–45kDa and its mutants were expressed
in <italic>E. coli</italic> and isolated
by affinity chromatography on Ni-NTA agarose followed by FPLC on a
MonoS column.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.4">
        <title>ATPase Assay</title>
        <p>SLFN14 was
incubated with [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP in the presence or absence
of (CU)<sub>17</sub> RNA, 40S ribosomal subunits, and 80S ribosomes.
Reaction mixtures
were analyzed by chromatography on PEI cellulose.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.5">
        <title>Analysis of
SLFN14’s Association with Ribosome and Ribosomal
Subunits</title>
        <p>Different forms of SLFN14 were incubated with 40S
subunits, 60S subunits, or 80S ribosomes in the presence or absence
of AMPPNP or ADP and subjected to centrifugation through 10–30%
SDG. Fractions that corresponded to ribosomal complexes were resolved
via NuPAGE 4–12% Bis-Tris SDS–PAGE (Invitrogen) and
stained with SimplyBlue
SafeStain (Invitrogen) or tested with anti-SLFN14 antibodies, as indicated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.6">
        <title>rRNA Degradation</title>
        <p>To study rRNA degradation in lysates,
RRL or HEK293T cell extract was incubated in the presence of ATP and
GTP for different periods of time. To compare rRNA degradation in
RRL and 80S/SLFN14 binary system, 80S ribosomes were incubated with
SLFN14 in the presence of ATP and GTP. To investigate rRNA degradation
of purified ribosomal subunits, 40S or 60S subunits were incubated
with SLFN14 in the presence of ATP and GTP. To test the endonucleolytic
activity of SLFN14 in the ribosome-bound state, aforementioned SDG-purified
80S/SLFN14 complexes or 80S ribosomes were incubated at 37 °C
and
assayed. To compare the endonucleolytic activity of rabbit and murine
native forms of SLFN14 in the degradation of 18S rRNA, proteins were
incubated with 40S subunits. After incubation, RNA was isolated and
analyzed by DAFGE or denaturing PAGE, as appropriate.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.7">
        <title>mRNA and tRNA
Degradation</title>
        <p>The 5′-end <sup>32</sup>P-labeled HBBmod
mRNA, GUSmod mRNA, tRNA<sup>His</sup>, or tRNA<sup>Val</sup> was incubated
with SLFN14 in the presence of ATP for different periods
of time. To study the dependence of SLFN14 on metal ions with respect
to cleavage activity, SLFN14 was incubated with 5′-end <sup>32</sup>P-labeled GUSmod mRNA in the presence of ATP and 1 mM metal
ion,
as appropriate. After incubation, RNA was isolated and resolved via
6% denaturing PAGE. Gels were dried and autoradiographed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.8">
        <title>Analysis of
Ribosome and Ribosomal Subunit Integrity after rRNA
Degradation</title>
        <p>To test the integrity of the ribosome and ribosomal
subunits after rRNA cleavage in the binary system, 80S ribosomes or
40S or 60S subunits were incubated in the presence or absence of SLFN14
and subjected to centrifugation via 10–30% SDG. To study the
integrity of 80S monosomes and polysomes after
RNA cleavage in lysate, RRL after incubation in the presence of ATP,
GTP, and CHX or without incubation was subjected to centrifugation
via 10–50% SDG. After centrifugation, the rRNA appearance and
protein content
of 80S complex fractions were assayed by DAFGE and SDS–PAGE,
respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.9">
        <title>Functional Activity of rRNA-Cleaved Ribosomes
in the Translation
Cycle</title>
        <p>To compare the activity of cleaved and intact ribosomes
in the formation of 80S initiation complexes, the Met-Puro assay was
employed essentially as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> MVHL-STOP mRNA, eIFs 1, 1A, 2, 3, 4A, 4B, 4F, 35S-labeled Met-tRNA<sub>i</sub><sup>Met</sup>, and intact or cleaved 40S subunits
were incubated in the presence of ATP and GTP, supplemented with eIF5,
eIF5B, and intact or cleaved 60S subunits, as appropriate, and additionally
incubated. After assembly, ribosomal complexes were treated with puromycin
and extracted with ethyl acetate. <sup>35</sup>S-labeled methionyl-puromycin
formation was measured
by scintillation counting of the ethyl acetate extract. To compare
the activity of cleaved and intact ribosomes in the entire translation
cycle, different stages of translation, initiation, elongation, termination,
and ribosomal recycling, were reconstituted <italic>in vitro</italic> from individual purified components and assayed by toeprint essentially
as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.10">
        <title>RRL Ribosomal
Profile Preparation</title>
        <p>Flexi RRL supplemented
with 70 mM KCl and 1 mM GMPPNP was incubated and subjected to centrifugation
via 10–30% SDG. Fractions (200 μL) were collected. Ribosomes
and ribosomal
subunit-containing fractions were determined by the analysis of their
rRNA content via DAFGE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.11">
        <title>SLFN14 Protein Level and Localization in
Cells</title>
        <p>To test the
distribution of SLFN14 in the RRL ribosomal profile, SDG fractions
were subjected to SDS–PAGE and assayed by immunoblotting. To
calculate the SLFN14:80S ribosome ratio, the 80S complex and different
amounts of purified SLFN14 were subjected to SDS–PAGE and assayed
by immunoblotting. To estimate the prevalence of SLFN14 among 80S
ribosome-associated proteins in RRL, the 80S complex fraction after
RRL ribosomal profiling was subjected to SDS–PAGE and stained
with SimplyBlue SafeStain. To compare the SLFN14 protein level in
RRL and different rabbit tissue lysates, 40 μg of total protein
of RRL from two different sources (Promega and Green Hectares) and
brain, lung, and liver rabbit tissue lysates were subjected to SDS–PAGE
and assayed by immunoblotting with anti-SLFN14 and anti-eIF2α
(loading control) antibodies. To determine the distribution of SLFN14
between the nucleus and cytoplasm in cells, 40 μg of total protein
of nuclear or cytoplasmic extracts of HEK293T or MCF7 cells was subjected
to SDS–PAGE and assayed by immunoblotting with anti-SLFN14,
anti-HDAC2 (nuclear marker), and anti-GAPDH (cytoplasmic marker) antibodies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.12">
        <title>Endonucleolytic Activity of Different Recombinant Forms of SLFN14</title>
        <p>After affinity purification of SLFN14–65kDa on 80S ribosomes
by centrifugation through SDG, the 80S/SLFN14–65kDa complex,
80S/empty vector expression complex, and empty 80S ribosome
were incubated, and rRNA degradation was assayed by DAFGE. To test
the endonucleolytic activity of SLFN14–45kDa and its mutants,
proteins were incubated with 5′-end <sup>32</sup>P-labeled
HBBmod mRNA in the presence or absence of 1 mM Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions,
as indicated. After incubation, RNA was isolated
and resolved via 6% denaturing PAGE. Gels were dried and autoradiographed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.13">
        <title>Sequence and Structure Specificity of SLFN14 in Cleavage of
Free and Ribosome-Associated mRNA</title>
        <p>To test the sequence and
structure specificity of SLFN14 in the cleavage of free mRNA, SLFN14
was incubated with GUSmod mRNA or HBBmod mRNA, mRNA was isolated,
and cleavage sites were determined by AMV reverse transcriptase-mediated
extension of <sup>32</sup>P-labeled primer complementary to mRNA.
cDNA products
were resolved via 6% denaturing PAGE. To compare the site specificity
of SLFN14 in the cleavage of free and ribosome-associated mRNA, 80S
initiation and elongation complexes were assembled on HBBmod mRNA <italic>in vitro</italic> from individual purified components, purified
by SDG centrifugation, and analyzed by toeprint as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> SDG-purified complexes were incubated with SLFN14,
and
mRNA was isolated and assayed by primer extension.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.14">
        <title>Ribosomal
Position of SLFN14</title>
        <p>40S subunits were incubated
with SLFN14. Cleavage sites in 18S rRNA were identified by the extension
of corresponding primers complementary to rabbit 18S rRNA.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec3.1">
        <title>SLFN14
Protein Is Responsible for the Endonucleolytic Cleavage
of RNA in RRL</title>
        <p>Before starting the RRL fractionation search
of the unknown endoribonuclease involved in NGD, we assembled the
stalled ribosomal elongation complex (stalled EC) in an <italic>in
vitro</italic> reconstituted system on a model mRNA and purified it
by centrifugation through the sucrose density gradient (SDG). Model
“HBBmod” mRNA comprises the β-globin 5′-untranslated
region (5′-UTR) and nonapeptide-encoding open reading frame
(ORF) followed by a stem structure of 27 nucleotide base pairs (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). This stem was successfully employed for the
assembly of stalled EC and the detection of NGD-associated endonucleolytic
cleavage of mRNA in yeast.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup> The efficient
formation of purified stalled EC was confirmed
by a toeprint assay. According to this technique, the ribosomal complex
on mRNA yields a toeprint signal at its leading edge. Our reconstituted
complexes revealed toeprint signals located at the beginning of a
stem, indicating that they are true stalled ECs (in Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, compare lanes 1 and 2). To detect endonucleolytic
cleavage, stalled EC was incubated with RRL or its ribosomal salt
wash (RSW) and mRNA was isolated and assayed by primer extension.
Although we did not observe any changes after incubation with RRL
(Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, lane 4), strong cleavage was found
after incubation with RSW within the stem, a few nucleotides downstream
of the stalled EC toeprint signal (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B, lane 3), suggesting the enrichment of the responsible endoribonuclease
in the ribosome-associated fraction of proteins. We could not identify
the precise position of cleavage because of the nucleotide sequence
compression in this area of the stem. To isolate the endoribonuclease
activity, we undertook protein purification from RSW of RRL employing
the combination of different fractionation techniques coupled with
testing of intermediate fractions for mRNA cleavage of stalled EC.
Mass spectrometry of the final protein at 99% purity in the fraction
identified it as a C-terminally truncated form (approximately 95kDa)
of SLFN14 (the full-length rabbit form is 114kDa) (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). The short form of the protein may result from
alternative mRNA splicing or proteolytic cleavage of full-length SLFN14
specifically in reticulocytes. SLFN14 belongs to the Schlafen protein
family found in mammals and encoded by six <italic>Slfn</italic> genes
in humans. All SLFN proteins share a highly conserved N-terminus containing
a putative AAA domain involved in ATP binding,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> whereas only long <italic>Slfn</italic> genes (including <italic>Slfn14</italic>) possess a C-terminal extension with motives found
in superfamily I DNA/RNA helicases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> Members
of this family are involved in an antiviral
immune response,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> differentiation,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> and T-cell development.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup></p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Native rabbit C-terminally truncated SLFN14
causes endonucleolytic
cleavage of rRNA in RRL and purified ribosomes as well as of mRNA
in ribosome-associated and free states. (A) Structure of HBBmod mRNA. <italic>HBB</italic> is the name of the gene encoding β-globin protein.
(B) Endonucleolytic cleavage of ribosome-bound HBBmod mRNA in stalled
EC in the presence of RRL and RSW assayed by primer extension (lanes
3 and 4). Efficiency of stalled EC formation assembled from purified
components <italic>in vitro</italic> analyzed by toeprint (lanes 1
and 2). Positions of full-length, stalled EC, and cleavage signals
are indicated. Lanes G, A, T, and C depict the corresponding DNA sequence.
(C) Purification scheme for SLFN14 (left). Purified SLFN14 resolved
by SDS–PAGE (right). (D) Endonucleolytic cleavage of HBBmod
mRNA in stalled EC and the free state by SLFN14 tested by primer extension.
The empty triangle points to the cleavage position presented in both
free and ribosome-associated mRNA. Black triangles indicate cleavage
sites in free mRNA only. (E) Kinetics of rRNA degradation in RRL and
HEK293T cell extract assayed by DAFGE. (F) Kinetics of degradation
of rRNA by SLFN14 in RRL and purified 80S ribosomes analyzed by DAFGE.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0001" id="gr1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To confirm our finding, stalled
EC was incubated
with native SLFN14. We observed a similar cleavage of mRNA as in the
presence of RSW (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D, lanes 1 and 2,
empty triangle). Surprisingly, the incubation of HBBmod mRNA alone,
not in the stalled EC, with SLFN14 resulted in multiple additional
endonucleolytic cleavages distributed along mRNA (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D, lanes 3 and 4, filled triangles), suggesting
that the activity of SLFN14 is independent of the ribosome. Because
SLFN14 alone manifests the activity and, at the same time, is enriched
with RSW, we tested the potential effect of SLFN14 on the degradation
of rRNA in RRL. In contrast to HEK293T (human embryonic kidney) cell
extract, RRL incubation at 37 °C within 12 h resulted in a complete
endonucleolytic cleavage
of 28S rRNA as revealed via denaturing agarose/formaldehyde gel electrophoresis
(DAFGE), whereas 18S rRNA degraded much slower (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>E). To confirm the role of SLFN14 in the
degradation of rRNA, we assayed the protein with purified rabbit 80S
ribosomes. Incubation of SLFN14 with 80S ribosomes in an equimolar
ratio demonstrated a final rRNA degradation pattern identical to that
of RRL (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>F). The slightly different
initial pattern could be explained by the protection of the ribosome
with ribosome-associated proteins in RRL. Thus, although SLFN14 causes
the endonucleolytic cleavage of mRNA in stalled EC, a role more general
than the initially suggested role in the NGD process cannot be ruled
out.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.2">
        <title>SLFN14 Specifically Binds the Ribosome and Ribosomal Subunits
and Cleaves Different Types of RNA in a Mg<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-Dependent and ATP-Independent Manner</title>
        <p>To test whether
SLFN14 cleaves rRNA in individual ribosomal subunits, we incubated
purified 40S or 60S subunits with the excess of isolated SLFN14 to
accelerate degradation kinetics and analyzed RNA via DAFGE. Again,
we observed a characteristic endonucleolytic cleavage pattern (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A,B). To examine the universality of the process,
we used 5′-end <sup>32</sup>P-labeled mRNA and tRNA transcripts.
Randomly chosen modified β-glucuronidase
(GUSmod) and already described HBBmod mRNAs as well as His-tRNA and
Val-tRNA after incubation with SLFN14 revealed endonucleolytic cleavage
patterns in denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C–F). Therefore, SLFN14 degrades different
types of cellular RNA in a
binary system.</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>SLFN14 binds the ribosome and ribosomal subunits and cleaves
different
types of RNA in a Mg<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-dependent and
ATP-independent manner. (A and B) Kinetics of degradation of rRNA
by SLFN14 in purified 40S subunits and 60S subunits, respectively,
assayed by DAFGE. (C–F) Kinetics of degradation of 5′-end <sup>32</sup>P-labeled HBBmod mRNA, GUSmod mRNA, His-tRNA, and Val-tRNA,
respectively, by SLFN14 analyzed by denaturing PAGE. (G) Thin layer
chromatography analysis of SLFN14’s ATPase activity in the
presence or absence of (CU)<sub>17</sub> RNA, 40S subunits, or 80S
ribosomes. DHX29 helicase (positive control) is ATPase; its hydrolyzing
activity is stimulated by 40S subunits. Positions of [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP and [<sup>32</sup>P]P<sub>i</sub> are indicated. (H)
Association of SLFN14 with 80S ribosomes or 40S and 60S subunits in
the presence or absence of nucleotides, as indicated, assayed by SDG
centrifugation and SDS–PAGE of peak ribosomal fractions. (I)
rRNA degradation in the SDG-purified 80S/SLFN14 complex before or
after incubation tested by DAFGE. (J) Dependence of SLFN14 endonucleolytic
activity on metal ions and ATP analyzed by denaturing PAGE.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0002" id="gr2" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Because SLFN14 harbors the AAA
domain, we studied
its ATPase activity by thin layer chromatography. Interestingly, SLFN14
contains the truncated 129-amino acid AAA domain, compared to the
200–250-amino
acid regular one. Importantly, some AAA proteins are inactive
as ATPases, and some do not even bind ATP. Therefore, it is not surprising
that SLFN14 did not hydrolyze [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP and hydrolysis
was not stimulated by (CU)<sub>17</sub> RNA, 40S ribosomal subunits,
or 80S ribosomes (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>G). To investigate
the interaction of SLFN14 with the ribosome, we mixed SLFN14 with
40S or 60S subunits or 80S ribosomes in the presence of AMPPNP or
ADP and in the absence of a nucleotide without incubation to prevent
degradation and purified complexes by SDG centrifugation. SLFN14 efficiently
bound to the ribosome and ribosomal subunits in a nucleotide-independent
manner (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>H). Following incubation of
such SDG-purified 80S/SLFN14 complexes caused rRNA degradation (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>I). The activity of several characterized endoribonucleases
(for example, RNase L, Dicer, Ago2, and SMG6) depends on Mg<sup>2+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup> ions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> Consistently,
SLFN14 cleaved GUSmod mRNA in the binary
system in the presence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Mn<sup>2+</sup>, but
not Zn<sup>2+</sup>, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Fe<sup>2+</sup>, or Fe<sup>3+</sup> ions, and the activity was ATP-independent (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>J).</p>
        <p>To confirm the accuracy of the assignment of endonuclease
activity
to SLFN14, we cloned 104kDa full-length as well as 95, 85, and 65kDa
(SLFN14–65kDa)
C-terminally truncated His-tagged forms of human protein for expression
in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells. Although rabbit SLFN14 contains
a 10 kDa C-terminal extension compared to the human homologue, the
sequences of both proteins are 78% identical and 86% similar
over their entire lengths. All forms were expressed, but only SLFN14–65kDa
was found to be soluble in small quantities. We isolated SLFN14–65kDa
employing Ni-NTA resin followed by affinity purification through
80S ribosome association during SDG centrifugation. As a control,
we used the same purification protocol for the empty vector (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). 80S ribosome-bound SLFN14–65kDa, but
not a control, after incubation at 37 °C for
12 h caused endonucleolytic rRNA degradation (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B).</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Endonucleolytic activity of recombinant human SLFN14–65kDa
and sequence and structure specificity of SLFN14 in cleavage of free
and ribosome-associated mRNA. (A) Affinity purification of SLFN14–65kDa
on 80S ribosomes by centrifugation through SDG assayed by SDS–PAGE
and Coomassie staining. (B) rRNA degradation in the SDG-purified 80S/SLFN14–65kDa
complex, the 80S/empty vector expression complex, and the empty 80S
ribosome after incubation analyzed by DAFGE. Native rabbit SLFN14
is a positive control (lane 4). (C) Structure of GUSmod mRNA. <italic>GUS</italic> is the name of the gene encoding β-glucuronidase
protein. (D and E) Endonucleolytic cleavage of free GUSmod mRNA (D),
free HBBmod mRNA (E, lanes 4 and 5), and ribosome-bound HBBmod mRNA
(E, lanes 6–9) in 80S initiation (80S) and elongation complexes
(EC) by SLFN14 assayed by primer extension. Efficiency of formation
of ribosomal complexes assembled from purified components <italic>in vitro</italic> analyzed by toeprint (E, lanes 1–3). The
empty triangle points to the cleavage position presented in both free
and ribosome-associated mRNA. Black triangles indicate cleavage positions
in free mRNA only. Positions of full-length cDNA and toeprints corresponding
to ribosomal complexes as well as single-stranded and structured regions
within mRNAs are indicated. Lanes C, T, A, and G depict corresponding
DNA sequences.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0003" id="gr3" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.3">
        <title>Sequence and Structure
Specificity of SLFN14 in RNA Cleavage</title>
        <p>Next, we determined
sequence and structure preferences in RNA cleavage.
For that, we utilized HBBmod and GUSmod mRNAs mentioned above. HBBmod
mRNA has already
been described, whereas GUSmod mRNA comprises the single-stranded
5′-UTR of CAA repeats with a centrally introduced 9 bps stem
followed by β-glucuronidase ORF (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). After incubation of either mRNA with SLFN14, it was isolated
and assayed by primer extension. In both cases, cleavages were distributed
along all mRNA, and we did not reveal any sequence or structure preferences
(Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D,E, lanes 4 and 5; empty and filled
triangles). To compare the cleavage pattern of mRNA in free and ribosome-bound
states, we reconstituted 80S initiation and elongation (with one elongation
step) ribosomal complexes on HBBmod mRNA from purified components <italic>in vitro</italic> (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E, lanes 1–3)
and treated them with SLFN14. In both complexes, SLFN14 cleaved
mRNA almost exclusively at one of many sites observed for free mRNA
(Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>E, lanes 6–9, empty triangle),
which is spatially closest to ribosome-associated
SLFN14.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.4">
        <title>After rRNA Cleavage by SLFN14, 80S Ribosomes Remain Intact and
Active in Translation Whereas Individual Ribosomal Subunits Degrade
into Components</title>
        <p>To examine the integrity of ribosome and
ribosomal subunits after rRNA cleavage by SLFN14, purified 80S ribosomes
or 40S and 60S subunits were treated with SLFN14 and subjected to
SDG centrifugation. 80S ribosomes remain intact in a gradient (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A), despite rRNA cleavage (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B), and all ribosomal proteins as well as SLFN14 remain associated
(Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C); on the other hand, peaks of 40S
and 60S subunits disappear (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D,E). Probably,
cleavage of the RNA-rich intersubunit area, which is hidden in the
ribosome, is crucial for ribosomal subunit degradation. To correlate
our findings with the fate of ribosomes in RRL, we also subjected
RRL, before and after incubation at 37 °C, to SDG
centrifugation. Importantly, incubation was conducted in the presence
of cycloheximide (CHX) to exclude polysome runoff. This antibiotic
interferes with the translocation step during protein
synthesis and, in such a way, blocks the translation elongation stage.
As seen from the ribosomal profile, polysomes after incubation separate
into monosomes, as a result of polysome-associated mRNA cleavage,
and the overall amount of ribosomes decreases by 26 ± 3%, suggesting
their partial degradation into components (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>F). In agreement with our findings on purified 80S
ribosomes, monosomes remain intact in the SDG profile despite rRNA
cleavage (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>G). Next, we decided to test
the functional activity of ribosomes in translation after their cleavage
in RRL. For that, we incubated RRL overnight at 37 °C, increased
the ionic strength to separate cleaved ribosomes into subunits, and
purified them via centrifugation in high-salt SDG (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>H). Ribosomal subunits
with cleaved rRNAs were as active in the methionyl-puromycin assay
as intact ones assuming that the translational activity of cleaved
ribosomal subunits is not compromised (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>I). To confirm our observation, we compared intact and cleaved ribosomal
subunits in all stages of translation (initiation, elongation, termination,
and ribosomal recycling) in an <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstituted
system employing MVHL-STOP mRNA. This mRNA comprises β-globin
5′-UTR, MVHL-tetrapeptide-encoding ORF and a stop codon, followed
by β-globin 3′-UTR (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>J,
top panel). In a manner consistent with methionyl-puromycin assay
results, we found that the toeprint pattern for 80S initiation and
pretermination complexes and the disappearance of toeprint after termination
and ribosomal recycling stages were identical for intact and cleaved
ribosomal subunits (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>J, bottom panel).
Our finding is surprising, but not without precedent. Some strains
of bacterial species (for example, <italic>Salmonella</italic>) have naturally fragmented 23S rRNA.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Integrity and translation
activity of ribosomes and ribosomal subunits
after rRNA cleavage by SLFN14. (A) Integrity of 80S ribosomes after
incubation with SLFN14 assayed by SDG centrifugation. (B and C) rRNA
appearance and protein content, respectively, of 80S ribosomes after
SLFN14 treatment and SDG purification analyzed by DAFGE and SDS–PAGE,
respectively. (D and E) Degradation of 40S subunits and 60S subunits,
respectively, after incubation with SLFN14 assayed by SDG centrifugation.
(F) Ribosomal profiling of RRL before and after incubation at 37 °C
in the presence of CHX obtained by SDG centrifugation. The total amount
of ribosomes was decreased by 26 ± 3% (average ± standard
deviation; <italic>n</italic> = 3) after incubation. Upper fractions
were omitted for the sake of clarity. (G) rRNA appearance of 80S monosomes
after incubation of RRL at 37 °C and ribosomal profiling. (H)
rRNA appearance of cleaved 80S ribosome-derived 40S and 60S subunits
purified from RRL after incubation at 37 °C and centrifugation
through high-salt SDG. (I) Methionyl-puromycin assay of 80S initiation
complex formation with purified intact/cleaved ribosomal subunits.
(J) Structure of MVHL-STOP mRNA (top panel). Toeprint analysis of
ribosomal complexes at different stages of translation assembled on
MVHL-STOP mRNA <italic>in vitro</italic> with purified intact/cleaved
ribosomal subunits (bottom). Lanes C, T, A, and G depict the cDNA
sequence of MVHL-STOP mRNA. Positions of full-length cDNA and of toeprints
corresponding to ribosomal complexes are indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0004" id="gr4" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.5">
        <title>Ribosomal Position, Cytoplasmic Distribution,
and Protein Level
of SLFN14 in RRL</title>
        <p>To determine the ribosomal position of SLFN14,
we identified cleavage sites of 18S rRNA in the 40S/SLFN14 binary
complex. Despite 28S rRNA appearing to be preferentially attacked
in ribosomes, it is almost 3 times longer than 18S rRNA. Therefore,
we decided to assay only 18S rRNA. SLFN14 cuts at the distal end of
expansion segments ES3S, ES6S, and ES12S (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A), suggesting the approximate location of protein at the
low part of the body of the 40S subunit and, presumably, the 80S ribosome
(Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B,C). Notably, the existence of extension
segments is a feature of the eukaryotic ribosome.</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Ribosomal position of
SLFN14. (A) Identification of prevalent cleavage
sites in 18S rRNA after incubation of 40S ribosomal subunits with
SLFN14 assayed by primer extension. Black triangles indicate the position
and expansion segment location of residues cleaved by SLFN14. Primers
1–3 are described in the <xref rid="notes-3" ref-type="notes">Supporting Information</xref>. (B and C) Intersubunit side and platform side views, respectively,
of 18S rRNA nucleotides cleaved by SLFN14 mapped onto the crystal
structure of the <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> 40S subunit
(Protein Data Bank entry 3U5B). 18S rRNA (magenta) is shown in backbone representation.
Protected nucleotides are colored green, red, and blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0005" id="gr5" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Further, we examined the cytoplasmic distribution
of SLFN14 in RRL. We run mRNA-free and, therefore, polysome-free RRL
(Promega) in SDG to separate 80S ribosomes, 60S subunits, 40S subunits,
and free proteins. To assign peaks, we isolated and analyzed their
rRNA content. SLFN14 was found in 80S ribosome-containing fractions,
as revealed by immunoblotting of the entire gradient (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A) (unshaped diffused immunoblotting signals for
fractions 21–23 are most likely the background rather than
SLFN14), in an equimolar
ratio with 80S ribosomes (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B). Moreover,
SLFN14 represents one of the major ribosome-associated proteins in
SDS–denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS–PAGE)
(Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>C).</p>
        <fig id="fig6" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>SLFN14 protein level and localization
in different cell types.
(A) SLFN14 distribution (bottom) in the ribosomal profile of mRNA-free
RRL (Promega) (top) after SDG centrifugation assayed by immunoblotting.
(B and C) Estimation of the SLFN14 to 80S ribosome ratio and SLFN14
abundance, respectively, in the SDG-purified 80S complex from RRL
analyzed by immunoblotting and SDS–PAGE, respectively. (D)
SLFN14 protein level in two different sources of RRL and rabbit brain,
lung, and liver tissue lysates tested by immunoblotting with anti-SLFN14
and anti-eIF2α (loading control) antibodies. (E) SLFN14 subcellular
distribution in HEK293T and MCF7 cells assayed by immunoblotting with
anti-SLFN14, anti-HDAC2 (nuclear marker), and anti-GAPDH (cytoplasmic
marker) antibodies.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0006" id="gr6" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.6">
        <title>Nucleated Cells Employ
Multiple Levels of Protection from Endonuclease
Activity of SLFN14</title>
        <p>Next, we performed the set of experiments
to understand how other cell types remain protected from the endonuclease
activity of SLFN14. We compared the protein level of SLFN14 in RRL
and randomly selected rabbit brain, lung, and liver tissue lysates
by immunoblotting. The level of SLFN14 expression is dramatically
higher in RRL than in tissue lysates, where the amount of protein
is below the detection limit (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D). Importantly,
SLFN14 is represented exclusively by the C-terminally truncated form
in RRL from different sources, eliminating the effect of lysate preparation
on the length of the protein. Then, we detected the subcellular localization
of SLFN14 in randomly chosen HEK293T and MCF7 (human breast cancer)
cells. For that, nuclear and cytoplasmic extracts of cells were prepared
and assayed for the presence of protein by immunoblotting. On the
basis of the nuclear localization of Schlafens 5, 8, and 9, all long
SLFN family members are predicted to be located in the nucleus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> Consistently, SLFN14 was found solely in nuclear extracts of both
cell lines (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>E). Notably, the detected
protein in both cell types is the full-length form of SLFN14. Interestingly,
reticulocytes and mature erythrocytes are the only non-nucleated cell
types in mammals, and this fact may explain the cytoplasmic presence
of SLFN14 in RRL. On the basis of our data, we hypothesize that only
the short form of protein reveals the endonuclease activity. Therefore,
the low expression level, full-length state, and nuclear localization
create multiple levels of protection from endonuclease activity of
SLFN14 in other rabbit tissues.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.7">
        <title>Murine Full-Length SLFN14
neither Cleaves RNA nor Binds to the
Ribosome</title>
        <p>Our next aim was to test the hypothesis that full-length
SLFN14 is inactive compared to the C-terminally truncated form. Because
we could not obtain recombinant full-length SLFN14 in a soluble state,
we decided to isolate the endogenous native protein from the available
natural source. Therefore, we detected and purified it from the Krebs
ascites cell lysate employing the combination of fractionation techniques
and chasing the protein by immunoblotting (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A). Murine full-length SLFN14 is a 102 kDa polypeptide and,
like the human form, is highly homologous to rabbit SLFN14. To study
the endonucleolytic activity, murine protein at different concentrations
was incubated with 40S ribosomal subunits, and 18S rRNA was isolated
and assayed by PAGE. In contrast to a rabbit form, it did not cause
the cleavage of 18S rRNA (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B). Further,
we asked whether full-length SLFN14, despite the absence of endonucleolytic
activity, may still associate with the ribosome and ribosomal subunits.
Because of the high adsorption of proteins to the gradient tube and
the limited amount of murine SLFN14, we assayed the SDG-purified ribosomal
complexes by immunoblotting. Again in contrast to a rabbit short form,
the murine full-length homologue bound to neither the 40S subunit
nor the 80S ribosome (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C, left panel).
To test whether the murine shorter
form of protein can associate with the 80S ribosome, we cloned the
65 kDa C-terminally truncated version of murine SLFN14 (murine SLFN14–65kDa),
similar to rabbit SLFN14–65kDa, for the expression in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells. Because murine SLFN14–65kDa was found
to be soluble in small quantities after expression, we
assayed its interaction with the 80S ribosome employing the same protocol
that was used for rabbit SLFN14–65kDa. As expected, murine
SLFN14–65
kDa along with its even shorter form (Δ<italic>S</italic>LFN14–65kDa)
strongly binds to the 80S ribosome as revealed
by SDG centrifugation (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C, middle panel).
Moreover, murine SLFN14–65kDa causes the endonucleolytic cleavage
of both rRNAs after incubation
of the SDG-purified 80S/murine SLFN14–65kDa complex (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C, right panel). In conclusion,
the endonucleolytic activity and the ribosomal binding site of SLFN14
are hidden in the presence of the C-terminal part of the protein.
It would be interesting to know the mechanism underlying the appearance
of the C-terminally truncated form, but this question is beyond the
scope of this work.</p>
        <fig id="fig7" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Analysis of ribosomal binding and endonucleolytic activities
of
native murine full-length SLFN14 and mutational analysis of recombinant
human SLFN14. (A) Purification scheme for native murine SLFN14 (left).
Purified SLFN14 assayed by SDS–PAGE and immunoblotting (right).
(B) Endonucleolytic cleavage of 18S rRNA in the 40S subunit by murine
full-length and rabbit C-terminally truncated native forms of SLFN14
at different concentrations tested by denaturing PAGE. (C) Association
of native murine and rabbit SLFN14 proteins with 40S subunits and
80S ribosomes assayed by SDG centrifugation and immunoblotting of
peak ribosomal fractions (left). Association of recombinant murine
SLFN14–65kDa with 80S ribosomes assayed by SDG centrifugation
and Coomassie staining (middle). rRNA degradation in the SDG-purified
80S/murine SLFN14–65kDa complex and empty 80S ribosome after
incubation analyzed by DAFGE (right). (D) Purified recombinant human
SLFN14–45kDa resolved by SDS–PAGE. (E) Endonucleolytic
activity of SLFN14–45kDa vs native rabbit SLFN14 analyzed by
denaturing PAGE. The concentration of the recombinant or native form
in the reaction is 0.9 μM or 11 nM, respectively. (F) Ribosomal
binding of SLFN14–45kDa tested by SDG centrifugation and SDS–PAGE
(top). Location of the ribosomal binding site in human SLFN14 (bottom).
(G) Purified recombinant human SLFN14–45kDa mutants resolved
by SDS–-PAGE. (H) Endonucleolytic activity of different SLFN14–45kDa
point mutants assayed by denaturing PAGE. (I) Location of point mutations
in SLFN14–45kDa.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2015-00302y_0007" id="gr7" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.8">
        <title>Mutational Analysis of SLFN14 Revealed the Ribosomal Binding
Site and the Aspartate Essential for the Endonucleolytic Activity
of Protein</title>
        <p>To study the catalytic activity of SLFN14, we
employed the mutational analysis. Because the only soluble recombinant
form, SLFN14–65kDa, was available in a limited amount, in the
next clone we removed
an additional 20 kDa from the C-terminus. SLFN14–45kDa was
highly expressed and completely soluble. We purified it until
high homogeneity employing the combination of Ni-NTA affinity resin
and FPLC on MonoS column techniques (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D). Like the native protein, SLFN14–45kDa caused the endonucleolytic
cleavage of RNA in a Mg<sup>2+</sup>-dependent
manner, but much less efficiently, indicating that the active center
is partially compromised (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>E, lanes
1–5).
To rule out the potential cleavage activity associated with the copurified
bacterial endogenous proteins, we performed the expression and protein
purification protocols for the empty vector exactly as for SLFN14–45kDa.
Compared to native and recombinant SLFN14 forms, we did not obtain
RNA degradation in the presence or absence of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions
for the empty vector expression control (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>E, lanes 6 and 7). Interestingly, in contrast to SLFN14–65kDa,
SLFN14–45kDa could not associate with the 80S ribosome,
suggesting the location of the ribosomal binding site within 179 amino
acids beside the AAA domain to the C-terminus (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>F). Thus, SLFN14–45kDa was chosen as the basis for
the point mutation analysis. Like well-characterized
RNase L, Dicer, Ago2, and SMG6, SLFN14 is the Mg<sup>2+</sup>- and
Mn<sup>2+</sup>-dependent and ATP-independent enzyme. It is shown
that Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion is coordinated by one Asp and one Asn in
the catalytic center of RNase L,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> by two
Asp and two Gln residues in Dicer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> by an Asp-Asp-His
motif in Ago2,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> and by one Asp in the
essential Asp-Asp-Asp motif in SMG6.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> Therefore,
Asp is one of the key amino acids in the
active center of these enzymes. We identified 10 Asp residues within
SLFN14–45kDa,
which are conserved among mammals. Importantly, two Asp residues
belong to the Walker B motif 244LIGVDD249, which is the signature
motif of the AAA domain. It is well-known that the Walker B motif,
which contains the consensus sequence hhhhD(E/D),
where h is a hydrophobic acid, is involved in Mg<sup>2+</sup> coordination
and ATP hydrolysis. Interestingly, several AAA proteins are not active
as ATPases, and some do not even bind ATP. Therefore, we cloned, expressed
in <italic>E. coli</italic>, and purified four Asp single-point mutants.
We substituted
each Asp in the Walker B motif and randomly selected for the mutation
two other conservative ones. RNA degradation analysis revealed that
the D249A mutant was inactive and the activity of the D248A mutant
was strongly decreased, whereas others caused the cleavage with a
similar characteristic pattern (Figure <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>G–I).
Thus, Asp249, which probably coordinates the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion,
is essential for the endonucleolytic activity of SLFN14. Importantly,
because endonuclease activity has not previously been reported for
AAA ATPases, it is equally possible that Asp249 could be required
for the structural integrity of the catalytic center or even the entire
protein.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In an attempt to identify
the endoribonuclease involved in the
no-go decay, we employed the RRL fractionation approach coupled with
testing of intermediate fractions in exmaining the ability to cause
the endonucleolytic cleavage of mRNA in the reconstituted stalled
EC. This approach resulted in the purification of the C-terminally
truncated form of SLFN14, which is ∼20 kDa shorter than the
114 kDa full-length rabbit protein. Interestingly, immunoblotting
analysis of RRL from different sources did not reveal the presence
of the full-length form of the enzyme. The function of SLFN14 is completely
unknown, and there has been no work concerning its characterization
at a biochemical or cellular level published. SLFN14 belongs to the
Schlafen protein family based on the presence of specific slfn signature
motifs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup> The SLFN family is limited to mammals and
represents a diverse group
of proteins with essential sequence variability among species. For
example, there are eight murine SLFNs and six human SLFN,s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> suggesting that they may have different species
specific functions. The precise
role of SLFN proteins in the cell remains to be identified; however,
several members of the family are found to be involved in development,
cell proliferation, and immune response.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> SLFN14 contains the AAA domain at the N-terminus and
the motif, homologous to the superfamily of DNA/RNA helicases, at
the C-terminus. AAA proteins, where AAA is the abbreviation for ATPase
associated with diverse cellular activities, make up the large and
functionally diverse protein family involved in a wide variety of
processes such as DNA replication, protein degradation, membrane fusion,
microtubule severing, peroxisome biogenesis, signal transduction,
and the regulation of gene expression. Notably, SLFN14 possesses the
shortened 129-amino acid AAA domain, compared to the 200–250-amino
acid regular one, without several signature motifs. For example,
the Walker A motif, which is involved in ATP binding, is absent. In
contrast to other SLFN members, SLFN14 is highly homologous among
all species where it is present, for example, in rabbit, human, chimpanzee,
cow, rat, dog, and mouse.</p>
      <p>In the control
experiment, native rabbit SLFN14 caused the endonucleolytic cleavage
of mRNA in the proximity of the stalled EC. Surprisingly, this enzyme
also resulted in multiple cleavages all along mRNA in the binary SLFN14/mRNA
complex in a ribosome-independent manner. Because SLFN14 is enriched
with RSW, we tested its potential effect on the stability of rRNA
in RRL and found that both 28S and 18S rRNAs became fully degraded
with the formation of the characteristic endonucleolytic cleavage
pattern after the incubation of RRL for 12 h at 37 °C. Absolutely
the same final degradation pattern was obtained after
the incubation for 12 h of the 80S/SLFN14 binary complex with the
equimolar ratio of components
assuming that SLFN14 is indeed involved in the rRNA cleavage in RRL.
Consistently, it also cut rRNA when it was mixed with individual ribosomal
subunits, producing again the characteristic degradation pattern.
To confirm the universality of endonucleolytic activity, SLFN14 was
assayed in the presence of different types of RNA. It caused the cleavage
of all tested mRNAs and tRNAs. In agreement with the enrichment in
RSW, SLFN14 binds to the ribosome and both ribosomal subunits, and
the association is ATP-independent. Ribosomal binding unambiguously
indicates the role of this protein in the translation regulation.
Like those of well-characterized RNase L, Dicer, Ago2, and SMG6 endoribonucleases,
the nuclease activity of SLFN14 is Mg<sup>2+</sup>- and Mn<sup>2+</sup>-dependent and ATP-independent. Moreover, despite the presence of
the
AAA domain, SLFN14 does not hydrolyze ATP and the hydrolysis is not
stimulated by either the ribosome or RNA. It is not surprising, because
some AAA proteins do not even bind ATP. Because of the high structural
diversity, the nuclease domains responsible for the endonucleolytic
activity of many enzymes are not identified yet, and this is the case
for SLFN14. However, like previously mentioned endoribonucleases,
SLFN14 shares the same divalent ion-mediated mechanism of phosphodiester
bond activation in the catalytic center of the protein.</p>
      <p>To confirm
the correct assignment of the endonucleolytic activity
to SLFN14, we purified from <italic>E. coli</italic> the recombinant
human SLFN14–65kDa, which represents the C-terminally truncated
form of protein. Unfortunately,
we could not obtain a longer form in a soluble state after expression.
This protein efficiently binds to the ribosome and causes RNA degradation,
showing that the C-terminal third of SLFN14 is dispensable for both
activities. To test the sequence and structure specificities of SLFN14
in the cleavage of RNA, we assayed the enzyme in the presence of model
mRNAs with the definite single-stranded and structured regions. We
did not detect any sequence and structure preferences. We assume that
the hydrolysis takes place in the energetically favorable phosphodiester
bonds, which,
in turn, are defined by the tertiary structure of RNA. In contrast
to multiple cleavages of the free mRNA, ribosome-bound SLFN14 cuts
mRNA in the 80S initiation complex and different elongation complexes
predominantly at the spatially closest energetically favorable site.
Because SLFN14 in association
with the ribosome also cleaves rRNAs, we identified its ribosomal
binding site employing the primer extension technique. In the binary
40S/SLFN14 complex, the enzyme cuts 18S rRNA at the distal end of
expansion segments ES3S, ES6S, and ES12S, indicating its location
at the low part of the body of the 40S subunit and likely at the corresponding
low part of the 60S subunit in the 80S ribosome. Interestingly, expansion
segments are absent in prokaryotic ribosomes, and their functions
mainly remain obscure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> After rRNA cleavage
of individual ribosomal subunits,
they both degrade into components. In contrast, after rRNA cleavage
of 80S ribosomes, the last remain undegraded. Interestingly, the simultaneous
presence of several cuts in rRNA does not influence the integrity
of the 80S ribosome. Analysis of the intracellular distribution of
SLFN14 in RRL revealed that the enzyme is associated with ribosomes
and is absent in the free form in the cytoplasm. Moreover, it is overexpressed
and is presented in an equimolar ratio with ribosomes, indicating
the enormous content of this endoribonuclease in reticulocytes. As
a result, SLFN14 is one of few major ribosome-associated proteins
in RRL. In a manner consistent with the high ribosomal affinity, SLFN14
in RRL cleaves first of all ribosomal and ribosome-associated RNA
but potentially may cleave any type of RNA, resulting in the separation
of polysomes into monosomes. Surprisingly, cleaved 80S ribosomes are
active in all stages of translation (initiation, elongation, termination,
and ribosomal recycling). Because the rRNA-rich intersubunit area
remains hidden in the ribosome, the integrity and the catalytic centers
involved in translation activity of ribosomes, obviously, are not
compromised.</p>
      <p>We also tried to understand the mechanism by which
other cell types
preserve the RNA integrity from the endonucleolytic activity of SLFN14.
We found that in contrast to reticulocytes, the SLFN14 level is below
the detection limit in brain, lung, and liver tissues. Our data are
supported by two other reports in which the relative level of SLFN14
expression was found to be very low in primary normal human melanocytes
and malignant melanoma cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup> and was
shown to be very low or even below the detection
level in HEK293, HEK293T, HeLa, CEM, and Jurkat cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> Our analysis of the subcellular distribution
in nucleated
cells revealed that SLFN14 is located in the nucleus and is represented
by the full-length form in HEK293T and MCF7 cells. Thus, the low expression
level and nuclear localization may create the barrier for RNA degradation
by SLFN14. Consistently, we did not detect the RNA cleavage after
incubation of HEK293T lysate, although the latter contains SLFN14
as revealed by immunoblotting. Moreover, because SLFN14 is represented
by the full-length version in tested nucleated cells and by the C-terminally
truncated version in RRL, we assign the endonuclease activity to the
short form of the protein. It is well-known that some members of caspases,
the family of cysteine proteases,
become activated by the proteolytic cleavage of their pro forms. To
test our hypothesis, we purified native murine full-length SLFN14
from Krebs ascites cell lysate. In contrast to the short form, the
full-length SLFN14 did not bind to the ribosome and ribosomal subunits
and did not cleave the rRNA, confirming our hypothesis.</p>
      <p>Finally,
we employed the mutational analysis to identify the ribosomal
binding site and to gain insights into the organization of the catalytic
center of SLFN14. We located the ribosomal binding site within 179
amino acids in the central part of the protein beside the AAA domain
to the C-terminus. Like those of well-characterized RNase L, Dicer,
Ago2, and SMG6 endoribonucleases, the activity of SLFN14 strictly
depends on Mg<sup>2+</sup> and Mn<sup>2+</sup> ions. Aspartic acid
plays the essential role of the coordination of divalent ion in the
catalytic center of all four mentioned endoribonucleases. Analyzing
different point mutants of SLFN14, we found that Asp249 is critical
for its endonucleolytic activity. Asp249 is located in the Walker
B motif, which is the signature motif of the AAA domain. Interestingly,
the Walker B motif of SLFN14 with the sequence 244LIGVDD249 belongs
to the minor subgroup of Walker B motifs within AAA proteins with
the consensus sequence hhhhD(E/D), where h is a hydrophobic acid.
Generally, the last amino acid of the consensus sequence is glutamate,
and only few members of AAA proteins contain aspartate instead. Another
important detail is that the AAA domain of SLFN14 is substantially
shorter than the regular AAA domain of AAA proteins (129 amino acids
vs 200–250 amino acids), and as a result, some signature motifs
are missing.
Thus, we assume that the evolutionarily modified AAA domain of SLFN14,
which originally couples ATP hydrolysis with conformational changes
of protein, lost ATP hydrolyzing activity but retained the ability
to coordinate Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion and currently constitutes the part
of the catalytic center of the enzyme. However, because endonuclease
activity has not been ascribed so far to the AAA domain, it is equally
possible that Asp249 is important for the structural integrity of
the catalytic center or even the entire protein.</p>
      <p>On the basis
of our data, we suggest several possible target processes
for SLFN14. The first proposed process is limited to reticulocytes.
Mammalian reticulocytes do not have a cell nucleus but contain a network
of ribosomes and the endoplasmic reticulum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> They become fully matured erythrocytes as their ribosomes are degraded
by intracellular enzymes. In particular, polysomes separate into monosomes,
reduce in number, and disappear, and the total RNA content decreases
in parallel.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> The rate of RNA degradation during
reticulocyte maturation <italic>in vitro</italic> at 37 °C is
4%
per hour. Additionally, ribosomes and ribosome-associated RNA are
degraded at a rate greater than that of free RNA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> To date, reticulocyte maturation and, particularly,
RNA degradation have been studied at the cellular level, but the mechanism
is still unknown. Several reports of the characterization of ribonucleases
responsible for RNA degradation have been presented, but their data
are contradictory to each other.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> We found that SLFN14 binds specifically
and exceptionally to ribosomes
and ribosomal subunits and cleaves ribosomal and ribosome-associated
RNA. These results are in a good agreement with the preferential degradation
of ribosomes and ribosome-associated RNA rather than free RNA during
intact rabbit reticulocyte maturation <italic>in vitro</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> Ribosomal binding of SLFN14 is a good strategy
for the
targeted degradation of actively translating mRNAs. This approach
may help reticulocytes save energy for other cellular processes because
the energy production is also terminated during reticulocyte maturation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup> Importantly, the requirement to degrade different
RNAs
may explain the sequence nonspecificity of SLFN14. We determined that
incubation of SLFN14 with ribosomes
at a physiological ratio results in complete rRNA degradation in only
12 h, which is also consistent with the low RNA degradation rate in
intact
reticulocytes. RNA degradation along with clearance from many cellular
organelles and the lack of DNA in mammalian reticulocytes are unique
among vertebrates. As a result, mammalian erythrocytes are optimized
for oxygen transport. Therefore, the <italic>Slfn14</italic> gene
could originate in the evolution of mammals presumably to contribute
to the efficiency of erythrocytes. Second, SLFN14 could be involved
in the antiviral host response. It is well-known that RNase L is an
interferon (IFN)-activated endoribonuclease,
which destroys total cellular RNA, including viral RNA. The expression
of several members of the Schlafen protein family is induced by IFN-α
in mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup> Although SLFN14 was not tested,
all <italic>Slfn</italic> genes are located in the same chromosomal
locus at least in mouse,
rat, and human,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> and the expression of
SLFN14 should be also upregulated
in response to the IFN stimulus. Therefore, upon activation, SLFN14
may play a role in the clearance of total cellular RNA similar to
that of RNase L. Finally, the enzyme may be the missing endoribonuclease
in the NGD pathway. To date, we have insufficient experimental data
to confirm or rule out this guess. Despite our suggestions, the real
process for the activity of SLFN14 is yet to be identified. However,
because only a few endoribonucleases involved in mammalian translation
control have been characterized so far, the discovery and biochemical
analysis of novel endoribonuclease SLFN14 expand our knowledge of
the role of this class of enzymes in the ribosome-mediated processes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <notes id="notes-3" notes-type="si">
      <title>Supporting Information Available</title>
      <p>Descriptions of
plasmid construction, cell extracts, and denaturing agarose/formaldehyde
gel electrophoresis (DAFGE) and detailed protocols for all experimental
procedures. The Supporting Information is available free of charge
on the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org">ACS Publications website</ext-link> at DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00302">10.1021/acs.biochem.5b00302</ext-link>.</p>
    </notes>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary Material</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1">
        <media xlink:href="bi5b00302_si_001.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>bi5b00302_si_001.pdf</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
    <notes id="notes-1" notes-type="funding-statement">
      <p>This work was supported by National Institutes of
Health Grant GM097014 to A.V.P.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="notes-2" notes-type="conflict-of-interest">
      <p>The authors
declare no competing financial interest.</p>
    </notes>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Louie
Semaan for the helpful discussion.</p>
    </ack>
    <glossary id="dl1">
      <def-list>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <def-item>
          <term>5′-UTR</term>
          <def>
            <p>5′-untranslated
region</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CHX</term>
          <def>
            <p>cycloheximide</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>DAFGE</term>
          <def>
            <p>denaturing agarose/formaldehyde
gel electrophoresis</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>EC</term>
          <def>
            <p>elongation complex</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ER</term>
          <def>
            <p>endoplasmic reticulum</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>IFN</term>
          <def>
            <p>interferon</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>mRNA</term>
          <def>
            <p>messenger RNA</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NGD</term>
          <def>
            <p>no-go decay</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NMD</term>
          <def>
            <p>nonsense-mediated
decay</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>NSD</term>
          <def>
            <p>nonstop
decay</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>ORF</term>
          <def>
            <p>open
reading frame</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PAGE</term>
          <def>
            <p>polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RISC</term>
          <def>
            <p>RNA-induced silencing complex</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RRL</term>
          <def>
            <p>rabbit reticulocyte lysate</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>RSW</term>
          <def>
            <p>ribosomal salt wash</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SDG</term>
          <def>
            <p>sucrose density
gradient.</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Endoribonucleases:
Enzymes gaining
spotlight in mRNA metabolism</article-title>. <source>FEBS J.</source>
<volume>277</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>–<lpage>641</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968858</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Tomecki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dziembowski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Novel endoribonucleases
as central players in various
pathways of eukaryotic RNA metabolism</article-title>. <source>RNA</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1692</fpage>–<lpage>1724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20675404</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The unfolded protein
response: From stress pathway to homeostatic
regulation</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>334</volume>, <fpage>1081</fpage>–<lpage>1086</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22116877</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Hollien</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Decay of endoplasmic
reticulum-localized mRNAs during the unfolded protein response</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>313</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Polysomal ribonuclease
1 exists in a latent form on polysomes prior to estrogen activation
of mRNA decay</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>1156</fpage>–<lpage>1162</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kedersha</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schoenberg</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Polysome-bound
endonuclease
PMR1 is targeted to stress granules via stress-specific binding to
TIA-1</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>8803</fpage>–<lpage>8813</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16982678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mantha</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Identification of
apurinic/apyrimidinic
endonuclease 1 (APE1) as the endoribonuclease that cleaves c-myc
mRNA</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>3946</fpage>–<lpage>3958</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19401441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Claverie-Martin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>ARD-1 cDNA from
human
cells encodes a site-specific single-strand endoribonuclease that
functionally resembles <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RNase E</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>272</volume>, <fpage>13823</fpage>–<lpage>13828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9153239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Tourriere</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gallouzi</surname><given-names>I. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chebli</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Capony</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mouaikel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van der Geer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tazi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>RasGAP-associated endoribonuclease
G3Bp: Selective RNA degradation and phosphorylation-dependent localization</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>7747</fpage>–<lpage>7760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604510</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Doma</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>RNA quality
control in eukaryotes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>668</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18022361</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Isken</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Maquat</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Quality control of eukaryotic
mRNA: Safeguarding cells from abnormal mRNA function</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1833</fpage>–<lpage>1856</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17671086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yepiskoposyan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Metze</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zamudio Orozco</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kleinschmidt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muhlemann</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Nonsense-mediated mRNA decay in human
cells: Mechanistic insights, functions beyond quality control and
the double-life of NMD factors</article-title>. <source>Cell. Mol. Life
Sci.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>677</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19859661</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Doma</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Endonucleolytic
cleavage of eukaryotic mRNAs with stalls in translation elongation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>440</volume>, <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hedrick</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Schlafen, a new family
of growth regulatory genes that affect thymocyte development</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>668</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9846487</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Pisareva</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pisarev</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Komar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hellen</surname><given-names>C. U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pestova</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Translation
initiation
on mammalian mRNAs with structured 5′UTRs requires DExH-box
protein DHX29</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>135</volume>, <fpage>1237</fpage>–<lpage>1250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19109895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Pisarev</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Skabkin</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pisareva</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Skabkina</surname><given-names>O. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rakotondrafara</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hellen</surname><given-names>C. U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pestova</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The role
of ABCE1 in
eukaryotic posttermination ribosomal recycling</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20122402</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Pestova</surname><given-names>T.
V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lomakin</surname><given-names>I. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dever</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hellen</surname><given-names>C. U.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The joining
of ribosomal
subunits in eukaryotes requires eIF5B</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>403</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659855</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Geserick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Klemm</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zerrahn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Modulation
of T cell development and activation by novel members of the Schlafen
(slfn) gene family harbouring an RNA helicase-like motif</article-title>. <source>Int. Immunol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1535</fpage>–<lpage>1548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15351786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boggan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>O’Neill</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Schlafen-1
causes a cell
cycle arrest by inhibiting induction of cyclin D1</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>280</volume>, <fpage>30723</fpage>–<lpage>30734</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15946944</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sandig</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Limmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pavon-Eternod</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weitzman</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Codon-usage-based
inhibition of HIV protein synthesis by human schlafen 11</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>491</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23000900</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Schlafen-3: A novel
regulator
of intestinal differentiation</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys.
Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>388</volume>, <fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19703412</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Crozat</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Croker</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Siggs</surname><given-names>O. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Theofilopoulos</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khovananth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moresco</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Akira</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An Slfn2 mutation causes
lymphoid and myeloid immunodeficiency due to loss of immune cell quiescence</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20190759</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Katsoulidis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mavrommatis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Woodard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sassano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carayol</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sawicki</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Munshi</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Platanias</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Role of
interferon α
(IFNα)-inducible Schlafen-5 in regulation of anchorage-independent
growth and invasion of malignant melanoma cells</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>285</volume>, <fpage>40333</fpage>–<lpage>40341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20956525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gonda</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Subcellular localization
of the Schlafen protein family</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys.
Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>370</volume>, <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18355440</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zeqiraj</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Orlicky</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thevakumaran</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pillon</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ceccarelli</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Juang</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>D. Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gaughan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brinton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perelygin</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kourinov</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guarne</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sicheri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Dimeric Structure
of Pseudokinase RNase L Bound to 2–5A Reveals a Basis for Interferon-Induced
Antiviral Activity</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24462203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tropea</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Court</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Structural
insight into the mechanism of double-stranded RNA processing by ribonuclease
III</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439209</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Jinek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Doudna</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A three-dimensional view
of the molecular machinery of RNA interference</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>457</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19158786</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>F. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tolia</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aragon</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Joshua-Tor</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Purified Argonaute2
and an siRNA form recombinant human RISC</article-title>. <source>Nat.
Struct. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>349</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15800637</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Glavan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Behm-Ansmant</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Izaurralde</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Structures of the PIN
domains of SMG6 and SMG5 reveal a nuclease within the mRNA surveillance
complex</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>5117</fpage>–<lpage>5125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053788</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ayers</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Casola</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Perez-Lamigueiro</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chippindale</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pritham</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>de la Casa-Esperón</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Evolution
of the Schlafen genes, a gene family associated with embryonic lethality,
meiotic drive, immune processes and orthopoxvirus virulence</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>447</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19619625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Ben-Shem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Garreau de Loubresse</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Melnikov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jenner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yusupova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yusupov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The structure
of the eukaryotic ribosome at 3.0 Å resolution</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>334</volume>, <fpage>1524</fpage>–<lpage>1529</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Baldini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pannacciuli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>The maturation rate of reticulocytes</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>629</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13796139</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Stryckmans</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cronkite</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Giacomelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schiffer</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schnappaut</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>The maturation
and fate
of reticulocytes after in vitro labelling with tritiated amino acids</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5638563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>In vivo degradation
of rat globin
messenger RNA during maturation of reticulocytes</article-title>. <source>J. Biochem.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">479137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Glowacki</surname><given-names>E.
R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Millette</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>Polyribosomes
and the
loss of hemoglobin synthesis in the maturing reticulocyte</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14255752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Burka</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Characteristic
of RNA
degradation in the erythroid cell</article-title>. <source>J. Clin.
Invest.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1266</fpage>–<lpage>1272</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5794250</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>Purification and characterization
of ribonuclease from rabbit reticulocytes</article-title>. <source>Biochim.
Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>92</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14243789</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Stavy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Elson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>1964</year>) <article-title>On ribonuclease
activity in reticulocyte
ribosomes</article-title>. <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
<volume>91</volume>, <fpage>606</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14262447</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref39">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Partial purification
and properties of a ribonuclease from rabbit reticulocytes</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>243</volume>, <fpage>6464</fpage>–<lpage>6473</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5726896</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Protein synthesis in
the maturing reticulocyte</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>242</volume>, <fpage>1533</fpage>–<lpage>1540</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6023221</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Gronowicz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Maturation
of the reticulocyte
in vitro</article-title>. <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6097593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref42">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Mavrommatis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arslan</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sassano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kroczynska</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Platanias</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Expression and regulatory
effects of murine Schlafen (Slfn) genes in malignant melanoma and
renal cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>288</volume>, <fpage>33006</fpage>–<lpage>33015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24089532</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>