<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T20:00:57Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4870812" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4870812</identifier><datestamp>2016-05-19</datestamp><setSpec>actaneurocomm</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Acta Neuropathol Commun</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Acta Neuropathol Commun</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Acta Neuropathologica Communications</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2051-5960</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4870812</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4870812</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4870812</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27193190</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">324</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40478-016-0324-5</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The ALS/FTLD associated protein C9orf72 associates with SMCR8 and WDR41 to regulate the autophagy-lysosome pathway</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sullivan</surname>
            <given-names>Peter M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhou</surname>
            <given-names>Xiaolai</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Robins</surname>
            <given-names>Adam M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paushter</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Dongsung</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Smolka</surname>
            <given-names>Marcus B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Fenghua</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>607-2550667</phone>
            <fax>607-2555961</fax>
            <email>fh87@cornell.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Weill Institute for Cell and Molecular Biology, Cornell University, 345 Weill Hall, Ithaca, NY 14853 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <elocation-id>51</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© Sullivan et al. 2016</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Hexanucleotide repeat expansion in the C9orf72 gene is a leading cause of frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS). Reduced expression of C9orf72 has been proposed as a possible disease mechanism. However, the cellular function of C9orf72 remains to be characterized. Here we report the identification of two binding partners of C9orf72: SMCR8 and WDR41. We show that WDR41 interacts with the C9orf72/SMCR8 heterodimer and WDR41 is tightly associated with the Golgi complex. We further demonstrate that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 associates with the FIP200/Ulk1 complex, which is essential for autophagy initiation. C9orf72 deficient mice, generated using the CRISPR/Cas9 system, show severe inflammation in multiple organs, including lymph node, spleen and liver. Lymph node enlargement and severe splenomegaly are accompanied with macrophage infiltration. Increased levels of autophagy and lysosomal proteins and autophagy defects were detected in both the spleen and liver of C9orf72 deficient mice, supporting an in vivo role of C9orf72 in regulating the autophagy/lysosome pathway. In summary, our study elucidates potential physiological functions of C9orf72 and disease mechanisms of ALS/FTLD.</p>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s40478-016-0324-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Frontotemporal lobar degeneration</kwd>
        <kwd>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</kwd>
        <kwd>Autophagy</kwd>
        <kwd>Lysosome</kwd>
        <kwd>C9orf72</kwd>
        <kwd>SMCR8</kwd>
        <kwd>WDR41</kwd>
        <kwd>Ulk1</kwd>
        <kwd>FIP200/RB1CC1</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100005202</institution-id>
              <institution>Muscular Dystrophy Association</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
          <award-id>255396</award-id>
          <principal-award-recipient>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>Fenghua</given-names>
            </name>
          </principal-award-recipient>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source>
            <institution-wrap>
              <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000065</institution-id>
              <institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</institution>
            </institution-wrap>
          </funding-source>
          <award-id>R01NS088448-01</award-id>
          <principal-award-recipient>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>Fenghua</given-names>
            </name>
          </principal-award-recipient>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2016</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) are two devastating neurodegenerative diseases, which due to overlaps in clinical presentations, pathological features, and genetic causes, are considered two manifestations of a continuous disease spectrum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p>
      <p>Many novel genes have been recently associated with ALS/FTLD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Among these, hexanucleotide repeat expansion in the C9orf72 gene has been shown to be the main cause of ALS/FTLD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], for which three disease mechanisms have been proposed: toxicity of RNA foci formed by RNA repeats, toxicity induced by dipeptide repeat aggregation as a result of repeat associated non-ATG mediated RNA translation (RAN), and reduced expression of the C9orf72 gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Recently, several animal models have been established to investigate repeat associated gain of toxicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] as well as the physiological functions of C9orf72 in mammals. While neuron and glia specific C9orf72 ablation or intracerebral mRNA knockdown does not seem to cause motor neuron disease in mouse models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], two recent studies on whole body C9orf72 deficient mice demonstrate that C9orf72 deficiency results in severe immune dysregulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], suggesting that loss of C9orf72 function could lead to mis-regulated inflammatory responses.</p>
      <p>Despite many attempts at characterizing the exact molecular function of C9orf72, its cellular role is still not entirely clear. Bioinformatics studies have predicted C9orf72 to be a member of DENN domain containing proteins which typically function as guanine exchange factors for Rab GTPases, key regulators of membrane trafficking in eukaryotic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. One study has demonstrated physical interactions between C9orf72 and Rab7 and Rab11, GTPases involved in late endosome maturation or endosome recycling, respectively, and a role of C9orf72 in autophagy regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, direct regulation of these Rab GTPases by C9orf72 was not demonstrated in this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p>
      <p>In order to gain insight into C9orf72 function, we performed a proteomic screen for C9orf72 binding partners. We showed that C9orf72 forms a tight complex with SMCR8, another DENN domain containing protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], and WDR41, a WD40 repeat protein. We further demonstrated the physical interaction between C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 and the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex, which is an essential regulator of autophagy initiation. Our results are consistent with two recent reports on the C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 interaction published while this manuscript was under preparation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Furthermore, our data from C9orf72 deficient mice support a role of C9orf72 in immune regulation and the autophagy-lysosome pathway.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Material and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>DNA and Plasmids</title>
        <p>Human C9orf72 (C9-L), WDR41 and SMCR8 cDNAs were from the human ORFome 8.1 library and cloned into pQCXIN, pEGFP-N1 or pEGFP-N2, respectively, with an N-terminal (C9orf72) or C-terminal (WDR41 and SMCR8) GFP tag. The short C9orf72 isoform was cloned from C9-L into pEGFP-C1 with the following 3' primer: tgacCTCGAGttacttgagaagaaagccttcatg. WDR41 and SMCR8 were also cloned into pcDNA3.1 myc his A (Invitrogen) to generate C-terminal myc his tagged constructs. Additionally, C9orf72 and WDR41 were cloned into p3xFLAG-CMV7.1 (Sigma) to generate N-terminal FLAG tagged constructs. Myc-ATG13, FLAG-ATG101 and p3xFLAG-CMV10-hFIP200 were obtained from Addgene (plasmid #31965, 22877 and 24300, respectively).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Pharmacological Reagents and Antibodies</title>
        <p>The following primary antibodies were used in this study: anti-FLAG (M2) and anti-myc (9E10) from Sigma-Aldrich, anti-GAPDH from Abcam (ab8245), anti-LC3B (GTX127375) and anti-C9orf72 (GTX119776) from GeneTex, anti-Cathepsin D (sc-6486), anti-Ulk1 (sc-33182) and anti-C9orf72 (sc-138763) from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, anti-C9orf72 (AP12928b) and anti-FIP200 (17250-1-AP) from Proteintech, anti-SMCR8 from Bethyl Laboratories, anti-WDR41 from Abgent, rat anti-CD68 from AbD Serotec, sheep anti-progranulin from R&amp;D systems and anti-mouse LAMP1 (553792) from BD Biosciences. Anti-mouse prosaposin antibody was generated by Pocono Rabbit Farm and Laboratory and was previously characterized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Anti-C9orf72-long isoform [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] was a gift from Dr. Janice Robertson (University of Toronto); anti-GFP antibody was a gift from Dr. Anthony Bretscher (Cornell University); and anti-GPP130 was a gift from Dr. William Brown (Cornell University). The following secondary antibodies were used: donkey anti-mouse 800 and donkey anti-rabbit 800 from LI-COR, AlexaFluor donkey anti-goat 680, donkey anti-rabbit 680, donkey anti-mouse 680, and donkey anti-rat 680 from Invitrogen, and donkey anti-mouse 568 from Biotium. Hoechst stain was obtained from Invitrogen. Brefeldin A (BFA) and nocodazole were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich and used at a final concentration of 300 μM and 20 mM, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Mouse strains</title>
        <p>C9orf72 knockout mice were produced using CRISPR/Cas9 genome editing with a guide RNA (gRNA) targeting exon 2 of mouse gene 3110043O21RIK. C57BL/6 J x FvB/N mouse embryos were injected with gRNA and Cas9 mRNA at the Cornell Transgenic Core Facility. Editing was confirmed by sequencing PCR products from genomic DNA and loss of protein products was determined by Western blot of tissue lysate. Offspring from the founder containing 1 bp deletion were used for the study except the 10 month old founder mice. The following primers were used to genotype C9orf72 knockout mice: 5′- gcggctacctttgcttac -3′ (WT forward), 5′- tggcggctacctttgcta -3 (KO forward) and 5′- tgcccaggagacacaacata -3′ (common reverse).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Cell culture and DNA transfection</title>
        <p>HEK293T cells were maintained in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s Medium (Cellgro) supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine serum (Gibco) and 1 % Penicillin–Streptomycin (Invitrogen) in a humidified incubator at 37 °C and 5 % CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were transiently transfected with polyethyleneimine as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Immunoprecipitation and protein analysis</title>
        <p>Cells were lysed in 50 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 % Triton X-100, and 0.1 % deoxycholic acid with protease inhibitors (Roche). Lysates were incubated with GFP-Trap beads (ChromoTek) or anti-FLAG antibody conjugated beads (Sigma-Aldrich) for 2–3 h at 4 °C. Beads were washed 3 times with 50 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, and 1 % Triton X-100. Samples were denatured in 2xSDS sample buffer (4 % SDS, 20 % glycerol, 100 mM Tris pH 6.8, 0.2 g/L bromophenol blue) by boiling for 3 min. Samples were run on 8 % or 12 % polyacrylamide gels and transferred to PVDF membranes (Millipore). Membranes were blocked in either Odyssey Blocking Buffer (LI-COR Biosciences) or 5 % non-fat milk in PBS for 1 h followed by incubation with primary antibodies overnight at 4 °C. Membranes were washed 3 times with Tris-buffered saline with 0.1 % Tween-20 (TBST) then incubated with secondary antibody for 2 h at room temperature. Membranes were washed 3 times with TBST and imaged using an Odyssey Infrared Imaging System (LI-COR Biosciences).</p>
        <p>To quantify protein levels in tissue samples, tissues were homogenized in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 % Triton X-100, 0.1 % SDS and 0.1 % deoxycholic acid) with protease inhibitors on ice and then equal volume of 2X SDS sample buffer was added before sonication. 50 μg of each protein sample was loaded onto a 12 % poly-acrylamide gel. Blots were analyzed by LiCor Odyssey system and normalized to GAPDH.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>SILAC and mass spectrometry analysis</title>
        <p>N2a cells were grown a minimum of five generations in DMEM with 10 % dialyzed FBS (Sigma) supplemented with either light (C12, N14 arginine and lysine) or heavy (C13, N15 arginine and lysine) amino acids. The heavy cells were transfected in two 15 cm dishes with GFP-C9orf72 expression constructs while the light cells were transfected with pEGFP-C1 as a control. Two days after transfection, cells were lysed in 50 mM Tris pH8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 1 % Triton, 0.1 % deoxycholic acid with protease inhibitors (Roche). The lysates were subject to anti-GFP immunoprecipitation using GFP-Trap beads (ChromoTek). The presence of GFP and GFP-C9orf72 in immunoprecipitated samples was confirmed by SDS-PAGE and Krypton staining (Invitrogen). Samples were then combined and boiled 5 min with 1 % DTT followed by alkylation by treating samples with a final concentration of 28 mM iodoacetamide. Proteins were precipitated on ice for 30 min with a mixture of 50 % acetone/49.9 % ethanol/0.1 % acetic acid. Proteins were pelleted and washed with this buffer, re-precipitated on ice, and dissolved in 8 M urea/50 mM Tris pH 8.0 followed by dilution with three volumes of 50 mM Tris pH 8.0/150 mM NaCl. Proteins were digested overnight at 37 ° C with 1 μg mass-spec grade Trypsin (Promega). The resulting peptide samples were cleaned up for mass spectrometry by treatment with 10 % formic acid and 10 % trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) and washed twice with 0.1 % acetic acid on pre-equilibrated Sep-Pak C18 cartridges (Waters). Samples were eluted with 80 % acetonitrile (ACN)/0.1 % acetic acid into silanized vials (National Scientific) and evaporated using a SpeedVac. Samples were re-dissolved in H2O with ~1 % formic acid and 70 % ACN. Peptides were separated using hydrophilic interaction liquid chromatography (HILIC) on an Ultimate 300 LC (Dionex). Each fraction was evaporated with a SpeedVac and resuspended in 0.1 % TFA with 0.1 pM angiotensin internal standard. Samples were run on a Thermo LTQ Orbitrap XL mass spectrometer and data analyzed using the SORCERER system (Sage-N research).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining</title>
        <p>Mouse tissues were fixed with 4 % formaldehyde. After dehydration with 70 % ethanol, tissues were embedded with paraffin. The tissues were sliced to 8 μm. Followed by deparaffiinization with xylene and ethanol (100 %, 95 %, 80 %) and rehydration with tap water, the slides were stained in hematoxalin for 3 min, destained with acid ethanol and rinsed with tap water, and then stained with eosin for 30 s. The slides were then dehydrated with ethanol and xylene and mounted.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Immunofluorescence microscopy</title>
        <p>HeLa cells grown on glass coverslips were fixed in 3.7 % paraformaldehyde for 15 min, washed 3 times with PBS, and permeabilized and blocked in Odyssey Blocking Buffer with 0.05 % saponin or 0.1 % Triton for 20 min. Primary antibodies diluted in blocking buffer with 0.05 % saponin were applied to the cells overnight at 4 °C. Coverslips were washed 3 times with PBS. Secondary antibodies and Hoechst stain diluted in blocking buffer with 0.05 % saponin were applied to the cells for 2 h at room temperature. Coverslips were washed and mounted onto slides with Fluoromount G (Southern Biotech). Images were acquired on a CSU-X spinning disc confocal microscope (Intelligent Imaging Innovations) with an HQ2 CCD camera (Photometrics) using a 100x objective.</p>
        <p>Mouse tissues were perfused and fixed with 4 % formaldehyde. After gradient dehydration with 15 % and 30 % sucrose, tissues were embedded with OCT compound (Sakura Finetek USA) and sectioned with Cryotome. For the immunostaining, tissue sections were permeabilized and blocked in Odyssey blocking buffer with 0.05 % saponin for 1 h. Primary antibodies were incubated in blocking buffer overnight at 4 °C. Sections were washed and incubated in secondary antibodies conjugated to Alexaflour 488, 568, or 660 (Invitrogen). Sections were washed three more times and coverslips mounted onto slides with Fluoromount G (Southern Biotech). Images were acquired on a CSU-X spinning disc confocal microscope (Intelligent Imaging Innovations) with an HQ2 CCD camera (Photometrics) using a 40x objective.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The data were presented as mean ± SEM. Two-group analysis was performed using the Student’s <italic>t</italic> test. <italic>P</italic>-values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec12" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>C9orf72 forms a complex with SMCR8 and WDR41</title>
        <p>In humans, two C9orf72 protein isoforms are generated from three alternatively spliced transcripts, a long form (C9-L) and a short form (C9-S), with multiple studies showing that the protein and mRNA level of the C9-L form are decreased in C9/ALS patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. To decipher the protein interaction network of C9orf72, a SILAC (stable isotope labeling of amino acids in cell culture) based proteomic screen was performed in the neuroblastoma cells line neuro-2a (N2a) using GFP-C9orf72 (C9-L) as the bait and GFP as a control (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). Several proteins were found to be enriched in the C9orf72 immunoprecipitations (IPs) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S1). The top two hits from the screen were SMCR8 and WDR41, two proteins of unknown functions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Interestingly, like C9orf72, SMCR8 was also predicted to contain a DENN domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The interaction between C9orf72, SMCR8, and WDR41 was verified using co-IPs in transfected HEK293T cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a-c</xref>). SMCR8 strongly interacts with GFP-C9orf72 but not GFP in the co-IP experiment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Moreover, co-expression of C9orf72 consistently increases the level of SMCR8, suggesting that C9orf72 might stabilize overexpressed SMCR8. However, the short isoform of human C9orf72 (C9-S) does not bind SMCR8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Thus we focus on the C9-L form for the rest of the study (hereafter referred to as C9orf72). While we failed to detect any interaction between WDR41 and C9orf72 or SMCR8 when WDR41 is expressed with either C9orf72 or SMCR8 alone, WDR41 strongly co-immunoprecipitates with C9orf72 and SMCR8 when C9orf72 and SMCR8 are co-expressed, suggesting that WDR41 interacts only with the C9orf72/SMCR8 heterodimer (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, 2c).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>SILAC proteomic screen for C9orf72 binding partners. <bold>a</bold> Schematic workflow of SILAC proteomic screen used to identify C9orf72 protein interactions. <bold>b</bold> Volcano plot of SILAC hits. Hits with more than 10 peptides are plotted. Top hits identified in the heavy fraction are highlighted</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Co-immunoprecipitation between C9orf72, SMCR8 and WDR41. <bold>a</bold> GFP-tagged human C9orf72 isoform I (GFP-C9-L) or isoform II (GFP-C9-S) were overexpressed with SMCR8-myc in HEK293T cells and immunoprecipitated by anti-GFP beads. <bold>b</bold> SMCR8-GFP and WDR41-myc were coexpressed with or without FLAG-C9-L and the lysates were immunoprecipitated using anti-GFP antibodies. <bold>c</bold> GFP-C9-L and FLAG-WDR41 were co-expressed with or without SMCR8-myc as indicated and the lysates were immunoprecipitated using anti-GFP antibodies</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Cellular localization of C9orf72, SMCR8 and WDR41</title>
        <p>To gain insight into the cellular function of the C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 complex, we expressed these proteins in HeLa cells and examined their distribution within the cell. Both C9orf72 and SMCR8 show diffuse cytoplasmic localization, when expressed alone or together (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a and b</xref>). Nuclear localization was observed for C9orf72, especially the GFP-tagged C9orf72 but not SMCR8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a and b</xref>). WDR41 also shows diffuse cytoplasmic distribution (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">c</xref>). However, careful examination reveals enrichment of WDR41 at the cis-Golgi, which is confirmed when labelled by the cis-Golgi protein GPP130 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). This is further supported by treatment of cells with BrefeldinA, which causes the Golgi to collapse. Even after such treatment, WDR41 remains colocalized with GPP130, indicating that WDR41 is tightly associated with the Golgi membrane. Similar results were obtained after treatment with nocodazole, a microtubule destabilizing drug that causes the Golgi to disperse (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Cellular localization of C9orf72, SMCR8 and WDR41. <bold>a</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with FLAG-C9orf72 (C9-L), SMCR8-myc or WDR41-GFP. Cells were stained with anti-FLAG or anti-myc to visualize FLAG-C9orf72 or SMCR8-myc, respectively. Maximum projection images from confocal sections are shown. Scale bar = 10 μm. <bold>b</bold> HeLa cells were transfected with GFP-C9orf72 (C9-L) and SMCR8-myc. Cells were stained with anti-myc antibodies to visualize SMCR8-myc. <bold>c</bold> WDR41-GFP expressing HeLa cells were treated with DMSO control, 0.3 mM BrefeldinA (BFA), or 20 mM Nocodazole for 2 h. Cells were stained with anti-GPP130 antibodies to label cis-Golgi. Single confocal images are shown for b and c. Scale bar = 10 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Interaction of C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 with the FIP200 autophagy initiation complex</title>
        <p>A previously reported proteomics screen identified SMCR8 as a binding partner for FIP200 (also called RB1CC1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], a protein involved in autophagy initiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. However, the interaction between SMCR8 and FIP200 is barely detectable by co-IP when only these two proteins are overexpressed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Interestingly, we found that co-transfection of C9orf72 and SMCR8 allows much stronger binding of SMCR8 to FIP200, which is further enhanced by WDR41 overexpression, suggesting that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 forms a ternary complex to interact with FIP200 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). The weaker binding between SMCR8 and FIP200 when SMCR8 is expressed alone in HEK293T cells is most likely explained by very low endogenous levels of C9orf72 and WDR41 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). Ulk1, a kinase that interacts with FIP200 in the autophagy initiation complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], binds the C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 in a similar manner as FIP200 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Furthermore, C9orf72, SMCR8 and WDR41 are all detected in the FIP200 immunoprecipitates (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). ATG13 and ATG101, two other proteins associated with FIP200/Ulk1 also interact with C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c and d</xref>). These data support that the formation of the C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 complex allows their interaction with the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 complex interacts with FIP200/Ulk1. <bold>a</bold> Co-immunoprecipitation between C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 and FIP200 and Ulk1. HEK293T cells were transfected with FLAG-FIP200 and C9orf72, SMCR8 and/or WDR41 as indicated. Cells were lysed 40 h after transfection and lysates were immunoprecipated with anti-GFP antibodies. Lysates and immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blots as indicated. * indicated non-specific bands recognized by anti SMCR8 antibodies in the IP products. Representative images from 3 independent experiments are shown. <bold>b</bold> Co-immunoprecipitation between C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 and FIP200. HEK293T cells were transfected as indicated and lysed and immunoprecipitated using anti-FLAG antibodies. Lysates and immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blots. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Co-immunoprecipitation between C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 and ATG101 (c) or ATG13 (d). HEK293T cells were transfected as indicated and lysed and immunoprecipitated using anti-GFP antibodies. Lysates and immunoprecipitates were analyzed by Western blots. <bold>e</bold> Schematic drawing of the interaction between C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 and the FIP200/Ulk1 complex. WDR41 interacts with the C9orf72/SMCR8 dimer to form ternary complex, which then interacts with the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Generation and characterization of C9orf72 deficient mice</title>
        <p>Three protein isoforms of mouse C9orf72 homolog (I, 55 kDa; II, 35 kDa and III; 50 kDa) have been identified with isoform I (55 kDa), the functional homolog of C9-L in humans, being the dominant form in most tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In order to investigate the function of C9orf72 in vivo, we generated C9orf72 deficient mice using the CRISPR/Cas9 system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Guide RNA targeted close to the start codon of the mouse C9orf72 isoform I and III was co-injected with the Cas9 mRNA into the pronuclei of fertilized eggs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). All the offspring displayed Cas9 mediated cleavage and editing from non-homologous end joining mediated repair. We chose one founder containing a one-nucleotide deletion at the beginning of the C9orf72 open reading frame, resulting in a frame shift at residue 33 that produces a stop codon at amino acid 40 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Based on the splicing patterns, the one nucleotide deletion should cause the loss of protein products for C9orf72 isoforms I (55 kDa) and III (50 kDa), but should not affect isoform II (35 kDa). Indeed, Western blot using several antibodies shows loss of C9orf72 isoform I protein in homozygous offspring from the above-mentioned founder (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>, and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S2). We failed to detect isoform II and III in our Western blots with all the C9orf72 antibodies tested and thus we cannot determine whether these isoforms are affected by the CRISPR/Cas9 editing. While C9orf72 isoform I is detectable in all tissues examined, its level is highest in spleen, followed by kidney, brain, and heart, and much lower in the liver and muscle (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). This expression pattern is consistent with a recent publication demonstrating the highest levels of C9orf72 in CD11b<sup>+</sup> myeloid cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Generation of C9orf72 deficient mice. <bold>a</bold> Schematic drawing of the mouse homologue of C9orf72, 3110043O21RIK, and the site targeted for editing by CRISPR/Cas9. <bold>b</bold> Sequencing traces of wildtype (top) and edited (bottom) C9orf72 from genomic PCR show a one nucleotide deletion (highlighted with yellow) near the Cas9 cleavage site. <bold>c</bold> Western blot analysis of C9orf72 protein levels in wild type (WT) and C9orf72-/- (KO) mouse tissues with anti-C9-L antibodies. <bold>d</bold> Representative images of cervical lymph nodes and spleen from 4-5 months old WT and C9orf72-/- mice. Scale bar = 2 mm (lymph node); 1 cm (spleen)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
        <p>Our C9orf72 deficient mice do not have any apparent growth defects (data not shown) but display an obvious lymph node and spleen enlargement phenotype (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>), consistent with recent reports on another two independent lines of C9orf72 knockout mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. While occasional mild splenomegaly was observed in the 2 month old C9orf72 deficient mice, this phenotype becomes more severe with age, with the 4-5 month old C9orf72 deficient mouse having a spleen 2-3 times the size of its littermate control (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S3). This is also seen in two of the 10 month old founder mice from the CRISPR mediated editing (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S3). The liver also shows slight enlargement but there are no obvious gross anatomical defects in the brain of C9orf72 deficient mice (data not shown).</p>
        <p>Hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining of the C9orf72 deficient spleen reveals enlarged germinal centers (GCs) and abundant extramedullary hematopoietic cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). High magnification shows the enlarged GCs are packed with immature immune cells, among which plasma cells are often observed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Several types of hematopoietic cells are enriched in the red pulp (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). Immunostaining with anti-CD68 antibodies shows macrophage accumulation or infiltration in the red pulp of the spleen (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>), which is also seen in the peripheral regions of cervical lymph nodes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>) and to a lesser extent, liver of C9orf72 deficient mice at 4 months of age (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8b</xref>). In C9orf72-/- liver tissues, infiltrated immune cells were observed in both hepatic portal area and hepatic parenchyma (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Surrounding by the infiltrated immune cells, necrotic hepatocytes are occasionally seen in C9orf72-/- liver tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a</xref>). Despite macrophage infiltration in multiple peripheral organs, microglia, the counterpart of macrophages in the central nervous system, do not show any obvious changes in number and morphology in the C9orf72 deficient mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>C9 deficiency in mice results in an enlarged spleen phenotype and macrophage infiltration into the spleen. <bold>a</bold> H&amp;E staining of spleen tissues from 5 month old of WT or C9orf72 -/- mouse with zoomed images of germinal center (GC) and red pulp (RP). (GC): Arrows indicate plasma cells and the arrowheads indicate immature immune cells). (RP): arrowheads indicate myeloid precursors; arrows indicate erythroid precursors. Scale bar = 500 μm (100 μm in the zoomed in images for GC and RP). <bold>b</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old spleen sections (red pulp region) of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse CD68, prosaposin (PSAP), and progranulin (PGRN) antibodies. Nuclei are labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative CD68+ macrophage cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm. <bold>c</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old spleen sections (red pulp region) of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse Lamp1, and cathepsin D (CathD) antibodies. Nuclei are labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Increased macrophage infiltration and lysosomal proteins in the cervical lymph node of C9 deficient mice. <bold>a</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old cervical lymph nodes sections (peripheral region) of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse CD68, prosaposin (PSAP), and progranulin (PGRN) antibodies. Nuclei is labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative CD68+ macrophage cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm. <bold>b</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old cervical lymph nodes sections (peripheral region) of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse Lamp1, and cathepsin D (CathD) antibodies. Nuclei are labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig><fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>C9 deficiency in mice results in macrophage infiltration and increased levels of lysosomal proteins in the liver. <bold>a</bold> H&amp;E staining of liver tissues from 10 month old of WT or C9orf72 -/- mouse. (ii) and (iii) are high power magnification images of the hepatic parenchyma, arrowhead indicates infiltrated immune cells; arrow points to necrotic hepatocyte. (v) and (vi) are high power magnification images of the hepatic portal area, arrowhead indicates infiltrated immune cells. PV, portal vein. Scale bar: 500 μm in (i) and (iv), 100 μm in (ii, iii, v, vi) <bold>b</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old liver sections of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse CD68, prosaposin (PSAP), and progranulin (PGRN) antibodies. Nuclei are labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative CD68+ macrophage cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm. <bold>c</bold> Immunostaining of 4 month old liver sections of WT and C9orf72-/- mice with anti-mouse Lamp1, and cathepsin D (CathD) antibodies. Nuclei are labelled with DAPI. Insert shows representative cells. Representative pictures from three pairs of mice are shown. Scale bar = 40 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig><fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Microglia do not show any obvious abnormalities in C9orf72 deficient mice. Brain sections from 10 month old WT and C9orf72-/- mice were stained with anti-LAMP1, Iba1 and cathepsin D antibodies. Similar results were seen with 5 month old C9orf72-/- mouse. Scale bar = 50 μm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Autophagy and lysosome defects in the C9orf72 deficient mice</title>
        <p>Because C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 co-immunoprecipitates with the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex, we investigated possible autophagy/lysosome defects in the C9orf72 deficient mice. Interestingly, Ulk1 deficiency has also been reported to result in splenomegaly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Western blot analysis showed significantly increased levels of several proteins involved in the autophagy/lysosomal pathway in spleen and liver lysates of the 2 month old C9orf72 deficient mice compared to littermate controls, including LC3-I, LAMP1, and prosaposin (PSAP), even before the appearance of an obvious splenomegaly phenotype, suggesting that autophagy/lysosome defects might precede anatomical spleen abnormalities (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a, b</xref>). Although no obvious changes in lysosomal morphology were seen in the C9orf72-/- macrophages, increased levels of the lysosomal proteins progranulin (PGRN), PSAP, LAMP1 and cathepsin D (CathD) are seen in CD68 positive macrophages in the lymph nodes, spleen and liver of C9orf72 deficient mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). This might suggest that loss of C9orf72 causes a defect in the lysosome that requires upregulation of lysosomal proteins to compensate. Conversion of LC3-I to LC3-II is an indicator of autophagy initiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Although LC3-I levels are dramatically increased in C9orf72 deficient spleen lysates, LC3-II levels are significantly reduced (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a, b</xref>), suggesting that loss of C9orf72 causes a defect in autophagy initiation. Despite these changes in multiple peripheral tissues, brain lysates do not show any apparent increases in autophagy or lysosomal proteins in the 2 month old C9orf72 deficient mice compared to controls (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10a, b</xref>).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>C9 deficiency in mice leads to increased levels of autophagy-lysosome proteins in the spleen. <bold>a</bold> Western blot analysis of tissue lysates from spleen, liver, and brain of WT and knockout mice. Representative pairs are shown. <bold>b</bold> Quantification of autophagy and lysosomal protein levels in knockout mice relative to WT controls. Data are presented as Mean ± SEM, n = 3–6. *, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; **, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40478_2016_324_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The cellular function of C9orf72 has been under intensive investigation since hexanucleotide repeat expansion in the C9orf72 gene was shown to be the main cause of ALS/FTLD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], with reduced C9orf72 expression proposed as one of the disease mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In this study, we searched for protein interactors for C9orf72 and identified SMCR8 and WDR41 as two binding partners of C9orf72, consistent with two recently published reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. We further demonstrated that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 interacts with the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex involved in autophagy initiation. Our data also showed that C9orf72 deficient mice display defects in autophagy/lysosome pathway, supporting a critical role of C9orf72 in autophagy/lysosome regulation.</p>
      <p>Many other genes involved in membrane trafficking and autophagy have been associated with ALS/FTLD, including TBK1, OPTN, SQSTM1/p62, UBQLN2, VCP/p97 and CHMP2B [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Progranulin, the gene mutated in a vast majority of FTLD with ubiquitin positive TDP-43 aggregates, was recently shown to play a critical role in regulating lysosomal function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and the progranulin protein was shown to reside in the lysosome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. TMEM106B, a risk factor for FTLD with progranulin mutations, also regulates lysosomal morphology and function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Our current results further support that dysfunction in the autophagy lysosome pathway is implicated in the disease progression of ALS/FTLD caused by C9orf72 mutations. C9orf72 deficiency in C. elegans and zebrafish has been shown to result in locomotion defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], supporting the notion that C9orf72 haploinsufficiency could contribute to ALS/FTLD progression. While neuron and glia specific C9orf72 ablation or intracerebral mRNA knockdown does not seem to cause motor neuron disease in mouse models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], our data and recent data by others consistently demonstrate that whole body C9orf72 deficiency produces severe immune dysregulation in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In one study, lysosomal abnormalities were also observed in microglia isolated from C9orf72 deficient mice and in the motor cortex and spinal cord of ALS patients with C9orf72 mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. These findings strongly suggest that C9orf72 may regulate motor neuron survival through regulation of inflammatory responses by affecting autophagy-lysosomal function of microglia and macrophages. In contrast, our studies failed to detect any obvious abnormalities of microglia in our C9orf72 deficient mice (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). It is possible that this may simply be due to our mice not being old enough (10 months old) for us to detect a microglial phenotype. It is also likely that microglial abnormalities may become apparent in the C9orf72 deficient mice upon additional insults to the nervous system.</p>
      <p>The physical interaction between the C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 complex and the autophagy initiation complex FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) suggests that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 might regulate autophagy through the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex. However, exactly how C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 regulates autophagy remains unclear. It is interesting that WDR41 is enriched at the Golgi, as the ER-Golgi intermediate compartment has been shown to serve as a key membrane source for autophagosome biogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. One possibility is that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 serves as a substrate and a downstream signaling component after Ulk1 activation. Interestingly, SMCR8 was shown to be a substrate for Ulk1 in a recent study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. This observation together with reduced autophagy initiation in C9or72-/- spleen tissues argues that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 functions downstream of Ulk1 activation during autophagy activation. Autophagy defects in C9orf72-/- mice might trigger upregulation of autophay/lysosome genes to compensate for the defect. Although we failed to identify any Rab GTPases as C9orf72 interactors in our proteomic screen, C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 was shown to interact with Rab8a and Rab39b and functions as a guanine nucleotide exchange factor (GEF) for Rab GTPases in a recent study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. However, the effect of Ulk1 phosphorylation on the GEF activities remains to be determined. Future endeavors are needed to further understand the mechanistic functions and regulations of C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 complex at molecular and cellular levels. More studies are also needed to characterize neuronal and microglial phenotypes due to C9orf72 loss, possibly upon additional challenges, to explain how C9orf72 deficiency contributes to ALS/FTLD progression.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We describe the identification of two binding partners for C9orf72: SMCR8 and WDR41. We demonstrated that C9orf72/SMCR8/WDR41 interacts with the FIP200/Ulk1/ATG13/ATG101 complex. We also generated C9orf72 deficient mice and showed that loss of C9orf72 leads to macrophage infiltration in multiple organs. Additionally, C9orf72 deficiency leads to autophagy defects and increased levels of many lysosomal proteins, supporting a critical role of C9orf72 in regulating autophagy/lysosomal pathway and inflammation in vivo.</p>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>Ethical approval</title>
        <p>All applicable international, national, and/or institutional guidelines for the care and use of animals were followed.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <app-group>
      <app id="App1">
        <sec id="Sec21">
          <title>Additional files</title>
          <p>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="40478_2016_324_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1">
              <label>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Levels of endogenous versus overexpressed C9orf72 in N2a and HEK293T cells. N2a (a) and HEK293T (b) cells were transfected with GFP control or GFP-C9orf72. Cells were lysed 2 days after transfection and lysates were subjected to Western blot using anti-C9orf72 antibodies (Proteintech). (PDF 146 kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="40478_2016_324_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM2">
              <label>Additional file 2: Table S1.</label>
              <caption>
                <p>List of hits from the SILAC proteomic screen. Proteins with more than 10 peptides and Log2 fold changes (GFP/GFP-C9orf72) &lt; -1.00 are listed. Count = total number of peptides identified; count-h: peptides in the heavy fraction; count-l: peptides in the light fraction. (PDF 155 kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="40478_2016_324_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM3">
              <label>Additional file 3: Figure S2.</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Absence of C9orf72 isoform I in the C9orf72 CRISPR targeted mice. a. Western blot of brain lysates from WT or C9orf72 deficient (KO) mice using various C9orf72 antibodies as indicated. b. Western blot analysis of C9orf72 protein levels in wild type (WT) and C9orf72 knockout (KO) mouse tissues with anti-C9-L antibodies. (PDF 147 kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
            <media position="anchor" xlink:href="40478_2016_324_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4">
              <label>Additional file 4: Figure S3.</label>
              <caption>
                <p>C9orf72 deficiency in mice leads to age dependent spleen enlargement. Representative images of spleen dissected from 2 month, 5 month and 10 month old WT and C9or72-/- mice are shown. Scale bar = 1 cm. (PDF 217 kb)</p>
              </caption>
            </media>
          </p>
        </sec>
      </app>
    </app-group>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Competing interests</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Authors’ contributions</bold>
        </p>
        <p>FH conceived the project. FH, PS and XZ designed the experiments. FH, PS, XZ, AR, DP performed experiments and analyzed the data. DS and MS performed mass spec analysis. FH, PS and XZ wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Dr. Haiyuan Yu (Cornell University) for cDNAs; Dr. Janice Robertson (University of Toronto), Dr. Anthony Bretscher and Dr. William Brown (Cornell University) for antibodies; and Ms. Xiaochun Wu for technical assistance. This work is supported by funding to F.H. from the Weill Institute for Cell and Molecular Biology, the Muscular Dystrophy Association and NINDS (R01NS088448-01) and by funding to X. Z. from the Weill Institute Fleming Postdoctoral Fellowship.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Achi</surname>
              <given-names>EY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudnicki</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ALS and Frontotemporal Dysfunction: A Review</article-title>
          <source>Neurol Res Int</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>2012</volume>
          <fpage>806306</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/806306</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22919484?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22919484</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Atanasio</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Decman</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikiz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siao</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brydges</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>LaRosa</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fury</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burfeind</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zamfirova</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warshaw</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orengo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oyejide</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fralish</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Auerbach</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poueymirou</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Freudenberg</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gong</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zambrowicz</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valenzuela</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yancopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thurston</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lai</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9orf72 ablation causes immune dysregulation characterized by leukocyte expansion, autoantibody production, and glomerulonephropathy in mice</article-title>
          <source>Sci Rep</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>23204</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep23204</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26979938?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979938</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Atkinson</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez-Martos</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atkin</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vickers</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9ORF72 expression and cellular localization over mouse development</article-title>
          <source>Acta Neuropathol Commun</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40478-015-0238-7</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26408000?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408000</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Behrends</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sowa</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gygi</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Network organization of the human autophagy system</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>466</volume>
          <fpage>68</fpage>
          <lpage>76</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09204</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20562859?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562859</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belzil</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bauer</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prudencio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gendron</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stetler</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>IK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pregent</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daughrity</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rademakers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boylan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patel</surname>
              <given-names>TC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrucelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reduced C9orf72 gene expression in c9FTD/ALS is caused by histone trimethylation, an epigenetic event detectable in blood</article-title>
          <source>Acta Neuropathol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>895</fpage>
          <lpage>905</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-013-1199-1</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24166615?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24166615</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brady</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The frontotemporal lobar degeneration risk factor, TMEM106B, regulates lysosomal morphology and function</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>685</fpage>
          <lpage>695</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/dds475</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23136129?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23136129</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Burrell JR, Halliday GM, Kril JJ, Ittner LM, Gotz J, Kiernan MC, Hodges JR. The frontotemporal dementia-motor neuron disease continuum. Lancet. 2016.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Canafoglia</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morbin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scaioli</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pareyson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D'Incerti</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fugnanesi</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tagliavini</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berkovic</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franceschetti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Recurrent generalized seizures, visual loss, and palinopsia as phenotypic features of neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis due to progranulin gene mutation</article-title>
          <source>Epilepsia</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>e56</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/epi.12632</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24779634?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24779634</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen-Plotkin</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Unger</surname>
              <given-names>TL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallagher</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bill</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwong</surname>
              <given-names>LK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Volpicelli-Daley</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busch</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akle</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grossman</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Deerlin</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trojanowski</surname>
              <given-names>JQ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>TMEM106B, the Risk Gene for Frontotemporal Dementia, Is Regulated by the microRNA-132/212 Cluster and Affects Progranulin Pathways</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>11213</fpage>
          <lpage>11227</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0521-12.2012</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22895706?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895706</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chew</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gendron</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Prudencio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sasaguri</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castanedes-Casey</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansen-West</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bieniek</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bauer</surname>
              <given-names>PO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitelaw</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rousseau</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stankowski</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stetler</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daughrity</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perkerson</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desaro</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnston</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Overstreet</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edbauer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rademakers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boylan</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fryer</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrucelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neurodegeneration. C9ORF72 repeat expansions in mice cause TDP-43 pathology, neuronal loss, and behavioral deficits</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>348</volume>
          <fpage>1151</fpage>
          <lpage>1154</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa9344</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25977373?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977373</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ciura</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lattante</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Le Ber</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Latouche</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tostivint</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brice</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabashi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Loss of function of C9orf72 causes motor deficits in a zebrafish model of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>Ann Neurol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>180</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 23720273?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23720273</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cong</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ran</surname>
              <given-names>FA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barretto</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Habib</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marraffini</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>339</volume>
          <fpage>819</fpage>
          <lpage>823</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1231143</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23287718?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287718</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DeJesus-Hernandez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackenzie</surname>
              <given-names>IR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boeve</surname>
              <given-names>BF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boxer</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baker</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rutherford</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finch</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flynn</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adamson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kouri</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wojtas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sengdy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsiung</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karydas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seeley</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Josephs</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coppola</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geschwind</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wszolek</surname>
              <given-names>ZK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knopman</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petersen</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boylan</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graff-Radford</surname>
              <given-names>NR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rademakers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expanded GGGGCC hexanucleotide repeat in noncoding region of C9ORF72 causes chromosome 9p-linked FTD and ALS</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.09.011</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21944778?>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farg</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sundaramoorthy</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sultana</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atkinson</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levina</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halloran</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gleeson</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blair</surname>
              <given-names>IP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soo</surname>
              <given-names>KY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atkin</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9ORF72, implicated in amytrophic lateral sclerosis and frontotemporal dementia, regulates endosomal trafficking</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>3579</fpage>
          <lpage>3595</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddu068</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24549040?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24549040</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrari</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kapogiannis</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huey</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Momeni</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>FTD and ALS: a tale of two diseases</article-title>
          <source>Curr Alzheimer Res</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>273</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156720511795563700</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21222600?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21222600</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ge</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melville</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schekman</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The ER-Golgi intermediate compartment is a key membrane source for the LC3 lipidation step of autophagosome biogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Elife</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>e00947</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.00947</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23930225?>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padukkavidana</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vaegter</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brady</surname>
              <given-names>OA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zheng</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackenzie</surname>
              <given-names>IR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldman</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nykjaer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strittmatter</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sortilin-mediated endocytosis determines levels of the frontotemporal dementia protein, progranulin</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>654</fpage>
          <lpage>667</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2010.09.034</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21092856?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21092856</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jiang J, Zhu Q, Gendron TF, Saberi S, McAlonis-Downes M, Seelman A, Stauffer JE, Jafar-Nejad P, Drenner K, Schulte D, Chun S, Sun S, Ling SC, Myers B, Engelhardt J, Katz M, Baughn M, Platoshyn O, Marsala M, Watt A, Heyser CJ, Ard MC, De Muynck L, Daughrity LM, Swing DA, Tessarollo L, Jung CJ, Delpoux A, Utzschneider DT, Hedrick SM, de Jong PJ, Edbauer D, Van Damme P, Petrucelli L, Shaw CE, Bennett CF, Da Cruz S, Ravits J, Rigo F, Cleveland DW, Lagier-Tourenne C. Gain of Toxicity from ALS/FTD-Linked Repeat Expansions in C9ORF72 Is Alleviated by Antisense Oligonucleotides Targeting GGGGCC-Containing RNAs. Neuron. 2016.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ju</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuentealba</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Piwnica-Worms</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloh</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weihl</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Valosin-containing protein (VCP) is required for autophagy and is disrupted in VCP disease</article-title>
          <source>J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>187</volume>
          <fpage>875</fpage>
          <lpage>888</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200908115</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20008565?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008565</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jun</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Han</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jang</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaang</surname>
              <given-names>BK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>TMEM106B, a frontotemporal lobar dementia (FTLD) modifier, associates with FTD-3-linked CHMP2B, a complex of ESCRT-III</article-title>
          <source>Mol Brain</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13041-015-0177-z</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26651479?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26651479</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Klionsky DJ, Abdelmohsen K, Abe A, Abedin MJ, Abeliovich H, Acevedo Arozena A, Adachi H, Adams CM, Adams PD, Adeli K, Adhihetty PJ, Adler SG, Agam G, Agarwal R, Aghi MK, Agnello M, Agostinis P, Aguilar PV, Aguirre-Ghiso J, Airoldi EM, Ait-Si-Ali S, Akematsu T, Akporiaye ET, Al-Rubeai M, Albaiceta GM, Albanese C, Albani D, Albert ML, Aldudo J, Algul H, Alirezaei M, Alloza I, Almasan A, Almonte-Beceril M, Alnemri ES, Alonso C, Altan-Bonnet N, Altieri DC, Alvarez S, Alvarez-Erviti L, Alves S, Amadoro G, Amano A, Amantini C, Ambrosio S, Amelio I, Amer AO, Amessou M, Amon A, An Z, Anania FA, Andersen SU, Andley UP, Andreadi CK, Andrieu-Abadie N, Anel A, Ann DK, Anoopkumar-Dukie S, Antonioli M, Aoki H, Apostolova N, Aquila S, Aquilano K, Araki K, Arama E, Aranda A, Araya J, Arcaro A, Arias E, Arimoto H, Ariosa AR, Armstrong JL, Arnould T, Arsov I, Asanuma K, Askanas V, Asselin E, Atarashi R, Atherton SS, Atkin JD, Attardi LD, Auberger P, Auburger G, Aurelian L, Autelli R, Avagliano L, Avantaggiati ML, Avrahami L, Awale S, Azad N, Bachetti T, Backer JM, Bae DH, Bae JS, Bae ON, Bae SH, Baehrecke EH, Baek SH, Baghdiguian S, Bagniewska-Zadworna A, Bai H, Bai J, Bai XY, Bailly Y, Balaji KN, Balduini W, Ballabio A, Balzan R, Banerjee R, Banhegyi G, Bao H, Barbeau B, Barrachina MD, Barreiro E, Bartel B, Bartolome A, Bassham DC, Bassi MT, Bast RC, Jr., Basu A, Batista MT, Batoko H, Battino M, Bauckman K, Baumgarner BL, Bayer KU, Beale R, Beaulieu JF, Beck GR, Jr., Becker C, Beckham JD, Bedard PA, Bednarski PJ, Begley TJ, Behl C, Behrends C, Behrens GM, Behrns KE, Bejarano E, Belaid A, Belleudi F, Benard G, Berchem G, Bergamaschi D, Bergami M, Berkhout B, Berliocchi L, Bernard A, Bernard M, Bernassola F, Bertolotti A, Bess AS, Besteiro S, Bettuzzi S, Bhalla S, Bhattacharyya S, Bhutia SK, Biagosch C, Bianchi MW, Biard-Piechaczyk M, Billes V, Bincoletto C, Bingol B, Bird SW, Bitoun M, Bjedov I, Blackstone C, Blanc L, Blanco GA, Blomhoff HK, Boada-Romero E, Bockler S, Boes M, Boesze-Battaglia K, Boise LH, Bolino A, Boman A, Bonaldo P, Bordi M, Bosch J, Botana LM, Botti J, Bou G, Bouche M, Bouchecareilh M, Boucher MJ, Boulton ME, Bouret SG, Boya P, Boyer-Guittaut M, Bozhkov PV, Brady N, Braga VM, Brancolini C, Braus GH, Bravo-San Pedro JM, Brennan LA, Bresnick EH, Brest P, Bridges D, Bringer MA, Brini M, Brito GC, Brodin B, Brookes PS, Brown EJ, Brown K, Broxmeyer HE, Bruhat A, Brum PC, Brumell JH, Brunetti-Pierri N, Bryson-Richardson RJ, Buch S, Buchan AM, Budak H, Bulavin DV, Bultman SJ, Bultynck G, Bumbasirevic V, Burelle Y, Burke RE, Burmeister M, Butikofer P, Caberlotto L, Cadwell K, Cahova M, Cai D, Cai J, Cai Q, Calatayud S, Camougrand N, Campanella M, Campbell GR, Campbell M, Campello S, Candau R, Caniggia I, Cantoni L, Cao L, Caplan AB, Caraglia M, Cardinali C, Cardoso SM, Carew JS, Carleton LA, Carlin CR, Carloni S, Carlsson SR, Carmona-Gutierrez D, Carneiro LA, Carnevali O, Carra S, Carrier A, Carroll B, Casas C, Casas J, Cassinelli G, Castets P, Castro-Obregon S, Cavallini G, Ceccherini I, Cecconi F, Cederbaum AI, Cena V, Cenci S, Cerella C, Cervia D, Cetrullo S, Chaachouay H, Chae HJ, Chagin AS, Chai CY, Chakrabarti G, Chamilos G, Chan EY, Chan MT, Chandra D, Chandra P, Chang CP, Chang RC, Chang TY, Chatham JC, Chatterjee S, Chauhan S, Che Y, Cheetham ME, Cheluvappa R, Chen CJ, Chen G, Chen GC, Chen H, Chen JW, Chen JK, Chen M, Chen P, Chen Q, Chen SD, Chen S, Chen SS, Chen W, Chen WJ, Chen WQ, Chen X, Chen YH, Chen YG, Chen Y, Chen YJ, Chen YQ, Chen Z, Cheng A, Cheng CH, Cheng H, Cheong H, Cherry S, Chesney J, Cheung CH, Chevet E, Chi HC, Chi SG, Chiacchiera F, Chiang HL, Chiarelli R, Chiariello M, Chieppa M, Chin LS, Chiong M, Chiu GN, Cho DH, Cho SG, Cho WC, Cho YY, Cho YS, Choi AM, Choi EJ, Choi EK, Choi J, Choi ME, Choi SI, Chou TF, Chouaib S, Choubey D, Choubey V, Chow KC, Chowdhury K, Chu CT, Chuang TH, Chun T, Chung H, Chung T, Chung YL, Chwae YJ, Cianfanelli V, Ciarcia R, Ciechomska IA, Ciriolo MR, Cirone M, Claerhout S, Clague MJ, Claria J, Clarke PG, Clarke R, Clementi E, Cleyrat C, Cnop M, Coccia EM, Cocco T, Codogno P, Coers J, Cohen EE, Colecchia D, Coletto L, Coll NS, Colucci-Guyon E, Comincini S, Condello M, Cook KL, Coombs GH, Cooper CD, Cooper JM, Coppens I, Corasaniti MT, Corazzari M, Corbalan R, Corcelle-Termeau E, Cordero MD, Corral-Ramos C, Corti O, Cossarizza A, Costelli P, Costes S, Cotman SL, Coto-Montes A, Cottet S, Couve E, Covey LR, Cowart LA, Cox JS, Coxon FP, Coyne CB, Cragg MS, Craven RJ, Crepaldi T, Crespo JL, Criollo A, Crippa V, Cruz MT, Cuervo AM, Cuezva JM, Cui T, Cutillas PR, Czaja MJ, Czyzyk-Krzeska MF, Dagda RK, Dahmen U, Dai C, Dai W, Dai Y, Dalby KN, Dalla Valle L, Dalmasso G, D'Amelio M, Damme M, Darfeuille-Michaud A, Dargemont C, Darley-Usmar VM, Dasarathy S, Dasgupta B, Dash S, Dass CR, Davey HM, Davids LM, Davila D, Davis RJ, Dawson TM, Dawson VL, Daza P, de Belleroche J, de Figueiredo P, de Figueiredo RC, de la Fuente J, De Martino L, De Matteis A, De Meyer GR, De Milito A, De Santi M, de Souza W, De Tata V, De Zio D, Debnath J, Dechant R, Decuypere JP, Deegan S, Dehay B, Del Bello B, Del Re DP, Delage-Mourroux R, Delbridge LM, Deldicque L, Delorme-Axford E, Deng Y, Dengjel J, Denizot M, Dent P, Der CJ, Deretic V, Derrien B, Deutsch E, Devarenne TP, Devenish RJ, Di Bartolomeo S, Di Daniele N, Di Domenico F, Di Nardo A, Di Paola S, Di Pietro A, Di Renzo L, DiAntonio A, Diaz-Araya G, Diaz-Laviada I, Diaz-Meco MT, Diaz-Nido J, Dickey CA, Dickson RC, Diederich M, Digard P, Dikic I, Dinesh-Kumar SP, Ding C, Ding WX, Ding Z, Dini L, Distler JH, Diwan A, Djavaheri-Mergny M, Dmytruk K, Dobson RC, Doetsch V, Dokladny K, Dokudovskaya S, Donadelli M, Dong XC, Dong X, Dong Z, Donohue TM, Jr., Doran KS, D'Orazi G, Dorn GW, 2nd, Dosenko V, Dridi S, Drucker L, Du J, Du LL, Du L, du Toit A, Dua P, Duan L, Duann P, Dubey VK, Duchen MR, Duchosal MA, Duez H, Dugail I, Dumit VI, Duncan MC, Dunlop EA, Dunn WA, Jr., Dupont N, Dupuis L, Duran RV, Durcan TM, Duvezin-Caubet S, Duvvuri U, Eapen V, Ebrahimi-Fakhari D, Echard A, Eckhart L, Edelstein CL, Edinger AL, Eichinger L, Eisenberg T, Eisenberg-Lerner A, Eissa NT, El-Deiry WS, El-Khoury V, Elazar Z, Eldar-Finkelman H, Elliott CJ, Emanuele E, Emmenegger U, Engedal N, Engelbrecht AM, Engelender S, Enserink JM, Erdmann R, Erenpreisa J, Eri R, Eriksen JL, Erman A, Escalante R, Eskelinen EL, Espert L, Esteban-Martinez L, Evans TJ, Fabri M, Fabrias G, Fabrizi C, Facchiano A, Faergeman NJ, Faggioni A, Fairlie WD, Fan C, Fan D, Fan J, Fang S, Fanto M, Fanzani A, Farkas T, Faure M, Favier FB, Fearnhead H, Federici M, Fei E, Felizardo TC, Feng H, Feng Y, Ferguson TA, Fernandez AF, Fernandez-Barrena MG, Fernandez-Checa JC, Fernandez-Lopez A, Fernandez-Zapico ME, Feron O, Ferraro E, Ferreira-Halder CV, Fesus L, Feuer R, Fiesel FC, Filippi-Chiela EC, Filomeni G, Fimia GM, Fingert JH, Finkbeiner S, Finkel T, Fiorito F, Fisher PB, Flajolet M, Flamigni F, Florey O, Florio S, Floto RA, Folini M, Follo C, Fon EA, Fornai F, Fortunato F, Fraldi A, Franco R, Francois A, Frankel LB, Fraser ID, Frey N, Freyssenet DG, Frezza C, Friedman SL, Frigo DE, Fu D, Fuentes JM, Fueyo J, Fujitani Y, Fujiwara Y, Fujiya M, Fukuda M, Fulda S, Fusco C, Gabryel B, Gaestel M, Gailly P, Gajewska M, Galadari S, Galili G, Galindo I, Galindo MF, Galliciotti G, Galluzzi L, Galy V, Gammoh N, Gandy S, Ganesan AK, Ganesan S, Ganley IG, Gannage M, Gao FB, Gao F, Gao JX, Garcia Nannig L, Garcia Vescovi E, Garcia-Macia M, Garcia-Ruiz C, Garg AD, Garg PK, Gargini R, Gassen NC, Gatica D, Gatti E, Gavard J, Gavathiotis E, Ge L, Ge P, Ge S, Gean PW, Gelmetti V, Genazzani AA, Geng J, Genschik P, Gerner L, Gestwicki JE, Gewirtz DA, Ghavami S, Ghigo E, Ghosh D, Giammarioli AM, Giampieri F, Giampietri C, Giatromanolaki A, Gibbings DJ, Gibellini L, Gibson SB, Ginet V, Giordano A, Giorgini F, Giovannetti E, Girardin SE, Gispert S, Giuliano S, Gladson CL, Glavic A, Gleave M, Godefroy N, Gogal RM, Jr., Gokulan K, Goldman GH, Goletti D, Goligorsky MS, Gomes AV, Gomes LC, Gomez H, Gomez-Manzano C, Gomez-Sanchez R, Goncalves DA, Goncu E, Gong Q, Gongora C, Gonzalez CB, Gonzalez-Alegre P, Gonzalez-Cabo P, Gonzalez-Polo RA, Goping IS, Gorbea C, Gorbunov NV, Goring DR, Gorman AM, Gorski SM, Goruppi S, Goto-Yamada S, Gotor C, Gottlieb RA, Gozes I, Gozuacik D, Graba Y, Graef M, Granato GE, Grant GD, Grant S, Gravina GL, Green DR, Greenhough A, Greenwood MT, Grimaldi B, Gros F, Grose C, Groulx JF, Gruber F, Grumati P, Grune T, Guan JL, Guan KL, Guerra B, Guillen C, Gulshan K, Gunst J, Guo C, Guo L, Guo M, Guo W, Guo XG, Gust AA, Gustafsson AB, Gutierrez E, Gutierrez MG, Gwak HS, Haas A, Haber JE, Hadano S, Hagedorn M, Hahn DR, Halayko AJ, Hamacher-Brady A, Hamada K, Hamai A, Hamann A, Hamasaki M, Hamer I, Hamid Q, Hammond EM, Han F, Han W, Handa JT, Hanover JA, Hansen M, Harada M, Harhaji-Trajkovic L, Harper JW, Harrath AH, Harris AL, Harris J, Hasler U, Hasselblatt P, Hasui K, Hawley RG, Hawley TS, He C, He CY, He F, He G, He RR, He XH, He YW, He YY, Heath JK, Hebert MJ, Heinzen RA, Helgason GV, Hensel M, Henske EP, Her C, Herman PK, Hernandez A, Hernandez C, Hernandez-Tiedra S, Hetz C, Hiesinger PR, Higaki K, Hilfiker S, Hill BG, Hill JA, Hill WD, Hino K, Hofius D, Hofman P, Hoglinger GU, Hohfeld J, Holz MK, Hong Y, Hood DA, Hoozemans JJ, Hoppe T, Hsu C, Hsu CY, Hsu LC, Hu D, Hu G, Hu HM, Hu H, Hu MC, Hu YC, Hu ZW, Hua F, Hua Y, Huang C, Huang HL, Huang KH, Huang KY, Huang S, Huang WP, Huang YR, Huang Y, Huber TB, Huebbe P, Huh WK, Hulmi JJ, Hur GM, Hurley JH, Husak Z, Hussain SN, Hussain S, Hwang JJ, Hwang S, Hwang TI, Ichihara A, Imai Y, Imbriano C, Inomata M, Into T, Iovane V, Iovanna JL, Iozzo RV, Ip NY, Irazoqui JE, Iribarren P, Isaka Y, Isakovic AJ, Ischiropoulos H, Isenberg JS, Ishaq M, Ishida H, Ishii I, Ishmael JE, Isidoro C, Isobe KI, Isono E, Issazadeh-Navikas S, Itahana K, Itakura E, Ivanov AI, Iyer AK, Izquierdo JM, Izumi Y, Izzo V, Jaattela M, Jaber N, Jackson DJ, Jackson WT, Jacob TG, Jacques TS, Jagannath C, Jain A, Jana NR, Jang BK, Jani A, Janji B, Jannig PR, Jansson PJ, Jean S, Jendrach M, Jeon JH, Jessen N, Jeung EB, Jia K, Jia L, Jiang H, Jiang L, Jiang T, Jiang X, Jiang Y, Jimenez A, Jin C, Jin H, Jin L, Jin M, Jin S, Jinwal UK, Jo EK, Johansen T, Johnson DE, Johnson GV, Johnson JD, Jonasch E, Jones C, Joosten LA, Jordan J, Joseph AM, Joseph B, Joubert AM, Ju D, Ju J, Juan HF, Juenemann K, Juhasz G, Jung HS, Jung JU, Jung YK, Jungbluth H, Justice MJ, Jutten B, Kaakoush NO, Kaarniranta K, Kaasik A, Kabuta T, Kaeffer B, Kagedal K, Kahana A, Kajimura S, Kakhlon O, Kalia M, Kalvakolanu DV, Kamada Y, Kambas K, Kaminskyy VO, Kampinga HH, Kandouz M, Kang C, Kang R, Kang TC, Kanki T, Kanneganti TD, Kanno H, Kanthasamy AG, Kantorow M, Kaparakis-Liaskos M, Kapuy O, Karantza V, Karim MR, Karmakar P, Kaser A, Kaushik S, Kawula T, Kaynar AM, Ke PY, Ke ZJ, Kehrl JH, Keller KE, Kemper JK, Kenworthy AK, Kepp O, Kern A, Kesari S, Kessel D, Ketteler R, Kettelhut ID, Khambu B, Khan MM, Khandelwal VK, Khare S, Kiang JG, Kiger AA, Kihara A, Kim AL, Kim CH, Kim DR, Kim DH, Kim EK, Kim HY, Kim HR, Kim JS, Kim JH, Kim JC, Kim KW, Kim MD, Kim MM, Kim PK, Kim SW, Kim SY, Kim YS, Kim Y, Kimchi A, Kimmelman AC, Kimura T, King JS, Kirkegaard K, Kirkin V, Kirshenbaum LA, Kishi S, Kitajima Y, Kitamoto K, Kitaoka Y, Kitazato K, Kley RA, Klimecki WT, Klinkenberg M, Klucken J, Knaevelsrud H, Knecht E, Knuppertz L, Ko JL, Kobayashi S, Koch JC, Koechlin-Ramonatxo C, Koenig U, Koh YH, Kohler K, Kohlwein SD, Koike M, Komatsu M, Kominami E, Kong D, Kong HJ, Konstantakou EG, Kopp BT, Korcsmaros T, Korhonen L, Korolchuk VI, Koshkina NV, Kou Y, Koukourakis MI, Koumenis C, Kovacs AL, Kovacs T, Kovacs WJ, Koya D, Kraft C, Krainc D, Kramer H, Kravic-Stevovic T, Krek W, Kretz-Remy C, Krick R, Krishnamurthy M, Kriston-Vizi J, Kroemer G, Kruer MC, Kruger R, Ktistakis NT, Kuchitsu K, Kuhn C, Kumar AP, Kumar A, Kumar D, Kumar R, Kumar S, Kundu M, Kung HJ, Kuno A, Kuo SH, Kuret J, Kurz T, Kwok T, Kwon TK, Kwon YT, Kyrmizi I, La Spada AR, Lafont F, Lahm T, Lakkaraju A, Lam T, Lamark T, Lancel S, Landowski TH, Lane DJ, Lane JD, Lanzi C, Lapaquette P, Lapierre LR, Laporte J, Laukkarinen J, Laurie GW, Lavandero S, Lavie L, LaVoie MJ, Law BY, Law HK, Law KB, Layfield R, Lazo PA, Le Cam L, Le Roch KG, Le Stunff H, Leardkamolkarn V, Lecuit M, Lee BH, Lee CH, Lee EF, Lee GM, Lee HJ, Lee H, Lee JK, Lee J, Lee JH, Lee M, Lee MS, Lee PJ, Lee SW, Lee SJ, Lee SY, Lee SH, Lee SS, Lee S, Lee YR, Lee YJ, Lee YH, Leeuwenburgh C, Lefort S, Legouis R, Lei J, Lei QY, Leib DA, Leibowitz G, Lekli I, Lemaire SD, Lemasters JJ, Lemberg MK, Lemoine A, Leng S, Lenz G, Lenzi P, Lerman LO, Lettieri Barbato D, Leu JI, Leung HY, Levine B, Lewis PA, Lezoualc'h F, Li C, Li F, Li FJ, Li J, Li K, Li L, Li M, Li Q, Li R, Li S, Li W, Li X, Li Y, Lian J, Liang C, Liang Q, Liao Y, Liberal J, Liberski PP, Lie P, Lieberman AP, Lim HJ, Lim KL, Lim K, Lima RT, Lin CS, Lin CF, Lin F, Lin FC, Lin K, Lin KH, Lin PH, Lin T, Lin WW, Lin YS, Lin Y, Linden R, Lindholm D, Lindqvist LM, Lingor P, Linkermann A, Liotta LA, Lipinski MM, Lira VA, Lisanti MP, Liton PB, Liu B, Liu C, Liu CF, Liu F, Liu HJ, Liu J, Liu JJ, Liu JL, Liu K, Liu L, Liu Q, Liu RY, Liu S, Liu W, Liu XD, Liu X, Liu XH, Liu Y, Liu Z, Liuzzi JP, Lizard G, Ljujic M, Lodhi IJ, Logue SE, Lokeshwar BL, Long YC, Lonial S, Loos B, Lopez-Otin C, Lopez-Vicario C, Lorente M, Lorenzi PL, Lorincz P, Los M, Lotze MT, Lovat PE, Lu B, Lu J, Lu Q, Lu SM, Lu S, Lu Y, Luciano F, Luckhart S, Lucocq JM, Ludovico P, Lugea A, Lukacs NW, Lum JJ, Lund AH, Luo H, Luo J, Luo S, Luparello C, Lyons T, Ma J, Ma Y, Ma Z, Machado J, Machado-Santelli GM, Macian F, MacIntosh GC, MacKeigan JP, Macleod KF, MacMicking JD, MacMillan-Crow LA, Madeo F, Madesh M, Madrigal-Matute J, Maeda A, Maeda T, Maegawa G, Maellaro E, Maes H, Magarinos M, Maiese K, Maiti TK, Maiuri L, Maiuri MC, Maki CG, Malli R, Malorni W, Maloyan A, Mami-Chouaib F, Man N, Mancias JD, Mandelkow EM, Mandell MA, Manfredi AA, Manie SN, Manzoni C, Mao K, Mao Z, Mao ZW, Marambaud P, Marconi AM, Marelja Z, Marfe G, Margeta M, Margittai E, Mari M, Mariani FV, Marin C, Marinelli S, Marino G, Markovic I, Marquez R, Martelli AM, Martens S, Martin KR, Martin SJ, Martin S, Martin-Acebes MA, Martin-Sanz P, Martinand-Mari C, Martinet W, Martinez J, Martinez-Lopez N, Martinez-Outschoorn U, Martinez-Velazquez M, Martinez-Vicente M, Martins WK, Mashima H, Mastrianni JA, Matarese G, Matarrese P, Mateo R, Matoba S, Matsumoto N, Matsushita T, Matsuura A, Matsuzawa T, Mattson MP, Matus S, Maugeri N, Mauvezin C, Mayer A, Maysinger D, Mazzolini GD, McBrayer MK, McCall K, McCormick C, McInerney GM, McIver SC, McKenna S, McMahon JJ, McNeish IA, Mechta-Grigoriou F, Medema JP, Medina DL, Megyeri K, Mehrpour M, Mehta JL, Mei Y, Meier UC, Meijer AJ, Melendez A, Melino G, Melino S, de Melo EJ, Mena MA, Meneghini MD, Menendez JA, Menezes R, Meng L, Meng LH, Meng S, Menghini R, Menko AS, Menna-Barreto RF, Menon MB, Meraz-Rios MA, Merla G, Merlini L, Merlot AM, Meryk A, Meschini S, Meyer JN, Mi MT, Miao CY, Micale L, Michaeli S, Michiels C, Migliaccio AR, Mihailidou AS, Mijaljica D, Mikoshiba K, Milan E, Miller-Fleming L, Mills GB, Mills IG, Minakaki G, Minassian BA, Ming XF, Minibayeva F, Minina EA, Mintern JD, Minucci S, Miranda-Vizuete A, Mitchell CH, Miyamoto S, Miyazawa K, Mizushima N, Mnich K, Mograbi B, Mohseni S, Moita LF, Molinari M, Moller AB, Mollereau B, Mollinedo F, Mongillo M, Monick MM, Montagnaro S, Montell C, Moore DJ, Moore MN, Mora-Rodriguez R, Moreira PI, Morel E, Morelli MB, Moreno S, Morgan MJ, Moris A, Moriyasu Y, Morrison JL, Morrison LA, Morselli E, Moscat J, Moseley PL, Mostowy S, Motori E, Mottet D, Mottram JC, Moussa CE, Mpakou VE, Mukhtar H, Mulcahy Levy JM, Muller S, Munoz-Moreno R, Munoz-Pinedo C, Munz C, Murphy ME, Murray JT, Murthy A, Mysorekar IU, Nabi IR, Nabissi M, Nader GA, Nagahara Y, Nagai Y, Nagata K, Nagelkerke A, Nagy P, Naidu SR, Nair S, Nakano H, Nakatogawa H, Nanjundan M, Napolitano G, Naqvi NI, Nardacci R, Narendra DP, Narita M, Nascimbeni AC, Natarajan R, Navegantes LC, Nawrocki ST, Nazarko TY, Nazarko VY, Neill T, Neri LM, Netea MG, Netea-Maier RT, Neves BM, Ney PA, Nezis IP, Nguyen HT, Nguyen HP, Nicot AS, Nilsen H, Nilsson P, Nishimura M, Nishino I, Niso-Santano M, Niu H, Nixon RA, Njar VC, Noda T, Noegel AA, Nolte EM, Norberg E, Norga KK, Noureini SK, Notomi S, Notterpek L, Nowikovsky K, Nukina N, Nurnberger T, O'Donnell VB, O'Donovan T, O'Dwyer PJ, Oehme I, Oeste CL, Ogawa M, Ogretmen B, Ogura Y, Oh YJ, Ohmuraya M, Ohshima T, Ojha R, Okamoto K, Okazaki T, Oliver FJ, Ollinger K, Olsson S, Orban DP, Ordonez P, Orhon I, Orosz L, O'Rourke EJ, Orozco H, Ortega AL, Ortona E, Osellame LD, Oshima J, Oshima S, Osiewacz HD, Otomo T, Otsu K, Ou JJ, Outeiro TF, Ouyang DY, Ouyang H, Overholtzer M, Ozbun MA, Ozdinler PH, Ozpolat B, Pacelli C, Paganetti P, Page G, Pages G, Pagnini U, Pajak B, Pak SC, Pakos-Zebrucka K, Pakpour N, Palkova Z, Palladino F, Pallauf K, Pallet N, Palmieri M, Paludan SR, Palumbo C, Palumbo S, Pampliega O, Pan H, Pan W, Panaretakis T, Pandey A, Pantazopoulou A, Papackova Z, Papademetrio DL, Papassideri I, Papini A, Parajuli N, Pardo J, Parekh VV, Parenti G, Park JI, Park J, Park OK, Parker R, Parlato R, Parys JB, Parzych KR, Pasquet JM, Pasquier B, Pasumarthi KB, Patschan D, Patterson C, Pattingre S, Pattison S, Pause A, Pavenstadt H, Pavone F, Pedrozo Z, Pena FJ, Penalva MA, Pende M, Peng J, Penna F, Penninger JM, Pensalfini A, Pepe S, Pereira GJ, Pereira PC, Perez-de la Cruz V, Perez-Perez ME, Perez-Rodriguez D, Perez-Sala D, Perier C, Perl A, Perlmutter DH, Perrotta I, Pervaiz S, Pesonen M, Pessin JE, Peters GJ, Petersen M, Petrache I, Petrof BJ, Petrovski G, Phang JM, Piacentini M, Pierdominici M, Pierre P, Pierrefite-Carle V, Pietrocola F, Pimentel-Muinos FX, Pinar M, Pineda B, Pinkas-Kramarski R, Pinti M, Pinton P, Piperdi B, Piret JM, Platanias LC, Platta HW, Plowey ED, Poggeler S, Poirot M, Polcic P, Poletti A, Poon AH, Popelka H, Popova B, Poprawa I, Poulose SM, Poulton J, Powers SK, Powers T, Pozuelo-Rubio M, Prak K, Prange R, Prescott M, Priault M, Prince S, Proia RL, Proikas-Cezanne T, Prokisch H, Promponas VJ, Przyklenk K, Puertollano R, Pugazhenthi S, Puglielli L, Pujol A, Puyal J, Pyeon D, Qi X, Qian WB, Qin ZH, Qiu Y, Qu Z, Quadrilatero J, Quinn F, Raben N, Rabinowich H, Radogna F, Ragusa MJ, Rahmani M, Raina K, Ramanadham S, Ramesh R, Rami A, Randall-Demllo S, Randow F, Rao H, Rao VA, Rasmussen BB, Rasse TM, Ratovitski EA, Rautou PE, Ray SK, Razani B, Reed BH, Reggiori F, Rehm M, Reichert AS, Rein T, Reiner DJ, Reits E, Ren J, Ren X, Renna M, Reusch JE, Revuelta JL, Reyes L, Rezaie AR, Richards RI, Richardson DR, Richetta C, Riehle MA, Rihn BH, Rikihisa Y, Riley BE, Rimbach G, Rippo MR, Ritis K, Rizzi F, Rizzo E, Roach PJ, Robbins J, Roberge M, Roca G, Roccheri MC, Rocha S, Rodrigues CM, Rodriguez CI, de Cordoba SR, Rodriguez-Muela N, Roelofs J, Rogov VV, Rohn TT, Rohrer B, Romanelli D, Romani L, Romano PS, Roncero MI, Rosa JL, Rosello A, Rosen KV, Rosenstiel P, Rost-Roszkowska M, Roth KA, Roue G, Rouis M, Rouschop KM, Ruan DT, Ruano D, Rubinsztein DC, Rucker EB, 3rd, Rudich A, Rudolf E, Rudolf R, Ruegg MA, Ruiz-Roldan C, Ruparelia AA, Rusmini P, Russ DW, Russo GL, Russo G, Russo R, Rusten TE, Ryabovol V, Ryan KM, Ryter SW, Sabatini DM, Sacher M, Sachse C, Sack MN, Sadoshima J, Saftig P, Sagi-Eisenberg R, Sahni S, Saikumar P, Saito T, Saitoh T, Sakakura K, Sakoh-Nakatogawa M, Sakuraba Y, Salazar-Roa M, Salomoni P, Saluja AK, Salvaterra PM, Salvioli R, Samali A, Sanchez AM, Sanchez-Alcazar JA, Sanchez-Prieto R, Sandri M, Sanjuan MA, Santaguida S, Santambrogio L, Santoni G, Dos Santos CN, Saran S, Sardiello M, Sargent G, Sarkar P, Sarkar S, Sarrias MR, Sarwal MM, Sasakawa C, Sasaki M, Sass M, Sato K, Sato M, Satriano J, Savaraj N, Saveljeva S, Schaefer L, Schaible UE, Scharl M, Schatzl HM, Schekman R, Scheper W, Schiavi A, Schipper HM, Schmeisser H, Schmidt J, Schmitz I, Schneider BE, Schneider EM, Schneider JL, Schon EA, Schonenberger MJ, Schonthal AH, Schorderet DF, Schroder B, Schuck S, Schulze RJ, Schwarten M, Schwarz TL, Sciarretta S, Scotto K, Scovassi AI, Screaton RA, Screen M, Seca H, Sedej S, Segatori L, Segev N, Seglen PO, Segui-Simarro JM, Segura-Aguilar J, Seki E, Seiliez I, Sell C, Semenkovich CF, Semenza GL, Sen U, Serra AL, Serrano-Puebla A, Sesaki H, Setoguchi T, Settembre C, Shacka JJ, Shajahan-Haq AN, Shapiro IM, Sharma S, She H, Shen CJ, Shen CC, Shen HM, Shen S, Shen W, Sheng R, Sheng X, Sheng ZH, Shepherd TG, Shi J, Shi Q, Shi Y, Shibutani S, Shibuya K, Shidoji Y, Shieh JJ, Shih CM, Shimada Y, Shimizu S, Shin DW, Shinohara ML, Shintani M, Shintani T, Shioi T, Shirabe K, Shiri-Sverdlov R, Shirihai O, Shore GC, Shu CW, Shukla D, Sibirny AA, Sica V, Sigurdson CJ, Sigurdsson EM, Sijwali PS, Sikorska B, Silveira WA, Silvente-Poirot S, Silverman GA, Simak J, Simmet T, Simon AK, Simon HU, Simone C, Simons M, Simonsen A, Singh R, Singh SV, Singh SK, Sinha D, Sinha S, Sinicrope FA, Sirko A, Sirohi K, Sishi BJ, Sittler A, Siu PM, Sivridis E, Skwarska A, Slack R, Slaninova I, Slavov N, Smaili SS, Smalley KS, Smith DR, Soenen SJ, Soleimanpour SA, Solhaug A, Somasundaram K, Son JH, Sonawane A, Song C, Song F, Song HK, Song JX, Song W, Soo KY, Sood AK, Soong TW, Soontornniyomkij V, Sorice M, Sotgia F, Soto-Pantoja DR, Sotthibundhu A, Sousa MJ, Spaink HP, Span PN, Spang A, Sparks JD, Speck PG, Spector SA, Spies CD, Springer W, Clair DS, Stacchiotti A, Staels B, Stang MT, Starczynowski DT, Starokadomskyy P, Steegborn C, Steele JW, Stefanis L, Steffan J, Stellrecht CM, Stenmark H, Stepkowski TM, Stern ST, Stevens C, Stockwell BR, Stoka V, Storchova Z, Stork B, Stratoulias V, Stravopodis DJ, Strnad P, Strohecker AM, Strom AL, Stromhaug P, Stulik J, Su YX, Su Z, Subauste CS, Subramaniam S, Sue CM, Suh SW, Sui X, Sukseree S, Sulzer D, Sun FL, Sun J, Sun SY, Sun Y, Sundaramoorthy V, Sung J, Suzuki H, Suzuki K, Suzuki N, Suzuki T, Suzuki YJ, Swanson MS, Swanton C, Sward K, Swarup G, Sweeney ST, Sylvester PW, Szatmari Z, Szegezdi E, Szlosarek PW, Taegtmeyer H, Tafani M, Taillebourg E, Tait SW, Takacs-Vellai K, Takahashi Y, Takats S, Takemura G, Takigawa N, Talbot NJ, Tamagno E, Tamburini J, Tan CP, Tan L, Tan ML, Tan M, Tan YJ, Tanaka K, Tanaka M, Tang D, Tang G, Tanida I, Tanji K, Tannous BA, Tapia JA, Tasset-Cuevas I, Tatar M, Tavassoly I, Tavernarakis N, Taylor A, Taylor GS, Taylor GA, Taylor JP, Taylor MJ, Tchetina EV, Tee AR, Teixeira-Clerc F, Telang S, Tencomnao T, Teng BB, Teng RJ, Terro F, Tettamanti G, Theiss AL, Theron AE, Thomas KJ, Thome MP, Thomes PG, Thorburn A, Thorner J, Thum T, Thumm M, Thurston TL, Tian L, Till A, Ting JP, Titorenko VI, Toker L, Toldo S, Tooze SA, Topisirovic I, Torgersen ML, Torosantucci L, Torriglia A, Torrisi MR, Tournier C, Towns R, Trajkovic V, Travassos LH, Triola G, Tripathi DN, Trisciuoglio D, Troncoso R, Trougakos IP, Truttmann AC, Tsai KJ, Tschan MP, Tseng YH, Tsukuba T, Tsung A, Tsvetkov AS, Tu S, Tuan HY, Tucci M, Tumbarello DA, Turk B, Turk V, Turner RF, Tveita AA, Tyagi SC, Ubukata M, Uchiyama Y, Udelnow A, Ueno T, Umekawa M, Umemiya-Shirafuji R, Underwood BR, Ungermann C, Ureshino RP, Ushioda R, Uversky VN, Uzcategui NL, Vaccari T, Vaccaro MI, Vachova L, Vakifahmetoglu-Norberg H, Valdor R, Valente EM, Vallette F, Valverde AM, Van den Berghe G, Van Den Bosch L, van den Brink GR, van der Goot FG, van der Klei IJ, van der Laan LJ, van Doorn WG, van Egmond M, van Golen KL, Van Kaer L, van Lookeren Campagne M, Vandenabeele P, Vandenberghe W, Vanhorebeek I, Varela-Nieto I, Vasconcelos MH, Vasko R, Vavvas DG, Vega-Naredo I, Velasco G, Velentzas AD, Velentzas PD, Vellai T, Vellenga E, Vendelbo MH, Venkatachalam K, Ventura N, Ventura S, Veras PS, Verdier M, Vertessy BG, Viale A, Vidal M, Vieira H, Vierstra RD, Vigneswaran N, Vij N, Vila M, Villar M, Villar VH, Villarroya J, Vindis C, Viola G, Viscomi MT, Vitale G, Vogl DT, Voitsekhovskaja OV, von Haefen C, von Schwarzenberg K, Voth DE, Vouret-Craviari V, Vuori K, Vyas JM, Waeber C, Walker CL, Walker MJ, Walter J, Wan L, Wan X, Wang B, Wang C, Wang CY, Wang D, Wang F, Wang G, Wang HJ, Wang H, Wang HG, Wang HD, Wang J, Wang M, Wang MQ, Wang PY, Wang P, Wang RC, Wang S, Wang TF, Wang X, Wang XJ, Wang XW, Wang Y, Wang YJ, Wang YT, Wang ZN, Wappner P, Ward C, Ward DM, Warnes G, Watada H, Watanabe Y, Watase K, Weaver TE, Weekes CD, Wei J, Weide T, Weihl CC, Weindl G, Weis SN, Wen L, Wen X, Wen Y, Westermann B, Weyand CM, White AR, White E, Whitton JL, Whitworth AJ, Wiels J, Wild F, Wildenberg ME, Wileman T, Wilkinson DS, Wilkinson S, Willbold D, Williams C, Williams K, Williamson PR, Winklhofer KF, Witkin SS, Wohlgemuth SE, Wollert T, Wolvetang EJ, Wong E, Wong GW, Wong RW, Wong VK, Woodcock EA, Wright KL, Wu C, Wu D, Wu GS, Wu J, Wu M, Wu S, Wu WK, Wu Y, Wu Z, Xavier CP, Xavier RJ, Xia GX, Xia T, Xia W, Xia Y, Xiao H, Xiao J, Xiao S, Xiao W, Xie CM, Xie Z, Xilouri M, Xiong Y, Xu C, Xu F, Xu H, Xu J, Xu L, Xu X, Xu Y, Xu ZX, Xu Z, Xue Y, Yamada T, Yamamoto A, Yamanaka K, Yamashina S, Yamashiro S, Yan B, Yan X, Yan Z, Yanagi Y, Yang DS, Yang JM, Yang L, Yang M, Yang PM, Yang P, Yang Q, Yang W, Yang WY, Yang X, Yang Y, Yang Z, Yao MC, Yao PJ, Yao X, Yao Z, Yasui LS, Ye M, Yedvobnick B, Yeganeh B, Yeh ES, Yeyati PL, Yi F, Yi L, Yin XM, Yip CK, Yoo YM, Yoo YH, Yoon SY, Yoshida KI, Yoshimori T, Young KH, Yu H, Yu JJ, Yu JT, Yu J, Yu L, Yu WH, Yu XF, Yu Z, Yuan J, Yuan ZM, Yue BY, Yue J, Yue Z, Zacks DN, Zacksenhaus E, Zaffaroni N, Zaglia T, Zakeri Z, Zecchini V, Zeng J, Zeng M, Zeng Q, Zervos AS, Zhang DD, Zhang F, Zhang G, Zhang GC, Zhang H, Zhang J, Zhang JP, Zhang L, Zhang MY, Zhang X, Zhang XD, Zhang Y, Zhao M, Zhao WL, Zhao X, Zhao YG, Zhao Y, Zhao YX, Zhao Z, Zhao ZJ, Zheng D, Zheng XL, Zheng X, Zhivotovsky B, Zhong Q, Zhou GZ, Zhou G, Zhou H, Zhou SF, Zhou XJ, Zhu H, Zhu WG, Zhu W, Zhu XF, Zhu Y, Zhuang SM, Zhuang X, Ziparo E, Zois CE, Zoladek T, Zong WX, Zorzano A, Zughaier SM (2016) Guidelines for the use and interpretation of assays for monitoring autophagy (3rd edition). Autophagy 12:1-222.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koppers</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blokhuis</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westeneng</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Terpstra</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zundel</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vieira de Sa</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schellevis</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waite</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veldink</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Berg</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasterkamp</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9orf72 ablation in mice does not cause motor neuron degeneration or motor deficits</article-title>
          <source>Ann Neurol</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>426</fpage>
          <lpage>438</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24453</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26044557?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26044557</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kundu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindsten</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Selak</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ney</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ulk1 plays a critical role in the autophagic clearance of mitochondria and ribosomes during reticulocyte maturation</article-title>
          <source>Blood</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>1493</fpage>
          <lpage>1502</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2008-02-137398</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18539900?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539900</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lagier-Tourenne</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baughn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rigo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watt</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chun</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ling</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polymenidou</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drenner</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Artates</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McAlonis-Downes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Markmiller</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutt</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzo</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cady</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloh</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenberg</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeo</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>XD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleveland</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ravits</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Targeted degradation of sense and antisense C9orf72 RNA foci as therapy for ALS and frontotemporal degeneration</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>E4530</fpage>
          <lpage>4539</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1318835110</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24170860?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24170860</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lang</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fellerer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwenk</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuhn</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kremmer</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edbauer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Capell</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haass</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Membrane orientation and subcellular localization of transmembrane protein 106B (TMEM106B), a major risk factor for frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <fpage>19355</fpage>
          <lpage>19365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.365098</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22511793?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22511793</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Le Ber</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Frontotemporal lobar dementia and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis associated with c9orf72 expansion</article-title>
          <source>Rev Neurol (Paris)</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <fpage>475</fpage>
          <lpage>481</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurol.2015.04.004</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26032484</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ESCRT, autophagy, and frontotemporal dementia</article-title>
          <source>BMB Rep</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>827</fpage>
          <lpage>832</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5483/BMBRep.2008.41.12.827</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19123971?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19123971</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levine</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daniels</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gatta</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The product of C9orf72, a gene strongly implicated in neurodegeneration, is structurally related to DENN Rab-GEFs</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>499</fpage>
          <lpage>503</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts725</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23329412?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329412</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ling</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polymenidou</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleveland</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Converging mechanisms in ALS and FTD: disrupted RNA and protein homeostasis</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>416</fpage>
          <lpage>438</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2013.07.033</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23931993?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23931993</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liscic</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grinberg</surname>
              <given-names>LT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zidar</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gitcho</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cairns</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ALS and FTLD: two faces of TDP-43 proteinopathy</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>772</fpage>
          <lpage>780</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2008.02195.x</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18684309?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18684309</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu Y, Pattamatta A, Zu T, Reid T, Bardhi O, Borchelt DR, Yachnis AT, Ranum LP. C9orf72 BAC Mouse Model with Motor Deficits and Neurodegenerative Features of ALS/FTD. Neuron. 2016.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mali</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esvelt</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aach</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guell</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>DiCarlo</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norville</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Church</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>RNA-guided human genome engineering via Cas9</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>339</volume>
          <fpage>823</fpage>
          <lpage>826</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1232033</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23287722?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287722</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O'Rourke</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bogdanik</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muhammad</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gendron</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cady</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>EY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarrow</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grant</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ho</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carmona</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simpkinson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lall</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daughrity</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrucelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>EB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloh</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9orf72 BAC Transgenic Mice Display Typical Pathologic Features of ALS/FTD</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>892</fpage>
          <lpage>901</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.10.027</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26637796?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26637796</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O'Rourke</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bogdanik</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yanez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lall</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muhammad</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ho</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carmona</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vit</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarrow</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bell</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harms</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dangler</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Underhill</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goodridge</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloh</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9orf72 is required for proper macrophage and microglial function in mice</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>351</volume>
          <fpage>1324</fpage>
          <lpage>1329</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaf1064</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26989253?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26989253</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>OM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabrera</surname>
              <given-names>GT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gendron</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKeon</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metterville</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wightman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salameh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boylan</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daughrity</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sapp</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horvitz</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bosco</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Jong</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrucelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mueller</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human C9ORF72 Hexanucleotide Expansion Reproduces RNA Foci and Dipeptide Repeat Proteins but Not Neurodegeneration in BAC Transgenic Mice</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>902</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.11.018</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26637797?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26637797</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>OM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghasemi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Emerging mechanisms of molecular pathology in ALS</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>1767</fpage>
          <lpage>1779</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI71601</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25932674?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25932674</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rademakers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Blitterswijk</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Motor neuron disease in 2012: Novel causal genes and disease modifiers</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>63</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2012.276</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23318296?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23318296</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Renton</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Majounie</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waite</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon-Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rollinson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibbs</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schymick</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laaksovirta</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van Swieten</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Myllykangas</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalimo</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paetau</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abramzon</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Remes</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaganovich</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duckworth</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ding</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harmer</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hernandez</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mok</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryten</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trabzuni</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guerreiro</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orrell</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neal</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murray</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pearson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansen</surname>
              <given-names>IE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sondervan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seelaar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halliwell</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Callister</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toulson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richardson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerhard</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snowden</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mann</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neary</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nalls</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peuralinna</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansson</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isoviita</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaivorinne</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holtta-Vuori</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikonen</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sulkava</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benatar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wuu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chio</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Restagno</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Borghero</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sabatelli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heckerman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rogaeva</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zinman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rothstein</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sendtner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drepper</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eichler</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alkan</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdullaev</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pack</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dutra</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pak</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hardy</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singleton</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heutink</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pickering-Brown</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tienari</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Traynor</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A hexanucleotide repeat expansion in C9ORF72 is the cause of chromosome 9p21-linked ALS-FTD</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.09.010</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21944779?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21944779</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rohrer</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Isaacs</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mizielinska</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mead</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lashley</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wray</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sidle</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fratta</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orrell</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hardy</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holton</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Revesz</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossor</surname>
              <given-names>MN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warren</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>C9orf72 expansions in frontotemporal dementia and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>301</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(14)70233-9</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25638642?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25638642</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rusten</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simonsen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ESCRT functions in autophagy and associated disease</article-title>
          <source>Cell Cycle</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>1166</fpage>
          <lpage>1172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.7.9.5784</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18418046?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18418046</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sellier C, Campanari ML, Julie Corbier C, Gaucherot A, Kolb-Cheynel I, Oulad-Abdelghani M, Ruffenach F, Page A, Ciura S, Kabashi E, Charlet-Berguerand N. Loss of C9ORF72 impairs autophagy and synergizes with polyQ Ataxin-2 to induce motor neuron dysfunction and cell death. Embo J. 2016.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Damiano</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franceschetti</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Canafoglia</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morbin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pareyson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mole</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staropoli</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sims</surname>
              <given-names>KB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahl</surname>
              <given-names>HH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bahlo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berkovic</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Strikingly Different Clinicopathological Phenotypes Determined by Progranulin-Mutation Dosage</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>1102</fpage>
          <lpage>1107</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2012.04.021</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22608501?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22608501</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stagi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klein</surname>
              <given-names>ZA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gould</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bewersdorf</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strittmatter</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lysosome size, motility and stress response regulated by fronto-temporal dementia modifier TMEM106B</article-title>
          <source>Mol Cell Neurosci</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>226</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcn.2014.07.006</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25066864?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25066864</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stanley</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ragusa</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hurley</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The beginning of the end: how scaffolds nucleate autophagosome biogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Trends Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2013.07.008</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23999079?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23999079</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maroof</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merkle</surname>
              <given-names>FT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koszka</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Intoh</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Armstrong</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moccia</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davis-Dusenbery</surname>
              <given-names>BN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eggan</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The mouse C9ORF72 ortholog is enriched in neurons known to degenerate in ALS and FTD</article-title>
          <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1725</fpage>
          <lpage>1727</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3566</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24185425?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24185425</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Therrien M, Rouleau GA, Dion PA, Parker JA. Deletion of C9ORF72 results in motor neuron degeneration and stress sensitivity in C. elegans. PLoS One. 2013;8.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tran</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gendron</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chalasani</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nickerson</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrucelli</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weng</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gao</surname>
              <given-names>FB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential Toxicity of Nuclear RNA Foci versus Dipeptide Repeat Proteins in a Drosophila Model of C9ORF72 FTD/ALS</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>1207</fpage>
          <lpage>1214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.09.015</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26402604?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402604</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vancha</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Govindaraju</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parsa</surname>
              <given-names>KV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jasti</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez-Garcia</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ballestero</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of polyethyleneimine polymer in cell culture as attachment factor and lipofection enhancer</article-title>
          <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6750-4-23</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15485583?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485583</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tale of two diseases: amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and frontotemporal dementia</article-title>
          <source>Neurol India</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>347</fpage>
          <lpage>351</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0028-3886.141174</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25237937?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25237937</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Waite</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baumer</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>East</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neal</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morris</surname>
              <given-names>HR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ansorge</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blake</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reduced C9orf72 protein levels in frontal cortex of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and frontotemporal degeneration brain with the C9ORF72 hexanucleotide repeat expansion</article-title>
          <source>Neurobiol Aging</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <fpage>1779 e1775-1779 e1713</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2014.01.016</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24559645</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wood</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A hexanucleotide repeat expansion in C9ORF72 links amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and frontotemporal dementia</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>595</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2011.162</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22009283?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009283</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xiao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>MacNair</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGoldrick</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKeever</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLean</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keith</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zinman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rogaeva</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isoform-specific antibodies reveal distinct subcellular localizations of C9orf72 in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</article-title>
          <source>Ann Neurol</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>568</fpage>
          <lpage>583</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24469</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26174152?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174152</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xiao S, MacNair L, McLean J, McGoldrick P, McKeever P, Soleimani S, Keith J, Zinman L, Rogaeva E, Robertson J. C9orf72 isoforms in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis and Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration. Brain Res. 2016.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iyer</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aravind</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Discovery of Novel DENN Proteins: Implications for the Evolution of Eukaryotic Intracellular Membrane Structures and Human Disease</article-title>
          <source>Front Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>283</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 23248642?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23248642</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bastos de Oliveira</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smolka</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prosaposin facilitates sortilin-independent lysosomal trafficking of progranulin</article-title>
          <source>J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>210</volume>
          <fpage>991</fpage>
          <lpage>1002</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201502029</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26370502?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26370502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>