<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:54:43Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4207803" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4207803</identifier><datestamp>2014-10-27</datestamp><setSpec>plospath</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4207803</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4207803</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4207803</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25340845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25340845</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PPATHOGENS-D-14-00790</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2">
          <subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Biochemistry</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Proteins</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Immune System Proteins</subject>
                <subj-group>
                  <subject>Immune Receptors</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                    <subject>Pattern Recognition Receptors</subject>
                  </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Developmental Biology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Molecular Development</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Cytokines</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
          <subj-group>
            <subject>Immunology</subject>
            <subj-group>
              <subject>Immune System</subject>
              <subj-group>
                <subject>Innate Immune System</subject>
              </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Novel Function of Human Pumilio Proteins in Cytoplasmic Sensing of Viral Infection</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Pumilio Proteins Facilitate Viral RNA Sensing</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Narita</surname>
            <given-names>Ryo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Takahasi</surname>
            <given-names>Kiyohiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Murakami</surname>
            <given-names>Etsu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hirano</surname>
            <given-names>Emi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Seiji P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">
<sup>¤</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yoneyama</surname>
            <given-names>Mitsutoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kato</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fujita</surname>
            <given-names>Takashi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Genetics, Institute for Virus Research, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institute for Innovative NanoBio Drug Discovery and Development, Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Science, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Division of Molecular Immunology, Medical Mycology Research Center, Chiba University, Chiba, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology, Graduate School of Biostudies, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan</addr-line>
</aff>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="editor">
          <name>
            <surname>Gack</surname>
            <given-names>Michaela U.</given-names>
          </name>
          <role>Editor</role>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Harvard Medical School, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>tfujita@virus.kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></corresp>
        <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
          <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con">
          <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: RN HK TF. Performed the experiments: RN KT EM EH SPY MY. Analyzed the data: RN MY HK TF. Wrote the paper: RN HK TF.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn1" fn-type="current-aff">
          <label>¤</label>
          <p>Current address: Osaka City Institute of Public Health and Environmental Sciences, Osaka, Japan</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <elocation-id>e1004417</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2014 Narita et al</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Narita et al</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>RIG-I-like receptor (RLR) plays a pivotal role in the detection of invading pathogens to initiate type I interferon (IFN) gene transcription. Since aberrant IFN production is harmful, RLR signaling is strictly regulated. However, the regulatory mechanisms are not fully understood. By expression cloning, we identified Pumilio proteins, PUM1 and PUM2, as candidate positive regulators of RIG-I signaling. Overexpression of Pumilio proteins and their knockdown augmented and diminished IFN-β promoter activity induced by Newcastle disease virus (NDV), respectively. Both proteins showed a specific association with LGP2, but not with RIG-I or MDA5. Furthermore, all of these components were recruited to NDV-induced antiviral stress granules. Interestingly, biochemical analyses revealed that Pumilio increased double-stranded (ds) RNA binding affinity of LGP2; however, Pumilio was absent in the dsRNA-LGP2 complex, suggesting that Pumilio facilitates viral RNA recognition by LGP2 through its chaperon-like function. Collectively, our results demonstrate an unknown function of Pumilio in viral recognition by LGP2.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="summary">
        <title>Author Summary</title>
        <p>Mammals utilize innate immune system to counteract viral infections. The host pattern-recognition receptors, such as RIG-I-like receptors (RLRs), sense invading pathogens and initiate innate immune responses. RLRs are composed of three RNA helicases, RIG-I, MDA5 and LGP2, and detect a series of RNA viruses, such as influenza or hepatitis C virus, in the cytoplasm. Upon RNA virus infection, RLRs transmit signals through mitochondrial adaptor protein, IPS-1, to activate transcription factor IRF-3/7, resulting in the production of type I interferon (IFN). Type I IFN plays a crucial role in innate immune system by inducing a hundreds of interferon-stimulated genes and its induction is tightly controlled at transcriptional and translational steps. Pumilio proteins are originally identified as translational repressor through direct binding to specific sequence motifs in the 3′ untranslated regions of specific mRNA, and regulate critical biological processes, such as development and differentiation. In this report, we identified human Pumilio proteins, PUM1 and PUM2, as candidate regulators of IFN signaling. Our results demonstrated an unknown function of Pumilio in viral recognition by LGP2.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>This work was supported by independent grants from Japan Science and Technology Agency (PRESTO), from Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT) of Japan (innovative areas, infection competency, no. 24115004 and scientific research A, no. 23249023), from Daiichi Sankyo Foundation of Life Science, and from the Takeda Science Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
        <page-count count="11"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta id="data-availability">
          <meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
          <meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
    <notes>
      <title>Data Availability</title>
      <p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p>
    </notes>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The host innate immune system is the first line of defense against invading pathogens. Pattern-recognition receptors (PRRs) detect pathogen molecules, termed pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs), to initiate innate immune responses <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kawai1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yan1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Ireton1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Schlee1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Viruses invade host cells to replicate their genome and produce new infectious virions. RIG-I-like receptors (RLRs), including RIG-I, MDA5 and LGP2, sense the invasion and generation of viral RNA PAMPs and trigger antiviral responses <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama3" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. In the resting state, RIG-I and MDA5 exist in an autorepressed state, in which N-terminal caspase activation and recruitment domains (CARDs) are masked by the helicase domain; however, upon virus infection, these helicases are activated and oligomerized along with RNAs to form filament-like structures <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Peisley1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Signals from RLRs are relayed to an adaptor, IPS-1 (also known as MAVS, VISA, Cardif) <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Seth1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Meylan1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kawai2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, which then recruits TRAF adaptors, protein kinases TBK-1, IKK-i and IKK complex to activate transcription factors IRF-3, -7 and NF-κB <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Fitzgerald1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Sato1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Knockout mouse studies have shown that RIG-I and MDA5 play a pivotal role in the detection of a series of RNA viruses in vivo <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kato1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. RIG-I detects Sendai virus, NDV and influenza A virus, whereas viruses belong to picornaviridae are sensed by MDA5. Although the mechanism underlying the differential sensing of different viruses by RIG-I and MDA5 is not completely understood, it is proposed that virus specificity comes from the dsRNA length and 5′-end structure of viral RNA <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kato2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Pichlmair1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Hornung1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Schlee2" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. LGP2 was originally thought to be a negative regulator because it lacks CARD, which is crucial for signal transduction. However, knockout and knock-in mouse studies have shown that LGP2 functions as a positive regulator via its ATPase activity <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Satoh1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, consistent with its high affinity binding with dsRNA <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama3" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Takahasi1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Recent studies have reported that RLR signaling is subject to numerous regulations <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kato3" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. TRIM25 positively regulates signaling through interactions with RIG-I and ubiquitination <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Gack1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Riplet (also termed RNF135 and REUL) positively regulates RIG-I signaling through ubiquitination of RIG-I, independent of TRIM25 <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Oshiumi1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. On the other hand, ubiquitin ligases, RNF125 <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Arimoto1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> and A20 <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, and deubiquitinating enzymes, DUBA <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kayagaki1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> and CYLD <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Friedman1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, are reported to function as negative regulators of RIG-I signaling. In addition to the ubiquitination of signaling peptides, involvement of the free ubiquitin chain has been proposed <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Furthermore, accumulating reports suggest the importance of the virus-induced stress response in antiviral innate immunity. In particular, viral infection induces antiviral stress granules (avSGs), including RIG-I, MDA5, LGP2 and viral RNA <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Onomoto1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Ng1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Fung1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Our expression cloning for antiviral signal regulators identified Pumilio proteins. Pumilio proteins (also termed PUF, Pumilio/FBF) are evolutionary conserved from plants to mammals and were originally identified as translational repressors through direct binding to the specific sequence termed the Nanos response element (NRE) present within the 3′-UTR of target mRNAs, thereby regulating various processes: embryonic development, stem cell differentiation, cell cycle and mitochondrial biogenesis <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Forbes1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Parisi1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. In this report, we describe a novel and non-translational function of Pumilio proteins in viral recognition by LGP2.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Pumilio Proteins Positively Regulate RIG-I Signaling in Response to NDV Infection</title>
        <p>We previously identified RIG-I by expression cloning of the human cDNA library using virus-inducible reporter gene activity as the readout <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. This strategy allowed us to identify other candidate regulators of antiviral signaling, Pumilio proteins. Pumilio proteins share a highly conserved C-terminal Pumilio-homology domain (PUM-HD) <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. In humans, two genes encoding PUM1 and PUM2 exist. Human PUM1 and PUM2 have similar domain structures and have high homology in their primary structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). It was reported that PUM-HD is responsible for sequence-specific RNA binding, whereas the function of the N-terminal portion is unknown. We obtained two independent clones encoding full-length PUM1 and one clone of PUM2 (missing coding amino acids 1-368) by expression cloning. We constructed expression vectors for full-length PUM1 and PUM2 and examined their effect on <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter activity in L929 cells. Overexpression of PUM1 and PUM2 augmented <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter activity induced by NDV infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). As <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter is regulated by both IRFs and NF-κB, we investigated whether PUM1 and PUM2 affect promoter activity regulated by IRFs (p-55C1B) and NF-κB (p-55A2). PUM1 and PUM2 augmented p-55C1BLuc activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1C</xref>), as well as p-55A2Luc activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1D</xref>), suggesting that PUM1 and PUM2 mediate the activation of both IRFs and NF-κB transcription factors. In accord with the increased IFN promoter activity, NDV RNA replication was suppressed by the overexpression of PUM1 and PUM2 24 h after NDV infection, suggesting that PUM1 and PUM2 share antiviral potential (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1E</xref>). It is known that translational repression by PUM-HD depends on H850 in PUM2 <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Friend1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> and this residue was conserved between PUM1 (H972) and PUM2. Therefore, we constructed expression vectors for their alanine mutants and tested their antiviral activity. Interestingly, these mutants markedly enhanced NDV-induced <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1F</xref>), suggesting that the enhancing function is independent of the translational repression function of Pumilio proteins.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g001</object-id>
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Overexpression of PUM1 and PUM2 results in enhanced NDV-induced <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter activity.</title>
            <p>(A) Schematic representation of PUM1 and PUM2. PUM-HD shows high sequence similarity between PUM1 and PUM2. Positions of histidine (H) residues critical for NRE recognition are indicated. (B–D) L929 cells were transfected with the indicated reporter gene, p-125Luc (B), p-55C1BLuc (C) or p-55A2Luc (D), and pRL-tk, together with the expression vector for PUM1 or PUM2. The cells were stimulated by NDV infection for 9 h and subjected to a dual-luciferase assay. (E) L929 cells were transfected with an expression vector for PUM1 or PUM2. The cells were infected with NDV for 24 h, and then NDV RNA levels were determined by quantitative RT-PCR. (F) L929 cells were transfected with p-125Luc and pRL-tk, together with the expression vector for wt and histidine mutants of PUM1 or PUM2 as indicated. The cells were stimulated by NDV infection and subjected to a dual-luciferase assay. Data are from one representative of at least two independent experiments; means and S.D. of duplicate experiments are shown (*p&lt;0.05).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g001"/>
        </fig>
        <p>To further investigate the function of PUM1 and PUM2 in IFN induction, we performed siRNA-mediated knockdown. siRNA targeting for human PUM1 and PUM2 suppressed the expression of endogenous PUM1 and PUM2 protein, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). As expected, knockdown of endogenous PUM1 or PUM2 impaired the mRNA expression of <italic>IFNB1</italic> and <italic>CXCL10</italic>, one of the IFN-stimulated genes, in response to NDV infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g002">Figure. 2B and C</xref>). We also examined IRF-3 phosphorylation in the PUM knockdown cells, as well as IRF-3 dimerization. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s001">Figure S1A and B</xref>, both phosphorylation and dimerization of IRF-3 were impaired in the Pumilio knockdown cells. Furthermore, the production of IFN-β protein was also reduced by PUM1 or PUM2 knockdown upon NDV infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). Conversely, NDV RNA copies were increased by knockdown of PUM1 or PUM2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g002">Figure 2E</xref>). To rule out the possibility that Pumilio proteins regulate NDV-induced IFN production through affecting the expression level of RLRs, we examined the basal level of RLRs in the Pumilio knockdown cells. The knockdown of Pumilio proteins did not affect the basal and IFN-induced expression level of RLRs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s002">Figure S2</xref>). Finally, we also tested synthetic oligonucleotides, such as poly I:C, <italic>in vitro</italic>-transcribed 5′pppRNA and poly dA:dT. In contrast to NDV infection, the knockdown of Pumilio proteins did not affect the IFN production in response to these stimuli (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s001">Figure S1C</xref>). These results suggest that PUM1 and PUM2 positively regulate antiviral responses against NDV by controlling IFN production.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g002</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Knockdown of PUM1 and PUM2 downregulates NDV-induced gene activation.</title>
            <p>(A–C) HEK293T cells were transfected with control siRNA (siN.C.) or siRNA targeting human PUM1 or PUM2 for 48 h. Knockdown efficiency was confirmed by immunoblotting with anti-PUM1, anti-PUM2 and anti-β-actin antibodies (A). The cells were infected with NDV for 9 h, and <italic>IFNB</italic> (B) and <italic>CXCL10</italic> (C) mRNA levels were determined by quantitative RT-PCR. (D and E) HEK293T cells were transfected with control siRNA or siRNA targeting PUM1 or PUM2 for 48 h. The cells were infected with NDV for 24 h. The culture media were collected and subjected to IFN-β ELISA (D). Total cellular RNA was extracted and subjected to qRT-PCR for NDV RNA (E). Data are from one representative of at least two independent experiments; means and S.D. of duplicate experiments are shown (*p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g002"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Physical Association of PUM1 and PUM2 with LGP2</title>
        <p>It has been shown that NDV infection is mainly detected by one of the RLRs, RIG-I <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kato1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. TRIM25 regulates the activation of RIG-I through ubiquitination of RIG-I <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Gack1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In addition, IPS-1 is an adaptor protein essential for RLR signaling <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Kumar1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Sun1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. To elucidate the regulatory mechanism, the physical association of full-length PUM1 and PUM2 with RLRs, TRIM25 and IPS-1 was examined by co-immunoprecipitation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3A</xref>, LGP2, but not RIG-I nor MDA5 was precipitated with PUM1 or PUM2. No interaction of PUM1 and PUM2 with TRIM25 and IPS-1 was detectable, indicating that PUM1 and PUM2 selectively interact with LGP2. We also investigated whether PUM1 and PUM2 interacted with each other. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s003">Figure S3</xref>, PUM2 associated with PUM1. This result suggested that PUM1 and PUM2 exist as heteromeric complex.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g003</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Physical association of PUM1 and PUM2 with LGP2 and involvement of N- and C-terminal domains of PUM1 and PUM2 in IFN induction.</title>
            <p>(A) HEK293T cells were transfected with expression vector HA-tagged RIG-I, MDA5, LGP2 or IPS-1, together with Flag-tagged PUM1 or PUM2. For TRIM25, HEK293T cells were transfected with Flag-tagged PUM1 or PUM2, together with Myc-tagged TRIM25. The cell lysates were subjected to anti-Flag or anti-c-Myc immunoprecipitation (IP), followed by Western blotting. Western blotting result of total lysate is shown as a reference (Input, 5%). (B) L929 cells were transfected with control shRNA construct (pU6i-control) or shRNA for LGP2 (pU6i-LGP2#1 and #2) and expression vectors for PUM1 or PUM2 and p-125Luc reporter and pRLtk as indicated. The cells were stimulated by infection with NDV for 9 h and subjected to the dual luciferase assay. (C) Schematic representation of PUM1 or PUM2 deletion mutants used for IP experiments. (D) HEK293T cells were transfected with expression vectors for the indicated proteins and for HA-tagged LGP2. The cell lysates were subjected to IP with anti-Flag, followed by immunoblotting with anti-HA. Immunoblotting result of total lysate is shown as a reference (Input, 5%). (E) L929 cells were transfected with expression vectors for the wild type or mutant of PUM1 or PUM2 and p-125Luc reporter and pRL-tk as indicated. Cells were stimulated by infection with NDV for 9 h and subjected to the dual luciferase assay. Data are from one representative of at least two independent experiments (means and s.d. of duplicate experiments.)</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g003"/>
        </fig>
        <p>LGP2 was shown to function as a positive regulator of RIG-I- and MDA5-mediated antiviral responses <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Satoh1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Specific associations between LGP2 and PUM1 and PUM2 prompted us to investigate the involvement of LGP2 in Pumilio-mediated transactivation. L929 cells were transfected with the expression vector for shRNA either non-targeted or targeted to LGP2, then transactivation by PUM1 or PUM2 was examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3B</xref>). Knockdown of LGP2 markedly attenuated transactivation by PUM1 or PUM2, suggesting that the observed physical interaction between LGP2 and PUM1 and PUM2 is relevant to the biological activity of these regulators.</p>
        <p>To elucidate the involvement of C-terminal PUM-HD in the association between LGP2 and PUM1 and PUM2, expression vectors for PUM-HD (PUM1dN and PUM2dN) and the rest (PUM1dC and PUM2dC) were constructed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3C</xref>). Co-immunoprecipitation using the mutants revealed that LGP2 interacted with PUM1 and PUM2 lacking PUM-HD as strongly as with the respective full-length proteins, while interaction with PUM-HD (dN constructs) was undetectable. Consistent with the lack of interaction between PUM-HD and LGP2, PUM1H972A and PUM2H850A efficiently co-precipitated with LGP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). We also determined the domain of LGP2 responsible for the interaction with Pumilio proteins. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s004">Figure S4</xref>, LGP2 helicase domain is important for LGP2 to interact with Pumilio proteins. These results suggest that PUM1 and PUM2 interact with LGP2 through the N-terminal domain.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Involvement of Both N- and C-Terminal Domains of PUM1 and PUM2 in the Activation of Antiviral Response</title>
        <p>To further elucidate the mechanism of transactivation by PUM1 and PUM2, full-length and dN and dC mutants were tested for <italic>IFNB</italic> promoter activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3E</xref>). Full-length PUM1 and PUM2 but neither dC nor dN enhanced NDV-induced IFN-β reporter activity, indicating that both PUM-HD and the N-terminal portion are necessary for transactivation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>Co-localization of PUM1 and PUM2 in avSGs upon NDV Infection</title>
        <p>It is reported that PUM1 and PUM2 are recruited to stress granules (SGs) upon stress responses, such as oxidative stress or starvation <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Vessey1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Previously, we reported that virus infection induces SG-like aggregates containing SG markers, RLR and several antiviral proteins, and termed the aggregate antiviral SGs (avSGs) <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Onomoto1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. avSGs are thought to function as a platform for detection of viral RNA by RLR and as action sites of antiviral proteins. We determined the cellular localization of PUM1 and PUM2 by immunostaining. In uninfected cells, PUM1 and PUM2 localized diffusely in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). NDV infection induced co-localization of PUM1 and PUM2 into cytoplasmic speckle-like aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4A</xref>). We confirmed that a SG marker, TIAR, localized with the speckles containing PUM1 in NDV-infected cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4B</xref>); therefore, these aggregates correspond to avSG. We also confirmed that LGP2 localized in the avSG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4C</xref>)</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g004</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Cellular localization of PUM1, PUM2 and LGP2.</title>
            <p>(A–C) HeLa cells were mock-treated or infected with NDV for 9 h, fixed and stained with the indicated antibodies. Nuclei were stained with DAPI. (D) HEK293T cells were transfected with the expression vector for Flag-PUM1dN or Flag-PUM2dN for 48 h and mock treated or infected with NDV for 9 h. The cells were stained with anti-Flag or anti-TIAR.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g004"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Both N- and C-terminal domains of Pumilio proteins are required for transactivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3E</xref>) and the N-terminal domain is responsible for interaction with LGP2. We therefore explored the function of C-terminal PUM-HD in terms of cellular localization. Flag-tagged PUM1dN and PUM2dN were expressed in cells and the cells were infected with NDV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4D</xref>). In uninfected cells, these mutants were diffusely accumulated in nuclei and cytoplasm; however, upon viral infection, these proteins localized with avSG, suggesting that PUM-HD is responsible for the localization of PUM proteins in avSG. We also determined the cellular localization of PUM1dC and PUM2dC. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s005">Figure S5D</xref>, PUM1dC diffusely localized in the cytoplasm of NDV-infected cells, whereas PUM2dC was recruited to the avSGs in response to NDV infection.</p>
        <p>To explore the possibility that PUM1 and PUM2 are required for avSG formation, the effect of knockdown of PUM1 and PUM2 on avSG formation was examined. As shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s005">Figure S5A</xref>, knockdown of PUM1 or PUM2 expression did not alter avSG induction in NDV-infected cells, suggesting that PUM1 and PUM2 do not notably affect avSG assembly. We also examined the recruitment of Pumilio proteins and LGP2 in LGP2 KO cells and Pumilio knockdown cells, respectively. The knockdown of Pumilio proteins did not affect the localization of LGP2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s005">Figure S5B</xref>). Furthermore, Pumilio proteins were recruited to the avSGs in response to NDV in LGP2 KO cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s005">Figure S5C</xref>), indicating that Pumilio proteins were not involved in the recruitment of LGP2 to the avSGs and vice versa.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>PUM1 and PUM2 Augment dsRNA Binding Activity of LGP2</title>
        <p>Finally, to elucidate the mechanism of the enhancement of IFN gene expression by PUM1 and PUM2, we examined dsRNA binding activity of LGP2 in the presence or absence of PUM1 and PUM2. Electrophoresis mobility shift assay (EMSA) was performed using synthetic dsRNA and recombinant proteins. LGP2 bound to the probe, resulting in a slow-migrating complex. We confirmed that this slow-migrating band was a complex of the probe and LGP2 by a supershift experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g005">Figure 5A</xref>). PUM1 and PUM2 exhibited very weak binding with the probe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). Interestingly, the LGP2-dsRNA complex intensity was increased with the addition of PUM1 and PUM2; however, the mobility of the complex is hardly affected. Dissociation constant for LGP2 in the absence and presence of PUM1 or PUM2 was determined by Scatchard plot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). The Kd value indicates that PUM1 and PUM2 increased the dsRNA-binding activity of LGP2. We also purified recombinant PUM1 and PUM2 lacking PUM-HD (PUM1dC and PUM2dC) and subjected them to a binding assay (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s006">Figure S6A and B</xref>). Essentially similar results were obtained, indicating that the N-terminal domain of PUM1 and PUM2 is sufficient for increasing the dsRNA binding affinity of LGP2.</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g005</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>
<italic>In vitro</italic> binding assay of dsRNA and LGP2.</title>
            <p>(A and B) Recombinant LGP2 proteins (0.125 µg) were mixed with <sup>32</sup>P-labeled dsRNA in the presence of a control mouse IgG or anti-Flag antibody (0.1, 0.2 or 0.4 µg) (A) or in the presence or absence of Pumilio proteins (0.1, 0.3 or 0.5 µg) (B). The mixture were separated by acrylamide gel and the radioactivity was analyzed. (C) LGP2 dsRNA binding affinities in the absence (filled circles) or presence of PUM1 (open square) or PUM2 (filled triangle) were analyzed and the Kd values were determined.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g005"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Because the complex mobility in EMSA did not change in the presence or absence of Pumilio proteins, we examined whether the association between Pumilio proteins and LGP2 is affected in the presence or absence of dsRNA. Recombinant PUM1 and PUM2 proteins produced as GST fusion were mixed with recombinant Flag-tagged LGP2 in the presence or absence of dsRNA and pulled down with glutathione Sepharose (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s007">Figure S7</xref>). In the absence of dsRNA, we confirmed the association between PUM1 and PUM2 with LGP2; however, in the presence of dsRNA, this association was undetectable, suggesting that upon binding of LGP2 with dsRNA, PUM1 and PUM2 are released from the complex, consistent with the EMSA results. Taken together, we hypothesized that Pumilio proteins changed the conformation of LGP2 through physical associations to increase its dsRNA binding affinity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g006">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="ppat-1004417-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004417.g006</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Hypothetical model for regulation of LGP2 by PUM1 and PUM2 in avSG.</title>
            <p>N-terminal domain of PUM1 and PUM2 possess intrinsic affinity to LGP2. This interaction confers higher binding affinity of LGP2 to viral dsRNA. Conformational change of LGP2 is one of the explanations for the increased affinity. Viral infection such as NDV induces avSGs and accumulation of viral dsRNA, LGP2, PUM1, PUM2 and other avSG markers into avSGs. Within avSG, dsRNA interacts with LGP2/PUM complex, producing LGP2/dsRNA complex and Pumilio proteins are released from the complex. Then, LGP2 triggers signals presumably in cooperation with RIG-I or MDA5. X: potential interacting partner of C-terminal domain of PUM1 and PUM2 determining their avSG localization.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1004417.g006"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We found that Pumilio proteins enhanced NDV-induced activation of the <italic>IFNB</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Knockdown of PUM1 and PUM2 respectively attenuated gene activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g002">Figure 2</xref>), suggesting that PUM1 and PUM2 function non-redundantly. Furthermore, PUM1 and PUM2 accelerated the activation of IRFs and NF-κB transcription factors, suggesting their action in signal transduction, rather than post-transcriptional steps. Interestingly, PUM1 and PUM2 selectively interact with LGP2 but not with RIG-I, MDA5, IPS-1 or TRIM25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). LGP2 knockdown diminished <italic>IFNB</italic> gene induction augmented by PUM1 and PUM2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3B</xref>), suggesting that PUM1 and PUM2 augment viral RNA sensing mediated by LGP2. It was shown that LGP2 does not participate in the detection of synthetic oligonucleotides, such as poly I:C or in vitro-transcribed 5′pppRNA <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Satoh1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Consistent with this, the knockdown of PUM1 and PUM2 did not affect the IFN production induced by poly I:C, 5′pppRNA or poly dA:dT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s001">Figure S1C</xref>). LGP2 exhibits strong binding activity to dsRNA; however, it lacks CARD, through which the signal is relayed to IPS-1. Therefore, it has been hypothesized that LGP2 cooperates with either RIG-I or MDA5. Our findings uncovered a new mechanism of sensing viral RNA by LGP2, PUM1 and PUM2.</p>
      <p>Deletion analyses of PUM1 and PUM2 revealed that both N- and C-terminal regions are required for up-regulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3E</xref>). The N-terminal region is sufficient for interaction with LGP2 and to increase the binding affinity to dsRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g003">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s007">S7</xref>). The C-terminal region, also termed PUM-HD, is sufficient for translocation to avSG upon viral infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g004">Figure 4D</xref>), although the underlying mechanism is unknown.</p>
      <p>PUM1 and PUM2 have been known to regulate mRNA translation through sequence-specific recognition of NRE within the target mRNA. It was proposed that PUM-HD consists of 8 repeats of the module and each module recognizes a single nucleotide in NRE <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. It was shown that single amino acid substitution is sufficient to abolish NRE binding and the translational regulation of PUM2 <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Friend1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. On the other hand, we found that NRE binding-deficient mutants (PUM1H972A and PUM2H850A) augment virus-induced signaling as strongly as the respective wt protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g001">Figure 1F</xref>), suggesting that Pumilio proteins facilitate two independent biological functions in translational and antiviral signal regulation. It is tempting to speculate that the repeated modules recognize component(s) associated with avSGs.</p>
      <p>Concerning the molecular mechanism, we found that PUM1 and PUM2 increased dsRNA binding affinity of LGP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g005">Figure 5</xref>). However, interestingly, we did not observe the ternary complex of dsRNA, LGP2 and PUM1 or PUM2; furthermore, the interaction between LGP2 and PUM1 or PUM2 was lost when dsRNA was added (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1004417.s007">Figure S7</xref>). We therefore hypothesize that PUM1 and PUM2 have a cooperative function with LGP2 through physical association to increase its binding affinity to dsRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1004417-g006">Figure 6</xref>). It has been shown that LGP2 facilitates RIG-I- and MDA5-mediated signaling <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Satoh1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Also it was shown that LGP2 and RIG-I interact <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Saito1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. In light of these observations, it is probable that increased dsRNA binding of LGP2 facilitates RLR signaling.</p>
      <p>Viral infection induces the formation of avSGs, including conventional SG markers, RIG-I, MDA5, LGP2, PKR, OAS, RNase L, DHX36, TRIM25, PUM1 and PUM2, some of which are critical in sensing non-self viral RNA and triggering antiviral signaling. Unlike SGs induced by physical stress, viral RNA is accumulated in virus-induced avSGs <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Onomoto1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Ng1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoo1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. In summary, these results support the idea that avSGs act as a critical platform for sensing and discriminating viral RNA as a defense mechanism against viral infections. Although the IFN system is absent in plants, Pumilio proteins participate in the antiviral response in plants <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Huh1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, suggesting that the principal mechanism of sensing non-self RNA is evolutionarily conserved.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s4a">
        <title>Cell Culture and Reagents</title>
        <p>L929 cells were maintained in minimal essential medium (MEM) (nacalai tesque,) containing 5% fetal bovine serum (FBS). HEK293T and HeLa cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) (nacalai tesque) containing 10% FBS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4b">
        <title>Plasmid Constructs</title>
        <p>The p-125 Luc, p-55C1B Luc, p-55A2 Luc, pU6i and pU6i-shLGP2 have been described previously <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama3" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. pEF-Flag-PUM1 and PUM2 was obtained by subcloning cDNA into the empty vector pEF-BOS. Mutants were generated using the KOD -plus- Mutagenesis Kit (TOYOBO). TRIM25 cDNA was purchased from OriGene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4c">
        <title>RNAi</title>
        <p>Negative control siRNA and siRNA targeting PUM1 or PUM2 were purchased from BONAC. siRNAs were transfected using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. After 48 h, the cells were stimulated as indicated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4d">
        <title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title>
        <p>Total RNA was isolated using Sepasol reagent (nacalai tesque), treated with DNase I (Roche) and subjected to reverse transcription using a High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems). mRNA levels were monitored with the StepOne plus Real Time PCR System and TaqMan Fast Universal Master Mix (Applied Biosystems). TaqMan primer and probe sets for 18S rRNA, human IFNB1 and human CXCL10 were purchased from Applied Biosystems. The RNA copy numbers of the gene of interest were normalized to that of internal 18S rRNA. NDV replication levels were monitored with Fast SYBR PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) using the primers specific for the NDV F gene.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4e">
        <title>Antibodies</title>
        <p>Anti-Flag and anti-HA antibody were purchased from Sigma and Cell Signaling Technology, respectively. Anti-GST anti-β-actin, anti-c-Myc, anti-Pumilio1, anti-Pumilio2 and anti-TIAR antibodies were from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA). Anti-IRF-3, anti-RIG-I, anti-MDA5 and anti-LGP2 antibody were described previously <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Onomoto1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Mori1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Alexa 488- and 594-conjugated anti-rabbit or anti-goat IgG antibodies (Invitrogen) were used as secondary antibodies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4f">
        <title>Immunostaining</title>
        <p>The cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (nacalai tesque) for 10 min, permeabilized with an acetone: methanol (1∶1) solution, and blocked with 5 mg/ml bovine serum albumin (BSA) (nacalai tesque) for 30 min. The cells were incubated with the indicated primary antibodies overnight at 4°C, and then incubated with the relevant Alexa-conjugated antibodies at room temperature for 1 h. Nuclei were stained with DAPI (nacalai tesque). The cells were analyzed with a microscope (Leica microsystems).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4g">
        <title>Luciferase Assay</title>
        <p>Luciferase assay was performed as described previously <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama3" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega) was used according to the manufacturer's protocol.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4h">
        <title>Co-immunoprecipitation</title>
        <p>The indicated plasmids were transfected with HEK293T cells using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). The cell lysates were incubated with anti-Flag or anti-c-Myc antibody on ice for 30 min. The pre-washed Protein G Sepharose (GE Healthcare) was added to the mixture, which was rotated at 4°C overnight. After washing, the precipitates were eluted and separated by SPS-PAGE, followed by Western blotting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4i">
        <title>Viruses</title>
        <p>NDV was grown in the allantonic cavities of 9-day-old embryonated eggs. The cells were mock treated or infected with NDV at 37°C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4j">
        <title>Native PAGE for IRF-3 Dimer Detection</title>
        <p>The cell lysates were subjected to Native PAGE and Western blotting as described previously <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Mori1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4k">
        <title>Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)</title>
        <p>The cell culture supernatants were collected and subjected to ELISA with a human IFN-β ELISA kit (TORAY, Tokyo, Japan) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4l">
        <title>Recombinant Proteins</title>
        <p>Recombinant LGP2 was produced as 6xHis-LGP2 fusion using baculovirus and High Five cells. 6xHis-LGP2 was bound to Ni Sepharose 6 Fast Flow (GE Healthcare), and then eluted by elution buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, 1.5 mM DTT and 500 mM imidazole.</p>
        <p>The intact PUM1 and PUM2 were amplified by PCR and inserted into a modified pGex-6p-1 vector (GE Healthcare). The C-terminal His6-tag was inserted using a KOD plus mutagenesis kit (TOYOBO) to produce N-terminal GST and C-terminal His6 tagged proteins. The vectors were transformed into an <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) strain. Bacteria were first grown at 37°C in LB medium containing 100 µg/ml ampicillin at 160 rpm. Protein expression was induced by the addition of 0.1 mM IPTG when the absorbance at 600 nm was approximately 0.4. The cells were then grown at 16°C for 16 h at 90 rpm. The cells were harvested by centrifugation and were suspended in a lysis buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 500 mM NaCl, and 20 mM imidazole supplemented with protease Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche Diagnostics) and were lysed via sonication and centrifugation. The supernatant was suspended in Ni Sepharose 6 Fast Flow (GE Healthcare), then the resin was washed with lysis buffer, and the protein was eluted by elution buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 500 mM NaCl, and 500 mM imidazole. The protein was diluted by phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and mixed with Glutathione Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare) for 16 h. The mixture was washed with PBS and proteins were eluted by a buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, and 20 mM reduced glutathione.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4m">
        <title>Electrophoresis Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA)</title>
        <p>Recombinant LGP2 proteins were mixed with <sup>32</sup>P-labeled synthetic dsRNA (25/25c) <xref rid="ppat.1004417-Takahasi2" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> in a reaction mixture (20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1.5 mM DTT) in the presence or absence of recombinant Pumilio proteins. After incubation at 37°C for 15 min, the reaction mixture was applied to a 15% acrylamide gel (TBE buffer) and the radioactivity was detected with an Image Analyzer (FUJIFILM, Tokyo, Japan).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4n">
        <title>GST-Pull Down Assay</title>
        <p>Recombinant LGP2 proteins were mixed with Pumilio proteins in a reaction mixture (20 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1.5 mM DTT) in the presence or absence of synthetic dsRNA (25/25c) at 37°C for 15 min. Pre-washed Glutathione Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare) was added to the mixture and incubated at room temperature for 1 h. After washing, the precipitates were separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by Western blotting.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5">
      <title>Supporting Information</title>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s001">
        <label>Figure S1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>PUM1 and PUM2 positively regulate NDV-induced IFN induction.(A-C) HEK293T cells were transfected with control siRNA or siRNA targeting PUM1 or PUM2 for 48 h. The cells were mock-treated or infected with NDV for 7, 8 or 9 h. The cell lysates were separated by Native PAGE, followed by immunoblotting with anti-pIRF-3 (A) or anti-IRF-3 (B) antibodies. The cells were infected or transfected with the indicated nucleotides for 24 h. The culture media were collected and subjected to IFN-β ELISA (C).</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s001.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s002">
        <label>Figure S2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>The knockdown of Pumilio proteins did not affect the expression level of RLRs. HEK293T cells were transfected with control siRNA or siRNA targeting human PUM1 or PUM2 for 48 h. The cells were mock-treated or treated with human IFN-β (1000 U/ml) for 24 h. The cell lysates were subjected to SDS-PAGE, followed by immunoblotting with anti-RIG-I, anti-MDA5, anti-LGP2 or anti-β-actin antibodies.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s002.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s003">
        <label>Figure S3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Physical interaction between PUM1 and PUM2. HEK293T cells were transfected with a HA-tagged PUM2 together with Flag-tagged PUM1. The cell lysates were subjected to IP with anti-Flag, followed by Western blotting.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s003.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s004">
        <label>Figure S4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>PUM1 and PUM2 interacted with LGP2 through its helicase domain. HEK293T cells were transfected with a HA-tagged LGP2 full-length, helicase domain (dCTD) or CTD together with Flag-tagged PUM1 or PUM2. The cell lysates were subjected to IP with anti-Flag, followed by Western blotting.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s004.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s005">
        <label>Figure S5</label>
        <caption>
          <p>PUM1 and PUM2 are not required for NDV-induced avSG formation. (A and B) HeLa cells were transfected with control siRNA or siRNA targeting PUM1 or PUM2. After 48 h, the cells were mock-infected or infected with NDV for 9 h. The cells were then fixed and stained with anti-TIAR and anti-NDV NP (A) or anti-TIAR and anti-LGP2 (B) antibodies. (C) LGP2 WT or KO cells were infected with NDV for 9 h. The cells were fixed and stained with anti-PUM1 and anti-PUM2 (Upper) or anti-PUM1 and anti-TIAR (Lower) antibodies. (D) HEK293T cells were transfected with Flag-tagged PUM1dC or PUM2dC for 48 h and infected with NDV for 9 h. The cells were fixed and stained with anti-Flag and anti-TIAR antibodies.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s005.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s006">
        <label>Figure S6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>
<italic>In vitro</italic> binding assay of dsRNA and LGP2 in the presence or absence of PUM1dC or PUM2dC. (A) Recombinant LGP2 (0.125 µg) proteins were mixed with <sup>32</sup>P-labeled dsRNA in the presence or absence of Pumilio proteins lacking PUM-HD (PUM1dC and PUM2dC, 0.5 µg). The mixture was separated by acrylamide gel and the radioactivity was analyzed. (B) LGP2 dsRNA binding affinities in the absence (filled circles) or presence of PUM1dC (open square) or PUM2dC (filled triangle) were analyzed and the Kd values were determined.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s006.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1004417.s007">
        <label>Figure S7</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Association between LGP2 with PUM1 or PUM2 in the presence or absence of dsRNA. Recombinant LGP2 proteins (0.5 µg) were mixed with Pumilio proteins (0.5 µg) in the presence or absence of dsRNA (25/25c, 0.4 µg). The mixture (10 µl) was then incubated with Glutathione Sepharose. After washing, the precipitates were eluted and separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by Western blotting.</p>
          <p>(PDF)</p>
        </caption>
        <media xlink:href="ppat.1004417.s007.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank T. Sakaguchi (Hiroshima University) for the anti-NP antibody.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kawai1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Toll-like receptors and their crosstalk with other innate receptors in infection and immunity</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616434</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama1">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>RNA recognition and signal transduction by RIG-I-like receptors</article-title>. <source>Immunological reviews</source>
<volume>227</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19120475</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Yan1">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Intrinsic antiviral immunity</article-title>. <source>Nature immunology</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22344284</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Ireton1">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ireton</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>M</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>RIG-I like receptors in antiviral immunity and therapeutic applications</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>906</fpage>–<lpage>919</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21994761</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Schlee1">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schlee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The chase for the RIG-I ligand—recent advances</article-title>. <source>Molecular therapy: the journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1254</fpage>–<lpage>1262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20461060</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama2">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Natsukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shinobu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The RNA helicase RIG-I has an essential function in double-stranded RNA-induced innate antiviral responses</article-title>. <source>Nature immunology</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>730</fpage>–<lpage>737</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208624</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Yoneyama3">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imaizumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyagishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Shared and unique functions of the DExD/H-box helicases RIG-I, MDA5, and LGP2 in antiviral innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Journal of immunology</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>2851</fpage>–<lpage>2858</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Wu1">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peisley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for dsRNA recognition, filament formation, and antiviral signal activation by MDA5</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>152</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23273991</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Peisley1">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Peisley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>RIG-I forms signaling-competent filaments in an ATP-dependent, ubiquitin-independent manner</article-title>. <source>Molecular cell</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23993742</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Xu1">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>VISA is an adapter protein required for virus-triggered IFN-beta signaling</article-title>. <source>Molecular cell</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153868</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Seth1">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ea</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of MAVS, a mitochondrial antiviral signaling protein that activates NF-kappaB and IRF 3</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16125763</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Meylan1">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Meylan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moradpour</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Cardif is an adaptor protein in the RIG-I antiviral pathway and is targeted by hepatitis C virus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>437</volume>: <fpage>1167</fpage>–<lpage>1172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177806</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kawai2">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coban</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>IPS-1, an adaptor triggering RIG-I- and Mda5-mediated type I interferon induction</article-title>. <source>Nature immunology</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>981</fpage>–<lpage>988</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16127453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kumar1">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Essential role of IPS-1 in innate immune responses against RNA viruses</article-title>. <source>The Journal of experimental medicine</source>
<volume>203</volume>: <fpage>1795</fpage>–<lpage>1803</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785313</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Sun1">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The specific and essential role of MAVS in antiviral innate immune responses</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>633</fpage>–<lpage>642</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713980</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Fitzgerald1">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McWhirter</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Faia</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Latz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>IKKepsilon and TBK1 are essential components of the IRF3 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Nature immunology</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12692549</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Sato1">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suemori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asagiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Distinct and essential roles of transcription factors IRF-3 and IRF-7 in response to viruses for IFN-alpha/beta gene induction</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>539</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11070172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kato1">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Differential roles of MDA5 and RIG-I helicases in the recognition of RNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>441</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625202</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kato2">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikamo-Satoh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Length-dependent recognition of double-stranded ribonucleic acids by retinoic acid-inducible gene-I and melanoma differentiation-associated gene 5</article-title>. <source>The Journal of experimental medicine</source>
<volume>205</volume>: <fpage>1601</fpage>–<lpage>1610</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18591409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Pichlmair1">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pichlmair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naslund</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liljestrom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>RIG-I-mediated antiviral responses to single-stranded RNA bearing 5′-phosphates</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>314</volume>: <fpage>997</fpage>–<lpage>1001</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17038589</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Hornung1">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellegast</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brzozka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>5′-Triphosphate RNA is the ligand for RIG-I</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>314</volume>: <fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>997</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17038590</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Schlee2">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schlee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hagmann</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wimmenauer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recognition of 5′ triphosphate by RIG-I helicase requires short blunt double-stranded RNA as contained in panhandle of negative-strand virus</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19576794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Satoh1">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumagai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>LGP2 is a positive regulator of RIG-I- and MDA5-mediated antiviral responses</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1512</fpage>–<lpage>1517</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080593</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Takahasi1">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Takahasi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumeta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuduki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shigemoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Solution structures of cytosolic RNA sensor MDA5 and LGP2 C-terminal domains: identification of the RNA recognition loop in RIG-I-like receptors</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>
<volume>284</volume>: <fpage>17465</fpage>–<lpage>17474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19380577</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kato3">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahasi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>RIG-I-like receptors: cytoplasmic sensors for non-self RNA</article-title>. <source>Immunological reviews</source>
<volume>243</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21884169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Gack1">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gack</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>TRIM25 RING-finger E3 ubiquitin ligase is essential for RIG-I-mediated antiviral activity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>446</volume>: <fpage>916</fpage>–<lpage>920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392790</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Gao1">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>REUL is a novel E3 ubiquitin ligase and stimulator of retinoic-acid-inducible gene-I</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e5760</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19484123</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Oshiumi1">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Oshiumi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Riplet/RNF135, a RING finger protein, ubiquitinates RIG-I to promote interferon-beta induction during the early phase of viral infection</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>
<volume>284</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>–<lpage>817</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017631</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Arimoto1">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Arimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hishiki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Negative regulation of the RIG-I signaling by the ubiquitin ligase RNF125</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>7500</fpage>–<lpage>7505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17460044</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Lin1">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakhaei</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharif-Askari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Negative regulation of the retinoic acid-inducible gene I-induced antiviral state by the ubiquitin-editing protein A20</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>
<volume>281</volume>: <fpage>2095</fpage>–<lpage>2103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Kayagaki1">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kayagaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phung</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>DUBA: a deubiquitinase that regulates type I interferon production</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>318</volume>: <fpage>1628</fpage>–<lpage>1632</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991829</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Friedman1">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legarda-Addison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The tumour suppressor CYLD is a negative regulator of RIG-I-mediated antiviral response</article-title>. <source>EMBO reports</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>930</fpage>–<lpage>936</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18636086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Jiang1">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinch</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brautigam</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ubiquitin-induced oligomerization of the RNA sensors RIG-I and MDA5 activates antiviral innate immune response</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>959</fpage>–<lpage>973</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22705106</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Onomoto1">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Onomoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jogi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Critical role of an antiviral stress granule containing RIG-I and PKR in viral detection and innate immunity</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e43031</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22912779</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Ng1">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jogi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onomoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Encephalomyocarditis virus disrupts stress granules, the critical platform for triggering antiviral innate immune responses</article-title>. <source>Journal of virology</source>
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>9511</fpage>–<lpage>9522</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23785203</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Fung1">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Production of a dominant-negative fragment due to G3BP1 cleavage contributes to the disruption of mitochondria-associated protective stress granules during CVB3 infection</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e79546</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260247</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Yoo1">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahasi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ouda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Onomoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>DHX36 enhances RIG-I signaling by facilitating PKR-mediated antiviral stress granule formation</article-title>. <source>PLoS pathogens</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1004012</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24651521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Murata1">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Binding of pumilio to maternal hunchback mRNA is required for posterior patterning in Drosophila embryos</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>80</volume>: <fpage>747</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7889568</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Forbes1">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Nanos and Pumilio have critical roles in the development and function of Drosophila germline stem cells</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<volume>125</volume>: <fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9435288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Parisi1">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The Drosophila pumilio gene encodes two functional protein isoforms that play multiple roles in germline development, gonadogenesis, oogenesis and embryogenesis</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>153</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471709</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Dubnau1">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barditch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gossweiler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The staufen/pumilio pathway is involved in Drosophila long-term memory</article-title>. <source>Current biology: CB</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12593794</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Chen1">
        <label>42</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uyhazi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Pumilio 1 suppresses multiple activators of p53 to safeguard spermatogenesis</article-title>. <source>Current biology: CB</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22342750</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Wang1">
        <label>43</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Modular recognition of RNA by a human pumilio-homology domain</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202039</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Friend1">
        <label>44</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kroll-Conner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A conserved PUF-Ago-eEF1A complex attenuates translation elongation</article-title>. <source>Nature structural &amp; molecular biology</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Vessey1">
        <label>45</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vessey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaccani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Dendritic localization of the translational repressor Pumilio 2 and its contribution to dendritic stress granules</article-title>. <source>The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>6496</fpage>–<lpage>6508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775137</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Saito1">
        <label>46</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Regulation of innate antiviral defenses through a shared repressor domain in RIG-I and LGP2</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>582</fpage>–<lpage>587</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Huh1">
        <label>47</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Arabidopsis Pumilio protein APUM5 suppresses Cucumber mosaic virus infection via direct binding of viral RNAs</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source>
<volume>110</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269841</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Mori1">
        <label>48</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Identification of Ser-386 of interferon regulatory factor 3 as critical target for inducible phosphorylation that determines activation</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>
<volume>279</volume>: <fpage>9698</fpage>–<lpage>9702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14703513</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ppat.1004417-Takahasi2">
        <label>49</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Takahasi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoneyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishihori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumeta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Nonself RNA-sensing mechanism of RIG-I helicase and activation of antiviral immune responses</article-title>. <source>Molecular cell</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>–<lpage>440</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>