<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:59:06Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4664827" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4664827</identifier><datestamp>2016-06-01</datestamp><setSpec>jgenphysiol</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Physiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Gen. Physiol</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jgp</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jgp</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of General Physiology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1295</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1540-7748</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4664827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4664827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4664827</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26621776</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201511495</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.201511495</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Differential mechanisms of Cantú syndrome–associated gain of function mutations in the <italic>ABCC9</italic> (SUR2) subunit of the K<sub>ATP</sub> channel</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="short">SUR2 disease mutant mechanisms</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cooper</surname>
            <given-names>Paige E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sala-Rabanal</surname>
            <given-names>Monica</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Sun Joo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Nichols</surname>
            <given-names>Colin G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">2</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Cell Biology and Physiology</institution>, and <label>2</label><institution>Center for the Investigation of Membrane Excitability Diseases, Washington University School of Medicine, Saint Louis, MO 63110</institution></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Correspondence to Colin G. Nichols: <email>cnichols@wustl.edu</email></corresp>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>P.E. Cooper and M. Sala-Rabanal contributed equally to this paper.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>146</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>527</fpage>
      <lpage>540</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2015</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2015 Cooper et al.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="openaccess">
          <license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:href="JGP_201511495_thumb.gif"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="precis">
        <p>Mutations that increase the activity of ATP-sensitive potassium channels through either enhanced activation by MgADP or decreased sensitivity to inhibition by ATP can lead to Cantú syndrome.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cantú syndrome (CS) is a rare disease characterized by congenital hypertrichosis, distinct facial features, osteochondrodysplasia, and cardiac defects. Recent genetic analysis has revealed that the majority of CS patients carry a missense mutation in <italic>ABCC9</italic>, which codes for the sulfonylurea receptor SUR2. SUR2 subunits couple with Kir6.x, inwardly rectifying potassium pore-forming subunits, to form adenosine triphosphate (ATP)-sensitive potassium (K<sub>ATP</sub>) channels, which link cell metabolism to membrane excitability in a variety of tissues including vascular smooth muscle, skeletal muscle, and the heart. The functional consequences of multiple uncharacterized CS mutations remain unclear. Here, we have focused on determining the functional consequences of three documented human CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations: human P432L, A478V, and C1043Y. The mutations were engineered in the equivalent position in rat SUR2A (P429L, A475V, and C1039Y), and each was coexpressed with mouse Kir6.2. Using macroscopic rubidium (<sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup>) efflux assays, we show that K<sub>ATP</sub> channels formed with P429L, A475V, or C1039Y mutants enhance K<sub>ATP</sub> activity compared with wild-type (WT) channels. We used inside-out patch-clamp electrophysiology to measure channel sensitivity to ATP inhibition and to MgADP activation. For P429L and A475V mutants, sensitivity to ATP inhibition was comparable to WT channels, but activation by MgADP was significantly greater. C1039Y-dependent channels were significantly less sensitive to inhibition by ATP or by glibenclamide, but MgADP activation was comparable to WT. The results indicate that these three CS mutations all lead to overactive K<sub>ATP</sub> channels, but at least two mechanisms underlie the observed gain of function: decreased ATP inhibition and enhanced MgADP activation.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="introduction">
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <p>ATP-sensitive potassium (K<sub>ATP</sub>) channels, found in many excitable tissues, including brain (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ashford et al., 1988</xref>), heart (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Noma, 1983</xref>), pancreatic islets (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cook and Hales, 1984</xref>), and skeletal and smooth muscle (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Standen et al., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Winquist et al., 1989</xref>) are hetero-octameric protein complexes composed of four pore-forming inwardly rectifying potassium channel Kir6.X subunits, each associated with one sulfonylurea receptor subunit (SURX) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Shyng and Nichols, 1997</xref>). K<sub>ATP</sub> channels link cell metabolism with membrane excitability as a result of intracellular nucleotide regulation of channel activity. ATP binds directly to the pore-forming Kir6.X subunits (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tucker et al., 1997</xref>) to inhibit the channel, and MgADP binds to SURX to activate the channel (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Nichols et al., 1996</xref>). Channels formed from different combinations of Kir6.1 (<italic>KCNJ8</italic>), Kir6.2 (<italic>KCNJ11</italic>) (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Inagaki et al., 1995a</xref>,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>), SUR1 (<italic>ABCC8</italic>), and SUR2 (<italic>ABCC9</italic>) subunit isoforms vary in nucleotide sensitivity and pharmacology (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Masia et al., 2005</xref>), as well as tissue localization (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aguilar-Bryan et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Inagaki et al., 1996</xref>), generating additional functional diversity of K<sub>ATP</sub> channels (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Nichols, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Akrouh et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
      <p>Cantú syndrome (CS) was first recognized as a unique disorder in 1982 (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cantú et al., 1982</xref>). Clinical hallmarks of CS include hypertrichosis, macrosomia, macrocephaly, coarse facial appearance, cardiomegaly, and skeletal abnormalities (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">van Bon et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>). Recent studies have shown that the majority of known CS patients have missense mutations in <italic>ABCC9</italic> (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">van Bon et al., 2012</xref>) or <italic>KCNJ8</italic> (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Brownstein et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>) that result in a gain of function (GOF) in K<sub>ATP</sub> channel activity. CS resulting from mutations in either subunit confirms that functional changes in the K<sub>ATP</sub> channels formed from them underlie the disease.</p>
      <p>Conversely, <italic>KCNJ11</italic> and <italic>ABCC8</italic>, which encode Kir6.2 and SUR1, respectively, generate K<sub>ATP</sub> channels in pancreatic β cells (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Inagaki et al., 1995a</xref>), and GOF mutations in either of these subunits give rise to neonatal diabetes mellitus (NDM) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gloyn et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Babenko et al., 2006</xref>), characterized by decreased insulin secretion and elevated blood glucose levels. Detailed analyses of NDM mutations in <italic>ABCC8</italic> demonstrate that distinct molecular mechanisms can underlie the increase in channel activity, including increased open probability (P<sub>o</sub>) (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Babenko et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Proks et al., 2007</xref>) and increased MgADP activation (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">de Wet et al., 2007b</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Masia et al., 2007</xref>). To understand the molecular mechanisms of CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations, we have engineered and analyzed channel properties for three CS mutations that localize to different regions of the protein: P429L, A475V, and C1039Y. Given the experimental difficulty of recording Kir6.1/SUR2 currents (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>), we studied Kir6.2+SUR2A channels in the present experiments, and by means of <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux assays in intact cells transiently transfected with WT or mutant subunits, we confirm that all three mutations result in overactive K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. Consistent with the diversity of mechanisms found in NDM patients with <italic>ABCC8</italic> mutations, we further show that CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> GOF mutations can result from at least two different mechanisms: decreased sensitivity to inhibition by ATP or enhanced channel activation by MgADP.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Homology modeling</title>
        <p>Models of human SUR2A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>) were built using Modeller v9.8 from the template of the multidrug ABC transporter Sav1866 (<italic>2ONJ</italic>, to model the “open” conformation) and heterodimeric ABC transporter TM287-TM288 (<italic>3QF4</italic>, to model the “closed” conformation), respectively. The TM0 domain and L0 loop (1–281) were omitted because of lack of sequence homology to any proteins of known structure. Two extended loops unique to SUR2A were also omitted: one connecting TM1 and NBD1 (614–672) and a second connecting NBD1 and TM2 (920–966). A multiple sequence alignment (MSA) was performed using ClustalW2 between SUR2 and the two template sequences in conjunction with other proteins of the human ABCC family (ABCC1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, and 10) for TM1 and NBD1 because of low sequence identity. High sequence identity enabled a reliable sequence alignment of TMD2 and NBD2 by MSA between SUR2 and SUR1, 2ONJ, and 3QF4.</p>
        <fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>CS mutations in SUR2. (A) Alignment of SUR2 (ABCC9) with the multidrug ABC transporter Sav1866 (2ONJ) and heterodimeric ABC transporter TM287-TM288 (3QF4), upon which we built homology models. (B and C) Key structural domains TMD1 and 2 and NBD1 and 2 are indicated, as well as predicted α-helical (pink) and β-strand (green) segments. (B) Homology models of “open” and “closed” conformations of the SUR2A protein, which are based on <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> Sav1866, a bacterial homologue of the human ABC transporter Mdr1 and heterodimeric ABC transporter TM287-TM288 (TM287/288) from <italic>Thermotoga maritime</italic>, respectively. Published CS mutations from previous reports are shown in green (open) and light pink (closed).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig1"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>ABCC9 mutagenesis and heterologous expression of K<sub>ATP</sub> channels</title>
        <p>The Quick Change II Site-Directed Mutagenesis kit (Agilent Technologies) was used to engineer P429L, A475V, and C1039Y mutations (equivalent to CS-associated P432L, A478V, and C1043Y mutations in human SUR2; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">van Bon et al., 2012</xref>) into rat SUR2A-pCMV6. Mutations were confirmed by direct sequencing of the entire SUR2A coding region. For channel expression, COSm6 cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 10<sup>5</sup> U/L penicillin, and 100 mg/L streptomycin. At 60–70% confluence, cells were transfected with the relevant plasmids using FuGENE6 transfection reagent (Promega). For experiments with homomeric CS mutant channels, cells were cotransfected with pCDNA3.1-mKir6.2-WT (0.6 µg) and WT or mutant pCMV6-ratSUR2A (SUR2) (1 µg). For experiments using heteromeric channels, cells were cotransfected with Kir6.2-WT, SUR2-WT, and mutant SUR2 at ratios of 0.6:0.5:0.5 (w/w/w). Cells transfected with GFP-pcDNA3.1 served as controls. A small amount of GFP DNA was coexpressed for identification of transfected cells in electrophysiology experiments.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Macroscopic <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux assays</title>
        <p>Cells were incubated overnight at 37°C in DMEM containing 1 µCi/ml <sup>86</sup>RbCl (PerkinElmer), and then incubated in Ringer’s solution (mM: 118 NaCl, 10 HEPES, 25 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 4.7 KCl, 1.2 KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 2.5 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, and 1.2 MgSO<sub>4</sub>, adjusted to pH 7.4 with NaOH) in (a) the absence (basal) or (b) the presence of 2.5 mg/ml oligomycin and 1 mM 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-glucose (metabolic inhibition [MI]), (c) the SUR2-specific K<sup>+</sup> channel opener pinacidil (PIN; 250 µM), or (d) a combination of MI and PIN to achieve maximal channel activation. Subsequently, at selected time points (2.5, 5, 7.5, 15, 25, and 40 min) the solution was collected and replaced with fresh solution. Upon completion of the assay, cells were lysed with 2% SDS and collected, and radioactivity in these samples was measured by liquid scintillation. <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux is expressed as a fraction of total content. A nonspecific efflux that inactivated with time was assumed to be present in all <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux experiments, and apparent rate constants for the K<sub>ATP</sub>-independent <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux were obtained from GFP-transfected cells using the equation:<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Rb efflux</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>−1</sub></italic> are the apparent activation and inactivation rate constants. K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux was also assumed to activate and inactivate with time and was obtained using the equation:<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Rb efflux</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where<italic> k<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>−1</sub></italic> are the rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-independent pathways (obtained from GFP-transfected cells by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd1">Eq. 1</xref>), and <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>−2</sub></italic> are the activation (<italic>k<sub>2</sub>)</italic> and inactivation (<italic>k<sub>−2</sub></italic>) rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-specific K<sup>+</sup> conductance. <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> is then assumed to be proportional to the number of active channels. To account for potential day-to-day variability, for every efflux experiment, a <italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> value was determined for untransfected cells and then incorporated as a fixed parameter in the equation to estimate the K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> for each construct. All k values are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Rate constants for homomeric fluxes</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Basal</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.006</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>PIN</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI+PIN</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="tbl2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Rate constants for heteromeric fluxes</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>Basal</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <italic>
                    <sub>−</sub>
                  </italic>
                  <bold>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.006</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>PIN</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <italic>
                    <sub>−</sub>
                  </italic>
                  <bold>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI+PIN</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.091</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <italic>
                    <sub>−</sub>
                  </italic>
                  <bold>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
        <table-wrap id="tbl3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Rate constants for fluxes in MI+GLIB</p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Condition</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>n</italic>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI+GLIB</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetP429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetA475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetC1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>MI+GLIB</bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k</italic>
                  </bold>
                  <italic>
                    <sub>−</sub>
                  </italic>
                  <bold>
                    <sub>1</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFP</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>k<sub>−</sub></italic>
                    <sub>2</sub>
                  </bold>
                </td>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SUR2A-WT</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.047</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.039</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.045</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.003</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetP429L</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.030</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetA475V</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.042</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hetC1039Y</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.031</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td>
                <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn>
              <p>MI+GLIB, MI plus glibenclamide.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Excised patch clamp</title>
        <p>After 24–48 h, transfected cells that fluoresced green under UV light were selected for analysis by excised patch-clamp experiments at room temperature in a perfusion chamber that allowed for the rapid switching of solutions. K<sub>int</sub> solution (mM: 140 KCl, 10 HEPES, and 1 EGTA, pH 7.4) was used as the standard pipette (extracellular) and bath (cytoplasmic) solution in these experiments. ATP or ADP was added as indicated. The appropriate amounts of MgCl<sub>2</sub> to be added in each Mg<sup>2+</sup>-nucleotide–containing solution to attain 0.5 mM of free Mg<sup>2+</sup> were calculated by means of the CaBuf program (Katholieke Universiteit Leuven). Membrane patches were voltage clamped using an Axopatch 1D amplifier (Molecular Devices), and currents were recorded at −50 mV (pipette voltage, 50 mV) in on-cell and inside-out excised patch configuration. Data were typically filtered at 1 kHz and digitized at 5 kHz with a Digidata 1322A (Molecular Devices) A-D converter. pClamp and Axoscope software (Molecular Devices) were used for data acquisition. For ATP inhibition, [ATP]-response relationships (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>) were fitted by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd3">Eq. 3</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>I<sub>rel</sub></italic> (relative current) is the current in the presence of a given concentration of ATP relative to current in zero ATP, <italic>K<sub>i</sub></italic> is the apparent ATP inhibition constant, and H is the Hill coefficient.</p>
        <p>For phosphatidylinositol (4,5)-bisphosphate (PIP<sub>2</sub>) activation experiments, an ammonium salt of l-α-phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate from porcine brain (Brain PI(4,5)P2; Avanti Polar Lipids, Inc.) was dissolved in K<sub>INT</sub> to make a 5-µg/µl working solution. For each patch, we estimated the relative P<sub>o</sub> by dividing the maximum steady-state current in zero ATP by the maximum steady-state current in PIP<sub>2</sub>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Homomeric mutant channels are overactive in various metabolic conditions</title>
        <p>CS-associated mutations have been found throughout the coding sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). For the present study, we focused on two previously unexamined mutations (human A478V and C1043Y corresponding to rat A475V and C1039Y, respectively), located in the TMD1 and TMD2 segments, and P432L (corresponding to rat P429L), also located in the TMD1 region. To examine K<sub>ATP</sub> channel activity in intact cells, we performed <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux assays under four different conditions: basal, MI, in the presence of PIN, and MI and PIN combined (MI+PIN). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>, homomeric expression of SUR2A-P429L, A475V, or C1039Y channels, results in a significantly higher basal <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux rate compared with WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2 A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3 A</xref>). P429L- and A475V-based channels, but not those composed of C1039Y, also showed a significantly higher rate of efflux compared with WT channels under MI conditions and in the presence of PIN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2, B and C</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3, B and C</xref>), consistent with the GOF observed in the basal condition. Maximal efflux rates (estimated using simultaneous exposure to MI and PIN) of P429L and A475V were comparable to SUR2A-WT, implying similar channel densities at the cell surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2 D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3 D</xref>). C1039Y showed significantly lower absolute fluxes in all stimulatory conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2, B–D</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3, B–D</xref>), implying a lower channel density at the membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Increased channel activity in intact cells expressing homomeric P429L-, A475V-, or C1039Y-containing K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux as a function of time was measured in GFP-transfected control cells (dashed) and in cells transiently expressing reconstituted Kir6.2-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels with WT, P429L, A475V, or C1039Y SUR2 subunits in homomeric configuration, in basal conditions (A), in the presence of MIs oligomycin and 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-glucose (B), in the K<sup>+</sup> channel opener PIN (C), or in the presence of both MI and PIN (D). The data represent means ± SEM of 6–10 experiments. Flux data were fit with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd1">Eq. 1</xref> (GFP) to obtain the rate constant <italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> or <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd2">Eq. 2</xref> to obtain the rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent efflux, <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>), where lines show mean fitted relationships.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig2"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>K<sub>ATP</sub> conductance is increased in basal and stimulated conditions in intact cells expressing homomeric P429L and A475V-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. (A–D) Rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux (<italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> in gray, proportional to nonspecific K<sup>+</sup> conductance and <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic>, proportional to K<sub>ATP</sub>-specific K<sup>+</sup> conductance) were calculated from data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>. *, P &lt; 0.05 as compared with WT (unpaired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test). Error bars represent mean ± SEM.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig3"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The ratio of K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent (<italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic>) rate constants in basal, MI, and PIN to the maximal K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent rate constant (in MI+PIN) should reflect the relative activation of each channel in these specific conditions. In the basal condition, the ratio was higher for all three mutations than for WT, markedly so for C1039Y (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 A</xref>). In PIN alone, although only P429L and A475V reach significance, the ratio of active channels in all three mutations are also increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4 C</xref>). Collectively, the results suggest that each mutant will result in higher channel activation under any stimulatory conditions, particularly for C1039Y.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Relative K<sub>ATP</sub> conductance is markedly increased in basal and stimulated conditions in intact cells expressing homomeric C1039Y K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. (A–C) The ratio of the rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux (<italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic>) in basal and PIN- or MI-stimulated conditions to the maximal activation (in MI+PIN) is plotted for WT and mutant channels. *, P &lt; 0.05 as compared with WT (unpaired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test). Error bars represent mean ± SEM.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig4"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>C1039Y (hC1043Y) overactivity results from enhanced open-state stability and decreased ATP sensitivity</title>
        <p><sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> flux assays provide evidence for overactivity in CS mutants, but do not provide any indication of underlying molecular mechanisms. We assessed the details of channel properties in inside-out excised patch-clamp electrophysiology experiments. Intrinsic sensitivity to ATP inhibition (in zero Mg<sup>2+</sup>) was similar for WT, P429L, and A475V channels (<italic>K<sub>i</sub></italic> = 7–9 µM). However, K<sub>ATP</sub> channels expressing C1039Y exhibited a significant right shift in ATP sensitivity (K<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> = 21.3 µM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 B</xref>). A diminished sensitivity to intracellular ATP may account, at least in part, for the increased activity of C1039Y-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels in basal conditions in the intact cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2 A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3 A</xref>). Consistent with reduced channel density, the maximal current in zero ATP was significantly lower in C1039Y channels than in WT, P429L, or A475V channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 C</xref>). The P<sub>o</sub> in the absence of inhibitory ATP (zero) was estimated by the application of PIP<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 2005</xref>). After the application of PIP<sub>2</sub>, both WT and C1039Y channels lost ATP sensitivity; however, the current in zero ATP increased for WT channels but not for C1039Y channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). The ratio of the initial maximum current in zero ATP to that in PIP<sub>2</sub> (WT: 0.70 ± 0.11 vs. C1039Y: 1.26 ± 0.21) reflects marked increase in WT maximum P<sub>o</sub> but no increase for C1039Y.</p>
        <fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>ATP sensitivity is decreased in C1039Y channels. Representative excised patch-current recordings from COSm6 cells coexpressing Kir6.2 and WT or CS mutant SUR2 subunits P429L, A475V, or C1039Y (A). Membrane potential was held at −50 mV, and negative currents (plotted as upward deflections) were recorded continuously on-cell and in inside-out excised patches exposed to K<sub>INT</sub> in the absence or presence of 0.01, 0.1, or 1 mM ATP; arrowheads mark the point of excision. (B) Dose–response data (mean ± SEM from 8–11 patches) was fit with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd3">Eq. 3</xref> to estimate the ATP concentration for half-maximal inhibition <italic>K<sub>i</sub></italic>: WT (9 µM), P429L (9 µM), A475V (7 µM), and C1039Y (21 µM). (C) Maximum patch-current immediately after patch excision (mean ± SEM from 8–11 patches). *, P &lt; 0.05 as compared with WT (unpaired <italic>t</italic> test). Error bars represent mean ± SEM.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig5"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 6.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>C1039Y channels decreased ATP sensitivity caused by increased P<sub>o</sub>. (A) Representative K<sub>ATP</sub> current traces after excision and in the presence of 1 mM ATP or 5 µg/µl PIP<sub>2</sub> as indicated. (B) Relative P<sub>o</sub> determined as a ratio of the maximum steady-state current in the patch upon excision, in the absence of nucleotides over the maximum current measured in PIP<sub>2</sub>. Individual patch data are represented by symbols (<italic>n</italic> = 7–10); error bars are the means ± SEM, respectively relative to P<sub>o</sub> = 0.70 ± 0.11 (WT) and 1.26 ± 0.21 (C1039Y). *, P &lt; 0.05 as compared with WT (unpaired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test).</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig6"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Overactivity in P429L (hP432L) and A475V (hA478V) results from increased MgADP activation</title>
        <p>We investigated the current response to intracellular MgADP in the presence of 0.1 mM ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7 A</xref>). MgADP-dependent activation was estimated as the ratio between the steady-state activated current in MgADP+ATP and the maximal current in zero ATP, immediately after excision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7 B</xref>). The relative current in MgADP was markedly higher than WT for P429L and A475V channels. Using this analysis, the current was also statistically higher for C1039Y channels. However, this analysis ignores the intrinsically lower sensitivity of C1039Y channels to ATP inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 C</xref>). An alternative estimation for the stimulatory action of Mg nucleotides is to calculate the ratio of current in MgADP+ATP to that in Mg-free ATP alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7 B</xref>, inset). This analysis implies no difference in the MgADP activation of C1039Y and WT channels. In addition, although the MgADP activation for P429L and A475V channels is more rapid than WT, activation of the C1039Y channel is even slower than WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7 C</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 7.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>P429L and A475V show enhanced MgADP activation. (A) Representative K<sub>ATP</sub> current traces after excision and in the presence of nucleotides as indicated. (B) MgADP activation, as a ratio between the steady-state current in the presence of MgADP and the maximum current measured in the patch upon excision, in the absence of nucleotides. Individual patch data represented by symbols (<italic>n</italic> = 11–24); error bars are the means ± SEM, respectively 26.8 ± 0.03% (WT), 56.9 ± 0.06% (P429L), 59.7 ± 0.1% (A475V), and 38.7 ± 0.04% (C1039Y). *, P &lt; 0.05 as compared with WT (unpaired Student’s <italic>t</italic> test). Inset shows the mean current measured in patches in the presence of 0.1 mM of Mg-free ATP (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5 B</xref>) subtracted from the mean value of steady-state current measured in patches in the presence of MgADP (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7 A</xref>). Error bars represent the propagated error from both experiments. (C) Half-time of activation by MgADP.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig7"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>GOF is reduced in heteromeric mutant channels</title>
        <p>All documented CS patients with mutations in <italic>ABCC9</italic> are heterozygous. To mimic the predicted heteromeric composition of channels in such patients, we also expressed each mutation in a 1:1 ratio with SUR2A-WT plus Kir6.2, and assessed channel activity by <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figs. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9</xref>). In all conditions, P429L, A475V, and C1039Y heteromeric channels display no significant increases in the rate of <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux compared with WT channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figs. 8 A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9 A</xref>). When normalized to the maximal efflux rates, channels with heteromeric expression of C1039Y are still considerably less active than WT. In the heteromeric state, maximal C1039Y channel fluxes were markedly higher than in the homomeric state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">Fig. 9 D</xref>), also implying a partial rescue of the surface expression of C1039Y subunits by WT subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figs. 8, B–D</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9, B–D</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig8" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 8.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Channel activity in cells expressing heteromeric P429L-, A475V-, or C1039Y-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux as a function of time was measured in GFP-transfected control cells (dashed) and in cells transiently expressing reconstituted Kir6.2-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels with WT or 1:1 mixtures of WT and P429L, A475V, or C1039Y mutant SUR2 subunits in basal conditions (A), in the presence of MIs oligomycin and 2-deoxy-<sc>d</sc>-glucose (B), in the K<sup>+</sup> channel opener PIN (C), or in the presence of both MI and PIN (D). The data represent means ± SEM of 6–10 experiments. Flux data were fit with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd1">Eq. 1</xref> (GFP) to obtain the rate constant <italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> or <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd2">Eq. 2</xref> to obtain the rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent efflux, <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>), where lines show mean fitted relationships.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig8"/>
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig9" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 9.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>K<sub>ATP</sub> conductance normalized in basal and stimulated conditions in heteromeric P429L-, A475V-, or C1039Y-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. (A–D) The rate constants for nonspecific efflux (<italic>k<sub>1</sub></italic> represented by gray area) and K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux (<italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic>), proportional to K<sub>ATP</sub>-specific K<sup>+</sup> conductance, were estimated from data shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>. Error bars represent mean ± SEM.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig9"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Altered response to glibenclamide in C1039Y channels</title>
        <p>Some NDM patients with GOF mutations in Kir6.2 or SUR1 have successfully been switched from insulin therapy to K<sub>ATP</sub> inhibitors such as glibenclamide (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Zung et al., 2004</xref>). However, a correlation between increased channel activity and diminished effectiveness of such drugs has been noted (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 2005</xref>). Therefore, to test the effectiveness of glibenclamide on overactive P429L, A475V, or C1039Y channels, expressed both homomerically and heteromerically; <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux experiments were performed in the presence of MI plus 10 µM glibenclamide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>). The time course of Rb<sup>+</sup> effluxes shows an unusual behavior in that although initial fluxes are markedly lower than in MI alone, the inhibition is not maintained through the time course of the assay. It is well understood that the inhibitory action of glibenclamide is a complex function of the metabolic conditions and decreases under conditions of MI (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Findlay, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 1999</xref>). To account for this behavior, the efflux data in glibenclamide were fit by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd2">Eq. 2</xref>, where positive values for <italic>k<sub>−2</sub></italic> now result in the rate of efflux actually increasing with time for A475V and P429L channels (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). From this analysis, the ratio of the <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> in MI plus glibenclamide to <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> in MI provides an estimate of the relative sensitivity to inhibition by glibenclamide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10 C</xref>). Although the glibenclamide sensitivity of A475V and P429L channels was not different from WT, C1039Y channels appeared almost insensitive to the drug. Qualitatively similar results were obtained with channels expressed in heteromeric mixture with WT subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10, B–D</xref>). As discussed below, this glibenclamide insensitivity is consistent with similar findings for SUR1 mutations that produce increased activity of resultant K<sub>ATP</sub> channels.</p>
        <fig id="fig10" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 10.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Decreased sensitivity to glibenclamide inhibition in C1039Y channels. <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux as a function of time was measured in GFP-transfected control cells and in cells transiently expressing K<sub>ATP</sub> channels composed of Kir6.2 plus WT or mutant SUR2 subunits (A), as well as in cells expressing a 1:1 mixture of WT and mutant SUR2 subunits. (B) Experiments were performed in MI plus glibenclamide. The data represent the means ± SEM of three to six experiments. Data were fit with <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="fd2">Eq. 2</xref> to obtain rate constants for K<sub>ATP</sub>-dependent efflux, <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic>. (C and D) <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> in glibenclamide plus MI divided by <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> in MI for each condition.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="JGP_201511495_Fig10"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>DISCUSSION</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Distinct mechanisms of K<sub>ATP</sub> GOF in CS ABCC9 mutations</title>
        <p>CS is a rare disease characterized by complex vascular and skeletal anomalies, the underlying cellular and molecular mechanisms of which we are only now beginning to understand (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nichols et al., 2013</xref>). The majority of genotyped CS patients are heterozygous for mutations in the genes encoding <italic>ABCC9</italic> (SUR2) (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">van Bon et al., 2012</xref>) in most cases, and <italic>KCNJ8</italic> (Kir6.1) (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Brownstein et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>) in others. A select few of these mutations have thus far been shown to form overactive K<sub>ATP</sub> channels (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>), and most remain unexplored. Here, we characterized three CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations, namely P429L (hP432L), A475V (hA478V), and C1039Y (hC1043Y), that localize to distinct regions of the SUR2 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). Each mutation leads to K<sub>ATP</sub> channel GOF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>), consistent with previous findings on isolated CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
        <p>In the only previous assessment of CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Harakalova et al. (2012)</xref> measured channel sensitivity to ATP in the presence of Mg<sup>2+</sup>. Mg nucleotides have complex activatory/inhibitory effects on K<sub>ATP</sub> channels: MgATP can both inhibit the Kir6.X subunit and be hydrolyzed to activatory MgADP at the SUR subunits (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Nichols, 2006</xref>). Therefore, such an analysis cannot separate mutant effects on ATP inhibition from those on Mg nucleotide activation. By separately assessing channel activity in response to Mg-free ATP and to MgADP, we show that CS-associated <italic>ABCC9</italic> mutations lead to increased channel activity via different mechanisms, as has also been observed with NDM-associated <italic>ABCC8</italic> mutations (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">de Wet et al., 2007a</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Masia et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2010</xref>). Specifically, we demonstrate that increased activity of P429L and A475V channels results from increased MgADP activation, whereas increased activity of C1039Y channels results predominantly from decreased ATP sensitivity caused by higher intrinsic open-state stability.</p>
        <p>Some NDM-causing GOF mutations in SUR1 have also been shown to reduce ATP sensitivity (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Tarasov et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Takagi et al., 2013</xref>), either by reducing inhibitory ATP-binding affinity or by increasing the intrinsic open-state stability of the channel (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Shyng and Nichols, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 2005</xref>). That PIP<sub>2</sub> decreases ATP sensitivity, but does not increase maximum currents, in the C1039Y channel implies that the intrinsic P<sub>o</sub> of these channels is near 1 (relative P<sub>o</sub> = 1.26 ± 0.21), significantly higher than for WT channels (relative P<sub>o</sub> = 0.70 ± 0.11; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>), explaining the intrinsically lower ATP sensitivity of the C1039Y channel.</p>
        <p>In addition to increasing channel activity, homomeric expression of C1039Y appears to decrease expression of channels in the membrane, detectable in both <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> flux and patch-clamp analyses. A similar dual effect of GOF mutations in both Kir6.2 (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2013</xref>) and SUR1 (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2010</xref>) has been shown previously. In these previous examples, decreased surface expression was demonstrated by Western blot analysis. Significant rescue of channel activity in heteromeric C1039Y/WT channels is consistent with the patterns from such mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8">Figs. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9">9</xref>); therefore, we suggest that in addition to reducing ATP sensitivity of expressed channels, C1039Y also decreases K<sub>ATP</sub> surface expression.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Implications for tissue pathology in CS</title>
        <p>Kir6.1 GOF mutations have also been found in two CS patients (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Brownstein et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>), confirming Kir6.1/SUR2 as the key subunit combination generating the overactive channels. Given the experimental difficulty of recording Kir6.1/SUR2 currents (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cooper et al., 2014</xref>), we used Kir6.2+SUR2A channels in the present study. <italic>ABCC9</italic> encodes two splice variants: SUR2A and SUR2B, which vary only in the last 40 amino acids. All CS-associated SUR2 mutations identified thus far are found within the core of the SUR2 protein, such that these mutations will be present in both SUR2A and SUR2B. SUR2A is predominant in skeletal muscle and heart, whereas SUR2B is expressed in the vasculature. 6.1/SUR2B may be the more dramatically affected combination, as vascular phenotypes seem to predominate in CS patients (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nichols et al., 2013</xref>): neither skeletal muscle weakness nor shortening of the QT interval on the electrocardiogram has been noted, as might be expected if Kir6.2/SUR2A were markedly activated.</p>
        <p>The severity of disease varies between CS patients such that not all reported features are exhibited by all patients. Direct comparison of the phenotypes of patients carrying the A475V and C1039Y equivalent mutations (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">van Bon et al., 2012</xref>) revealed hypertrichosis, macrosomia, macrocephaly, coarse features, cardiac anomalies, and umbilical hernia to be common to both, but pulmonary hypertension, cardiomegaly, osteopenia, hyperextensibility and lymphedema were only reported for the A475V equivalent patient. Because the reduced sensitivity to ATP inhibition caused by the C1039Y mutation results in greater relative basal channel activity than does the enhanced Mg nucleotide activation caused by A475V, a less severe disease phenotype for C1039Y suggests that reduced expression caused by this mutation may also be a consequence in vivo, as also reported for SUR1 NDM mutations (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Implications for therapeutic intervention in CS</title>
        <p>Finally, sulfonylureas, which inhibit K<sub>ATP</sub> channels via interaction with the SUR subunits, are effective treatments for NDM patients with <italic>ABCC8</italic>-activating mutations (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Babenko et al., 2006</xref>), and may be promising potential therapies for CS (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nichols et al., 2013</xref>). However, GOF mutations in Kir6.2 (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koster et al., 2005</xref>) and SUR1 (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Takagi et al., 2013</xref>) that increase channel open-state stability also typically decrease sensitivity to sulfonylureas, which may result in a lack of sulfonylurea therapeutic efficacy in patients with these mutations. Assessment of <sup>86</sup>Rb<sup>+</sup> efflux in glibenclamide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>) suggests that the same can be true of SUR2 GOF mutations, specifically C1039Y channels, which required a significantly higher <italic>k<sub>2</sub></italic> value, indicating reduced glibenclamide sensitivity (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). However, in general, SUR2 sensitivity to sulfonylureas is much lower than SUR1 sensitivity to these drugs (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Dörschner et al., 1999</xref>), and so, given the further reduction in drug sensitivity of GOF mutants, the introduction of sulfonylureas to treat CS patients is likely to require high doses, such that undesired inhibition of SUR1-based K<sub>ATP</sub> channels, leading to hypoglycemic effects, will need to be carefully considered. Such concerns may ultimately necessitate the development of Kir6.1- or SUR2-specific inhibitors to provide safer and more effective treatment options for CS patients.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant HL95010 (to C.G. Nichols). P.E. Cooper was supported by NIH training grant HL007275.</p>
      <p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
      <p>Merritt C. Maduke served as editor.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <def-list>
            <title>Abbreviations used in this paper:</title>
            <def-item>
              <term>CS</term>
              <def>
                <p>Cantú syndrome</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>GOF</term>
              <def>
                <p>gain of function</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>K<sub>ATP</sub></term>
              <def>
                <p>ATP-sensitive potassium</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>MI</term>
              <def>
                <p>metabolic inhibition</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>NDM</term>
              <def>
                <p>neonatal diabetes mellitus</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>PIN</term>
              <def>
                <p>pinacidil</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>PIP<sub>2</sub></term>
              <def>
                <p>phosphatidylinositol (4,5)-bisphosphate</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
            <def-item>
              <term>P<sub>o</sub></term>
              <def>
                <p>open probability</p>
              </def>
            </def-item>
          </def-list>
        </p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilar-Bryan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names><suffix>IV</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name><surname>González</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrera-Sosa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nguy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Cloning of the beta cell high-affinity sulfonylurea receptor: a regulator of insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>268</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.7716547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7716547</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akrouh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halcomb</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Sala-Rabanal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Molecular biology of K(ATP) channels and implications for health and disease</article-title>. <source>IUBMB Life.</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>971</fpage>–<lpage>978</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/iub.246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19787700</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashford</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sturgess</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trout</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Adenosine-5′-triphosphate-sensitive ion channels in neonatal rat cultured central neurones</article-title>. <source>Pflugers Arch.</source>
<volume>412</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00582512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2460821</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavé</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Busiah</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Czernichow</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scharfmann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguilar-Bryan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaxillaire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Froguel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Activating mutations in the ABCC8 gene in neonatal diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>355</volume>:<fpage>456</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa055068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16885549</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Towne</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luquette</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marinakis</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meinecke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kutsche</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campeau</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Mutation of KCNJ8 in a patient with Cantú syndrome with unique vascular abnormalities—Support for the role of K(ATP) channels in this condition</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Med. Genet.</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmg.2013.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24176758</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantú</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>García-Cruz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sánchez-Corona</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernández</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nazará</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<article-title>A distinct osteochondrodysplasia with hypertrichosis—Individualization of a probable autosomal recessive entity</article-title>. <source>Hum. Genet.</source>
<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00281261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7076246</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>Intracellular ATP directly blocks K<sup>+</sup> channels in pancreatic B-cells</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>311</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/311271a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6090930</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reutter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woelfle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grange</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Haaften</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Bon</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoischen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Cantú syndrome resulting from activating mutation in the KCNJ8 gene</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source>
<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>813</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.22555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24700710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Wet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mikhailov</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fotinou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dreger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vénien-Bryan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007a</year>
<article-title>Studies of the ATPase activity of the ABC protein SUR1</article-title>. <source>FEBS J.</source>
<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>3532</fpage>–<lpage>3544</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2007.05879.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561960</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Wet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aittoniemi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patch</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ellard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sansom</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007b</year>
<article-title>Increased ATPase activity produced by mutations at arginine-1380 in nucleotide-binding domain 2 of ABCC8 causes neonatal diabetes</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>18988</fpage>–<lpage>18992</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0707428104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18025464</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Wet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Proks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lafond</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aittoniemi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sansom</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A mutation (R826W) in nucleotide-binding domain 1 of ABCC8 reduces ATPase activity and causes transient neonatal diabetes</article-title>. <source>EMBO Rep.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>654</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/embor.2008.71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18497752</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dörschner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brekardin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uhde</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwanstecher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Schwanstecher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Stoichiometry of sulfonylurea-induced ATP-sensitive potassium channel closure</article-title>. <source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1060</fpage>–<lpage>1066</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10347249</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Findlay</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>The ATP sensitive potassium channel of cardiac muscle and action potential shortening during metabolic stress</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc. Res.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>761</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/28.6.760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gloyn</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antcliff</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Proks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruining</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slingerland</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molnes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Activating mutations in the gene encoding the ATP-sensitive potassium-channel subunit Kir6.2 and permanent neonatal diabetes</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source>
<volume>350</volume>:<fpage>1838</fpage>–<lpage>1849</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa032922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15115830</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harakalova</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Harssel</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terhal</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Lieshout</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Renkens</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amor</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Dominant missense mutations in ABCC9 cause Cantú syndrome</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>793</fpage>–<lpage>796</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonoi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names><suffix>IV</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Inazawa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguilar-Bryan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995a</year>
<article-title>Reconstitution of <italic>I</italic><sub>KATP</sub>: An inward rectifier subunit plus the sulfonylurea receptor</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>270</volume>:<fpage>1166</fpage>–<lpage>1170</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.270.5239.1166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7502040</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Namba</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonoi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horie</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizuta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995b</year>
<article-title>Cloning and functional characterization of a novel ATP-sensitive potassium channel ubiquitously expressed in rat tissues, including pancreatic islets, pituitary, skeletal muscle, and heart</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>270</volume>:<fpage>5691</fpage>–<lpage>5694</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.11.5691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890693</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonoi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguilar-Bryan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Seino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>A family of sulfonylurea receptors determines the pharmacological properties of ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>. <source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1011</fpage>–<lpage>1017</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80124-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8630239</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Sulfonylurea and K<sup>+</sup>-channel opener sensitivity of K<sub>ATP</sub> channels. Functional coupling of Kir6.2 and SUR1 subunits</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.114.2.203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10435998</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Remedi</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>ATP and sulfonylurea sensitivity of mutant ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> channels in neonatal diabetes: Implications for pharmacogenomic therapy</article-title>. <source>Diabetes.</source>
<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>2645</fpage>–<lpage>2654</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.54.9.2645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16123353</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grasso</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crinò</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barbetti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Functional characterization of a novel <italic>KCNJ11</italic> in frame mutation-deletion associated with infancy-onset diabetes and a mild form of intermediate DEND: A battle between K<sub>ATP</sub> gain of channel activity and loss of channel expression</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e63758</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23667671</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enkvetchakul</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Differential nucleotide regulation of KATP channels by SUR1 and SUR2A</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol.</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2005.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15893323</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Leon</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacMullen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A mutation in the TMD0-L0 region of sulfonylurea receptor-1 (L225P) causes permanent neonatal diabetes mellitus (PNDM)</article-title>. <source>Diabetes.</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1357</fpage>–<lpage>1362</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db06-1746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17317760</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>KATP channels as molecular sensors of cellular metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>440</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16554807</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shyng</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nestorowicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names><suffix>IV</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aguilar-Bryan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Permutt</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Adenosine diphosphate as an intracellular regulator of insulin secretion</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>272</volume>:<fpage>1785</fpage>–<lpage>1787</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.272.5269.1785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650576</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Grange</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>K<sub>ATP</sub> channels and cardiovascular disease: Suddenly a syndrome</article-title>. <source>Circ. Res.</source>
<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1059</fpage>–<lpage>1072</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.112.300514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>ATP-regulated K<sup>+</sup> channels in cardiac muscle</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>305</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/305147a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6310409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Mechanism of action of a sulphonylurea receptor SUR1 mutation (F132L) that causes DEND syndrome</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2011</fpage>–<lpage>2019</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddm149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17584766</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shyng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Octameric stoichiometry of the KATP channel complex</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>655</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.110.6.655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9382894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shyng</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Membrane phospholipid control of nucleotide sensitivity of KATP channels</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>282</volume>:<fpage>1138</fpage>–<lpage>1141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.282.5391.1138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804554</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Standen</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quayle</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brayden</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Hyperpolarizing vasodilators activate ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> channels in arterial smooth muscle</article-title>. <source>Science.</source>
<volume>245</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>180</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.2501869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2501869</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furuta</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miyawaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagashima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Clinical and functional characterization of the Pro1198Leu ABCC8 gene mutation associated with permanent neonatal diabetes mellitus</article-title>. <source>J. Diabetes Investig.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>273</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jdi.12049</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarasov</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riveline</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Froguel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaxillaire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A rare mutation in ABCC8/SUR1 leading to altered ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> channel activity and beta-cell glucose sensing is associated with type 2 diabetes in adults</article-title>. <source>Diabetes.</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1595</fpage>–<lpage>1604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db07-1547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18346985</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gribble</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trapp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Truncation of Kir6.2 produces ATP-sensitive K<sup>+</sup> channels in the absence of the sulphonylurea receptor</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source>
<volume>387</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/387179a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144288</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Bon</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilissen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grange</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hennekam</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kayserili</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reutter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ostergaard</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morava</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsiakas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Cantú syndrome is caused by mutations in ABCC9</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source>
<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1094</fpage>–<lpage>1101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2012.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22608503</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winquist</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heaney</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baskin</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Kaczorowski</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Glyburide blocks the relaxation response to BRL 34915 (cromakalim), minoxidil sulfate and diazoxide in vascular smooth muscle</article-title>. <source>J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther.</source>
<volume>248</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2464055</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castaño</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Argente</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muñoz-Calvo</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perez de Nanclares</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Shyng</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Neonatal diabetes caused by mutations in sulfonylurea receptor 1: Interplay between expression and Mg-nucleotide gating defects of ATP-sensitive potassium channels</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab.</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>E473</fpage>–<lpage>E478</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2010-1231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20810569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zung</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nimri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Zadik</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Glibenclamide treatment in permanent neonatal diabetes mellitus due to an activating mutation in Kir6.2</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab.</source>
<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>5504</fpage>–<lpage>5507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2004-1241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15531505</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>