<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T20:00:17Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4785547" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4785547</identifier><datestamp>2016-04-14</datestamp><setSpec>hgv</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="letter">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum Genome Var</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Human Genome Variation</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2054-345X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4785547</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4785547</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4785547</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27081522</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pii">hgv20157</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hgv.2015.7</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27081522</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Data Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Truncating mutation in <italic>NFIA</italic> causes brain malformation and urinary tract defects</article-title>
        <alt-title alt-title-type="running"><italic>NFIA</italic> mutation causes brain malformation and VUR</alt-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Negishi</surname>
            <given-names>Yutaka</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Miya</surname>
            <given-names>Fuyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="note1">
            <sup>10</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hattori</surname>
            <given-names>Ayako</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mizuno</surname>
            <given-names>Kentaro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hori</surname>
            <given-names>Ikumi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ando</surname>
            <given-names>Naoki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Okamoto</surname>
            <given-names>Nobuhiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kato</surname>
            <given-names>Mitsuhiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tsunoda</surname>
            <given-names>Tatsuhiko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yamasaki</surname>
            <given-names>Mami</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kanemura</surname>
            <given-names>Yonehiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kosaki</surname>
            <given-names>Kenjiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Saitoh</surname>
            <given-names>Shinji</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Pediatrics and Neonatology, Nagoya City University Graduate School of Medical Sciences</institution>, Nagoya, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Laboratory for Medical Science Mathematics, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences</institution>, Yokohama, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>
<institution>Department of Nephro-Urology, Nagoya City University Graduate School of Medical Sciences</institution>, Nagoya, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>
<institution>Department of Medical Genetics, Osaka Medical Center and Research Institute for Maternal and Child Health</institution>, Osaka, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>
<institution>Department of Pediatrics, Yamagata University Faculty of Medicine</institution>, Yamagata, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>
<institution>Department of Neurosurgery, Takatsuki General Hospital</institution>, Osaka, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>
<institution>Division of Regenerative Medicine, Institute for Clinical Research, Osaka National Hospital, National Hospital Organization</institution>, Osaka, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>
<institution>Department of Neurosurgery, Osaka National Hospital, National Hospital Organization</institution>, Osaka, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
        <aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>
<institution>Center for Medical Genetics, Keio University School of Medicine</institution>, Tokyo, <country>Japan</country>
</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label>
(<email>ss11@med.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email>)</corresp>
        <fn id="note1" fn-type="equal">
          <label>10</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>26</day>
        <month>02</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <fpage>15007</fpage>
      <lpage/>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>01</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 The Japan Society of Human Genetics</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>The Japan Society of Human Genetics</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          <!--author-paid-->
          <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if thematerial is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link></license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chromosome 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome involving the <italic>Nuclear factor I/A</italic> (<italic>NFIA</italic>) gene is characterized by corpus callosum hypoplasia or defects and urinary tract defects. Herein we report on a case resembling the 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome carrying a <italic>de novo</italic> truncating mutation (c.1094delC; p.Pro365Hisfs*32) in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene, confirming that haploinsufficiency of the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene is a major determinant of this syndrome.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Chromosome 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome (OMIM #613735) involving the <italic>Nuclear factor I/A</italic> (<italic>NFIA</italic>) gene is characterized by corpus callosum hypoplasia or defects, hydrocephalus or ventricular enlargement and urinary tract defects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> Only six cases of this contiguous gene-deletion syndrome have been reported in the literature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1 bib2 bib3 bib4 bib5">1–5</xref></sup> Additionally, Lu <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> reported two patients showing a similar phenotype, but with balanced translocations breakpoints in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> These authors also demonstrated ventricular enlargement, callosal agenesis and urinary tract defects in homozygous <italic>Nfia</italic><sup>−/−</sup> mice and heterozygous <italic>Nfia</italic><sup>+/−</sup> mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> Recently, Rao <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> reported a case exhibiting a similar phenotype with an intragenic deletion in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene, but no structural chromosomal abnormalities detected by CGH microarray. Although haploinsufficiency of the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene is considered the main contributor to the phenotype of this chromosome 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome, the evidence is not conclusive because no single nucleotide variant (SNV) in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene has been identified and chromosomal rearrangements including deletion or translocation could have a position effect disturbing the proper expression of the neighboring genes.</p>
    <p>We herein report on a case of an individual showing interhemispheric cysts, ventricular enlargement, callosal agenesis and urinary tract defects, and carrying a heterozygous <italic>de novo</italic> frameshift mutation in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene. These findings provide further strong evidence that haploinsufficiency of the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene is a main contributor of 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome, and the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene has a fundamental role in development of brain as well as urinary tract.</p>
    <p>This study was approved by the institutional review board of Nagoya City University Graduate School of Medical Sciences.</p>
    <p>The proband is a 5-year-old boy with no family history of the relevant diseases. Callosal agenesis was suspected from the 28th gestational week of the fetal period. The boy was born by cesarean section on the 41st gestational week due to enlargement of the head circumference and post-term pregnancy. His Apgar score was 9 at 5 min post partum, his weight was 3180 g (+0.4 s.d.) and his head circumference was 38.2 cm (+3.3 s.d.). No apparent external malformations were observed. Head magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) on the third day of life revealed interhemispheric cysts, ventricular enlargement and callosal agenesis; however, he was in good general condition. Regarding his developmental milestones, he was able to hold his head up by 4 months and started walking without support at 1 year and 3 months. He was observed speaking meaningful words at 2 years and 1 month, showing a slight delay in language, and his intelligence quotient at 4 years measured by the Tanaka–Binet Intelligence Scale was 75. No epileptic seizures have been observed to date, although electroencephalogram detected sharp waves in the frontal head area at 11 months. A follow-up MRI at 4 years revealed polymicrogyria in the right frontal lobe, while the size of the interhemispheric cysts, longitudinal cerebral fissure and ventricular system remained unchanged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figures 1a,b</xref>). Although no abnormal signals were observed in the spinal cord in a spine MRI carried out at 5 years, cystectasia and left hydronephrosis were observed. A voiding cysturethrogram performed at 5 years showed bilateral grade IV vesicoureteral reflux (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1c</xref>). His current head circumference is 56.1 cm (+3.8 s.d.) showing non-progressive enlargement of head circumference. He showed only a little dysmorphic facial features including mild macrocephaly, high forehead, and thin upper lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1d</xref>).</p>
    <p>We performed a whole-exome sequencing on the proband and his parents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2a</xref>). To do this, genomic DNA was extracted from peripheral blood using the QIAamp DNA Blood Midi Kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions (Qiagen, Tokyo, Japan). Three micrograms of DNA was sheared into 150-200-bp fragments using the Covaris DNA Shearing service (Covaris, Woburn, MA, USA). To capture the exonic DNA, we used the SureSelect XT Human All Exon V5 capture library (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). We then constructed a sequence library using the SureSelect XT Target Enrichment System for Illumina Paired-End Sequencing Library kit (Agilent Technologies), and performed DNA sequencing of 100-bp paired-end reads by using the Illumina HiSeq 2000 sequencer (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). On average, we obtained 5.85 Gb of sequence reads. The sequencing data was mapped to a reference genome (GRCh37/hg19) using Burrows-Wheeler Alignment tool (ver.0.6.1; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.574">http://www.bio-bwa.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>), and the average read depth of targeted regions was 67.5. Variant calling was performed using SAMtools (ver.0.1.16; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.samtools.sourceforge.net/">http://www.samtools.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>) and GATK (ver.1.6; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/gatk/</ext-link>) software. To identify the disease causative mutations, we excluded known variants found in public databases (dbSNP138, 1000 Genomes Project, and NHLBI ESP6500) and a control in-house database (154 Japanese individuals of normal and other diseases control), except for those also identified as pathogenic mutations in the NCBI ClinVar (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar/</ext-link>) and HGMD databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.org/">http://www.hgmd.org/</ext-link>). We focused on non-synonymous SNVs, insertions and deletions (indels), and splice-site variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2b</xref>). This analysis revealed a heterozygous frameshift mutation (c.1094delC; p.Pro365Hisfs*32) in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene (NM_001134673.3), which is absent in his parents, indicating that the mutation arose <italic>de novo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2c</xref>). The mutation was confirmed by Sanger sequencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2d</xref>). This deletion led to an open reading frameshift that introduced an early stop codon which truncated 114 aminoacids. Consequently, a truncated NFIA protein is generated by this mutation.</p>
    <p>The <italic>NFIA</italic> gene has four transcriptional variants in human. Functional significance of each isoform has not been clarified. Only isoform 2 lacks an alternative exon downstream of the identified deletion site (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="xob1">Supplementary Figure a</xref>). The c.1094delC mutation would create protein truncation in each isoform. To examine the expression level of each transcript PCR with reverse transcription reaction was performed by using RNA isolated from normal human brain tissues (adult cortex, cerebellum, spinal cord and fetal brain). <italic>NFIA</italic> isoform 2 transcript was less predominant compared with isoforms 1, 3 and 4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="xob1">Supplementary Figure b</xref>). Therefore, the c.1094delC mutation would induce more effects on longer isoforms 1, 3 and 4 than on isoform 2, and the exon of deletion site and/or next exon which are used in all wild-type isoforms as translation regions would have an important role in NFIA protein.</p>
    <p>Three molecular mechanisms are known to cause the complex central nervous system malformation syndrome associated with the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene: (1) interstitial deletion of chromosome 1p32-p31 involving the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene; (2) translocations of chromosome 1p32-p31 involving the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene; and (3) intragenic deletion in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene. Nine cases (6 deletions, 2 translocations and 1 intragenic deletion) of this syndrome have been reported to date,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1 bib2 bib3 bib4 bib5 bib6 bib7">1–7</xref></sup> with corpus callosum hypoplasia or defects and hydrocephalus, ventricular enlargement and developmental delays observed in all cases. Urinary tract defects, tethered spinal cord and type 1 Chiari malformation were also observed in six, four and three cases, respectively. Additionally, abnormal facies and marble skin have been reported. The present case showed ventricular enlargement, callosal agenesis, urinary tract defects, mildly dysmorphic facial features and an intelligence quotient in the borderline range. Thus, our case showed virtually the same phenotype as 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome. Since the single nucleotide deletion detected in our case is not likely to cause a position effect affecting surrounding genes, it indicates that haploinsufficiency of the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene is a major determinant of this syndrome.</p>
    <p>A truncating mutation in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene was previously reported in one patient with autistic spectrum disorder (c.112C&gt;T; p.R38*),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> but detailed clinical information was not available. Since urinary tract involvement is easily missed, it is conceivable that this previous patient may have the same phenotype, and comprehensive evaluation of the patient might uncover the underlying defects.</p>
    <p>The <italic>NFIA</italic> gene encodes a member of the nuclear factor I (NFI) family of transcription factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> NFI proteins control a range of key processes in central nervous system development including axon guidance and outgrowth, glial and neuronal cell differentiation, and neuronal migration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> Additionally, these molecules regulate midline glia formation in the cortex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup> and gliogenesis within the spinal cord.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> Thus, NFI functional defects could result in abnormal brain formation, especially in midline structures, and spinal cord defects leading to neurogenic urinary tract dysfunction and defects. Interestingly, haploinsufficiency of the <italic>NFIB</italic> and <italic>NFIX</italic> genes, which belong to the same NFI family, also cause callosal agenesis,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13 bib14 bib15">13–15</xref></sup> and missense mutations in the <italic>NFIX</italic> gene cause Sotos-like syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> Our case also demonstrated prominent macrocephaly, which is a major feature of Sotos syndrome. Therefore, mutations in NFI family genes may give rise to similar clinical presentations that encompass callosal agenesis and macrocephaly.</p>
    <p>In our case, identification of the mutation by whole-exome sequencing led us to identify urinary tract defects in the presymptomatic period, and untreated higher grades of vesicoureteral reflux may have resulted in renal scar formation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref></sup> Therefore, whole-exome sequencing can be a powerful tool in clinical practice for early diagnosis of congenital disorders.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>This study was supported in part by a grant for Research on Applying Health Technology from the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare of Japan to FM, NO, MK, MY, YK, KK and SS. We thank KA Boroevich for English proofreading.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
        <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="xob1">
        <label>Supplementary Figure</label>
        <media xlink:href="hgv20157-s1.pdf">
          <caption>
            <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Lu W
, 
Quintero-Rivera F
, 
Fan Y
, 
Alkuraya FS
, 
Donovan DJ
, 
Xi Q
et al. <article-title>NFIA haploinsufficiency is associated with a CNS malformation syndrome and urinary tract defects</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e80</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17530927</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Campbell CG
, 
Wang H
, 
Hunter GW
. <article-title>Interstitial microdeletion of chromosome 1p in two siblings</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genet</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–294.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12210325</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Koehler U
, 
Holinski-Feder E
, 
Ertl-Wagner B
, 
Kunz J
, 
von Moers A
, 
von Voss H
et al. <article-title>A novel 1p31.3p32.2 deletion involving the NFIA gene detected by array CGH in a patient with macrocephaly and hypoplasia of the corpus callosum</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pediatr</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>–468.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19763616</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Chen CP
, 
Su YN
, 
Chen YY
, 
Chern SR
, 
Liu YP
, 
Wu PC
et al. <article-title>Chromosome 1p32-p31 deletion syndrome: prenatal diagnosis by array comparative genomic hybridization using uncultured amniocytes and association with NFIA haploinsufficiency, ventriculomegaly, corpus callosum hypogenesis, abnormal external genitalia, and intrauterine growth restriction</article-title>. <source>Taiwan J Obstet Gynecol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>–352.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22030051</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Ji J
, 
Salamon N
, 
Quintero-Rivera F
. <article-title>Microdeletion of 1p32-p31 involving NFIA in a patient with hypoplastic corpus callosum, ventriculomegaly, seizures and urinary tract defects</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Genet</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–268.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24657733</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Shanske AL
, 
Edelmann L
, 
Kardon NB
, 
Gosset P
, 
Levy B
. <article-title>Detection of an interstitial deletion of 2q21-22 by high resolution comparative genomic hybridization in a child with multiple congenital anomalies and an apparent balanced translocation</article-title>. <source>Am J Med Genet A</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>–35.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15368480</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Rao A
, 
O'Donnell S
, 
Bain N
, 
Meldrum C
, 
Shorter D
, 
Goel H
et al. <article-title>An intragenic deletion of the NFIA gene in a patient with a hypoplastic corpus callosum, craniofacial abnormalities and urinary tract defects</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Genet</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24462883</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Iossifov I
, 
Ronemus M
, 
Levy D
, 
Wang Z
, 
Hakker I
, 
Rosenbaum J
et al. <article-title><italic>De novo</italic> gene disruptions in children on the autistic spectrum</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>–299.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22542183</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Qian F
, 
Kruse U
, 
Lichter P
, 
Sippel AE
. <article-title>Chromosomal localization of the four genes (NFIA, B, C, and X) for the human transcription factor nuclear factor I by FISH</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>
<year>1995</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>–73.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7590749</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Mason S
, 
Piper M
, 
Gronostajski RM
, 
Richards LJ
. <article-title>Nuclear factor one transcription factors in CNS development</article-title>. <source>Mol Neurobiol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>–23.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19058033</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Shu T
, 
Butz KG
, 
Plachez C
, 
Gronostajski RM
, 
Richards LJ
. <article-title>Abnormal development of forebrain midline glia and commissural projections in Nfia knock-out mice</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>–212.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514217</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Deneen B
, 
Ho R
, 
Lukaszewicz A
, 
Hochstim CJ
, 
Gronostajski RM
, 
Anderson DJ
et al. <article-title>The transcription factor NFIA controls the onset of gliogenesis in the developing spinal cord</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>–968.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17178400</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Sajan SA
, 
Fernandez L
, 
Nieh SE
, 
Rider E
, 
Bukshpun P
, 
Wakahiro M
et al. <article-title>Both rare and <italic>de novo</italic> copy number variants are prevalent in agenesis of the corpus callosum but not in cerebellar hypoplasia or polymicrogyria</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e1003823</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Malan V
, 
Rajan D
, 
Thomas S
, 
Shaw AC
, 
Louis Dit Picard H
, 
Layet V
et al. <article-title>Distinct effects of allelic NFIX mutations on nonsense-mediated mRNA decay engender either a Sotos-like or a Marshall-Smith syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–198.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20673863</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Steele-Perkins G
, 
Plachez C
, 
Butz KG
, 
Yang G
, 
Bachurski CJ
, 
Kinsman SL
et al. <article-title>The transcription factor gene Nfib is essential for both lung maturation and brain development</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>–698.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15632069</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Yoneda Y
, 
Saitsu H
, 
Touyama M
, 
Makita Y
, 
Miyamoto A
, 
Hamada K
et al. <article-title>Missense mutations in the DNA-binding/dimerization domain of NFIX cause Sotos-like features</article-title>. <source>J Hum Genet</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>–211.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22301465</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
Peters CA
, 
Skoog SJ
, 
Arant BS Jr
, 
Copp HL
, 
Elder JS
, 
Hudson RG
et al. <article-title>Summary of the AUA Guideline on Management of Primary Vesicoureteral Reflux in Children</article-title>. <source>J Urol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>184</volume>: <fpage>1134</fpage>–1144.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20650499</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ref-list content-type="data-citations">
      <title>Data Citations</title>
      <ref id="d1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="data"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>Shinji</given-names></name></person-group><data-title>HGV Database</data-title>. <year>2015</year>. <pub-id assigning-authority="figshare" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.574" pub-id-type="doi">10.6084/m9.figshare.hgv.574</pub-id>. </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Head MRI, voiding cysturethrogram (VCUG) and craniofacial appearance of our patient. (<bold>a</bold>) Axial T2-weighted image showing interhemispheric cysts, ventricular enlargement and polymicrogyria (arrow). (<bold>b</bold>) Mid-sagittal T1-weighted image showing callosal agenesis (asterisk). (<bold>c</bold>) The VCUG showed bilateral grade IV vesicoureteral reflux. (<bold>d</bold>) Representative photograph of the patient showing a little dysmorphic facial features including mild macrocephaly, high forehead, and thin upper lip. His parents gave informed consent for publication of this image.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="hgv20157-f1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Genetic analysis of the pedigree. (<bold>a</bold>) Family tree of the pedigree. (<bold>b</bold>) Filtering the candidate mutations. Numbers show the patient result. The top numbers indicate number of called variants by whole-exome sequencing. The second numbers indicate number of variants after filter out known variants in databases, except for those which were also known pathogenic mutations. The third number indicates number of variants after excluded synonymous change variants. The bottom numbers indicate number of variants consistent with the phenotype in the pedigree (that is, total of the <italic>de novo</italic>, autosomal recessive, X-linked and compound heterozygous variants). Finally, only one deletion variant was remained. (<bold>c</bold>) Identified frameshift mutation in the <italic>NFIA</italic> gene. (<bold>d</bold>) Sanger sequencing of the <italic>NFIA</italic> mutation. Patient had a heterozygous c.1094delC mutation (arrow) not found in his parents.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="hgv20157-f2"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>