<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T19:53:11Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4045318" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:4045318</identifier><datestamp>2015-05-12</datestamp><setSpec>acssd</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochemistry</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochemistry</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bi</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="coden">bichaw</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biochemistry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-2960</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1520-4995</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>American
Chemical Society</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC4045318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4045318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">4045318</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24819397</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi500380f</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Structure of the p300 Histone Acetyltransferase Bound
to Acetyl-Coenzyme A and Its Analogues</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1">
          <name>
            <surname>Maksimoska</surname>
            <given-names>Jasna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2">
          <name>
            <surname>Segura-Peña</surname>
            <given-names>Dario</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
          <xref rid="notes-1" ref-type="notes">∥</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3">
          <name>
            <surname>Cole</surname>
            <given-names>Philip
A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">§</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath4">
          <name>
            <surname>Marmorstein</surname>
            <given-names>Ronen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">†</xref>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">‡</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>†</label>Program
in Gene Expression and Regulation, <institution>The Wistar Institute</institution>, 3601 Spruce Street, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104, <country>United States</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>‡</label>Perelman
School of Medicine, <institution>University of Pennsylvania</institution>, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania 19104, <country>United States</country></aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>§</label>Department
of Pharmacology and Molecular Sciences, <institution>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>, 725 North Wolfe Street, Baltimore, Maryland 21205, <country>United States</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>E-mail: <email>marmor@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>. Phone: <phone>(215) 898-7740</phone>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>05</month>
        <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>05</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>03</day>
        <month>06</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>53</volume>
      <issue>21</issue>
      <fpage>3415</fpage>
      <lpage>3422</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>03</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>05</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 American Chemical Society</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>American Chemical Society</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p content-type="toc-graphic">
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0008" id="ab-tgr1"/>
        </p>
        <p>The
p300 and CBP transcriptional coactivator paralogs (p300/CBP)
regulate a variety of different cellular pathways, in part, by acetylating
histones and more than 70 non-histone protein substrates. Mutation,
chromosomal translocation, or other aberrant activities of p300/CBP
are linked to many different diseases, including cancer. Because of
its pleiotropic biological roles and connection to disease, it is
important to understand the mechanism of acetyl transfer by p300/CBP,
in part so that inhibitors can be more rationally developed. Toward
this goal, a structure of p300 bound to a Lys-CoA bisubstrate HAT
inhibitor has been previously elucidated, and the enzyme’s
catalytic mechanism has been investigated. Nonetheless, many questions
underlying p300/CBP structure and mechanism remain. Here, we report
a structural characterization of different reaction states in the
p300 activity cycle. We present the structures of p300 in complex
with an acetyl-CoA substrate, a CoA product, and an acetonyl-CoA inhibitor.
A comparison of these structures with the previously reported p300/Lys-CoA
complex demonstrates that the conformation of the enzyme active site
depends on the interaction of the enzyme with the cofactor, and is
not apparently influenced by protein substrate lysine binding. The
p300/CoA crystals also contain two poly(ethylene glycol) moieties
bound proximal to the cofactor binding site, implicating the path
of protein substrate association. The structure of the p300/acetonyl-CoA
complex explains the inhibitory and tight binding properties of the
acetonyl-CoA toward p300. Together, these studies provide new insights
into the molecular basis of acetylation by p300 and have implications
for the rational development of new small molecule p300 inhibitors.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement>
          <funding-source>National Institutes of Health, United States</funding-source>
        </funding-statement>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name>
          <meta-value>bi500380f</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name>
          <meta-value>bi-2014-00380f</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name>
          <meta-value/>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p id="sec1">p300 and its CBP paralog were first described as binding partners
of the adenovirus early region 1A (E1A) protein and the cAMP-regulated
enhancer (CRE) binding proteins, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref></sup> It
was later shown that these two highly homologous proteins, often termed
p300/CBP, contribute to transcriptional regulation through their inherent
histone acetyltransferase activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> p300 is a large
protein of ∼270 kDa and, in addition to its catalytic HAT region,
contains several other conserved domains, including an acetyllysine
binding bromodomain and zinc binding domains that directly interact
with multiple cellular proteins, including many transcriptional factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></sup> In addition to histones, p300 has been shown to acetylate more than
75 other substrate proteins, making it a highly promiscuous protein
acetyltransferase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref></sup> By acetylating different substrates, p300 is involved
in various signaling pathways and regulates multiple cellular processes
such as cell proliferation, differentiation, apoptosis, and DNA repair.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> Because of its pleiotropic roles, aberrant p300/CBP
activity, through mutation, chromosomal translocation, or other p300/CBP
dysregulation, has been implicated in various diseases, including
inflammation, cardiac disease, Huntington’s disease, and cancer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>−<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Because of the biological importance of p300/CBP and the link
between
aberrant p300/CBP activity and disease, there is a need to understand
the mechanism of p300/CBP-mediated acetylation. Biochemical studies
of p300 have revealed that the catalytic activity of the enzyme toward
cognate protein substrate is regulated by p300 autoacetylation of
multiple lysine residues in a proteolytically sensitive internal autoacetylation
loop.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> It was shown that this intermolecular p300
acetylation is required for p300-mediated transcriptional regulation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> The molecular basis for protein acetylation
by p300 was more recently elucidated through X-ray crystallography,
including the cocrystal structure of the p300 HAT domain with the
synthetic bisubstrate inhibitor Lys-CoA, and the structure of the
p300 catalytic core containing its bromodomain, CH2, and HAT region
also in a complex with the Lys-CoA inhibitor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> These structures, together with related enzymatic and mutational
studies, provided important insight into the catalytic mechanism of
p300/CBP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Mutagenesis and kinetic analysis
of the potential catalytic residues revealed that p300 residues Tyr1467
and Trp1436 play significant catalytic roles. On the basis of its
position in the active site, we proposed that Tyr1467 played a key
role in orienting the sulfur atom of acetyl-CoA and as a possible
general acid by protonating the CoA leaving group.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> We also proposed that Trp1436 plays a role in orienting
the cognate lysine side chain for nucleophilic attack of the acetyl-CoA
cofactor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Taken together with the fact
that p300 binds more tightly to more primitive bisubstrate analogues
like Lys-CoA but much weaker to bisubstrate analogues with longer
peptide chains, we proposed that p300 follows an unusual “hit-and-run”
(Theorell–Chance) enzymatic mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> In this mechanism, there is no stable ternary complex formed. Instead,
after acetyl-CoA binds, peptide substrate associates weakly with the
p300 surface, and the target lysine then protrudes through the tunnel
and reacts with the acetyl group.</p>
    <p>Both available p300 structures
are in complex with the Lys-CoA
bisubstrate inhibitor, capturing a postreaction state of the enzyme.
However, no structure that shows the conformation of the active site
before or after the protein substrate binds is currently available.
It is also not known if the protein substrate induces a conformational
change upon binding that might be required for catalysis to occur.
To address these issues, we determined the structures of the p300
HAT domain in the prereaction conformation in complex with acetyl-CoA,
in the postreaction conformation with CoA, and in an inhibited state
in complex with a nonhydrolyzable acetyl-CoA inhibitor, acetonyl-CoA.
Together, the results reported in this study provide new molecular
insights into p300-mediated protein acetylation and have implications
for the rational development of new small molecule p300 inhibitors.</p>
    <sec id="sec2">
      <title>Experimental
Procedures</title>
      <sec id="sec2.1">
        <title>Protein Expression and Purification</title>
        <p>The p300 HAT domain
(residues 1279–1666, Tyr1467Phe mutation) was cloned into a
pET-DUET vector with an N-terminal six-His tag and expressed in BL21(DE3) <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cells. Cells were grown at 37 °C until
they reached an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.8, and protein expression was
induced by adding 0.5 mM IPTG and cells grown overnight at 18 °C.
Cells were harvested and lysed by sonication in 25 mM HEPES (pH 7.5),
500 mM NaCl, and 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol (lysis buffer). The
lysate was cleared by centrifugation and applied to a Ni-NTA affinity
column. The protein was eluted from the column with an increasing
concentration of imidazole in lysis buffer (20–250 mM) and
treated overnight with TEV protease to cleave the His<sub>6</sub> tag.
Upon cleavage, the ligand of choice (acetyl-CoA, CoA, or acetonyl-CoA)
was added to the protein solution in a 3–4-fold molar excess
and incubated for 30 min to allow for binding. Protein was then subjected
to a trypsin protease digest to remove the autoacetylation loop at
room temperature for at least 12 h. The completeness of the digest
was followed by running a protein sample on a sodium dodecyl sulfate–polyacrylamide
gel electrophoresis (SDS–PAGE) gel to visualize formation of
the two subdomains, the larger N-terminal subdomain (∼30 kDa)
and the smaller C terminal subdomain (∼10 kDa). Completely
digested protein was further purified by applying it on an HiTrap
Q HP ion-exchange column equilibrated in 25 mM HEPES (pH 7.5), 50
mM NaCl, and 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol buffer and eluted with an
increasing concentration of NaCl (from 50 to 500 mM) and a size exclusion
Superdex 200 column equilibrated with 25 mM HEPES (pH 7.5), 150 mM
NaCl, and 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol. The purified protein was concentrated
to 6 mg/mL and used for crystallization.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.2">
        <title>Crystallization and Data
Collection</title>
        <p>Cocrystals of p300
with either CoA, acetyl-CoA, or acetonyl-CoA were obtained using hanging
drop vapor diffusion by mixing 2 μL of a protein/ligand solution
(6 mg/mL) with 1 μL of a crystallization solution [0.1 M HEPES
(pH 7.5), 16% PEG 3350, and 3–10% 2-propanol] at 4 °C.
Crystals were cryoprotected in a cryosolution containing 0.1 M HEPES
(pH 7.5), 18% PEG 3350, 8% 2-propanol, and 25% glycerol, flash-frozen
in liquid nitrogen, and subjected to X-ray diffraction at The National
Synchrotron Light Source (Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, NY)
using beamlines X6A and X29. Collected data were integrated and scaled
using HKL2000.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref></sup></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec2.3">
        <title>Structure Determination
and Refinement</title>
        <p>Structures were
determined by molecular replacement using PHASER<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> with the structure of the p300/Lys-CoA complex (Protein
Data Bank entry 3BIY) with the Lys-CoA inhibitor removed as a search model. Model building
and refinement were completed using COOT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> and PHENIX.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref></sup> The validity of each step
of refinement and rebuilding was monitored by <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub>. Data collection
and refinement statistics are listed in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>. Structure factors and coordinates of the structures have been deposited
in the Protein Data Bank as entries 4PZS (p300/acetyl-CoA), 4PZR (p300/CoA), and 4PZT (p300/acetonyl-CoA).</p>
        <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Data Collection and Refinement Statistics</title>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0">
            <colgroup>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
              <col align="left"/>
            </colgroup>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th style="border:none;" align="center"> </th>
                <th style="border:none;" align="center">p300/acetyl-CoA</th>
                <th style="border:none;" align="center">p300/CoA</th>
                <th style="border:none;" align="center">p300/acetonyl-CoA</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="4" style="border:none;" align="center" valign="bottom">Data Collection</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">space group</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>P</italic>4<sub>3</sub></td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>P</italic>4<sub>3</sub></td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>P</italic>4<sub>3</sub></td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">cell dimensions</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = 63.672 Å</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = 63.672 Å</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = 63.681 Å</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic> = 104.116 Å</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic> = 104.116 Å</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>c</italic> = 104.122 Å</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">α = β = γ = 90°</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">α = β = γ = 90°</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">α = β = γ = 90°</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">resolution (Å)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">50.00–1.94</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">50.00–2.10</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">50.00–2.80</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">total
no. of reflections,
unique</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">230494, 30678</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">83696, 24262</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">53041, 10279</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">
                  <italic>R</italic>
                  <sub>merge</sub>
                  <xref rid="t1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
                </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.101 (0.287)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.068 (0.359)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.119 (0.505)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>I</italic>/σ</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">17.3 (6.9)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">18.5 (3.6)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">14.8 (3.6)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">completeness (%)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">99.8 (98.5)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">99.7 (100.0)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">100.0 (100.0)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">redundancy</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">7.5 (7.4)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">3.4 (3.4)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">5.2 (5.2)</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td colspan="4" style="border:none;" align="center">Refinement</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub>/<italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub> (%)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">18.4/23.0</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">16.8/21.9</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">15.7/23.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">Ramanchandran
plot (%)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">favored</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">96.7</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">96.4</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">97.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">allowed</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">2.7</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">3.6</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">2.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">disallowed</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.6<xref rid="t1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">rmsd<xref rid="t1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref> for bond
lengths (Å)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.007</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.008</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">0.008</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">rmsd<xref rid="t1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">c</xref> for bond angles (deg)</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">1.115</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">1.075</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">1.234</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"><italic>B</italic> factor</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left"> </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">protein</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">26.1</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">40.7</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">38.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">ligand</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">23.0</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">37.8</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">32.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">solvent</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">31.0</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">43.3</td>
                <td style="border:none;" align="left">31.6</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn id="t1fn1">
              <label>a</label>
              <p>Data for the highest-resolution
shell are in given in parentheses.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t1fn2">
              <label>b</label>
              <p>Ramanchandran outliers: P1604 and
A1605.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="t1fn3">
              <label>c</label>
              <p>Root-mean-square
deviation.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="sec3">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="sec3.1">
        <title>Overall Structure
of p300 in Complex with Acetyl-CoA</title>
        <p>For structural studies,
we focused on the p300 HAT domain, residues
1279–1666. It was previously demonstrated that the active wild-type
HAT domain is toxic to bacterial cells and cannot be expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> Obtaining a homogeneous
p300 HAT domain for crystallographic studies involved expression and
purification from <italic>E. coli</italic> of an inactive C-terminally
truncated form, reconstitution of the active intact HAT domain by
semisynthetic protein ligation chemistry, proteolytic degradation
to cleave the acetylation loop, and a final purification of the heterodimeric
p300 HAT domain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> To avoid this complicated
and time-consuming procedure, we mutated the catalytic Tyr1467 to
phenylalanine to create a catalytically inactive mutant. This allowed
us to express an intact recombinant p300 HAT domain protein in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells in high yield (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Upon purification, the protein was incubated with acetyl-CoA
cofactor, CoA product, or acetonyl-CoA cofactor analogue and then
subjected to limited proteolysis by trypsin to remove the flexible
autoacetylation loop that inhibits crystallization. After trypsin
digestion, two subdomains, the larger N-terminal subdomain (∼30
kDa) and the smaller C-terminal subdomain (∼10 kDa), formed
a heterodimer that was further purified through ion-exchange and size
exclusion chromatography and crystallized under similar conditions
as described previously (Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Our extensive efforts to obtain crystals of
an intact p300 HAT domain either alone of with cofactor or cofactor
analogues were unsuccessful, and limited proteolysis of p300 without
added cofactor or cofactor analogues resulted in protein degradation
that was not amenable to crystallization (data not shown).</p>
        <fig id="fig1" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Expression
and purification of the catalytically inactive p300
HAT domain in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells. (A) SDS–PAGE
gel showing affinity-purified p300 HAT (first lane), the six-His tag
cleavage with TEV protease (second lane), and formation of a p300
heterodimer by trypsin digestion in the presence of acetyl-CoA (third
lane). Identical results of trypsin digestion were obtained in the
presence of CoA and acetonyl-CoA (data not shown). (B) Size exclusion
chromatogram of the heterodimeric p300 HAT domain (left) and SDS–PAGE
gel of the concentrated peak fractions used for crystallization (right).
The elution positions of molecular weight standards are indicated.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0002" id="gr1" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The crystal structures of the
p300/ligand complexes were determined
by molecular replacement using the p300/Lys-CoA structure as a search
model with the Lys-CoA excluded from the search model. Data collection
and refinement statistics for all structures are listed in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>.</p>
        <p>The overall fold of the p300 HAT domain
in complex with acetyl-CoA
or analogues is essentially the same as the p300 structure with Lys-CoA
(Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). For example, the root-mean-square
deviation (rmsd) for all shared protein and cofactor atoms between
the p300/Lys-CoA and p300/acetyl-CoA structures is 0.4 Å. The
central β-sheet is composed of seven β-strands and surrounded
by nine α-helices. Proteolysis of the p300 HAT domain within
the autoacetylation loop prior to crystallization results in a heterodimeric
HAT domain containing N- and C-terminal subdomains that are tightly
associated. Trypsin digestion removes ∼40 residues of the autoacetylation
loop. The last residue of the N-terminal subdomain that is visible
and can be modeled into the electron density map is Ser1534 (also
Ser1534 for the structure with acetonyl-CoA and Asn1532 for the structure
with CoA), while the first residue of the C-terminal subdomain visible
for all structures is Asp1579. This is in agreement with previously
determined boundaries for the trypsin-digested p300 HAT domain in
the presence of Lys-CoA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Three α-helices
and one β-strand come from the smaller C subdomain, which spans
the entire structure and caps opposite ends of the N subdomain. This
explains the resistance to this heterodimeric portion of the HAT domain
to proteolysis. The acetyl-CoA binding pocket has the same architecture
as the analogous region of the Lys-CoA binding site of the p300/Lys-CoA
complex. The adenosine ring is sandwiched between aliphatic carbons
of Arg1462 and Lys1456. Arg1410 makes several critical hydrogen bonds
to phosphates, and the pantetheine arm makes extensive interactions
with the substrate binding loop that closes off CoA binding in p300
(Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B).</p>
        <fig id="fig2" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Overall structure of p300 in complex with
acetyl-CoA. (A) Overall
structure of the p300 HAT domain in complex with acetyl-CoA. Acetyl-CoA
is colored green. An <italic>F</italic><sub>o</sub> – <italic>F</italic><sub>c</sub> electron density map calculated before the
acetyl-CoA was modeled is contoured to 2.5σ and colored blue;
the N- and C-terminal subdomains are colored salmon and blue, respectively,
and the substrate binding loop is colored red. The position of the
proteolyzed approximately 50-residue autoacetylation loop is indicated
as a dotted line. (B) Detailed view of the interactions of acetyl-CoA
within the p300 binding pocket. Protein residues unique to p300 cofactor
binding and coordination of a structurally conserved water molecule
are labeled. Residues coming from the N-terminal subdoman are colored
salmon, while Lys1456 from the substrate binding loop is colored red.
Lys-CoA is shown for comparison in gray. (C) Difference <italic>F</italic><sub>o</sub> – <italic>F</italic><sub>c</sub> electron density
maps for CoA, Ac-CoA, and acetonyl-CoA calculated before the cofactors
were modeled are colored light blue.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0003" id="gr2" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>While the positions of the atoms of the terminal acetyl group
of
acetyl-CoA lay in the same position with their corresponding atoms
of Lys-CoA (reaching toward the peptide substrate binding site), the
p300/acetyl-CoA structure reveals that the acetyl group is directed
toward the opposite side of the active site (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). Difference <italic>F</italic><sub>o</sub> – <italic>F</italic><sub>c</sub> electron density maps for different cofactors
clearly demonstrate the difference in the position of the terminal
groups in all three cofactors reported here (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). The methyl moiety of the acetyl group is nicely accommodated
by the hydrophobic residues Leu1398, Ile1395, and Ile1435. The carbonyl
oxygen is coordinated to a water molecule kept in place by the backbone
NH and CO groups of Trp1436 and Ile1395, respectively. Interestingly,
this water molecule is conserved among the p300 structures reported
here, and it likely has a role in neutralizing the negative charge
that develops on the oxygen atom during the enzymatic reaction (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). Positioned in this way, the sulfur atom of acetyl-CoA
is in a different position than it is in the Lys-CoA (or acetonyl-CoA)-containing
p300 structures, such that the sulfur is 2.2 Å from the end of
the Lys side chain portion of the Lys-CoA inhibitor. This position
makes it ideal for nucleophilic attack by the lysine in the enzymatic
reaction. In this way, the sulfur atom is still in position to be
protonated by the proposed general acid, Tyr1467,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> which is replaced by the Phe mutant in this structure,
after the acetyl transfer reaction occurs (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The cofactor sulfur atom in the wild-type and Tyr1467Phe
mutant p300 HAT domain bound to the Lys-CoA inhibitor assumes the
same position,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> arguing that the position of
the acetyl group in acetyl-CoA is not affected by the catalytic inactivating
Tyr1467Phe mutation. Taken together, we propose that the p300/acetyl-CoA
complex represents the state just before the reaction occurs and the
enzyme active site is ready to accept the substrate lysine.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.2">
        <title>Implications
for Lysine Substrate-Mediated Structural Changes
in p300</title>
        <p>All previously reported structures of p300 are bound
to the bisubstrate inhibitor Lys-CoA. Therefore, the relative contributions
of the acetyl-CoA and Lys cosubstrates to the active conformation
of the HAT domain are not known. A comparison of the p300 complexes
with Lys-CoA, acetyl-CoA, CoA, and acetonyl-CoA reveals that the overall
structures are essentially superimposable, revealing that the lysine
moiety does not contribute to the formation of the active p300 HAT
domain conformation (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A,B). Moreover,
the conformation of the p300 HAT domain appears to be independent
of the presence of additional p300 protein regions adjacent to the
HAT domain because the p300 HAT domain from the recently reported
p300 catalytic core structure (containing the p300 bromo, CH2, and
HAT domains) adopts the same conformation as the structures reported
here containing the isolated HAT domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> (Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). In addition, protein residues
that participate in binding of the lysine moiety of Lys-CoA adopt
the same orientations in the corresponding complexes with Ac-CoA,
CoA, and acetonyl-CoA. The only exception to this is residue Tyr1397.
This residue is hydrogen bonded to the terminal NH group of Lys-CoA
but is rotated ∼60° from the enzyme active site such that
Tyr1397 forms a hydrogen bond with the backbone NH group of Arg1627,
a terminal residue of an α-helix. However, the relatively modest
effect of a Tyr1397Phe mutation argues against the significance of
this structural reorientation of Tyr1397.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Taken together, this comparison suggests that lysine substrate binding
does not contribute to the formation of the active conformation of
the p300 HAT domain. This is in agreement with the proposed Theorell–Chance
catalytic mechanism of p300, whereby the enzyme binds tightly to acetyl-CoA
and then the lysine cosubstrate binds the enzyme with a much shorter
half-life.</p>
        <fig id="fig3" position="float">
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Comparison of the structure of p300 in complex with different ligands.
(A) Superimposition of the cocrystal structures of p300 with acetyl-CoA,
CoA, acetonyl-CoA, and Lys-CoA, and the HAT domain from the p300 catalytic
core structure (p300-CC) illustrating a negligible degree of protein
conformational change as a function of bound ligand or other adjacent
domains. (B) Close-up view of the superimposed ligand binding sites.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0004" id="gr3" position="float"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.3">
        <title>p300 in the Postreaction
State Bound to CoA and a Pseudopeptide
Substrate</title>
        <p>To obtain molecular insight into p300 in the postreaction
state, we obtained a structure of p300 bound to the CoA reaction product.
The overall structure of the protein is remarkably similar to the structure of p300
bound to the acetyl-CoA substrate with an rmsd of only 0.2 Å
for all protein and all shared cofactor atoms. However, a calculated <italic>F</italic><sub>o</sub> – <italic>F</italic><sub>c</sub> difference
electron density map suggested that the terminal thiol group of CoA
assumes two alternate conformations (Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). In one conformation, the sulfur atom assumes the same position
as acetyl-CoA, while in the other conformation, the sulfur atom overlaps
with the position of the sulfur atom in acetonyl-CoA and Lys-CoA (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). The two conformations of CoA refine to relative
occupancies of 60% and 40%, respectively. These alternative conformations
of CoA are not surprising considering that the terminal groups of
acetyl-CoA and acetonyl-CoA form interactions with the protein to
help fix their orientations, and the absence of these additional interactions
with CoA gives the terminal thiol group flexibility to assume different
positions.</p>
        <fig id="fig4" position="float">
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Structure of the p300 domain bound to CoA. (A) Superimposed active
site of p300 bound to CoA and Lys-CoA. Two PEG molecules (PEG1 and
PEG2) bound to the p300/CoA structure are colored yellow. An <italic>F</italic><sub>o</sub> – <italic>F</italic><sub>c</sub> electron
density map before the PEG molecules were modeled in is contoured
at 2.5σ and colored green. (B) Detailed view of the p300 active
site in complex with CoA and the two bound PEG molecules. Protein
residues that are important for hydrogen bonding and hydrophobic interactions
with the PEG molecules are labeled. (C) van der Waals sphere representation
of the PEG2 molecule and the protein residues forming the PEG binding
groove. The difference in the position of the groove forming residues
between the p300/CoA and p300/acetyl-CoA structures is shown. (D)
Putative substrate binding surface of p300. Residues that participate
in binding the substrate lysine side chain are colored orange, residues
forming a negatively charged binding pocket that is proposed to contribute
to substrate binding red, and residues forming a newly identified
potential substrate binding groove green.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0005" id="gr4" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>Interestingly, the refined p300/CoA structure reveals the
presence
of two well-ordered polyethyleneglycol (PEG) moieties, PEG1 and PEG2,
presumably derived from the intact PEG polymer used for crystallization,
proximal to the enzyme active site. PEG1 overlaps with the lysine
moiety of the bound Lys-CoA inhibitor, and PEG2 is in an adjacent
groove ∼3.6 Å from PEG1 (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A).</p>
        <p>PEG1 is within hydrogen bonding distance of the sulfur
atom of
one of the two orientations of the CoA molecule and is also hydrogen
bonded to the backbone carbonyl group of Ser1396. The aliphatic part
of PEG1 is also nicely nestled in a hydrophobic pocket formed by Trp1436,
Cys1438, and the aliphatic part of Tyr1397 (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). Notably, a corresponding PEG moiety is not observed in
the p300 structures bound to acetyl-CoA or acetonyl-CoA crystallized
under identical conditions. Presumably, the absence of the acetyl
group and water molecule of acetyl-CoA or the acetonyl group of acetonyl-CoA
allows the PEG moiety to effectively compete for this binding site
in a way that mimics a lysine substrate.</p>
        <p>PEG2 is bound right
outside the lysine binding pocket, within a
shallow groove formed by Arg1627 and Asp1444 (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). PEG2 is hydrogen bonded to Arg1627, Asp1444, and the backbone
carbonyl group of Asp1445, and its size fits nicely into the groove.
Interestingly, because of the position of Asp1444, this groove is
not accessible in the p300 structures with acetyl-CoA and acetonyl-CoA.
While Arg1627 is in the same position in all structures, Asp1444 is
flipped more toward Arg1627, making the groove between them much smaller
and unable to accommodate PEG2 (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C).</p>
        <p>The binding of PEG molecules near the p300 active site in the crystals
is potentially interesting because it might mimic how the lysine-bearing
protein substrate approaches or leaves the active site. Consistent
with the path of PEG2 mimicking the path of the peptide substrate
near the reactive lysine, several known histone substrates for p300
(for example, H3K14, H4K5, H4K8, and H4K12) contain one or two glycine
residues or other small residues flanking the acetylated lysine that
could be accommodated in this shallow groove. Many of the known non-histone
p300/CBP substrates also contain glycine or alanine residues next
to the primary acetylation site.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Indeed, a characterization
of the acetylation motifs of different HAT families revealed that
a glycine at position −1 is the dominant residue in the three
main HAT families.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></sup></p>
        <p>Previous studies
had identified a shallow negatively charged groove
formed by residues Ser1396, Tyr1397, Thr1357, and Asp1625 on the other
side of the lysine binding site as an important site for substrate
binding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D). We previously proposed that this negatively charged site, named
P2, located approximately 10 Å from the P1 site that binds the
cognate lysine, could interact with a positively charged lysine or
arginine side chain that is present three or four residues proximal
to the cognate lysine substrate of nearly all known p300 substrates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D). Taking this
data together with our current observations, we propose that the path
of at least a subset of p300 peptide substrates may track from PEG2
(groove 2) through the cognate lysine and toward P2 (groove 1) in
either an N-terminal to C-terminal or reverse direction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.4">
        <title>Structure of
p300 Bound to the Acetonyl-CoA Inhibitor</title>
        <p>Given the paucity
of inhibitor-bound structures of p300 and other
HATs, we determined the structure of p300 bound to the nonhydrolyzable
acetyl-CoA analogue, acetonyl-CoA, which contains an extra methylene
unit between CoA and the acetyl moiety. Given its high degree of similarity
to acetyl-CoA, acetonyl-CoA has been utilized as a general inhibitor
of acetyl-CoA utilizing enzymes, including HATs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> Not surprisingly, the structure of the p300/acetonyl-CoA
complex superimposes almost perfectly with the p300/Lys-CoA structure
with an rmsd of 0.4 Å for all protein and shared cofactor atoms.
This analogous conformation likely contributes to their similar inhibitory
properties. Consistent with this, both acetonyl-CoA and Lys-CoA point
in opposite directions relative to the acetyl group of acetyl-CoA
(Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="fig5" position="float">
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Structure of p300 bound to acetonyl-CoA.
Superposition of acetonyl-CoA,
acetyl-CoA, and Lys-CoA in the p300 binding site. For the sake of
clarity, the protein is displayed only for the p300/acetonyl-CoA structure.
Protein residues important for the orientation of the acetonyl group
are labeled.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0006" id="gr5" position="float"/>
        </fig>
        <p>A more detailed analysis
of the interaction of the acetonyl group
with the protein shows that the acetonyl group is nicely accommodated
in the binding site, with the carbonyl hydrogen bonded to the backbone
NH group of Leu1398 and the methyl group forming hydrophobic interactions
with Trp1436, Cys1438, and Tyr1446 (Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). These interactions that are mediated by the acetonyl group of
acetonyl-CoA are consistent with the observation that acetonyl-CoA
binds to p300 with an affinity that is ∼10-fold greater than
that of CoA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> To the best of our knowledge,
the structure of the p300/acetonyl-CoA complex represents the first
structure of acetonyl-CoA bound to a protein acetyltranferase.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Understanding the molecular basis for p300 acetylation is significant
because of the involvement of p300 in many biological processes, the
aberrant activity of p300 in many human diseases, and the implications
of such studies for developing small molecule p300 inhibitors. Until
now, the only p300 structures that have been reported are bound to
the bisubstrate inhibitor Lys-CoA,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> and structures
are notably missing for p300 bound with the acetyl-CoA substrate or
CoA product, thus limiting the molecular details about the p300 reaction
mechanism that could be gleaned. With this in mind, we determined
the structure of p300 in complex with acetyl-CoA, CoA, and a nonhydrolyzable
acetyl-CoA analogue inhibitor, acetonyl-CoA.</p>
      <p>A comparison of
the structures reported here with the p300/Lys-CoA
complex demonstrates that lysine substrate binding does not contribute
to the active conformation of p300 and implies that acetyl-CoA binding
plays a more dominant role in configuring p300 in an active conformation,
consistent with the proposed Theorell–Chance catalytic mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> The p300/CoA crystals also reveal two PEG moieties
bound proximal to the cofactor binding site, thus implicating a path
of protein substrate association. This region of polyethylene binding
to p300 remains accessible even when the adjacent p300 CH2 domain
and bromodomain are present, thus likely allowing for interactions
with potential protein substrates in the context of the intact p300
protein (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> Given that p300 is known to acetylate more than 70 different protein
substrates with somewhat diverse sequence characteristics flanking
the cognate lysine residue, it is possible that p300 does not engage
all substrates similarly. Therefore, the peptide path that is suggested
by PEG2 may apply to only substrates that have small side chains proximal
to the cognate lysine side chain.</p>
      <fig id="fig6" position="float">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Superposition of the p300/CoA structure
with the p300 catalytic
core (with Lys-CoA) and p300/acetonyl-CoA structures. (A) PEG binding
site in the context of the p300 catalytic core structure, demonstrating
the accessibility of the potential substrate binding site in the context
of this larger p300 construct. (B) Relative positions of acetonyl-CoA
and PEG molecules in the p300-CoA structure are shown, demonstrating
a possible target region for inhibitor development.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="bi-2014-00380f_0007" id="gr6" position="float"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Aside from the Lys-CoA bisubstrate p300 inhibitor,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> several synthetic and natural product small
molecule p300
inhibitors have been reported, including C646,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></sup> anarcardic acid,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref></sup> garcinol,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> curcumin,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></sup> epigallocatechin-3-gallate,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> and plumbagin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> Although
several derivatives of many of these inhibitors have been prepared
and evaluated in cells, their biochemical analyses <italic>in vitro</italic> have been incomplete, and their structures with HAT proteins bound
have not been determined; therefore, their mode of action is still
unclear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> The structure of the p300/acetonyl-CoA and
p300/CoA complexes with two PEG moieties bound proximal to the cofactor
binding site provides a more rational approach to developing potent
and selective small molecule p300 inhibitors. Both the acetonyl group
of acetonyl-CoA and PEG1, which overlap the lysine binding site of
p300, make stabilizing interactions with the p300 protein that may
provide a starting point for a fragment-based approach for developing
p300 inhibitors (Figure <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> One may then be able to “grow” potency by
extending the molecule into the CoA portion of the cofactor and “grow”
specificity by extending the molecule into the PEG2 region or the
shallow negatively charged groove that we had previously noted (Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup> Inhibitors designed
in this way may have potential as probes for the study of p300/CBP
function or as therapeutic agents for the treatment of p300/CBP-mediated
pathologies.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <notes id="notes-1">
      <title>Author Present Address</title>
      <p><sup>∥</sup> D.S.-P.: Department of Biology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia,
PA 19104.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="notes-2" notes-type="funding-statement">
      <p>This work was
supported by National Institutes of Health Grants GM062437 (to P.A.C.)
and GM060293 (to R.M.).</p>
    </notes>
    <notes id="NOTES-d3414e996-autogenerated" notes-type="conflict-of-interest">
      <p>The authors declare the
following competing financial interest(s): R.M. and P.A.C. declare
that they are cofounders and consultants for Acylin Therapeutics,
which is developing small molecule p300 inhibitors.</p>
    </notes>
    <glossary id="dl1">
      <def-list>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <def-item>
          <term>HAT</term>
          <def>
            <p>histone acetyltransferase</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CoA</term>
          <def>
            <p>coenzyme A</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>Ac-CoA</term>
          <def>
            <p>acetyl-coenzyme A</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>CBP</term>
          <def>
            <p>CREB binding protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>rmsd</term>
          <def>
            <p>root main square
deviation</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>PEG</term>
          <def>
            <p>poly(ethylene
glycol).</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Franza</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>; <name><surname>Schley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Association
of adenovirus early-region 1A proteins with cellular polypeptides</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1579</fpage>–<lpage>1589</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2431282</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Chrivia</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kwok</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Montminy</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Phosphorylated CREB binds specifically to the nuclear
protein CBP</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>365</volume>, <fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>859</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8413673</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The CBP co-activator is a histone
acetyltransferase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>384</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>643</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8967953</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit4"><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schiltz</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Russanova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The transcriptional
coactivators p300 and CBP are histone acetyltransferases</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>953</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8945521</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ghazawi</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interplay
of bromodomain and histone
acetylation in the regulation of p300-dependent genes</article-title>. <source>Epigenetics: Official Journal of the DNA Methylation Society</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>–<lpage>515</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20505343</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Boussouar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ney</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Rehg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Deursen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brindle</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A transcription-factor-binding surface
of coactivator p300 is required for haematopoiesis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>419</volume>, <fpage>738</fpage>–<lpage>743</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384703</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Activation
of p53 sequence-specific DNA binding by
acetylation of the p53 C-terminal domain</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>–<lpage>606</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9288740</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Lysine acetylation:
Codified crosstalk with other posttranslational
modifications</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18722172</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marmorstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Structure
and chemistry of the p300/CBP and Rtt109 histone acetyltransferases:
Implications for histone acetyltransferase evolution and function</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>741</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845255</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Smolik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>CBP/p300 in cell growth, transformation, and development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1553</fpage>–<lpage>1577</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887150</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Shikama</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Izuno</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Oguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sone</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wako</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Itou</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Clinical stage IE primary lymphoma of the nasal cavity: Radiation
therapy and chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>
<volume>204</volume>, <fpage>467</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9240537</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Russanova</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Barbie</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Human fibroblast
commitment to a senescence-like state in response to histone deacetylase
inhibitors is cell cycle dependent</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell.
Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>5210</fpage>–<lpage>5218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>N. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bannister</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Daigo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kouzarides</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Caldas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>p300 is required for orderly G1/S transition in human
cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16878158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fulco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pediconi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>An</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Levrero</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the p300 HAT domain
via a novel activation loop</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol.
Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15004546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Karanam</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Kinetic
and mass spectrometric analysis of p300 histone acetyltransferase
domain autoacetylation</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>281</volume>, <fpage>40292</fpage>–<lpage>40301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17065153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marmorstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The structural basis of protein acetylation
by the p300/CBP transcriptional coactivator</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>451</volume>, <fpage>846</fpage>–<lpage>850</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18273021</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Delvecchio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gaucher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aguilar-Gurrieri</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Panne</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structure
of the p300 catalytic core and implications for chromatin targeting
and HAT regulation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1040</fpage>–<lpage>1046</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23934153</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="cit18"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Segel</surname><given-names>I. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>Enzyme kinetics: Behavior and analysis
of rapid equilibrium and steady
state enzyme systems</source>, <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>Otwinowski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Processing of X-ray Diffraction Data Collected in Oscillation Mode</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>276</volume>, <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Storoni</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Likelihood-enhanced
fast translation functions</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>D61</volume>, <fpage>458</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Coot: Model-building
tools for molecular graphics</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>D60</volume>, <fpage>2126</fpage>–<lpage>2132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ioerger</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sacchettini</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Terwilliger</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>PHENIX:
Building new software for
automated crystallographic structure determination</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1948</fpage>–<lpage>1954</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Characterization and prediction of
lysine (K)-acetyl-transferase specific acetylation sites</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell. Proteomics</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>M111.011080</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dryer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>S-acetonyl-CoA. A nonreactive analog of acetyl-CoA</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>255</volume>, <fpage>7858</fpage>–<lpage>7862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6995455</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>O. D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Soccio</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ait-Si-Ali</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vassilev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wolffe</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>HATs off:
Selective synthetic inhibitors
of the histone acetyltransferases p300 and PCAF</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>595</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10882143</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>E.
M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Orry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Holbert</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hazzalin</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liszczak</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Larocca</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Saldanha</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Abagyan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Marmorstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Alani</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Virtual ligand screening of the p300/CBP
histone acetyltransferase: Identification of a selective small molecule
inhibitor</article-title>. <source>Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>482</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534345</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Anacardic acid (6-nonadecyl
salicylic acid), an inhibitor
of histone acetyltransferase, suppresses expression of nuclear factor-κB-regulated
gene products involved in cell survival, proliferation, invasion,
and inflammation through inhibition of the inhibitory subunit of nuclear
factor-κBα kinase, leading to potentiation of apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>111</volume>, <fpage>4880</fpage>–<lpage>4891</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18349320</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref28">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Balasubramanyam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Varier</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sadhale</surname><given-names>P. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Polyisoprenylated
benzophenone, garcinol, a natural histone acetyltransferase inhibitor,
represses chromatin transcription and alters global gene expression</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>33716</fpage>–<lpage>33726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref29">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Balasubramanyam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Varier</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Siddappa</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ranga</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Curcumin, a novel
p300/CREB-binding protein-specific inhibitor of acetyltransferase,
represses the acetylation of histone/nonhistone proteins and histone
acetyltransferase-dependent chromatin transcription</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>51163</fpage>–<lpage>51171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref30">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Epigallocatechin-3-gallate,
a histone acetyltransferase inhibitor, inhibits EBV-induced B lymphocyte
transformation via suppression of RelA acetylation</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19147572</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref31">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Ravindra</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Selvi</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Thanuja</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nagashayana</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Inhibition of lysine acetyltransferase
KAT3B/p300 activity by a naturally occurring hydroxynaphthoquinone,
plumbagin</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>284</volume>, <fpage>24453</fpage>–<lpage>24464</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570987</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref32">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Heery</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Pharmacological
targeting of lysine acetyltransferases
in human disease: A progress report</article-title>. <source>Drug Discovery
Today</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17198977</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref33">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Furdas</surname><given-names>S.
D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sippl</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Small molecule inhibitors
of histone acetyltransferases as epigenetic tools and drug candidates</article-title>. <source>Arch. Pharm. (Weinheim, Ger.)</source>
<volume>345</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>