<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T20:04:40Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5415847" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5415847</identifier><datestamp>2017-05-25</datestamp><setSpec>portlandopen</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochem J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biochem. J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">ppbiochemj</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BCJ</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biochemical Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0264-6021</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1470-8728</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Portland Press Ltd.</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5415847</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5415847</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5415847</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28258151</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28258151</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BCJ-2017-0085</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BCJ20170085</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Research Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>4</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>34</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>53</subject>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>45</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> SdrE captures complement factor H's C-terminus via a novel ‘close, dock, lock and latch' mechanism for complement evasion</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Yingjie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
            <given-names>Minhao</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hang</surname>
            <given-names>Tianrong</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
            <given-names>Chengliang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Yang</surname>
            <given-names>Ye</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pan</surname>
            <given-names>Weimin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Zang</surname>
            <given-names>Jianye</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Min</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
            <given-names>Xuan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1"><label>1</label>School of Life Science, Anhui University, 111 Jiulong Road, Hefei 230601, China</aff>
      <aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Hefei National Laboratory for Physical Sciences at Microscale, CAS Center for Excellence in Biomacromolecules, Collaborative Innovation Center of Chemistry for Life Sciences, and School of Life Sciences, University of Science and Technology of China, 96 Jinzhai Road, Hefei, Anhui 230026, China</aff>
      <aff id="af3"><label>3</label>Key Laboratory of Structural Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, 96 Jinzhai Road, Hefei, Anhui 230026, China</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1">Correspondence: Xuan Zhang (<email>xuanzbin@ustc.edu.cn</email>) or Min Zhang (<email>zhmin07@ustc.edu</email>)</corresp>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="an1">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epreprint">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>474</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>1619</fpage>
      <lpage>1631</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2017 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This is an open access article published by Portland Press Limited on behalf of the Biochemical Society and distributed under the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License 4.0 (CC BY-NC-ND)</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="BCJ-2017-0085.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <p>Complement factor H (CFH) is a soluble complement regulatory protein essential for the down-regulation of the alternative pathway on interaction with specific markers on the host cell surface. It recognizes the complement component 3b (C3b) and 3d (C3d) fragments in addition to self cell markers (i.e. glycosaminoglycans, sialic acid) to distinguish host cells that deserve protection from pathogens that should be eliminated. The <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> surface protein serine–aspartate repeat protein E (SdrE) was previously reported to bind human CFH as an immune-evasion tactic. However, the molecular mechanism underlying SdrE–CFH-mediated immune evasion remains unknown. In the present study, we identified a novel region at CFH's C-terminus (CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>), which binds SdrE N2 and N3 domains (SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>) with high affinity, and determined the crystal structures of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex. Comparison of the structure of the CFH–SdrE complex with other CFH structures reveals that CFH's C-terminal tail flips from the main body to insert into the ligand-binding groove of SdrE. In addition, SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> adopts a ‘close’ state in the absence of CFH, which undergoes a large conformational change on CFH binding, suggesting a novel ‘close, dock, lock and latch' (CDLL) mechanism for SdrE to recognize its ligand. Our findings imply that SdrE functions as a ‘clamp' to capture CFH's C-terminal tail via a unique CDLL mechanism and sequesters CFH on the surface of <italic>S. aureus</italic> for complement evasion.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>complement factor H</kwd>
        <kwd>crystal structure</kwd>
        <kwd>immune evasion mechanism</kwd>
        <kwd>ligand recognition</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> SdrE</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>As the first line of immune defence for humans, the complement system plays a crucial role in pathogen recognition, destruction and elimination [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This powerful defence system comprises more than 30 proteins in the blood or on the cell surface, which can be activated in a cascade-dependent process via three different pathways: the classic, lectin and alternative pathways [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The three pathways converge at the generation of complement component 3 (C3) and complement component 5 (C5) convertases, which results in cleavage of C3 into fragments C3a and C3b. The C3b fragment interacts with C5 convertase to cleave C5 into fragments C5a and C5b. On formation of the convertases, anaphylatoxins (C3a/C5a), the membrane-attack complex and opsonins (C3b) are generated [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>The alternative pathway is crucial for amplification of the complement cascade, because it accounts for between 80% and 90% of total complement activation [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. To avoid damage to host tissues, complement factor H (CFH) and C3b are applied to discriminate between host and foreign cells [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], with C3b spontaneously deposited on the surface of all cells (host cells, as well as pathogens) exposed to the activated complement system. CFH, a complement regulator in either soluble or membrane-bound form, binds to the C3b and C3d fragments, as well as to host-cell markers [polyanions, such as glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) and sialic acid] to distinguish host cells from pathogens or altered host cells (e.g. cancer cells) and protect host cells from unintended complement-mediated injury.</p>
      <p>CFH is composed of 20 complement-control protein (CCP) units (also known as short consensus repeats), with spacers consisting of three to eight amino acids between units. Each unit contains ∼60 amino acids, with the sequence highly conserved across units [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. As a key regulator in the alternative pathway, CFH is abundant in serum, with a concentration of ∼500 mg/ml. However, fluctuations in serum CFH concentrations can range from 116 mg/ml to 562 mg/ml according to different environmental and genetic factors [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The important regulatory function and high concentration of CFH make it a favourable target for surface binding by pathogens, in order to disguise themselves as normal host cells and escape elimination by the complement system [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It has been reported that the surface-exposed lipoprotein fHbp of <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> mimics the host carbohydrates to bind CFH–CCP6 [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The outer surface protein E (OspE) of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> binds to CFH–CCP20 in a similar way to host cells binding CFH–CCP20 via GAGs [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> surface protein SdrE, which belongs to the serine–aspartate repeat-containing protein (Sdr) subfamily within the microbial surface component recognizing adhesive matrix molecule (MSCRAMM) family, was recently reported to bind CFH as an immune-evasion tactic [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Sdr subfamily members adopt a similar structural pattern, including an N-terminal signal peptide (S), a functional ligand-binding region (A), a B region, a Ser–Asp repeated R region, a C-terminal cell wall membrane-spanning region (W), a hydrophobic membrane region (M) and a cytoplasmic tail (C). The N2 and N3 domains in the A region form IgG-like folds that bind ligands [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Although the fibrinogen (Fg)-bound structures of the N2–N3 domains of other MSCRAMM proteins, including SdrG [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], branch-point-binding protein (Bbp) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], clumping factor A (ClfA) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and B (ClfB) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], have been reported, little is known about how the newly identified ligand CFH is recognized by MSCRAMM family proteins. Furthermore, the molecular basis for SdrE–CFH recognition and SdrE–CFH-mediated immune evasion still remains to be elucidated.</p>
      <p>In the present study, we mapped the minimal binding region [amino acids 1206–1226 (CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>)] in CFH–CCP20 for interaction with SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>, and solved the structures of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> (PDB code: 5WTA) and the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex (PDB: 5WTB). Structural analysis and comparison with other MSCRAMM proteins revealed a novel closed state of SdrE, wherein the ligand-binding groove formed by the N2 and N3 domains is occupied by Loop<sup>A–B</sup> in the absence of ligand. To capture CFH's C-terminal tail, Loop<sup>A–B</sup> of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> rotates ∼180° to facilitate CFH binding. This indicates that SdrE recognizes its ligands by using a unique ‘close, dock, lock and latch' (CDLL) mechanism observed in the MSCRAMM protein family for the first time. Compared with the structures of CFH in complex with C3b, fHbp or OspE, a large conformational change of the C-terminal tail of CFH was observed on SdrE binding, demonstrating a novel recognition mechanism between CFH and its ligands. All these findings illustrate that SdrE binds to a unique region in CFH's C-terminal region with a high affinity for capturing CFH for complement evasion. Our findings suggest that SdrE functions as a ‘clamp' to capture the CFH C-terminal tail via a novel ‘CDLL' mechanism and sequesters CFH on the surface of <italic>S. aureus</italic> to evade the human immune system.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s2">
      <title>Experimental</title>
      <sec id="s2a">
        <title>Cloning, expression and purification</title>
        <p>DNA fragments encoding residues 270–599 of wild-type SdrE or its mutants were obtained by PCR and ligated to pET-22b(+) (Novagen) vector with a C-terminal 6×His tag. The construct was transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) strain and grown with shaking overnight at 37°C in a 20-ml starter culture of Luria–Bertani (LB) medium containing 100 µg/ml of ampicillin. The overnight starter culture was then transferred into 1 l of LB medium and incubated at 37°C with shaking until reaching an absorbance at 600 nm of ∼0.6. The culture was then induced with 0.4 mM IPTG and incubated at 16°C for 18–24 h. The cells were harvested by centrifugation (277 K, 6000<bold><italic>g</italic></bold>, 8 min) and suspended in lysis buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 500 mM NaCl and 5%(v/v) glycerol]. The cells were then homogenized by sonication and the lysate was centrifuged for 30 min at 12 000<bold><italic>g</italic></bold> and 277 K. The supernatant was loaded onto a Ni/NTA nickel-chelating column (Qiagen) pre-equilibrated with lysis buffer. The column was washed by approximately 20 column volumes of lysis buffer with 40 mM imidazole to remove contaminants. The eluted target protein was concentrated by centrifugal ultrafiltration (Millipore, 10-kDa cut-off) and further purified using a Superdex 75 16/60 size exclusion column (GE Healthcare) equilibrated with buffer consisting of 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 400 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol and 1 mM DTT. Various truncated fragments and mutants of human CFH were amplified by PCR and cloned to the pGEX-6P-1 vector. The recombinant proteins were expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) strain and purified by GST affinity chromatography.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2b">
        <title>Crystallization and data collection</title>
        <p>The apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> protein was concentrated to 20 mg/ml in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 400 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol and 1 mM DTT. The synthesized CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> peptide and SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> were mixed at a molar ratio of 5:1 and incubated at 277 K overnight. Initial crystallization screening was carried out at 298 K using a sitting-drop, vapour-diffusion method with commercial screen kits from Hampton Research (Crystal Screen, Crystal Screen 2, SaltRx 1, SaltRx 2, PEGRx 1, PEGRx 2 and Index). The apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> crystals were grown in 0.1 M citric acid, pH 3.5, 16% (w/v) PEG-3350 and 2% (v/v) 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol (MPD). The complex crystals were obtained from 0.1 M Hepes, pH 7.5, 0.2 M magnesium chloride and 30% (v/v) PEG-400. X-ray diffraction data for apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex were collected at 100 K at Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility (SSRF) beamline BL17U1 and BL18U1, respectively. Diffraction data were indexed, integrated and scaled using the programs iMOSFLM [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], POINTLESS [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and SCALA [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] in the CCP4i suite [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2c">
        <title>Structure determination, refinement and analysis</title>
        <p>The crystal structure of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> was determined by molecular replacement using Phaser [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] in the CCP4i suite with SdrG<sub>N2N3</sub> (PDB: 1R17) as the search model. After several runs of structure refinement using the programs REFMAC5 [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and COOT [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], the final model was refined to 2.3 Å (1 Å = 0.1 nm) resolution with an <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> of 19.4% and an <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub> of 25.2%. The SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex structure was solved by molecular replacement using apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> as the search model. The final model was refined to 3.3 Å resolution with an <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> of 22.2% and an <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub> of 28.1%. The quality of the final models was analysed using the program MolProbity [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Data collection and model refinement statistics are shown in <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085TB1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="BCJ-2017-0085TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Data collection and structure reﬁnement statistics</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Data collection</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Space group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub>2<sub>1</sub></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PDB ID</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5WTA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5WTB</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"> Unit cell parameters</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  a, b, c (Å)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.81, 61.73, 139.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.50, 117.50, 154.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  α, β, γ (°)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.89, 89.83, 73.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00, 90.00, 90.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Resolution range (Å)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.01–2.30 (2.42–2.30)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn1">1</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.75–3.30 (3.48–3.30)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Wavelength (Å)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9792</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9779</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unique reﬂections</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 992</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 291</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Completeness (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.5 (95.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.1 (97.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overall <italic>I</italic>/σ(<italic>I</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (1.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Multiplicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8 (2.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>R</italic><sub>sym</sub> (%)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn2">2</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4 (56.1)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Refinement</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Resolution range (Å)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00–2.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.75–3.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn3">3</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn4">4</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> RMSD bond lengths (Å)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> RMSD bond angles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.408</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.371</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"> Average B-factors (Å<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Water</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"> Ramachandran plot<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn5">5</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Most favoured regions (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Allowed regions (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">  Generously allowed regions (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"> MolProbity</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Clash score<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="tfn6">6</xref></sup>/percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.89/96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.63/89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Overall score/percentile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20/81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31/80</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>1</label><p>The values in parentheses refer to statistics in the highest shell.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>2</label><p><italic>R</italic><sub>sym</sub> = |<italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic>−|/|<italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic>| where <italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic> is the intensity of the <italic>i</italic>th measurement, and is the mean intensity for that reﬂection.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3"><label>3</label><p><italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> <italic>=</italic> Σ<sub>hkl</sub>||<italic>F</italic><sub>obs</sub>| − <italic>k</italic>|<italic>F</italic><sub>cal</sub>| |/Σ<sub>hkl</sub> |<italic>F</italic><sub>obs</sub>| where <italic>F</italic><sub>obs</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>cal</sub> are observed and calculated structure factors, respectively, calculated over all reflections used in the refinement.</p></fn><fn id="tfn4"><label>4</label><p><italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub>, is similar to <italic>R</italic><sub>work</sub> but calculated over a subset of reflections (5%) excluded from all stages of refinement.</p></fn><fn id="tfn5"><label>5</label><p>Statistics for the Ramachandran plot from an analysis using MolProbity.</p></fn><fn id="tfn6"><label>6</label><p>The MolProbity clash score indicates the number of steric overlaps &gt;0.4 Å per 1000 atoms.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2d">
        <title>GST pull-down assay</title>
        <p>Various truncated fragments and mutants of human CFH were overexpressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) cells. The cells were suspended in lysis buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 400 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol and 1 mM DTT] and then homogenized by sonication. After centrifugation of the lysates, the supernatant was incubated with 30 µl of GST beads (pre-equilibrated in lysis buffer) at 4°C for 1 h. The beads were washed with 1 ml of lysis buffer three times to remove the impurities. Then GST beads immobilized with GST–CFH were incubated with purified wild-type SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> or its mutant at 4°C for 1 h. The beads were washed with 1 ml of lysis buffer five times to remove proteins that were non-specific binding. Beads were boiled with SDS/sample buffer and proteins retained on the GST beads were analysed using SDS/PAGE (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B–D</xref> and see <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B and D</xref>).
<fig id="BCJ-2017-0085F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>CFH–CCP20 is responsible for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> binding</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of SdrE and CFH domain organization. S, signal sequence; N1–N3, ligand-binding region; B1–B3, B repeats region; R, serine–aspartate repeat region; W, wall-spanning region; M, membrane-spanning region; C, cytoplasmic, positively charged tail. The amino acid residue number identifying the boundary between each subdomain is indicated above. (<bold>B</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) GST pull-down assays of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with different fragments of the CFH fused to a GST tag. The retaining amino acid residues of each CFH fragment are indicated in each panel. (<bold>E</bold>) The ITC fitting curves of GST–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> to SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BCJ-2017-0085.01"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2e">
        <title>Isothermal titration calorimetry</title>
        <p>The interaction between SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> protein and GST–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> was analysed using isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) with a MicroCal iTC200 instrument (GE Healthcare) at 20°C in 50 mM Tris, pH 7.8, 400 mM NaCl and 0.5 mM tris(2-carboxyl)phosphine (TCEP). Experimental data were fitted to a single binding-site model and analysed using the ITC data analysis module of Origin 7.0 (MicroCal) provided by the manufacturer (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <sec id="s3a">
        <title>The C-terminal tail of CFH–CCP20 binds to SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with high affinity</title>
        <p>The CCP19–20 region of CFH was reported to be capable of discriminating between host and complement-activating cells [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. It is essential for binding the C3d part of C3b, and for the self cell markers such as GAGs and sialic acids. Some pathogen-secreted proteins, including the PspC [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] protein from <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and OspE [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] from <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic>, were also reported to recruit CFH through their interaction with the CCP19–20 units. SdrE is a newly identified CFH-binding protein that belongs to MSCRAMM family, which normally uses the extracellular domains N2 and N3 to bind ligands. Therefore, we hypothesized that SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> recruits CFH via interactions with CFH–CCP19–20 (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>).</p>
        <p>To test our hypothesis, we constructed four CFH fragments (CFH<sup>1107–1138</sup>, CFH<sup>1139–1168</sup>, CFH<sup>1166–1196</sup> and CFH<sup>1195–1231</sup>) within CCP19–20 fused to a GST tag at the N-terminus. <italic>In vitro</italic> GST pull-down assays confirm that the C-terminal 37 amino acids of CFH–CCP20 (CFH<sup>1195–1231</sup>) are capable of interacting with SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). To identify the shortest region in CFH–CCP20 responsible for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> binding, shorter CFH fragments were used for GST pull-down assays. As shown in <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>(C and D), a minimal segment containing 21 amino acid residues (CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>) is sufficient for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> interaction.</p>
        <p>Kajander et al. [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] reported that the CCP19–20 region binds the C3d fragment primarily through the CCP20 site, but binds C3b through the CCP19 site, and proposed a comprehensive molecular mechanism for target discrimination mediated by CFH in the alternative pathway. On host-cell surfaces, CFH binds to the C3b site and cell surface markers through CCP19 and CCP20 sites, respectively. This causes the rapid down-regulation of the alternative pathway and converts C3b to C3d on host-cell surfaces, resulting in additional CFH proteins recruited to the surface. While localized on the surfaces of pathogens lacking host-cell markers, CCP19–20 binds to C3b with lower affinity, subsequently activating the alternative pathway and initiating pathogen elimination [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. To evade complement-mediated destruction, some pathogens use surface proteins to sequester CFH to their cell surface. After confirming that the CFH–CCP20 domain is recognized by SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>, we determined the binding affinity of CCP20 to SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>, revealing that SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> strongly interacts with CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>, with a dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) value of ∼0.4 µΜ (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>), which is as high as that measured for the CCP20–C3d interaction [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. These findings indicate that the relatively strong binding of SdrE to CCP20 promotes efficient recruitment of CFH to the cell surface of <italic>S. aureus</italic> for complement disguise.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3b">
        <title>A novel ‘close' state of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with the ligand-binding groove occupied by Loop<sup>A–B</sup></title>
        <p>To investigate the molecular basis for CFH recognition by SdrE, we solved the crystal structures of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> in complex with CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>. SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> exists as a monomer in both solution and its crystal form (see Supplementary Figure S1). Four apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> monomers were found in one asymmetrical unit. Each subunit consists of two distinct domains: N2 (residues 270–419) and N3 (residues 420–586) (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>), packing against each other and separated by a short linker region. The N2 and N3 domains contain eight (A↑B↓C↑D1↑D2↓E↑F↓G↑) and nine (A′↓B′↑C′↓D′↑D1′↓D2′↑E′↓F′↑G′↓) antiparallel β-strands, respectively. The topologies of N2 and N3 domains are structurally similar, with both resembling the IgG-like fold, except that N2 lacks the D-strand (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Structural comparison with other reported MSCRAMM proteins reveals similar overall structures between SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and Bbp (PDB: 5CF3, RMSD of 2.7 Å over 304 Cα atoms), SdrG (PDB: 1R19, RMSD of 2.6 Å over 276 Cα atoms), ClfB (PDB: 4F24, RMSD of 3.4 Å over 237 Cα atoms) and SdrD (PDB: 4JE0, RMSD of 4.7 Å over 229 Cα atoms), but a novel ‘close' state with the ligand-binding groove occupied by Loop<sup>A–B</sup> (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). The Loop<sup>A–B</sup> in SdrE homologues either turns around to interact with the N2–N3 linker and G-strand in Bbp, SdrG and ClfB, or locates by the side of the groove as a loop in SdrD, to leave the groove in an ‘open' state for ligand binding. However, the Loop<sup>A–B</sup> in SdrE extends from the N2 domain to form a pair of antiparallel β-sheets with the G′-strand in the N3 domain. The β-sheet is stabilized by four pairs of main-chain hydrogen bonds, resulting in the ligand-binding groove of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> being locked in a ‘close' state (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C and D</xref>).
<fig id="BCJ-2017-0085F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><title>Crystal structure of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub></title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon representation of the structure of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and a schematic representation of the topology of the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> fold. The N2 and N3 domains are shown in purple and green, respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Structural comparison of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with its homologous structures; Loop<sup>A–B</sup> is coloured purple for SdrE, green for Bbp, red for SdrG, wheat for ClfB and blue for SdrD. (<bold>C</bold>) Surface representation of the ‘open' state of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with the Loop<sup>A–B</sup> deleted from the structure. (<bold>D</bold>) Cartoon representation of the ‘close' state of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>. The N2 and N3 domains are shown in purple and green, respectively. The ligand-binding groove is highlighted by a dashed red ellipse. Key residues that stabilize the ‘close' state are shown as sticks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BCJ-2017-0085.02"/></fig></p>
        <p>It is not the first time that the ‘close' conformation of MSCRAMM proteins has been mentioned. A ‘dock, lock and latch' (DLL) model was proposed for the SdrG based on its apo- and Fg-peptide-bound structures [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In this model, the Fg peptide docks into the ‘open'-form groove first. Then the C-terminal tail of N3 extends forward to ‘lock' the peptide in place and an additional G′′-strand is formed to ‘latch' on to the peptide–SdrG complex by interacting with the N2 domain. A ‘close' conformation of SdrG, which was generated by introducing a disulfide bond between the latch and the N2 domain, cannot bind Fg, demonstrating that the ‘open' state of the ligand-binding groove of SdrG is required for the initial docking of the ligand [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, a ClfA mutant, exhibiting an artificially closed binding groove through the introduction of a disulfide bond in a similar manner, retains the ability to bind Fg with lower affinity compared with that observed in wild-type proteins. Therefore, a different ligand-binding mechanism, the ‘latch, dock' (LD) model, was proposed for ClfA [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Although this ‘close' conformation was proposed, up until now no structural or other evidence was reported to clearly confirm this state of MSCRAMM proteins. The ‘close' state observed in the SdrE structure, in contrast to the previously proposed ‘close' state artificially formed by the ‘latch' of the N3 domain, is formed by Loop<sup>A–B</sup> protruding into the N2 domain to occupy the ligand-binding groove. This novel ‘close' state suggests a new ligand-binding mechanism for SdrE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3c">
        <title>CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> is recognized by SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> via a CDLL mechanism</title>
        <p>For further investigation, we solved the crystal structure of the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex. One SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> molecule and one CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> molecule form a heterodimer. Four SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> heterodimers, named heterodimer A–D, are found in one asymmetrical unit (see Supplementary Figure S2). Two SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> heterodimers form a tetramer via interaction of the C-terminal of four amino acids with the two CFH peptides (see Supplementary Figure S2). Gel filtration and PISA (proteins, interfaces, structures and assemblies) analysis clarify that the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex exists as a heterodimer in both solution and crystal form, respectively (see Supplementary Figure S2). Therefore, the tetrameric conformation associated with the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> structure was caused by crystal packing. The overall structures of the four SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> molecules are almost identical, with an average RMSD of 0.3 Å over 330 aligned Cα atoms. To simplify the description, we discuss only heterodimer A. As shown in <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, the CFH peptide forms a long β-strand and threads the ligand-binding groove between the N2 and N3 subdomains. Apart from four C-terminal residues (1223–1226), a well-defined electron density map is observed for the main chain of all other residues (1206–1222) and the side chain of some residues (see Supplementary Figure S3). Similar to Fg-bound Bbp, SdrG, ClfB and ClfA structures [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] (see Supplementary Figure S4), the CFH peptide forms an antiparallel β-sheet with G′-strand in N3, whereas the C-terminal G′-strand undergoes a rotation to surround the N-terminus of the CFH peptide. The C-terminal residues (587–598) missing in the apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> structure are ordered as a G″-strand on CFH binding in the complex structure, and extend to the N2 domain to compose complete β-sheets together with strands A, B and E (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). The buried surface between SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and CFH is considerably larger, approximately 1100 Å<sup>2</sup>. A total of 13 pairs of antiparallel, main-chain hydrogen bonds are formed by SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and the CFH peptide (see Supplementary Figure S5). All residues in SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> involved in the CFH binding belong to the G′-strand (572–586), demonstrating a critical role of the G′-strand in the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH interaction. In addition, side-chain interactions between SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and CFH include four hydrogen bonds and one hydrophobic interaction. The carbonyl oxygen of Asp<sup>334</sup> and Asp<sup>588</sup> from SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> form hydrogen bonds with Ser<sup>1208</sup> and Arg<sup>1206</sup> from CFH, respectively. The main-chain nitrogen of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub><sup>F433</sup> forms the hydrogen bond with the side-chain oxygen of CFH<sup>S1209</sup>. The side-chain nitrogen of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub><sup>Q419</sup> contributes another hydrogen bond via interaction with the hydroxyl group of CFH<sup>S1211</sup>. A hydrophobic pocket created by Leu<sup>335</sup>, Leu<sup>436</sup> and Ile<sup>583</sup> from SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> mediates the hydrophobic interaction with the side chain of CFH<sup>L1207</sup> (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>).
<fig id="BCJ-2017-0085F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><title>Crystal structure of the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Cartoon representation of the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex. N2 and N3 subdomains from the SdrE and the CFH peptide are coloured purple, green and yellow, respectively. Loop<sup>A–B</sup> is indicated by a red arrow. Key residues involved in the side-chain interactions between SdrE and CFH are shown as sticks in the zoom-in view. Hydrogen bonds involved in the SdrE–CFH interaction are shown as black dashes. (<bold>B</bold>) GST pull-down assays of GST–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> with SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and its mutants. (<bold>C</bold>) Identification of the key residues on CFH–CCP20 for SdrE binding. Key residues are coloured red. (<bold>D</bold>) Structural comparison of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> (wheat) and the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex (green). Loop<sup>A–B</sup> and Loop<sup>C′–D′</sup> are circled by red dashes and labelled in black. The change of the two conformations of Loop<sup>A–B</sup> is indicated by a red arrow. (<bold>E</bold>) A CDLL model for the SdrE–CFH interaction is shown as a cartoon.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BCJ-2017-0085.03"/></fig></p>
        <p>To verify our complex structure, SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> residues Asp<sup>334</sup>, Leu3<sup>35</sup>, Gln<sup>419</sup> and Asp<sup>588</sup>, which interact with CFH through side chains, were mutated to alanine, and their interaction with CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> was evaluated by GST pull-down assays. As shown in <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>, the mutations D334A, L335A and Q419A significantly weaken the interaction between SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and CFH, whereas the mutation D588A absolutely abolishes the interaction. Consistent with the structural analysis, our mutagenesis studies confirm the important roles of Asp<sup>334</sup>, Leu<sup>335</sup>, Gln<sup>419</sup> and Asp<sup>588</sup> from SdrE in the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH interaction. To identify residues of CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> that are important for binding SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>, each residue within CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> (except for alanine and glycine) was sequentially substituted by alanine (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). The binding ability of each mutant for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> was tested <italic>in vitro</italic> by GST pull-down assays. Remarkably, the mutations R1206A and S1208A absolutely abolish the interaction of CFH with SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>. Interaction between CFH and SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> is significantly weakened by the mutations S1209A and S1211A, whereas mutation L1207A results in the loss of half the binding capacity of CFH with SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>. Therefore, Arg<sup>1206</sup>, Leu<sup>1207</sup>, Ser1<sup>208</sup>, Ser<sup>1209</sup> and Ser<sup>1211</sup> are the key residues of CFH for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> binding.</p>
        <p>To investigate the ligand-binding mechanism associated with the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH interaction, we compared the apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> structure with that of the CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>-bound form. The overall structure of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> in either apo- or CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>-bound form is similar, with an RMSD of 2.8 Å over 293 aligned Cα atoms. Several significant conformational changes caused by the interaction of the CFH peptide are observed (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>). First, Loop<sup>A–B</sup> rotates ∼180° away from the ligand-binding groove to interact with the N2–N3 linker and the G-strand, which converts the ‘close’ groove to the ‘open' conformation for CFH binding. Second, residues from Val<sup>468</sup> to Leu<sup>476</sup> from Loop<sup>C′–D′</sup> become disordered after the ‘dock' procedure with the CFH peptide. This region of Loop<sup>C′–D′</sup> localizes in close proximity to the CFH-binding site in the apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> structure; however, after CFH binding, this region could be dislocated and become disordered. The third and most significant difference is the formation of the ‘lock' and ‘latch' structures in the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH complex. The C-terminus of the G′-strand bends around the N-terminal region of the CFH peptide to ‘lock’ the ligand in place, and extends further to form an additional G′′-strand to create β-sheets with β-strands in the N2 domain, thereby functioning as a ‘latch'. The novel ‘close' state of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and the structural comparison of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup>-bound SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> indicate a novel ligand-binding mechanism as a ‘CDLL' model among MSCRAMM proteins (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E</xref>). In addition, the ‘close' conformation implicates potential regulatory mechanisms associated with SdrE by unknown cellular components.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3d">
        <title>SdrE functions as a ‘clamp' to capture the C-terminal tail of the CFH for complement evasion</title>
        <p>CFH functions as a host-recognition molecule and complement regulator in the alternative pathway. Normal recognition of host cells by the CFH requires the interaction of different CFH–CCP complexes with C3b and markers on the cell surfaces. CCP1–4 and CCP19–20 represent binding sites for C3b [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The crystal structure of the CCP19–20–C3d complex revealed that C3d binds to both CCP19 and -20 [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). CCP6 and CCP20 are capable of binding heparin and other polyanions, including GAGs [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and CCP20 was also reported to be a sialic acid-binding site [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). Among all 20 CCP units, the C3b and host cell marker-binding sites on CCP19–20 play key roles in host recognition/discrimination and complement regulation. The dual interaction of CFH with C3b via the CCP19 site and with cell surface polyanions (heparin, GAGs, sialic acid) via the CCP20 site ensures optimal binding between the CFH and the host-cell surface. This results in rapid down-regulation of the alternative pathway and recruitment of additional CFH proteins to the surface to protect host cells. In contrast, microbes that lack such polyanions have far fewer CFH proteins located on their surfaces and are thereby susceptible to subsequent complement-mediated destruction. To escape elimination by the alternative pathway, some pathogens have developed novel strategies to recruit CFH to their surfaces, thus disguising themselves as normal host cells and evading immune attack. <italic>N. meningitidis</italic> subverts immune responses by using the surface protein fHbp to mimic host carbohydrates to recruit CFH [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Structural analysis combined with biochemical studies demonstrates that fHbp interacts with CFH–CCP6. The interaction interface between fHbp and CFH–CCP6 overlaps with the GAG-binding site on CFH–CCP6. Another outer surface protein, OspE of <italic>B. burgdorferi,</italic> was recently reported to bind to the same site as GAGs and sialic acid in CFH–CCP20 (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B and C</xref>) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, the binding site for SdrE on the CFH is unique (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4D</xref>). In the present study, we identified Arg<sup>1206</sup>, Leu<sup>1207</sup>, Ser<sup>1208</sup>, Ser<sup>1209</sup> and Ser<sup>1211</sup> of the CFH as the key residues required for SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> binding (see <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). These differ from the residues in CFH–CCP20 identified for C3d binding (1182, 1183, 1184 and 1203) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], binding of the cell markers heparin, GAGs and sialic acid (1182, 1183, 1186, 1188, 1189, 1198, 1215 and 1230) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and binding to the pathogen surface protein OspE (1182, 1183, 1189, 1198 and 1215) (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A–D</xref>) [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Although SdrE recruits CFH by interacting with CCP20, which represents a common binding site for surface proteins from different pathogens, our structural and biochemical analysis demonstrated that the interaction region in CCP20 and the CFH-binding mechanism associated with SdrE were unique (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A–D</xref>).
<fig id="BCJ-2017-0085F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><title>Structural comparison of the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex with C3d/sialic acid/OspE–CFH complexes</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>–<bold>D</bold>) Cartoon representation of crystal structures of CFH–CCP19–20 complexed with (<bold>A</bold>) C3d (cyan), (<bold>B</bold>) sialic acid (yellow), (<bold>C</bold>) OspE (pink) and (<bold>D</bold>) SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> (grey). CCP19 and CCP20 are coloured wheat and green, respectively. The SdrE-binding region on CCP20 is coloured and labelled red. Binding sites on CCP20 for C3d, sialic acid and OspE are shown in zoom-in windows, with the key residues on CCP20 labelled in black and highlighted by dashed red circles. (<bold>E</bold>) Proposed model for the CFH–SdrE-mediated immune evasion mechanism.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="BCJ-2017-0085.04"/></fig></p>
        <p>Structural comparison of CFH peptide bound to SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> with CFH–CCP20 complexed with C3d, sialic acid or OspE reveals a big conformational change of the C-terminal tail of CCP20 on SdrE binding (<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A–D</xref>). CCP20 interacts with C3d and sialic acid mainly through electrostatic interactions, mediated by its positively charged surface regions. The <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> surface protein OspE also uses a similar mechanism to bind the same region on CCP20 where sialic acid binds. Unique among these CFH ligands, SdrE's structural features make it suitable to function as a ‘clamp' for capturing CFH's C-terminal tail. As shown in the model in <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>(E), SdrE adopts a ‘close' conformation after integration on to the <italic>S. aureus</italic> surface during infection. When the host complement component C3b is deposited on the <italic>S. aureus</italic> surface, CFH binds to C3b through CCP1–4 and CCP19. Simultaneously, Loop<sup>A–B</sup> of SdrE<sub>N2</sub> rotates ∼180° to convert the ‘close' conformation to an ‘open' one to accommodate the C-terminal tail of CFH–CCP20. By undergoing a big conformational change, CCP20's C-terminal tail protrudes from the CFH to dock into the ligand-binding groove of SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> by forming an antiparallel β-sheet with the G′-strand of SdrE<sub>N3</sub>. In addition, SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> functions as a ‘clamp' to strongly stabilize the CFH–SdrE complex by locking and latching the CFH tail in its ligand-binding groove (see <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref> and <xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085F4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). Given that SdrE binds to CFH with a high affinity and functions as a ‘clamp' to capture CFH's C-terminal tail, SdrE efficiently recruits CFH proteins to <italic>S. aureus</italic> surfaces, followed by <italic>S. aureus</italic> recruitment of factor I using CFH–CCP1–4 and its surface protein ClfA to cleave C3b into iC3b [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In addition, to decrease C3b deposition, CFH also accelerates the decay of already formed C3 convertase C3bBb [<xref rid="BCJ-2017-0085C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], thereby limiting the amplification of the complement pathway. By using an SdrE–CFH-mediated immune evasion strategy, <italic>S. aureus</italic> is capable of successfully disguising itself as a host cell to evade host complement attack.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Many pathogens have developed immune-evasion strategies by recruiting CFH to their surfaces to disguise themselves as normal host cells, thus escaping elimination by the complement pathway. In the present study, we identified the minimal fragment of CFH responsible for interaction with the <italic>S. aureus</italic> surface protein SdrE and determined the crystal structures of apo-SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub> and the SdrE<sub>N2N3</sub>–CFH<sup>1206–1226</sup> complex. Structural analysis and biochemical studies demonstrate that SdrE binds to a unique region of CFH–CCP20 relative to the binding sites on CCP20 for other CFH ligands, including host-cell markers and pathogenic virulence factors. In contrast to reported molecular mechanisms associated with CFH-mediated immune evasion, SdrE recognizes CFH–CCP20 with a CDLL mechanism and functions as a ‘clamp' to capture CFH's C-terminal tail for complement evasion. Our results not only provide insights into the molecular mechanism of <italic>S. aureus</italic>’s complement disguise, but also shed light on the development of new therapeutics for the increasingly serious infections of <italic>S. aureus.</italic></p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank the staff at beamline BL17U1 and BL18U1 of the Shanghai Synchrotron Radiation Facility for assistance with data collection.</p>
    </ack>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list list-content="abbreviations">
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid1">C3</term>
          <def>
            <p>complement component 3</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid2">C5</term>
          <def>
            <p>complement component 5</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid3">CCP</term>
          <def>
            <p>complement-control protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid4">CFH</term>
          <def>
            <p>complement factor H</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid5">Fg</term>
          <def>
            <p>fibrinogen</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid6">GAG</term>
          <def>
            <p>glycosaminoglycan</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid7">ITC</term>
          <def>
            <p>isothermal titration calorimetry</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid8">LB</term>
          <def>
            <p>Luria–Bertani</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid9">MSCRAMM</term>
          <def>
            <p>microbial surface component recognizing adhesive matrix molecule</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid10">OspE</term>
          <def>
            <p>outer surface protein E</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term id="uid11">SdrE</term>
          <def>
            <p>serine–aspartate repeat protein</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <sec id="s6">
      <title>Author Contribution</title>
      <p>J. Zang, X. Zhang and M. Zhang provided the scientific direction and overall experimental design for the studies, Y. Zhang and T. Hang designed and performed the biochemical experiments, M. Wu was responsible for the crystal structure studies, and M. Wu and X. Zhang wrote the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s7">
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the Strategic Priority Research Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences [Grant No. XDB 08010101], the National Key Research and Development Program of China [Grant no. 2016YFA0400903] and the Foundation for Innovative Research Groups of the National Natural Science Foundation of China [Grant no. 31621002]. This work was also supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China [Grant Nos. U1532109, 31370756 and 31361163002], and the Scientific Research Grant of Hefei Science Centre of CAS [Grant Nos. 2015SRG-HSC043 and 2015HSC-UP019] to J. Zhang. This work was also supported by the Anhui Provincial Natural Science Foundation [Grant no. 1608085QC52] for X. Zhang and the National Natural Science Foundation of China [Grant no. 31400627] for M. Wu.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s8" sec-type="COI-statement">
      <title>Competing Interests</title>
      <p>The Authors declare that there are no competing interests associated with the manuscript.</p>
    </sec>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janeway</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Medzhitov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Innate immune recognition</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.20.083001.084359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861602</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Complement and immune defense: from innate immunity to human diseases</article-title>. <source>Immunol. Lett.</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2009.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19616581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The role of complement and complement receptors in induction and regulation of immunity</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>545</fpage>–<lpage>568</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.16.1.545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9597141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pangburn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cortés</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Complement control protein factor H: the good, the bad, and the inadequate</article-title>. <source>Mol. Immunol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>2187</fpage>–<lpage>2197</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2010.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20580090</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricklin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hajishengallis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Complement: a key system for immune surveillance and homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>785</fpage>–<lpage>797</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20720586</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harboe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mollnes</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The alternative complement pathway revisited</article-title>. <source>J. Cell. Mol. Med.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1074</fpage>–<lpage>1084</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2008.00350.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18419792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.-Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricklin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>B.J.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Structure of complement fragment C3b-factor H and implications for host protection by complement regulators</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>733</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19503104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>B.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Murine protein-H ss comprised of 20 repeating units, 61 amino-acids in length</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>83</volume>, <fpage>3963</fpage>–<lpage>3967</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.83.11.3963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2940596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esparza-Gordillo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soria</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buil</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almasy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blangero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fontcuberta</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Genetic and environmental factors influencing the human factor H plasma levels</article-title>. <source>Immunogenetics</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-004-0660-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Córdoba</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>de Jorge</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Translational mini-review series on complement factor H: genetics and disease associations of human complement factor H</article-title>. <source>Clin. Exp. Immunol.</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2007.03552.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18081690</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Würzner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Skerka</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Complement evasion of pathogens: common strategies are shared by diverse organisms</article-title>. <source>Mol. Immunol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>3850</fpage>–<lpage>3857</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2007.06.149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17768102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prosser</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caesar</surname><given-names>J.J.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kugelberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title><italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> recruits factor H using protein mimicry of host carbohydrates</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>458</volume>, <fpage>890</fpage>–<lpage>893</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19225461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oeemig</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodziejczyk</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meri</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kajander</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtinen</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for complement evasion by Lyme disease pathogen <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>288</volume>, <fpage>18685</fpage>–<lpage>18695</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.459040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23658013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echague</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nyalwidhe</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geoghegan</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> surface protein SdrE binds complement regulator factor H as an immune evasion tactic</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e38407</fpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22675461</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geoghegan</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Höök</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Adhesion, invasion and evasion: the many functions of the surface proteins of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336184</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponnuraj</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gurusiddappa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A ‘dock, lock, and latch’ structural model for a staphylococcal adhesin binding to fibrinogen</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>115</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00809-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14567919</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Crystal structures of Bbp from <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> reveal the ligand binding mechanism with fibrinogen α</article-title>. <source>Protein Cell</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>766</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13238-015-0205-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26349459</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smeds</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wann</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A structural model of the <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ClfA–fibrinogen interaction opens new avenues for the design of anti-staphylococcal therapeutics</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>e1000226</fpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19043557</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Crystal structures reveal the multi-ligand binding mechanism of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ClfB</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e1002751</fpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22719251</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Battye</surname><given-names>T.G.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kontogiannis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>A.G.W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title><italic>iMOSFLM</italic>: a new graphical interface for diffraction-image processing with <italic>MOSFLM</italic></article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>281</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910048675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460445</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Scaling and assessment of data quality</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444905036693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16369096</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Collaborative Computational Project, N</collab></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The CCP4 suite: programs for protein crystallography</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>760</fpage>–<lpage>763</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444994003112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299374</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grosse-Kunstleve</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winn</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Storoni</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>Phaser</italic> crystallographic software</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>658</fpage>–<lpage>674</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889807021206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murshudov</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vagin</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Refinement of macromolecular structures by the maximum-likelihood method</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444996012255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299926</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title><italic>Coot</italic>: model-building tools for molecular graphics</article-title>. <source>Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>2126</fpage>–<lpage>2132</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444904019158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>I.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leaver-Fay</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Molprobity: all-atom contacts and structure validation for proteins and nucleic acids</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>W375</fpage>–<lpage>W383</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17452350</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jokiranta</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.-Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seeberger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jòzsi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Binding of complement factor H to endothelial cells is mediated by the carboxy-terminal glycosaminoglycan binding site</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Pathol.</source>
<volume>167</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>–<lpage>1181</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)61205-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16192651</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C28">
        <label>28</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jokiranta</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hellwage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koistinen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Meri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Each of the three binding sites on factor H interacts with a distinct site on C3b</article-title>. <source>Mol. Immunol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>360</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0161-5890(98)90650-2</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C29">
        <label>29</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jòzsi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oppermann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The C-terminus of complement factor H is essential for host cell protection</article-title>. <source>Mol. Immunol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>2697</fpage>–<lpage>2706</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2006.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17208302</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C30">
        <label>30</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pangburn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Critical role of the C-terminal domains of factor H in regulating complement activation at cell surfaces</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>177</volume>, <fpage>6308</fpage>–<lpage>6316</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.177.9.6308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056561</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C31">
        <label>31</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ram</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gulati</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McQuillen</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pangburn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A novel sialic acid binding site on factor H mediates serum resistance of sialylated <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>187</volume>, <fpage>743</fpage>–<lpage>752</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.187.5.743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9480984</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C32">
        <label>32</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammerschmidt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haelbich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skerka</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The host immune regulator factor H interacts via two contact sites with the PspC protein of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and mediates adhesion to host epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>5848</fpage>–<lpage>5858</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.178.9.5848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17442969</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C33">
        <label>33</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajander</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtinen</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyvarinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isenman</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Dual interaction of factor H with C3d and glycosaminoglycans in host-nonhost discrimination by complement</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>2897</fpage>–<lpage>2902</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1017087108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21285368</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C34">
        <label>34</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pangburn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Discrimination between host and pathogens by the complement system</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>I15</fpage>–<lpage>I21</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.11.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19388159</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C35">
        <label>35</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsenz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambris</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dierich</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Localization of the complement-component-C3b-binding site and the cofactor activity for factor I in the 38kDa tryptic fragment of factor H</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source>
<volume>224</volume>, <fpage>389</fpage>–<lpage>398</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj2240389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6240261</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C36">
        <label>36</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaum</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A new map of glycosaminoglycan and C3b binding sites on factor H</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>181</volume>, <fpage>2610</fpage>–<lpage>2619</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.181.4.2610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18684951</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C37">
        <label>37</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prosser</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roversi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaum</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tyrrell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for complement factor H-linked age-related macular degeneration</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source>
<volume>204</volume>, <fpage>2277</fpage>–<lpage>2283</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20071069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17893204</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C38">
        <label>38</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaum</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uhrin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Stehle</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for sialic acid–mediated self-recognition by complement factor H</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.1696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25402769</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C39">
        <label>39</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C.Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guariento</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaum</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Structural basis for engagement by complement factor H of C3b on a self surface</article-title>. <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>463</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21317894</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C40">
        <label>40</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echague</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sholl</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geoghegan</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Clumping factor A interaction with complement factor I increases C3b cleavage on the bacterial surface of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and decreases complement-mediated phagocytosis</article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>1717</fpage>–<lpage>1727</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01065-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100856</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="BCJ-2017-0085C41">
        <label>41</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkelberger</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name> and <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W.-C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Complement and its role in innate and adaptive immune responses</article-title>. <source>Cell Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage> doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cr.2009.139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20010915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>