<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T20:05:52Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5546857" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5546857</identifier><datestamp>2018-08-01</datestamp><setSpec>jcem</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Clin. Endocrinol. Metab</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jcem</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jcem</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-972X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1945-7197</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Endocrine Society</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5546857</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5546857</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5546857</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28505279</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28505279</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jcem_201700161</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.2017-00161</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Clinical Research Articles</subject>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading">
            <subject>Pituitary and Neuroendocrinology</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </subj-group>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="category-oup-series">
          <subject>Editor's Choice</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Somatic <italic>USP8</italic> Gene Mutations Are a Common Cause of Pediatric Cushing Disease</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Faucz</surname>
            <given-names>Fabio R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tirosh</surname>
            <given-names>Amit</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
            <sup>2</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Tatsi</surname>
            <given-names>Christina</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Berthon</surname>
            <given-names>Annabel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hernández-Ramírez</surname>
            <given-names>Laura C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Settas</surname>
            <given-names>Nikolaos</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Angelousi</surname>
            <given-names>Anna</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Correa</surname>
            <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Papadakis</surname>
            <given-names>Georgios Z.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
            <sup>3</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chittiboina</surname>
            <given-names>Prashant</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
            <sup>4</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Quezado</surname>
            <given-names>Martha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
            <sup>5</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pankratz</surname>
            <given-names>Nathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lane</surname>
            <given-names>John</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
            <sup>6</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dimopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Aggeliki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mills</surname>
            <given-names>James L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">
            <sup>7</sup>
          </xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lodish</surname>
            <given-names>Maya</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Stratakis</surname>
            <given-names>Constantine A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
            <sup>1</sup>
          </xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Section on Endocrinology and Genetics, Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20892</aff>
        <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Sackler School of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv 6997801, Israel</aff>
        <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Radiology and Imaging Sciences, Warren Grant Magnuson Clinical Center, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20814</aff>
        <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Surgical Neurology Branch, National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20824</aff>
        <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Laboratory of Pathology, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland 20892</aff>
        <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, University of Minnesota Medical School, Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455</aff>
        <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Epidemiology Branch, Division of Intramural Population Health Research, National Institutes of Health, Rockville, Maryland 20852</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal">
          <label>*</label>
          <p>These authors contributed equally to this study.</p>
        </fn>
        <corresp id="cor1">Address all correspondence and requests for reprints to: Constantine A. Stratakis, MD, NICHD, NIH, 10 Center Drive, Building 10, NIH Clinical Research Center, Room 1-3330, MSC1103, Bethesda, Maryland 20892. E-mail: <email>stratakc@mail.nih.gov</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>102</volume>
      <issue>8</issue>
      <fpage>2836</fpage>
      <lpage>2843</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>08</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions/>
      <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jc.2017-00161.pdf"/>
      <abstract>
        <sec id="s1">
          <title>Context:</title>
          <p>Somatic mutations in the ubiquitin-specific protease 8 (<italic>USP8</italic>) gene have been recently identified as the most common genetic alteration in patients with Cushing disease (CD). However, the frequency of these mutations in the pediatric population has not been extensively assessed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2">
          <title>Objective:</title>
          <p>We investigated the status of the <italic>USP8</italic> gene at the somatic level in a cohort of pediatric patients with corticotroph adenomas.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
          <title>Design and Methods:</title>
          <p>The <italic>USP8</italic> gene was fully sequenced in both germline and tumor DNA samples from 42 pediatric patients with CD. Clinical, biochemical, and imaging data were compared between patients with and without somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
          <title>Results:</title>
          <p>Five different <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (three missense, one frameshift, and one in-frame deletion) were identified in 13 patients (31%), all of them located in exon 14 at the previously described mutational hotspot, affecting the 14-3-3 binding motif of the protein. Patients with somatic mutations were older at disease presentation [mean 5.1 ± 2.1 standard deviation (SD) vs 13.1 ± 3.6 years, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03]. Levels of urinary free cortisol, midnight serum cortisol, and adrenocorticotropic hormone, as well as tumor size and frequency of invasion of the cavernous sinus, were not significantly different between the two groups. However, patients harboring somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations had a higher likelihood of recurrence compared with patients without mutations (46.2% vs 10.3%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.009).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s5">
          <title>Conclusion:</title>
          <p>Somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations are a common cause of pediatric CD. Patients harboring a somatic mutation had a higher likelihood of tumor recurrence, highlighting the potential importance of this molecular defect for the disease prognosis and the development of targeted therapeutic options.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="teaser">
        <p>Mutations in the <italic>USP8</italic> gene have been identified in one third of patients from a cohort of 42 pediatric patients with Cushing disease, in association with increased likelihood of disease recurrence.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="2"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="29"/>
        <page-count count="8"/>
      </counts>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>As in adults, adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH)-producing pituitary adenomas are the most common cause of endogenous hypercortisolemia in children, especially after the age of 7 years (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Childhood Cushing disease (CD) is characterized by deceleration of the growth velocity with concomitant weight gain, along with other classic clinical features of CD (skin changes such as facial plethora, striae, acne, hirsutism, and easy bruising, disturbed mood, decreased bone mineral density, myopathy, and weakness) (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The treatment of choice for CD is transsphenoidal surgical resection (TSS) of the pituitary adenoma, with a success rate of 65% to &gt;95%, depending on the treatment center (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Patients with recurrence or failure to cure may be treated with repeat surgery, radiation, or medications (ketoconazole, metyrapone, mifepristone, or pasireotide).</p>
    <p>The molecular background of the corticotroph adenomas has been largely unknown until recently. Mutations in genes that cause syndromes associated with pituitary adenomas, such as multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (<italic>MEN1</italic>), multiple endocrine neoplasia type 4 (<italic>CDKN1B</italic>), familial isolated pituitary adenoma (<italic>AIP</italic>), McCune–Albright syndrome (<italic>GNAS1</italic>), Carney complex (<italic>PRKAR1A</italic>), pituitary adenoma with paraganglioma and pheochromocytoma [3PAs-collectively the succinate dehydrogenase complex, subunits A, B, C and D genes (SDHx), and pituitary blastoma (<italic>DICER1</italic>), do not account for the majority of the corticotropinomas (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p>
    <p>A recent study by Reincke <italic>et al.</italic> reported that somatic mutations of the ubiquitin-specific protease 8 (<italic>USP8;</italic> Ensembl: ENSG00000138592) gene are found in 40% of corticotroph adenomas (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The <italic>USP8</italic> gene codes for a protein with deubiquitinase activity that inhibits the lysosomal degradation of the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The gain-of-function somatic mutations impair binding of the inhibitory 14-3-3 proteins, resulting in increased deubiquitination of EGFR and induction of proopiomelanocortin (<italic>POMC</italic>) transcription and ACTH secretion (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p>
    <p>The detection of somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations in corticotroph adenomas has been replicated by other groups, but only one study included pediatric patients (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). A possibly lower frequency of this genetic defect in the pediatric population (17%) was suggested, but because of the small number of identified pediatric patients, their clinical and biochemical profile was not described separately from the adult population (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). We have enlarged this population, included the previously studied subgroup, and analyzed the frequency of somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations in the largest cohort of pediatric patients with CD available to date.</p>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="s6">
      <title>Subjects and Methods</title>
      <sec id="s7">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p>We screened our cohort of pediatric patients with pathologically confirmed corticotroph adenomas who presented at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Clinical Research Center between 1997 and 2015, to identify patients with CD who had undergone TSS and for whom germline DNA and tissue from the resected tumor were available for further studies. Of the 139 pediatric patients who were diagnosed with and treated for CD at the NIH during this time, we identified 42 patients for whom both blood and tumor samples were available for molecular studies. Twenty-four of the study subjects were part of the original cohort published by Perez-Rivas <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Their data have never before been analyzed separately. In addition, one patient was sequenced at the germline level in a previous study (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). For the patients who underwent repeat TSS for relapse of CD, we had available tumor samples only from one surgical intervention, and for that reason we were not able to compare the genetic profile of the initial and relapsed tumor.</p>
        <p>The diagnosis of CD was based on previously described criteria based on elevated levels of urinary free cortisol (UFC) and midnight serum cortisol level (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). ACTH-dependent CD was further confirmed by basal plasma ACTH &gt;30 pg/mL, suppression of serum cortisol &gt;69% during a high-dose dexamethasone suppression test (dose: 120 μg/kg, maximum 8 mg), and increase of ACTH and cortisol levels by &gt;35% and 20% compared with baseline, respectively, after corticotropin-releasing hormone administration (corticotropin-releasing hormone test). All patients underwent magnetic resonance imaging of the pituitary, and if a tumor was not visible on magnetic resonance imaging, bilateral inferior petrosal sinus sampling was performed. They all underwent TSS performed by a neurosurgeon with expertise in pituitary disorders, and ACTH-producing tumor was confirmed histologically after resection. Sociodemographic, clinical, imaging, and biochemical data before and after surgery were collected for all patients.</p>
        <p>The <italic>Eunice Kennedy Shriver</italic> National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Institutional Review Board approved this study. Written informed consent from the parents and assent from the minor patients were obtained at the time of the first visit (protocol 1997-CH-0076).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s8">
        <title><italic>USP8</italic> sequence analysis in peripheral and tumor DNA samples</title>
        <p>DNA was extracted from peripheral blood leukocytes and from microdissected tumor tissues with the Quick-DNA™ Universal Kit, according to manufacturer protocols (Zymo, Irvine, CA). For the 24 patients who were previously included in the study by Perez-Rivas <italic>et al</italic>. (<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="jc.2017-00161.st1.docx" id="d35e582" content-type="local-data">Supplemental Table 1</inline-supplementary-material>), repeat DNA extraction was performed from microdissected sections of the tumor after confirmation that they originated from the adenoma (diffuse staining for ACTH, with breakdown of the reticulin) and not from the adjacent normal pituitary. The complete <italic>USP8</italic> coding sequence of these blood and tumor samples was analyzed either by bidirectional Sanger sequencing (5 patients) or with whole exome sequencing (37 patients). All the variants identified by whole exome sequencing were confirmed with Sanger sequencing.</p>
        <p>Fourteen patients, from the original cohort of 139 patients, were previously sequenced by Sanger sequencing for known genes related to CD (including <italic>MEN1, AIP, PRKAR1A, CDKN1B,</italic> and <italic>CDKN2C</italic>) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Of those 14 patients, just 1 had resected tissue available and was included in this study. This patient was positive for a <italic>MEN1</italic> mutation (p.Arg4158) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) (<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="jc.2017-00161.st1.docx" id="d35e606" content-type="local-data">Supplemental Table 1</inline-supplementary-material>). Sanger sequencing for candidate pituitary tumor–causing genes was not performed for the remaining patients. However, all 41 remaining patients included in this manuscript are part of an ongoing whole exome sequencing project, and they are negative for mutations in the aforementioned known genes and other known candidate genes (data not shown). Part of these data were recently published (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s9">
        <title>Immunohistochemistry</title>
        <p>Pituitary tissues from one patient bearing the <italic>USP8</italic> mutation p.Ser718Pro and one patient with no <italic>USP8</italic> mutation were used for immunostaining. The tissues were obtained during surgery, fixed in formalin, and embedded in paraffin, and sections (5 µm) were mounted onto 3-aminopropyl-triethoxylasine coated slides (Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO). Routine staining with hematoxylin and eosin (Histoserv Inc, Germantown, MD) was performed on several sections across each sample. Unstained slides were used for immunostaining as follows: paraffin-embedded tumor slides were deparaffinized with Histoclear (National Diagnostics, Atlanta, GA) and rehydrated with ethanol gradient. The epitopes were retrieved by boiling for 20 minutes in Antigen Unmasking Solution (pH 6; Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA). For double coimmunofluorescence with ACTH and USP8, USP8 was visualized with rabbit anti-USP8 (sc-376130; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX), which was detected with antirabbit secondary antibody coupled to biotin (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch, West Grove, PA). Biotin was complexed with streptavidin peroxidase conjugate (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch), and horseradish peroxidase activity was detected with TSA-Alexa 488 fluorescently labeled horseradish peroxidase conjugate (Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR). After this, rabbit anti-ACTH (1:500; National Hormone and Peptide Program, UCLA, Torrance, CA) was directly detected by donkey antirabbit Alexa 594 (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA). USP8/ACTH costaining was analyzed under the Zeiss Axioplan microscope.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s10">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Continuous variables were compared between groups via Student <italic>t</italic> test, the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test, or the Kruskal–Wallis test, as appropriate. Measurements are reported as mean ± standard deviation (SD). Categorical variables were compared via <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> or Fisher’s exact test, as appropriate. An exact, two-tailed <italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Analysis was performed in the statistical software package SPSS, version 20.0 (IBM SPSS Statistics, Armonk, NY).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results" id="s11">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s12">
        <title>Patient characteristics</title>
        <p>In our cohort of 42 patients, there was a predominance of female patients (27 vs 15), with a mean age at diagnosis of 13.7 ± 3.4 years and an average duration of symptoms before diagnosis of 2.1 ± 1.5 years. The mean midnight serum cortisol and 24-hour UFC levels were 18.9 ± 13.5 μg/dL and 446 ± 610 μg/24 hours, respectively. The mean size of the identified pituitary adenomas was 6.2 ± 6.0 mm, and 4 of the 42 patients (9.5%) presented with evidence of cavernous sinus invasion (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Demographic Data of our Cohort of Patients</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="above" rules="groups">
            <col width="35.17" span="1"/>
            <col width="17.15" span="1"/>
            <col width="15.19" span="1"/>
            <col width="15.58" span="1"/>
            <col width="16.91" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age at diagnosis, y</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 ± 3.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female sex, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (64.3)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African American</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.5)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.3)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Caucasian</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (73.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenoma size, mm</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2 ± 6.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invasion to cavernous sinus, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.5)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Needed further management, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (28.6)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midnight plasma cortisol, μg/dL</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.9</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 ± 13.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma ACTH, pg/mL</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 ± 81.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 hour UFC, μg/24 h</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2851</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446 ± 610</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP, mm Hg</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 ± 16</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SBP <italic>z</italic> score</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 ± 1.3</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP, mm Hg</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 ± 11</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DBP <italic>z</italic> score</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 1.0</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup></td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 ± 8.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BMI <italic>z</italic> score</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 ± 0.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from first symptom to diagnosis, y</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.5</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <table-wrap-foot>
            <fn fn-type="abbr">
              <p>Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</p>
            </fn>
          </table-wrap-foot>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Postoperative follow-up was available in 35 patients (73.8%), with mean follow-up of 34.7 ± 37.9 months and median follow-up of 17 months. Thirty-eight of the patients (90.4%) achieved remission after surgery. Of the 4 patients who did not achieve remission after surgery, 1 underwent sellar radiation therapy, 2 were managed with ketoconazole, and 1 underwent both sellar radiation and ketoconazole treatment. Five of the 31 patients with initial remission developed recurrent CD over the course of the study, with a mean time to recurrence 46.4 ± 11.8 months (range 34–66 months). One of them was treated with repeat TSS, one underwent repeat pituitary surgery in addition to pituitary radiation therapy, and three are awaiting repeat TSS. Overall, 4 patients failed to achieve remission immediately after surgery, and 5 patients had recurrence of disease after initial remission. No significant difference was found when the percentage of patients with cavernous sinus invasion who harbored somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (2 of 13, or 15.4%) was compared with those with invasion who did not have <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (2 of 29, or 6.9%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.4) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Table 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>
              <bold>Clinical and Biochemical Characteristics of the Patients With and Without Somatic <italic>USP8</italic> Mutations</bold>
            </p>
          </caption>
          <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
            <col width="39.56" span="1"/>
            <col width="22.77" span="1"/>
            <col width="23.87" span="1"/>
            <col width="13.8" span="1"/>
            <thead>
              <tr>
                <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Somatic <italic>USP8</italic> Mutation, n = 13 (31.0%)</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No Somatic <italic>USP8</italic> Mutation, n = 29 (50.0%)</th>
                <th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <italic>P</italic>
                </th>
              </tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean age at diagnosis, y</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1 ± 2.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 ± 3.6</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female sex, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (84.6)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (55.2)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow up duration, mo</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1 ± 22.4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7 ± 4.8</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (3.4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> African American</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.9)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.9)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Caucasian</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (53.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (82.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthropometric data</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI <italic>z</italic> score</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 ± 1.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 0.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BMI <italic>z</italic> score ≥2, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (38.5)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (75.9)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Height <italic>z</italic> score</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.1 ± 1.2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.0 ± 1.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Height z-score ≤−0.5, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (76.9)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (72.4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tumor characteristics</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diameter, mm</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ± 7.0</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 ± 5.4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diameter ≥5 mm, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (69.2)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (44.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Invasion of cavernous sinus, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (15.4)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6.9)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biochemical data</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Midnight cortisol, μg/dL</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 ± 7.4</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 ± 15.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plasma ACTH, pg/mL</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7 ± 30.1</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.2 ± 94.3</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 24 hour UFC, μg/24 h</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">396 ± 466</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468 ± 671</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time from first symptoms to diagnosis</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Time, y</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.2</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 1.7</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥3 y, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (30.8)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (20.7)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Recurrence or failure to cure, n (%)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (46.2)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (10.3)</td>
                <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td>
              </tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s13">
        <title>Frequency of <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations</title>
        <p>We identified five different somatic mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) in 13 patients, resulting in a frequency of 31% in our cohort. All the mutations were heterozygous, and they were all located in exon 14 of the <italic>USP8</italic> gene. They consisted of three missense mutations (p.Ser718Pro–rs672601307, p.Ser718Cys–rs672601308, p.Pro720Arg–rs672601311) and two deletions of 1 (p.Ser718del) and 6 (p.Ser719_724del) amino acids. All these mutations are located at the hotspot of the gene at the 14-3-3 binding motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). None of the germline DNA samples were found to have <italic>USP8</italic> hotspot mutations.</p>
        <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 1.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Schematic representation of the <italic>USP8</italic> gene showing the somatic mutations identified. Vertical lines show the variant position. aa, amino acids. UTR, untranslated region.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jc.2017-00161f1"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s14">
        <title>Clinical and biochemical characteristics of the patients with somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations</title>
        <p>Patients harboring somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations had a later mean age at diagnosis of 15.1 ± 2.1 years, compared with 13.1 ± 3.6 years for those without <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (<italic>P</italic> = 0.03). They also had lower body mass index (BMI) <italic>z</italic> scores, with fewer patients having a BMI <italic>z</italic> score &gt;2 SD above the mean (38.5% vs 75.9%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.02), whereas the height <italic>z</italic> score was similar in the two groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>The biochemical profile of the two groups was similar, with no differences in the level of midnight serum cortisol, UFC, or ACTH before treatment. The size of the identified tumors was not significantly different in patients with <italic>USP8</italic> mutations compared with the patients without <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (diameter 8.0 ± 7.0 mm vs 5.4 ± 5.4 mm, respectively; <italic>P</italic> = 0.2), and the adenoma volumes were comparable in the two groups (200 ± 234 mm<sup>3</sup> vs 191 ± 186 mm<sup>3</sup>; <italic>P</italic> = 0.9). There was also no significant difference in the frequency of invasion of the cavernous sinus between the two groups (15.4% vs 6.9%; <italic>P</italic> = 0.4).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s15">
        <title>Outcomes</title>
        <p>Of the four patients with initial nonremission after pituitary surgery, one patient harbored a somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutation, and three did not. An analysis of these patients revealed that all patients had large, invasive adenomas with extension to the cavernous sinus and substantial tumor remnants after surgery. This result is expected because tumors harboring <italic>USP8</italic> mutations may have smaller volume in general (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Interestingly, however, all recurrences after initial remission (n = 5) occurred in tumors harboring somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations. The proportion of patients with recurrence among those with somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations was 5 in 13 (38.5%), compared with 0 in the remaining group (0 in 29; <italic>P</italic> = 0.0015).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s16">
        <title>Immunohistochemical analysis</title>
        <p>To investigate more specifically the effect of one of the somatic mutations detected in our cohort, we analyzed <italic>USP8</italic> expression by immunohistochemistry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). USP8 was exclusively expressed in the cytoplasm of the nonmutant tumors, whereas its expression was more nuclear in the mutated tumors, consistent with findings in previous reports (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p>
        <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
          <label>Figure 2.</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Immunohistochemistry staining of pituitary tumors with no <italic>USP8</italic> mutation (a, c, e, g) and with the somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutation p.Ser718Pro (b, d, f, h) for USP8 (a, b), ACTH (c, d), and DAPI (e, f) showing the nuclear localization of USP8.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic xlink:href="jc.2017-00161f2"/>
        </fig>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s17">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we report our experience with the identification of somatic <italic>USP8</italic> mutations in pediatric patients seen at the NIH. To our knowledge this is the largest pediatric cohort of patients with CD that has been screened for this genetic defect. A subset of these patients (n = 24) were previously reported in Perez-Rivas <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>); however, we performed repeat DNA extraction from the resected tissue after confirming that the selected cut of the tissue originated exclusively from the corticotroph adenoma, to exclude the possibility of mixing the tumor DNA sample with DNA from normal cells.</p>
      <p>We identified 13 patients with somatic mutations demonstrating a high frequency of <italic>USP8</italic> gene defects (31%) in our cohort. This finding is similar to the reported frequency in the adult population (around one-third of all adult patients with CD) and is higher than the low frequency (17%) previously documented in the pediatric patients with CD (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). A recent study by Ma <italic>et al.</italic> reported a frequency of somatic mutations in their adult population of ≤62.5%, suggesting that it is possible that the genetic background of corticotropinomas in children differs from that in adults (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), although the difference probably lies in the fact that the smaller size of pediatric ACTH-producing pituitary adenomas does not allow for full capture of tumor DNA and permits admixture of DNA from the surrounding normal cells.</p>
      <p>Notably, we documented a higher rate of subsequent recurrence of CD in our patients with <italic>USP8</italic> mutations. Previous reports suggested that the <italic>USP8</italic> mutated tumors are not as aggressive, with higher rates of remission (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The demonstration of a higher rate of recurrence in our pediatric population with <italic>USP8</italic> defects might suggest that CD in these children may have a different course than that in adults. However, it could also reflect the fact that only larger microadenomas and possibly more aggressive tumors were available for analysis in children with CD.</p>
      <p>The comparison of demographic, clinical, and biochemical data of patients with and without <italic>USP8</italic> mutations revealed an older age at diagnosis for patients with a <italic>USP8</italic> defect in the tumor. Although some previous studies showed that patients with <italic>USP8</italic> mutations had different levels of plasma ACTH compared with patients without mutations, this finding was not confirmed in other studies nor by our group; patients with USP8 mutations had lower ACTH levels (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) but the difference was not statistically significant (47.7 ± 30.1 vs. 82.2 ± 94.3, <italic>P</italic> = 0.2) (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Additionally, conflicting data on tumor size have been reported: Perez Rivas <italic>et al.</italic> reported that tumors in female patients with <italic>USP8</italic> somatic mutations were larger than those in the nonmutant group or in male patients with <italic>USP8</italic> defects, whereas Ma <italic>et al.</italic> and Hayashi <italic>et al.</italic> found that pituitary tumors were smaller in patients with <italic>USP8</italic> mutations (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In our population the size of the tumor in the two groups was similar; however, the available samples were usually from larger tumors, because those had sufficient material to be processed for research, which may have biased our results.</p>
      <p>Physiologically, the USP8 protein is a deubiquitinase involved in the ubiquitination pathway of EGFR degradation, resulting in its “rescue” from ubiquitination (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The inhibition of USP8 action is usually mediated by binding to 14-3-3 proteins after phosphorylation of the amino acid serine 718 (Ser718) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p>
      <p>All identified somatic mutations in our population are located in exon 14, at amino acids 718 to 723, which are highly conserved across species. They result in loss of 14-3-3 protein binding and catalytic cleavage of a 40-kDa fragment of the protein, leading to elevated deubiquitinase activity, “rescue” of EGFR from degradation, and elevated intracellular levels of EGFR (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). EGFR has been shown in the past to induce <italic>POMC</italic> expression, with mediation of Erk1/2 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Thus the high levels of EGFR, along with a possible independent effect of the mutated USP8 protein, result in increased <italic>POMC</italic> promoter activation and ACTH production by the corticotroph cells (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p>
      <p>The identification of a common molecular etiology explaining the pathogenesis of a large number of ACTH-producing pituitary adenomas is of foremost importance, especially because it can provide new treatment targets. The rate of recurrence of CD or failure to cure after the first TSS has been estimated as ≤25% in the pediatric population, and the probability of impairment of normal pituitary function after repeat surgery increases significantly (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"/>–<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In children, where final growth and puberty have not yet occurred, preservation of pituitary function and the possibility of less invasive treatments are critical.</p>
      <p>Recently Hayashi <italic>et al.</italic> reported that <italic>USP8</italic>-mutated tumors bear more somatostatin receptors subtype 5, which can be a target for pharmacologic treatment with specific somatostatin analogs such as pasireotide (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Additionally, EGFR-targeting agents, including tyrosine kinase inhibitors and monoclonal antibodies, are other promising options (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). For example, gefitinib, an EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor, was shown to decrease the expression of <italic>POMC,</italic> inhibiting ACTH production and corticotroph tumor cell growth in canine and mouse cells (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, studies of this medication in humans have not produced consistently good outcomes when tested on other tumors (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). A clinical trial is being conducted by Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> to evaluate its effect specifically in CD (ClinicalTrials.gov, identifier NCT02484755). USP8 protein–targeting medications could be used in this subgroup of patients, and inhibitors of the protein have already been designed for other malignancies (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p>
      <p>A limitation of this study is its small sample size. However, our goal was to elucidate the genetics of pediatric CD, which is a rare condition, and to our knowledge, our cohort is the largest of its kind, with patients of exclusively pediatric age who have been screened for <italic>USP8</italic> mutations. Another limitation is a possible bias in the selection of the patients included in the study: Because we had to include only patients with both blood and tumor tissue available, we excluded 97 patients for whom tumor DNA was missing who in these last few years have also presented with CD and were treated with TSS at the NIH. Thus, the patients we finally included in this study may represent those who had larger tumors at detection (although by imaging there was no difference, as presented in our results). These patients may have had a more aggressive tumors to begin with, and the detection of the <italic>USP8</italic> defect in them may be a coincidence rather than causative. In addition, “contamination” with normal cells is a big problem whenever one looks for a somatic mutation in a small specimen; although we took great care to detect such admixture, it is possible that we missed the presence of the mutation in patients with smaller tumors, making those with more aggressive lesions appear more frequently as <italic>USP8</italic>-mutation bearing. Additional studies are needed to define the effect of a <italic>USP8</italic> defect in the biologic behavior of an ACTH-producing tumor in both children and adults.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s18">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In almost one-third (31%) of tumors from patients with pediatric CD, we identified somatic <italic>USP8</italic> gene mutations. All defects were present at the hotspot location of exon 14 of the gene; mutations there appear to cause decreased EGFR degradation, which in turn leads to increased <italic>POMC</italic> expression and ACTH production. Pediatric patients with <italic>USP8</italic> mutations had more severe overall disease, with more failures of primary surgical resection and increased rate of recurrences. This study is part of a larger one aiming at defining the genetic causes of CD in children and adults (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group content-type="abbreviations">
      <fn id="abbr" fn-type="abbr">
        <p>Abbreviations: <def-list><def-item><term id="G1">3PAs</term><def><p>pituitary adenoma with paraganglioma/pheochromocytoma association</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">ACTH</term><def><p>adrenocorticotropic Hormone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3"><italic>AIP</italic></term><def><p>aryl hydrocarbon receptor-interacting protein gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">BMI</term><def><p>body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G5">CD</term><def><p>Cushing disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G6"><italic>CDKN1B</italic></term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1B gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G7"><italic>CDKN2C</italic></term><def><p>cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 2C</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G8"><italic>DICER1</italic></term><def><p>dicer, drosophila, homolog of, 1 gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G9"><italic>EGFR</italic></term><def><p>epidermal growth factor receptor gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G10"><italic>MEN1</italic></term><def><p>multiple endocrine neoplasia, type I gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G18">NIH</term><def><p>National Institutes of Health</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G11"><italic>POMC</italic></term><def><p>proopiomelanocortin gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G12"><italic>PRKAR1A</italic></term><def><p>protein kinase, camp-dependent, regulatory, type I, alpha gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G13">SD</term><def><p>standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G14">SDHx</term><def><p>collectively the succinate dehydrogenase complex, subunits A, B, C and D genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G15">TSS</term><def><p>transsphenoidal surgical resection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G16">UFC</term><def><p>urinary free cortisol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G17"><italic>USP8</italic></term><def><p>ubiquitin-specific protease 8 gene.</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>We thank Dr. Reincke and his group for collaboration on the USP8 project. We are grateful to our patients and the clinicians who support our study with referrals from around the nation and the world.</p>
    </ack>
    <ack>
      <p content-type="financial-disclosure">This study was supported by the Intramural Research Program, <italic>Eunice Kennedy Shriver</italic> National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health (to C.A.S.).</p>
      <p>Disclosure Summary: The authors have nothing to disclose.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feelders</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cushing’s syndrome</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>386</volume>(<issue>9996</issue>):<fpage>913</fpage>–<lpage>927</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004339</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Storr</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Paediatric Cushing’s syndrome: epidemiology, investigation and therapeutic advances</article-title>. <source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412607</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afshari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ardeshirpour</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gourgari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinaii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belyavskaya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyssikatos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhry</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chernomordik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzuchi</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gandjbakhche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Facial plethora: modern technology for quantifying an ancient clinical sign and its use in Cushing syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3928</fpage>–<lpage>3933</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26301943</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mastorakos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsiades</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsiades</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chrousos</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Skin manifestations of Cushing disease in children and adolescents before and after the resolution of hypercortisolemia</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Dermatol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9720685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serbis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinaii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rothenbuhler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boikos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of Cushing disease on bone mineral density in a pediatric population</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>156</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1001</fpage>–<lpage>1005</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20223476</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postoperative testing to predict recurrent Cushing disease in children</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2757</fpage>–<lpage>2765</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470618</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Storr</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pediatric Cushing’s disease: management issues</article-title>. <source>Indian J Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>S171</fpage>–<lpage>S175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23565371</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barkan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hollon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakharova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brahma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schteingart</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of transsphenoidal surgery for Cushing disease: a single-center experience over 32 years</article-title>. <source>Neurosurgery</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26348007</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis and clinical genetics of Cushing syndrome in pediatrics</article-title>. <source>Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27241967</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sbiera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deutschbein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weigand</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reincke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fassnacht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allolio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The new molecular landscape of Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26412158</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xekouki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szarek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bullova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giubellino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quezado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mastroyannis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mastorakos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wassif</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raygada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rentia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cougnoux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koziol</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>MdeL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyssikatos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belyavskaya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Malchoff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moline</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pituitary adenoma with paraganglioma/pheochromocytoma (3PAs) and succinate dehydrogenase defects in humans and mice</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>E710</fpage>–<lpage>E719</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25695889</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reincke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sbiera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theodoropoulou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osswald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beuschlein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meitinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno-Yamasaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saeger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ronchi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allolio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchfelder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strom</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fassnacht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mutations in the deubiquitinase gene <italic>USP8</italic> cause Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25485838</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>UBPY-mediated epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) de-ubiquitination promotes EGFR degradation</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>282</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1658</fpage>–<lpage>1669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17121848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Recurrent gain-of-function USP8 mutations in Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>Cell Res</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>306</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25675982</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Rivas</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theodoropoulou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraù</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nusser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faucz</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wildemberg</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assié</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beschorner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchfelder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Popovic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berr</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tóth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ardisasmita</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honegger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertherat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadelha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beuschlein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stalla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Korbonits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reincke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The gene of the ubiquitin-specific protease 8 is frequently mutated in adenomas causing Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>E997</fpage>–<lpage>E1004</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25942478</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tichomirowa</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boikos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raygada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papademetriou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drori-Herishanu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nesterova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanbellinghen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bours</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salvatori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beckers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of germline AIP, MEN1, PRKAR1A, CDKN1B and CDKN2C mutations in causing pituitary adenomas in a large cohort of children, adolescents, and patients with genetic syndromes</article-title>. <source>Clin Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>457</fpage>–<lpage>463</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20507346</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Ramírez</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatsi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faucz</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pankratz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chittiboina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valdés</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Corticotropinoma as a component of Carney complex [published online ahead of print May 30, 2017]</article-title>. <source>J Endocr Soc.</source> doi:10.1210/js.2017-00231.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Ramírez</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valdés</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lodish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pankratz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balsalobre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Faucz</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trivellin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chittiboina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dimopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bertherat</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Assié</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stratakis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Loss-of-function mutations in the CABLES1 gene are a novel cause of Cushing’s disease [published online ahead of print May 22, 2017]</article-title>. <source>Endocr Relat Cancer.</source> doi:10.1530/ERC-17-0131.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inoshita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The USP8 mutational status may predict drug susceptibility in corticotroph adenomas of Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>Eur J Endocrinol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26578638</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nijman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luna-Vargas</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velds</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brummelkamp</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dirac</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sixma</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A genomic and functional inventory of deubiquitinating enzymes</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>123</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>773</fpage>–<lpage>786</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16325574</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes-Turcu</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ventii</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation and cellular roles of ubiquitin-specific deubiquitinating enzymes</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489724</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizuno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>14-3-3-dependent inhibition of the deubiquitinating activity of UBPY and its cancellation in the M phase</article-title>. <source>Exp Cell Res</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>313</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>3624</fpage>–<lpage>3634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720156</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerperien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sotoca</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Zoelen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The Usp8 deubiquitination enzyme is post-translationally modified by tyrosine and serine phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Cell Signal</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>919</fpage>–<lpage>930</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23333852</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodoropoulou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reincke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fassnacht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Decoding the genetic basis of Cushing’s disease: USP8 in the spotlight</article-title>. <source>Eur J Endocrinol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>M73</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26012588</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Shlomo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mamelak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruyette</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>EGFR as a therapeutic target for human, canine, and mouse ACTH-secreting pituitary adenomas</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>4712</fpage>–<lpage>4721</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22105169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonser</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wind</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeVroom</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Outcome of surgical treatment of 200 children with Cushing’s disease</article-title>. <source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>892</fpage>–<lpage>901</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23372173</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wondisford</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A new medical therapy for Cushing disease?</article-title>
<source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>4621</fpage>–<lpage>4623</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22105164</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of resistance to ErbB-targeted cancer therapeutics</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2389</fpage>–<lpage>2392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>USP8 is a novel target for overcoming gefitinib resistance in lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>3894</fpage>–<lpage>3904</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>