<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><OAI-PMH
	xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd"><responseDate>2019-03-02T20:04:49Z</responseDate><request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5432510" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request><GetRecord><record><header><identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:5432510</identifier><datestamp>2017-05-17</datestamp><setSpec>scirep</setSpec><setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec></header><metadata><article xmlns="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.0/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.0/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC5432510</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5432510</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">5432510</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28507310</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2074</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-02074-8</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pousada</surname>
            <given-names>Guillermo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lupo</surname>
            <given-names>Vincenzo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cástro-Sánchez</surname>
            <given-names>Sheila</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Álvarez-Satta</surname>
            <given-names>María</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sánchez-Monteagudo</surname>
            <given-names>Ana</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baloira</surname>
            <given-names>Adolfo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Espinós</surname>
            <given-names>Carmen</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Valverde</surname>
            <given-names>Diana</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>dianaval@uvigo.es</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 6738</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6312.6</institution-id><institution>Dep. Biochemistry, Genetics and Immunology. Faculty of Biology, </institution><institution>University of Vigo, </institution></institution-wrap>As Lagoas Marcosende S/N, 36310 Vigo, Spain </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Grupo de Investigación Enfermedades Raras y Medicina Pediátrica, Instituto de Investigación Sanitaria Galicia Sur (IIS Galicia Sur), SERGAS-UVIGO, Vigo, Spain </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0399 600X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418274.c</institution-id><institution>Unit of Genetics and Genomics of Neuromuscular and Neurodegenerative Disorders, </institution><institution>Centro de Investigación Príncipe Felipe (CIPF), </institution></institution-wrap>46012 Valencia, Spain </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Neumology Service, Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Pontevedra, 36071 Pontevedra, Spain </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>7</volume>
      <elocation-id>1923</elocation-id>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2016</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2017</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement>
        <license license-type="OpenAccess">
          <license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>Pulmonary arterial hypertension is a progressive disease that causes the obstruction of precapillary pulmonary arteries and a sustained increase in pulmonary vascular resistance. The aim was to analyze functionally the variants found in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene and to establish a genotype-phenotype correlation. mRNA expression studies were performed using <italic>pSPL3</italic> vector, studies of subcellular localization were performed using <italic>pEGFP-N1</italic> vector and luciferase assays were performed using <italic>pGL3-Basic</italic> vector. We have identified 30 variants in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene in 27 of 55 patients. In 16 patients we detected pathogenic mutations. Minigene assays revealed that 6 variants (synonymous, missense) result in splicing defect. By immunofluorescence assay, we observed that 4 mutations affect the protein localization. Finally, 4 mutations located in the 5′UTR region showed a decreased transcriptional activity in luciferase assays. Genotype-phenotype correlation, revealed that patients with pathogenic mutations have a more severe phenotype (sPaP p = 0.042, 6MWT p = 0.041), a lower age at diagnosis (p = 0.040) and seemed to have worse response to phosphodiesterase-5-inhibitors (p = 0.010). Our study confirms that <italic>in vitro</italic> expression analysis is a suitable approach in order to investigate the phenotypic consequences of the nucleotide variants, especially in cases where the involved genes have a pattern of expression in tissues of difficult access.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH; OMIM #178600, ORPHA 422) is a rare, progressive disease that typically causes the obstruction of precapillary pulmonary arteries. It is characterized by a sustained increase in mean pulmonary artery pressure (mPaP) ≥ 25 mmHg at rest with normal pulmonary arterial wedge pressure (PAWP) ≤ 15 mmHg<sup>2</sup>. Syncope, dyspnea and chest pain are the main symptoms of PAH, which eventually lead to premature death due to right sided heart failure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In addition, an increase in pulmonary vascular resistance (PVR) is observed in these patients, mainly due to both thrombus formation and structural and functional changes in the vascular wall<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Mean age at presentation, ranges from 36 to 50 years in adults, although individuals at any age can be affected<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. This pathology is more frequent in women, with a ratio of 1.7:1 women to men<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. PAH is classified as idiopathic (IPAH), hereditary (HPAH) or associated with other conditions (APAH) such as connective tissue diseases, congenital heart diseases, portal hypertension and drug or toxin exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. When a genetic defect has been identified in IPAH patients, which cosegregates with disease, they have been classified as HPAH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Regarding to the genetic basis of PAH, the main gene involved is bone morphogenetic protein receptor type 2 (<italic>BMPR2</italic>), located on chromosome 2q33. Mutations in this gene have been identified in more than 80% of patients with HPAH, although only 20% of carriers eventually develop the disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. On the other hand, the frequency of <italic>BMPR2</italic> mutations in IPAH patients is much lower, ranging from 6–40%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. <italic>BMPR2</italic> encodes for a transmembrane serine/threonine kinase receptor belonging to the transforming growth factor beta (TGF-β) superfamily, and is specifically recognized by bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs), which are involved in several signalling pathways that regulate cellular differentiation, proliferation and apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Either loss of function or reduction in <italic>BMPR2</italic> expression may be sufficient to develop PAH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Mutational screening of <italic>BMPR2</italic> in PAH patients has been extensively reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. However, little is known about the real pathogenicity of missense, synonymous or intronic changes, among others, in the PAH development. Thus, it is well established that synonymous and also non-synonymous variants can affect the conformation and stability of mRNA, the splicing process, the accuracy of translation and the protein structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Moreover, splicing mutations represent more than 9% of the published changes, although experimental confirmation should increase the percentage of splicing mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. In this sense, the minigene assays have been reported as a good approach to evaluate potential splicing alterations produced by these variants of uncertain pathogenicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, especially when the gene expression profile is restricted and/or patient′s tissue samples are difficult to obtain, as in PAH. On the other hand, it is well known that mutations can lead to disease because the protein gets mislocalized and therefore, cannot carry out its activity properly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Finally, the role of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> variants in promoter region has been scarcely characterized, but known to affect gene expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Taking into account the importance of performing functional studies in order to determine if a variant is pathological, our main objectives were: (1) to investigate if the detected <italic>BMPR2</italic> mutations could be associated with alterations in mRNA processing, subcellular localization and/or transcriptional activity and therefore, they could cause an abnormal protein activity; and (2) to establish an accurate genotype-phenotype correlation, comparing the set of clinical and hemodynamic features of patients harbouring pathogenic mutations with those without them.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Description of the cohort</title>
        <p>This cohort has been described previously by our group and therefore, mutations in the <italic>BMPR2</italic>, <italic>ACVRL1</italic> (Activin A type II receptor like kinase 1), <italic>ENG</italic> (Endoglin) and/or <italic>KCNA5</italic> (Potassium voltage-gated channel, shakerrelated subfamily, member 5) genes have been previously reported by Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In summary, 55 unrelated PAH patients of Spanish origin (28 IPAH, 18 APAH associated to connective tissue disease, 4 related to HIV and 5 porto-pulmonary hypertension) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and 50 healthy controls without familial history of PAH were included. At the time of diagnosis 7 patients were in functional class (FC) I, 19 patients in FC II, 25 patients in FC III and 4 in FC IV. Thirty-three out of the 39 patients were considered responders to treatment, compared to only 2 out of 16 patients with pathogenic mutations. There was a decrease in proBNP of 482 ± 292 pcg/mL in responders after 6 months of treatment with significant differences regarding non-responders (115 ± 384 pcg/mL, p &lt; 0.001). Clinical features of patients are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Diagram of the population under study. This figure shows the total number of patients included in this study (55 patients) classified according to PAH type (28 patients with IPAH and 27 patients with APAH), gender, mean age at diagnosis and pathogenic mutations in <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. PAH: Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension; IPAH: Idiopathic Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension; Associated Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension; CTD: Connective Tissue Disease; HIV: Human Immunodeficiency Virus; P-P: Porto-Pulmonary Hypertension.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e485"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical features and hemodynamic parameters of patients included in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Clinical features and hemodynamic parameters</th><th rowspan="2">Total patients</th><th colspan="2">Patients with proven pathogenic mutations</th></tr><tr><th>Clinical data</th><th>p-value*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Number</italic>
</td><td>55</td><td>16</td><td>—</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Gender</italic>
</td><td>20 M/35 F</td><td>4 M/12 F</td><td>0.360</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Age at diagnosis</italic> (<italic>years</italic>)</td><td>49 ± 16</td><td>38 ± 16</td><td>0.040</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>mPaP</italic> (<italic>mmHg</italic>)</td><td>49 ± 14</td><td>47 ± 6</td><td>0.266</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>sPaP</italic> (<italic>mmHg</italic>)</td><td>70 ± 19</td><td>60 ± 9</td><td>0.042</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PVR</italic> (<italic>mmHg.l</italic>
<sup>−<italic>1</italic></sup>
<italic>.m</italic>
<sup>−1</sup>)</td><td>7.2 ± 3.3</td><td>7.9 ± 0.5</td><td>0.553</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>CI</italic> (<italic>l.m</italic>
<sup><italic>−1</italic></sup>
<italic>.m</italic>
<sup>−<italic>2</italic></sup>)</td><td>2.5 ± 0.7</td><td>2.3 ± 0.3</td><td>0.588</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>6MWT</italic> (<italic>m</italic>)</td><td>415 ± 146</td><td>570 ± 86</td><td>0.041</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>proBNP</italic> (<italic>pcg</italic>/<italic>mL</italic>)</td><td>1276 ± 434</td><td>1297 ± 465</td><td>0.526</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>PAH types</italic>
</td><td>28 IPAH/27 APAH</td><td>10 IPAH/6 APAH</td><td>0.137</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>No improvement upon treatment</italic>
</td><td>22</td><td>14</td><td>0.010</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are expressed as mean ± standard deviation; F: female, M: male; mPaP: mean pulmonary artery pressure; sPaP: systolic pulmonary artery pressure; PVR: pulmonary vascular resistence; CI: cardiac index; 6MWT: 6 minute walking test; IPAH: idiopathic pulmonary arterial hypertension; APAH: associated pulmonary arterial hypertension.</p><p>*Clinical features and hemodynamic parameters among patients with pathogenic changes in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene and without.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Mutational analysis of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene</title>
        <p>The molecular analysis of the 5′UTR region (539 bp) of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene revealed 5 nucleotide changes in 6 patients (11%), all of them in heterozygous state (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). All but one were females. Four patients had IPAH and one patient presented with PAH associated with systemic sclerosis. These 5 mutations were absent in a panel of 100 control chromosomes. However, c.1-301G &gt; A (rs116154690) mutation was found in the Ensembl Database with a 0.01 minor allele frequency (MAF). The <italic>in silico</italic> analysis predicted a negative impact on the splicing process for these variants, as expected (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Representative sequence electropherograms for the mutations in 5′UTR of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene (c.1-347C &gt; T, c.1-301G &gt; A, c.1-279C &gt; A, c.1-186A &gt; T and c.1-92C &gt; A) in PAH patients and <italic>In silico</italic> analysis of the effect on the binding site to transcriptions factors of variants found in 5′UTR region of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. MatInspector software found that these variants could create (SRF, DICE and FTF) or remove (MSX2) new binding sites for different factors. c.1-279C &gt; A seems to not the binding sites to transcriptions factors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e787"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>
<italic>In silico</italic> analysis of variants identify in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change</th><th>PolyPhen-2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>
</th><th>Pmut<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>
</th><th>Sift<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>
</th><th>Mutation Taster<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>
</th><th>NNSplice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>
</th><th>NetGene2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>
</th><th>Splice View<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>
</th><th>HSF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>c.1-347C &gt; T</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-301G &gt; A</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the aceptor site increases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-279C &gt; A</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-186A &gt; T</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-92C &gt; A</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.156_157delTC (p.S52Sfs*1)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site and the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>A new acceptor site is created</td></tr><tr><td>c.190A &gt; C (p.S64R)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Tolerated</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>A new donor site is created</td><td>Score for donor and acceptor site decreases</td></tr><tr><td>c.229A &gt; T (p.I77L)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>A new acceptor site is created</td></tr><tr><td>c.251G &gt; T (p.C84F)</td><td>Probably damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Score for the acceptor site increases</td><td>Score for the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.259C &gt; T (p.H87Y)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Score for the acceptor site decreases</td><td>Score for the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized and the acceptor</td></tr><tr><td>c.275A &gt; T (p.Q92L)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Pathologic</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for donor and acceptor site increases</td></tr><tr><td>c.327G &gt; A (p.Q109Q)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.327G &gt; C (p.Q109H)</td><td>Probably damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Tolerated</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.412C &gt; G (p.P138A)</td><td/><td/><td/><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.484G &gt; C (p.A162P)</td><td>Probably damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Score for the acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.600A &gt; C (p.L200L)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td></tr><tr><td>c.633A &gt; G (p.R211R)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized and the acceptor decrease</td></tr><tr><td>c.637C &gt; A (p.R213R)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for donor site increases and a new acceptor site is created</td></tr><tr><td>c.654T &gt; A (p.Y218*)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases and the main acceptor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main acceptor site decrease</td></tr><tr><td>c.742A &gt; G (p.R248G)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Pathologic</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site and the main acceptor site increases</td></tr><tr><td>c.790G &gt; A (p.D264N)</td><td>Possibly damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.835G &gt; T (p.V278V)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for donor site decreases and the acceptor site increase</td></tr><tr><td>c.893G &gt; A (p.W298*)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor and acceptor site decreases</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>The main donor site increase and a new acceptor site in created</td></tr><tr><td>c.981T &gt;  &gt;  &gt; C (p.P327P)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>Score for the main donor site decreases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>A new donor site is created</td></tr><tr><td>c.1021G &gt; A (p.V341M)</td><td>Possibly damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The WT consensus sequence is not recognized</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.1400A &gt; G (p.K467R)</td><td>Possibly damaging</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Damaging</td><td>Disease causing</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr><tr><td>c.1467G &gt; A (p.E489E)</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Score for the main donor site increases</td><td>Neutral</td><td>A new acceptor site is created</td></tr><tr><td>c.2324G &gt; A (p.S775N)</td><td>Benign</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Tolerated</td><td>Polymorphism</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>Neutral</td><td>The main donor site is not recognized</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>These mutations, located in the 5′UTR region, could affect the binding site for several transcription factors. Thus, c.1-347C &gt; T may create a new binding site for SRF (<italic>Serum response factor</italic>), c.1-186A &gt; T for DICE (<italic>Downstream Immunoglobulin Control Element</italic>), and c.1-92C &gt; A for FTF (<italic>Alpha (1)-fetoprotein transcription factor</italic>). The c.1-301G &gt; A change could delete the binding site for MSX2 (<italic>Muscle-segment homebox 2</italic>) and c.1-279C &gt; A did not produce changes in the analyzed binding sites (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p>
        <p>We have found 25 different variations in the coding region in 21 patients (38%), who included 12 patients with IPAH and 9 with APAH. The highest percentage of nucleotide alterations corresponds to missense changes, which represent 71% of total variations found, followed by synonymous changes (33%) and nonsense mutations (14%). These results were partially reported in Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p>
        <p>All the variations identified in this study have not been found in the different databases considered, such as dbSNP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP</ext-link>), ESP6500 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evs.gs.washington.edu/EVS/">http://evs.gs.washington.edu/EVS/</ext-link>), ExAC (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://exac.broadinstitute.org/">http://exac.broadinstitute.org/</ext-link>), and CSVS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csvs.babelomics.org/">http://csvs.babelomics.org/</ext-link>). Missense variations were analyzed <italic>in silico</italic> with different tools (<italic>PolyPhen-2, Pmut, Sift and Mutation Taster</italic>) to predict their pathogenicity and the impact on the disease. Likewise, all variations were analyzed <italic>in silico</italic> to know if these missense, synonymous and nonsense variations could affect donor/acceptor splice sites (<italic>NNSplice</italic>, <italic>NetGene2</italic>, <italic>Splice View</italic> and <italic>Human Splice Finder (HSF)</italic>). We classified the mutation as potentially pathogenic if at least two <italic>in silico</italic> tools detected any possible alteration in the canonical sequence recognition. These results are available in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Minigene assays</title>
        <p>After performing an exhaustive bioinformatics analysis of the mutations identified, we detected 22 changes that presumably affect the splicing process (Tables <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). To go in depth into the possible role of these putative splicing variants, we generated minigene constructions. Our results showed that 6 out of 22 mutations (27%) have an effect on mRNA processing. Three nucleotide changes were synonymous (c.633A &gt; G, c.835G &gt; T and c.981T &gt; C) and 3 were missense variants (c.251G &gt; T, c.412C &gt; G and c.1400A &gt; G). Besides, we confirmed that 2 nonsense changes (c.654T &gt; A and c.893G &gt; A) and 1 frameshift mutation (c.156_157delTC) produce a premature stop codon, as expected.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Changes with no effect on the mRNA processing.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change (amino acid change)</th><th>Exon</th><th>Number of patients</th><th>PAH type</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>c.190A</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.S64R)</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.229A</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.I77L)</td><td>2</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.259G</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.H87Y)</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.275A</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.Q92L)</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.Q109Q)</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.Q109H)</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>This study</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.484G</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.A162P)</td><td>4</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.600A</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.L200L)</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>rs55722784</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.637C</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.R213R)</td><td>6</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.742A</bold> &gt; <bold>G</bold> (p.R248G)</td><td>6</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.790G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.D264N)</td><td>6</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>CD061372</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1021G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.V341M)</td><td>8</td><td>3</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1467G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.E489E)</td><td>11</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Pathogenic mutations found in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene in our clinical series.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change</th><th>Region</th><th>Score <sup>(1)</sup>
</th><th>Effect on protein</th><th>Number of patients</th><th>PAH type</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>c.1-347C &gt; T</td><td>5′UTR</td><td>0</td><td>Expression is decreased</td><td>2</td><td>IPAH</td><td>This study</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-301G &gt; A</td><td>5′UTR</td><td>0</td><td>Expression is decreased</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>rs116154690</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-279C &gt; A</td><td>5′UTR</td><td>0</td><td>Expression is decreased</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>This study</td></tr><tr><td>c.1-92C &gt; A</td><td>5′UTR</td><td>0</td><td>Expression is decreased</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>This study</td></tr><tr><td>c.156_157delTC</td><td>Exon 2</td><td>2</td><td>p.S52Sfs*1</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.251G &gt; T</td><td>Exon 3</td><td>3</td><td>p.C84Ffs*12</td><td>2</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.412C &gt; G</td><td>Exon 3</td><td>0</td><td>p.P138_S140del</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>This study</td></tr><tr><td>c.633A &gt; G</td><td>Exon 6</td><td>2</td><td>p.E207_G212del</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.654T &gt; A</td><td>Exon 6</td><td>2</td><td>p.Y218*</td><td>1</td><td>APAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.835G &gt; T</td><td>Exon 6</td><td>1</td><td>p.L207_N284del</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.893G &gt; A</td><td>Exon 7</td><td>2</td><td>p.W298*</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.981T &gt; C</td><td>Exon 8</td><td>2</td><td>p.H324_E379del</td><td>2</td><td>IPAH/APAH <sup>(1)</sup>
</td><td>Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td>c.1400A &gt; G</td><td>Exon 10</td><td>2</td><td>p.K467Rfs*27</td><td>1</td><td>IPAH</td><td>This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(1)This mutation appears in a patient with IPAH and in a patient with APAH.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
        <p>The c.633A &gt; G mutation was first classified as a synonymous change: p.R211R. The mutant c.633A &gt; G minigene prevented the recognition of the main acceptor site. Direct sequencing of cDNA confirmed the creation of a new 3′ alternative site, leading to a deletion of 12 bp in the 5′ region of exon 6. The mutated protein would be p.E207_G212del, which would have 1034 amino acids in length. The c.835G &gt; T variant was first predicted as p.V278V. The construction showed that this mutation produces the skipping of exon 6, so the resulting protein (p.L207_N284del) would be 77 amino acids shorter than the wild-type BMPR2. Finally, the c.981T &gt; C mutation, predicted first as the p.P327P protein, would cause the skipping of exon 8 and therefore, a truncated protein of 985 amino acids (p.H324_E379del) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A,B,C</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>
<italic>In vitro</italic> mRNA processing for synonymous mutations (p.R211R, p.V278V and p.P327P) and missense mutations (p.C84F, p.P138A and p.K467R) that affect the splicing process, identified in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. The minigene assay shows the alterations caused by these mutations in mRNA processing. Three of them produces an exon skipping (p.L207_N284del, p.H324_E379del and p.C84Ffs*12) and three produces partial elimination of an exon (p.P138_S140del, p.E207_G212del and p.K467Rfs*27).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2540"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>Mutations predicted as missense changes would modify the splicing process. Thus, c.251G &gt; T, resulted in skipping of exon 3 and therefore, the encoded protein would have only 96 amino acids (p.C84Ffs*12). The c.412C &gt; G mutation would produce an alternative 5′splicing site resulting in a two-amino-acid shorter protein (p.P138_S140del), since the mutation would eliminate the main donor site and would generate a new donor splice site. The analysis of c.1400A &gt; G showed that this mutation creates a new splice donor site and therefore, the new protein would have only 494 amino acids (p.K467Rfs*27) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3D,E,F</xref>).</p>
        <p>Regarding the frameshift and nonsense mutations, they would generate shorter proteins due to premature stop codons: c.156_157delTC (p.S52Sfs*1), c.654T &gt; A (p.Y218*) and c.893G &gt; A (p.W298*) generating proteins of 54, 218 and 298 amino acids in length, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A,B,C</xref>). Finally, the minigene assays showed negative results for the remaining 13 synonymous changes and therefore, their potential pathogenicity remains elusive (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>
<italic>In vitro</italic> mRNA processing for frameshift mutation (p.S52Sfs*1) and nonsense mutations (p.Y218* and p.W298*) that produce a premature stop codon in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene, as expected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2569"/></fig>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Subcellular localization studies</title>
        <p>To determine the possible effect of the clinical mutations on the subcellular localization of the BMPR2 protein, we performed immunofluorescence assays. Our results indicated that in HeLa cells, the wild-type BMPR2 showed a plasma membrane and perinuclear localization (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). However, one frameshift mutation, c.156_157delTC (p.S52Sfs*1), one nonsense mutation, c.893G &gt; A (p.W298*), and one missense mutation, c.251G &gt; T (p.C84F), show an abnormal cytoplasmatic pattern (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The c.654T &gt; A (p.Y218*) mutation displayed a subcellular localization similar to that of wild-type, although some cells show a different punctate pattern of expression at the plasma membrane, compared to the wild-type BMPR2 protein (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The remaining missense mutations analyzed (c.190A &gt; C, c.229A &gt; T, c.259G &gt; T, c.275A &gt; T, c.327G &gt; C, c.412 C &gt; G, c.484 G &gt; C, c.742 A &gt; G, c.790 G &gt; A, c.1021 G &gt; A, c.1400 A &gt; G and c.2324 G &gt; A), mimic the pattern of the wild-type BMPR2 protein (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Representative photomicrograph showing subcellular localization of the BMPR2 wild-type and those mutants which pattern of expression is altered. All these constructs are GFP-tagged at the C-terminus. After 24 h post-transfection, HELA cells were fixed and mounted in Fluoromount-F. Images were visualized using a Leica TCS SP2 confocal system. Arrows indicates plasma membrane location. Asterisk indicates perinuclear region. The scale bar is 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2603"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Photomicrograph example of the subcellular localization, in HELA cells, of the BMPR2 wild-type and those mutants which pattern of expression is altered. All these constructs are GFP-tagged at the C-terminus. After 24 h post-transfection, HELA cells were fixed and mounted in Fluoromount-F. Images were visualized using a Leica TCS SP2 confocal system. The scale bar is 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2613"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Representative photomicrograph showing subcellular localization of the BMPR2 mutants which pattern of expression is not altered. All these constructs are GFP-tagged at the C-terminus. After 24 h post-transfection, HELA cells were fixed and mounted in Fluoromount-F. Images were visualized using a Leica TCS SP2 confocal system. The scale bar is 10μm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2623"/></fig>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Luciferase assay</title>
        <p>We observed statistically significant differences for 4 out of the 5 mutations in the gene transcriptional activity by luciferase assays. Three mutations (c.1-347 C &gt; T, c.1-301 G &gt; A and c.1-92 C &gt; A) showed a decreased transcriptional activity that ranges between 70–77% (p &lt; 0.0001) compared to wild-type levels. Remarkably, the c.1-279 C &gt; A mutation produced the greatest decrease in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> transcriptional activity: 93% (p &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The c.1-186 A &gt; T change led to a decrease of about 2% with no statistical significance (p = 0.495) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These pathogenic mutations (c.1-347 C &gt; T, c.1-301 G &gt; A. c.1-279 C &gt; A and c.1-92 C &gt; A) were found in 5 out of 55 patients included in this study.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Transcriptional activity of the 5′UTR region of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene containing different mutations (c.1-347C &gt; T, c.1-301G &gt; A, c.1-279C &gt; A, c.1-186A &gt; T and c.1-92C &gt; A). The pGL3-Basic vector containing no promoter element was used as negative control and the pGL3-Promoter vector fused with SV40 promoter element was used as positive control. c.1-347C &gt; T, c.1-301G &gt; A, c.1-279C &gt; A, and c.1-92C &gt; A mutations produces a decreased transcriptional activity of the 5′UTR region of the BMPR2 gene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_2074_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e2650"/></fig>
</p>
        <p>All pathogenic mutations found in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene in our clinical series are summarized in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Association with clinical features and hemodynamic parameters</title>
        <p>We classify 13 nucleotide variants found in 16 of 55 patients (29%) as pathogenic, according to the results obtained in the previously described assays. These mutations include synonymous, missense and nonsense mutations located in coding regions and changes located in the 5′UTR region. All of them have been described for the first time by our group, in this paper or in Pousada <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, except the c.1-301G &gt; A (rs116154690) mutation located in the 5′UTR region.</p>
        <p>We compared clinical features and hemodynamic parameters among patients with pathogenic changes in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene and without (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). We found statistically significant differences in systolic pulmonary artery pressure (sPaP; p = 0.042) and 6 minutes walking test (6MWT; p = 0.041): patients carrying a <italic>BMPR2</italic> mutation presented with a higher values for this parameter than non-carriers. In addition, individuals harboring mutations had a significantly lower age at diagnosis (p = 0.040). Besides, patients with mutations seemed to have worse response to phosphodiesterase-5-inhibitors (p = 0.010). The presence of mutations was unrelated to gender (p = 0.360), mPaP (p = 0.266), PVR (p = 0.553) and cardiac index (CI) (p = 0.588). Clinical or pathogenic mutations were seen in 10 patients with IPAH and 6 patients with APAH without statistical differences (p = 0.137), clinical and hemodynamic parameters did not show significant differences between IPAH and APAH.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The characterization of functional relevance of variants found in human diseases is being a challenge. The identification of a causal mutation is essential for molecular diagnosis and clinical management of many genetic disorders. However, there are still difficulties in distinguishing which variants may cause or contribute to disease. Some articles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> highlight that mutations directly affecting splice sites or altering potential regulatory elements are more prevalent. Current knowledge clearly indicates that, besides their protein coding potential, altered sequences can play an important role in RNA splicing. The functional characterization of these type of mutations will help in developing bioinformatics tools that allowed us to predict the causative effect of a particular mutation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>We hypothesized that variants located in the exonic region of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene could lead to alterations which affect the proper splicing process or cause an abnormal protein subcellular localization. In addition, mutations in the 5′UTR region could be associated with a decrease in the transcriptional activity. The analyzed variants show a high clinical interest since all of them have been identified in heterozygous state and most of these variants represent the only genetic variant found in the in some patients of the cohort included in this study. Patients were clinically evaluated in detail and the functional analysis of these variants could help us to better understand the low penetrance associated with <italic>BMPR2</italic> mutations.</p>
      <p>After mutational analysis of exonic and flanking regions of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene in patients with PAH, several mutations were predicted to affect the splicing process. However, it is difficult to discriminate between neutral and pathogenic variants, based on splice site conservation and bioinformatics predictions exclusively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Thus, it is necessary to perform specific analyses to ascertain their pathogenicity and their possible involvement in the mRNA processing.</p>
      <p>Twenty-two variants were detected and subsequently analyzed by <italic>in silico</italic> tools. Only 9 of them were predicted to render a shorter protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, either due to the deletion of some base pairs (c.412C &gt; G, c.633A &gt; G, c.1400A &gt; G), to the deletion of a whole exon (c.251G &gt; T, c.835G &gt; T, c.981T &gt; C), to a frameshift mutation which cause a premature stop codon (c.156_157delTC) or nonsense mutations (c.654T &gt; A, c.893G &gt; A). These mutations are located in exonic regions and have been shown to produce the elimination or creation of new splice sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. New cryptic dinucleotide sequences have been used for those mutations deleting some base pairs. Mutation c.412C &gt; G generates a GG acceptor site, Sharma <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> perform several experiments with a GG change in the acceptor splice site of Cystic Fibrosis (CF) gene that generate an alternative splice site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Mutation c.633A &gt; G, is a T-to-C change in the invariant GT dinucleotide donor splice site modifying the cryptic splice site as described for mutation p.Q1291H in CF disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Finally, GA dinucleotide in the donor splice site is generated for c.1400A &gt; G mutation, as previously described like a rare exception, in the <italic>FGFR</italic> gene family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. However, several splice sites that do not follow the GT-AG rule have been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>For synonymous mutations, we obtained an altered splicing pattern in 3 out of 7 mutations (c.633A &gt; G, c.835G &gt; T, c.981T &gt; C), using a minigene study approach. This result highlights the importance of carrying out functional studies since, to date, the pathogenicity of synonymous variants has been disregarded<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. The synonymous and other mutations under study (c.654T &gt; A, c.893G &gt; A, c.1400A &gt; G) were located in the serine/threonine kinase domain, characterized by the presence of highly conserved regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. These synonymous mutations alter the mRNA processing and lead to a shorter serine/threonine kinase domain. Giving the important role of this ATP-binding domain, any structural changes could avoid the interaction between SMADs proteins, inhibiting the TGF-β signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The remaining mutations associated with alterations in the splicing process are located in the N-terminal (c.156_157delTC and c.251G &gt; T) and in the transmembrane (c.412C &gt; G) domains. It is possible that nonsense and missense mutations that result in a premature stop codon could be degraded by nonsense mediated decay (NMD). Conversely, the mutations located in the transmembrane domain could yield a weaker anchorage of the BMPR2 protein, affecting its stability. Mutations in transmembrane domain of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene have been reported to trigger important physiological effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Nevertheless, since the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene is expressed in vascular endothelial cells, which are hardly accessible tissues, we could not perform functional analysis in specific tissues. It would also be interesting to analyze their impact in animal models and to check how these mutations could modify the phenotype <italic>in vivo</italic>. The splicing mutations represent more than 9% of published changes in PAH<sup>4</sup>, but experimental analyses could increase this percentage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Cooper <italic>et al</italic>. have estimated that 1.6% of missense substitutions affect the mRNA processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Additional functional analyses are necessary to establish the mechanism underlying disease since not all the mutations associated with splicing alterations are classified as such after <italic>in silico</italic> analysis and vice versa. In this sense, minigene assay has been reported as a good approach to evaluate possible splicing alterations related to all these variants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Otherwise, subcellular localization studies showed that the wild-type BMPR2 protein is located both in plasma membrane and perinuclear cell region, as has been reported by other authors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. The c.251G &gt; T (p.C84F) missense mutation showed a diffuse cytoplasmic expression pattern which is similar to that observed for other clinical mutations affecting cysteines in the extra cellular domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Instead, according to minigene assays, the c.251G &gt; T variant generates a frameshift mutation (p.C84Ffs*12). The p.S52Sfs*1 and p.W298* variants, which produce a truncated protein, are also mimicking a cytoplasmic expression pattern. However, one nonsense mutation (p.Y218*) behaves similar to the BMPR2 wild-type protein, although a different punctuate pattern at the plasma membrane is produced. These truncated form lacking transmembrane domain would probably lead to a mislocalization of the protein from plasma membrane. It has been reported that not only mutations located in N-terminal or ligand binding domains, but also mutations producing a premature stop codon, could be associated with alterations in protein localization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. These aberrant proteins could be retained in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and activate the ER quality control (ERQC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Those species retained in ER tend to dimerize with themselves and the wild-type protein, exerting a dominant negative functional effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The transduction signal mediated by BMPR2 also might be affected, inhibiting TGF-β pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. It is known that BMPR2 interacts with CAV1 (caveolin-1) in several cell types. In vascular smooth muscle cells this interaction regulates BMPR2 signaling, with an associated loss of BMPR2-dependent SMAD phosphorylation by decreasing the association between BMPR2 and BMPR1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, and a down-regulation of other genes such as <italic>SMADs</italic> when levels of <italic>CAV1</italic> are decreased<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Furthermore, patients carrying mutations responsible for alterations in subcellular localization, show high levels of endothelin-1 (ET-1) and reduced levels of nitric oxide (NO)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Down-regulation of BMPR2 stimulates the production of ET-1 and reduces the production of NO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. For this reason, we cannot discard the idea that mutants leading to an altered subcellular localization of BMPR2 could cause an endothelial imbalance of these two genetic modifiers. The aforementioned alterations and interactions at cellular level could be important in the context of homeostasis, providing an additional explanation for the variety of PAH phenotypes.</p>
      <p>It has been described, by Girerd <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, that mutations located in the BMPR2 cytoplasmic tail could have a role in the development of PAH disease despite not affecting SMAD signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Likewise, we have identified a variation located in the BMPR2 cytoplasmic tail (c.2324G &gt; A)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> which does not involve any alteration in subcellular localization, confirming the trafficking to the cell surface. Little is known about the function of the cytoplasmic tail, but several studies confirm the ability of these mutations to activate SMAD signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Additional functions have been described for this domain such as regulation of p38 and p42/44 MAPK and the interaction with LIMK, c-Src, Tctex and TRB3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, 5′UTR variants have been related to several pathologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. However, a recent study suggests that mutations in this region only represent a second hit for the development of PAH and can lead to an earlier onset of symptoms and more severe clinical course, modifying its penetrance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Patients carrying mutations in the 5′UTR region, despite not having any other alteration in the studied genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, seem to present a more severe phenotype. All constructions, except c.1-186A &gt; T, showed a decreased transcriptional activity, which could down-regulate BMPR2 expression and weaken Smad1/5 signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Thus, this could prevent BMPR1/BMPR2 complex binding and subsequent phosphorylation, thereby avoiding ligand binding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. For this reason the translocation to the nucleus could be inhibited, with full or partial reduction of gene expression pattern. These changes can affect cell homeostasis by impairing the binding sites of transcription factors binding sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>We have detected 30 total variants in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. Of those, we have confirmed some functional effect in 13 of them. Besides, for c.275A &gt; T, c.742A &gt; C, c.790G &gt; A and c.1021G &gt; A mutations, we not detect any difference with wild-type regarding to splicing and subcellular localization analysis. Likewise, due to the absence or low frequency of these changes in dbSNP, ESP6500, ExAc and CSVS databases (&lt;0.00001), its location in the serine/threonine kinase domain except for the first variant, and the classification of pathogenic by multiple software we consider them as VUS. After <italic>in vitro</italic> analysis, clinical mutations were detected in 29% of patients. This is, to our knowledge, the study with highest rate for BMPR2 mutations in which a functional analysis has been performed.</p>
      <p>After genotype-phenotype correlation analysis, we found significant statistical differences for age at diagnosis, sPaP, 6MWT and response to treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. Remarkably, patients with nonsense mutations present a less severe phenotype than patients with other pathogenic mutations. This could be explained by other mechanisms instead of NMD or perhaps a dominant negative effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. As suggested in mice, other pathways should take place in these cases in order to minimize the impact of <italic>BMPR2</italic> mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>.</p>
      <p>This study does not have enough power to clarify the different treatment effect related to the presence of mutations. Perhaps the worst response found in carriers of mutations may be due to a greater impact on cell proliferation in the media and layers intima of the pulmonary arteries due to the deterioration of the pathways regulated by <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. It would be very interesting to design prospective studies to determine which drugs would be most effective in patients with mutations in <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene and other genes involved in the development of PAH.</p>
      <p>Our study confirms that the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene is a leading player in the pathogenesis of PAH. An exhaustive analysis of this gene shows that a significant percentage of patients have some potentially pathogenic variant. The <italic>in vitro</italic> expression analysis is a good approach to determine the effect of the variants on mRNA processing, especially in those cases where the genes involved are expressed in tissues of difficult access. It is important to highlight the importance of investigating synonymous mutations and mutations located in the UTR regions, which can act as causal variants of disease as well.</p>
      <p>The pathophysiology of PAH shows a complex mechanism in which the TGF-β pathway plays a decisive role in the development of the disease, and a heterogeneous constellation of genetic arrangements could be responsible for the pulmonary vascular remodeling.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec10" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Material and Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Patients and samples</title>
        <p>Fifty-five patients with idiopathic or associated PAH (group 1 of the new classification of Nize)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> followed in our Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension Unit were enrolled. Cardiac catheterization was performed using the latest consensus diagnostic criteria of the ERS-ESC (mean resting pulmonary pressure ≥25 mmHg, PAWP &lt;15 mmHg) in all cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>. PAH was considered idiopathic after exclusion of all the possible clinical causes associated with the disease. Clinical history included use of drugs, especially appetite suppressants, and screening for connective tissue and hepatic diseases. The study also included serology for HIV (human immunodeficiency virus), autoimmunity, thoracic CT scan (computerized tomography scan) and echocardiography. Patients with chronic lung disease that could be related to PAH, were excluded. Patients were considered responders to treatment when they met the following criteria: improvement of at least one functional class or maintenance in functional class II, decreased proBNP, 10% increase in the distance walked on the 6 minutes test, no hospital admissions related PAH and no need for new specific treatment for PAH. Samples from fifty individuals provided by the Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo, were used as controls.</p>
        <p>Patients signed an informed consent and the Autonomic Ethics Committee approved the study (Galician Ethical Committee for Clinical Research; <italic>Comité Autonómico de Ética da Investigación de Galicia - CAEI de Galicia</italic>) followed the clinical-ethical practices of the Spanish Government and the Helsinki Declaration.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Identification and analysis of mutations in <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA was extracted from leukocytes isolated from venous blood using the FlexiGene DNA Kit (Qiagen, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. We performed a Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) with 50 ng of genomic DNA from each patient and control in a MJ MiniTM Gradient Thermal Cycler (Bio-Rad, Hercules, California, USA), using GoTaq® Green Master Mix (Promega Corporation, Madison, Wisconsin, USA), which contained Taq DNA polymerase, dNTPs, MgCl<sub>2</sub> and reaction buffer. Amplification conditions were as follows: 95 °C for 5 min, 35 cycles of 95 °C for 30 s, 55 °C for 30 s, 72 °C for 30 s and a final extension of 72 °C for 10 min. Forward and reverse primers, described by Deng Z <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> were used to amplify 5′UTR and coding region for <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene, and also intronic junctions. PCR products were separated by electrophoresis through 2% agarose gels containing ethidium bromide to confirm the PCR products, in a Sub-Cell GT chamber (Bio-Rad, Hercules, California, USA). The PCR products were then purified using the ExoSAP-IT kit (USB Corporation, Cleveland, Ohio, USA) and sequenced with the BigDye Terminator version 3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, California, USA) in a GeneAmp PCR System 2700 (Applied Biosystems, California, USA). The PCR products were precipitated and finally analyzed in an ABI PRISM 3100 genetic analyzer (Applied Biosystems, California, USA). Sequences were aligned to the reference Ensembl DNA sequence [ENST00000374580]. All detected changes were confirmed by a second independent PCR reaction and were identified in both forward and reverse strands.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>In silico analysis</title>
        <p>To predict whether a rare missense variant was deleterious, we used the combined results of four different computer algorithms: The Polymorphism Phenotyping Program (PolyPhen-2; available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph/">http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>, Pmut (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mmb2.pcb.ub.es:8080/PMut/">http://mmb2.pcb.ub.es:8080/PMut/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>, Sorting Intolerant from Tolerant (SIFT; available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.jcvi.org">http://sift.jcvi.org</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup> and MutationTaster2 software (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mutationtaster.org/">http://www.mutationtaster.org/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. We also analyzed intronic, synonymous, missense, nonsense and frameshift indels changes to predict whether those changes could potentially affect splicing process, by creating or eliminating donor/acceptor splice sites, with Neural Network SPLICE (<italic>NNSplice</italic>) 0.9 version from the Berkeley Drosophila Genome Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fruitfly.org:9005/seq_tools/splice.html">http://fruitfly.org:9005/seq_tools/splice.html</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup>, <italic>NetGene2</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetGene2">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetGene2</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup>, <italic>Splice View</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.itb.cnr.it/oriel/splice-view.html">http://bioinfo.itb.cnr.it/oriel/splice-view.html</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup> and Human Splicing Finder (<italic>HSF</italic>) 2.4.1 version (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.umd.be/HSF">http://www.umd.be/HSF</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>. Finally, alterations in binding sites of transcription factors in 5′UTR region of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene were evaluated with MatInspector software (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.genomatix.de/online_help/help_matinspector/matinspector_help.html">https://www.genomatix.de/online_help/help_matinspector/matinspector_help.html</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Design of minigene constructs</title>
        <p>To perform minigene assay, we generated fragments containing the exon where the mutation was located and 150–200 bp of flanking intronic regions. We amplified them by PCR from normal genomic DNA using primers described in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> and High Fidelity Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes, Espoo, Finland), and these fragments were subcloned into the pSPL3 vector (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA) at the <italic>Xho</italic>I/<italic>Nhe</italic>I restriction sites (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA) using T4DNA Ligase (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA) to generate a construct with wild-type fragments. The cloning was confirmed by PCR with primers 5′-CATGCTCCTTGGGATGTTGAT-3′ (<italic>forward</italic>) and 5′-ACTGTGCGTTACAATTTCTGG-3′ (<italic>reverse</italic>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Primer sequences for minigene fragments in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change (Amino acid change)</th><th>Primers</th><th>Size</th><th>Tª</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>c.156_157delTC</bold> (p.S52Sfs*2)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGGAATTCATGAACAGAAGAACG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCCTCGAAAAGTGCTGGAATTA</td><td>514bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.190A</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.S64R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGGAATTCATGAACAGAAGAACG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCCTCGAAAAGTGCTGGAATTA</td><td>514 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.229A</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.I77L)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGGAATTCATGAACAGAAGAACG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCCTCGAAAAGTGCTGGAATTA</td><td>514 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.251G</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.C84F)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.259G</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.H87Y)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.275A</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.Q92L)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.Q109Q)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.Q109H)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.412C</bold> &gt; <bold>G</bold> (p.P138A)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCATGAAATGTCTTTGGTATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCTACGCCCGGCTAATTTTTTA</td><td>582 bp</td><td>59 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.484G</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.A162P)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGACTTGGTGTTTTAGTGTTCC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGAAAGGGGTAGTGACTGATAA</td><td>521 bp</td><td>57 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.600A</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.L200L)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCCAGAATTTGGCTTTCATGC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGTTCACCTATGTTCCTAGTG</td><td>468 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.633A &gt; G</bold> (p.R211R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.637C &gt; A</bold> (p.R213R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.654T</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.Y218*)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.742A</bold> &gt; <bold>G</bold> (p.R248G)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.790G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.D264N)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.835G</bold> &gt; <bold>T</bold> (p.V278V)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGCATCAGCCATACTAGAACAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGCTGGAATTACAGATGTGTG</td><td>591 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.893G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.W298*)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGGTTTAAATTCCCCTTTCCATC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGAGTTTTACTCAGCTATCAAG</td><td>560 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.981T</bold> &gt; <bold>C</bold> (p.P327P)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGAGTGGCAGCATGTTTGTTAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGGTCTCGAACTCTTTACCTT</td><td>549 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1021G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.V341M)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGAGTGGCAGCATGTTTGTTAG R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGGTCTCGAACTCTTTACCTT</td><td>549 bp</td><td>58 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1400A</bold> &gt; <bold>G</bold> (p.K467R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGTTAGGATTTCCAAATGTGCC R 5′ → 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCGATTTGTGGCATTAGGCAAC</td><td>412 bp</td><td>57 °C</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1467G</bold> &gt; <bold>A</bold> (p.E489E)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AAGAATCTCGAGTCACCTTTTGAGCATGTTCC R 5′→ 3′: AAGAATGCTAGCCAGATTTCATCTTGCACTTG</td><td>549 bp</td><td>57 °C</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F: Forward; R: Reverse.</p><p>bp: Base pair.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Design of pEGFP-N1 constructs</title>
        <p>To perform cellular localization studies, we generated wild-type and mutated BMPR2 constructs. The human full-length cDNA of BMPR2, obtained from the MGC Human BMPR2 Sequence-Verified cDNA (ID: 6149698; GE Healthcare Dharmacon Inc, Lafayette, CO, USA), was subcloned into the mammalian expression vector pEGFP-N1, with the GFP at the C-terminal end (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA), with High Fidelity Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes, Espoo, Finland) and with primers 5′-GGAAGTCGACCATGACTTCCTCGCTGCAGCG-3′ (<italic>forward)</italic> and 5′-GCGCCTCGAGCATTTCACAGACAGTTCATTCC-3′ (<italic>reverse)</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Design of luciferase constructs</title>
        <p>The Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega, USA) was chosen to establish the activity of 5′UTR region in <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene. The 539 bp human <italic>BMPR2</italic> 5′UTR region was amplified by PCR from normal genomic DNA using the primers 5′-AAGAATGCTAGCGGAAGCACCGAAGCGAAAC-3′ (forward) and 5′-AAGAATCTCGAGCCCTGGGCCAGCCAAGAAT-3′ (reverse). PCR was performed with High Fidelity Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes, Espoo, Finland) and the resultant fragments were subcloned into the pGL3-Basic vector (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA) at the NheI/XhoI restriction sites (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, Massachusetts, USA), using T4DNA Ligase (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA) to generate a construct with wild-type 5′UTR region driving firefly luciferase expression gene. The fragments were inserted with the same orientation, and their sequences were confirmed by DNA sequencing using RVprimer3 and GLprimer2 (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA). The pGL3-Basic vector containing no promoter element was used as negative control and the pGL3-Promoter vector (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA) fused with SV40 promoter element was used as positive control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Directed Mutagenesis</title>
        <p>Mutagenesis of the wild-type fragments to generate mutant minigenes for each of the identified variants, mutagenesis of the wild-type cDNA of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene construct to performed cellular localization studies and mutagenesis of the wild-type 5′UTR region of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene (firefly luciferase) to generate mutant constructs for each change, was performed by using QuikChange XL-II Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene, Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The specific primer sequences containing the nucleotide changes for minigene constructs and cellular localization are indicated in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> and the primer sequences to luciferase constructs are available in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>. The p.S52Sfs*1, p.Y218* and p.W298* constructs for cellular localization were generated by subcloning the sequence of interest, amplified from pEGFP-N1: BMPR2 plasmid, into the SalI and BamHI restriction sites of the pEGFP-N1 vector. Plasmids were sequenced after site-directed mutagenesis to confirm their authenticity and to rule out additional nonspecific changes.<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used to perform mutagenesis for each minigene and subcellular localization in the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change (Amino acid change)</th><th>Primers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>c.156_157delTC</bold> (p.S52Sfs*2)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GGATAGGTGAGAGTAGAATCTCATGAAAATGGGACAATATTATG R 5′ → 3′: CATAATATTGTCCCATTTTCATGAGATTCTACTCTCACCTATCC</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.190A &gt; C</bold> (p.S64R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GGGACAATATTATGCTCGAAAGGTCGCACCTGCTATGG R 5′ → 3′: CCATAGCAGGTGCAACCTTTCGAGCATAATATTGTCCC</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.229A &gt; T</bold> (p.I77L)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GGGAGAAATCAAAAGGGGACTTAAATCTTGTAAAACAAGGC R 5′ → 3′: GCCTTGTTTTACAAGATTTAAGTCCCCTTTTGATTTCTCCC</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.251G &gt; T</bold> (p.C84F)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CTTTTTTGTATTCATATTGATTTATAGGATTTTGGTCTCACATTGGAG R 5′ → 3′: CTCCAATGTGAGACCAAAATCCTATAAATCAATATGAATACAAAAAAG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.259G &gt; T</bold> (p.H87Y)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: ATCTTGTAAAACAAGGATGTTGGTCTTACATTGGAGATCCC R 5′ → 3′: GGGATCTCCAATGTAAGACCAACATCCTTGTTTTACAAGAT</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.275A &gt; T</bold> (p.Q92L)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: TCACATTGGAGATCCCCTAGAGTGTCACTATGAAG R 5′ → 3′: CTTCATAGTGACACTCTAGGGGATCTCCAATGTGA</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G &gt; A</bold> (p.Q109Q)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CACTCCTCCCTCAATTCAAAATGGAACATACCGTTTC R 5′ → 3′: GAAACGGTATGTTCCATTTTGAATTGAGGGAGGAGTG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.327G &gt; C</bold> (p.Q109H)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CACTCCTCCCTCAATTCACAATGGAACATACCGTTTC R 5′ → 3′: GAAACGGTATGTTCCATTGTGAATTGAGGGAGGAGTG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.412C &gt; G</bold> (p.P138A)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CACCTCCTGACACAACAGCACTCAGTAAGTAAAGT R 5′ → 3′: ACTTTACTTACTGAGTGCTGTTGTGTCAGGAGGTG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.484G &gt; C</bold> (p.A162P)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: TGGCATCAGTCTCTGTATTACCTGTTTTGATAGTTGCC R 5′ → 3′: GGCAACTATCAAAACAGGTAATACAGAGACTGATGCCA</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.600A &gt; C</bold> (p.L200L)</td><td>F 5′→ 3′: CCAACAGTTTCAGATTATCGAGATCAAGAGAGGGTTCGG R 5′ → 3′: CCGAACCCTCTCTTGATCTCGATAATCTGAAACTGTTGG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.633A &gt; G</bold> (p.R211R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CAGCTGATTGGCCGGGGTCGATATGGAGC R 5′ → 3′: GCTCCATATCGACCCCGGCCAATCAGCTG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.637C &gt; A</bold> (p.R213R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AGCTGATTGGCCGAGGTAGATATGGAGCAGTATAT R 5′ → 3′: ATATACTGCTCCATATCTACCTCGGCCAATCAGCT</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.654T &gt; A</bold> (p.Y218*)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CGAGGTCGATATGGAGCAGTATAAAAAGGCTCCTTGG R 5′ → 3′: CCAAGGAGCCTTTTTATACTGCTCCATATCGACCTCG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.742A &gt; G</bold> (p.R248G)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: AATTTTATCAACGAAAAGAACATTTACGGAGTGCCTTTGATGGAAC R 5′ → 3′: GTTCCATCAAAGGCACTCCGTAAATGTTCTTTTCGTTGATAAAATT</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.790G &gt; A</bold> (p.D264N)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CCCGCTTTATAGTTGGAAATGAGAGAGTCACTGCA R 5′ → 3′: TGCAGTGACTCTCTCATTTCCAACTATAAAGCGGG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.835G &gt; T</bold> (p.V278V)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CGCATGGAATATTTGCTTGTTATGGAGTACTATCCCAATGT R 5′ → 3′: ACATTGGGATAGTACTCCATAACAAGCAAATATTCCATGCG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.893G &gt; A</bold> (p.W298*)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: ATTTAAGTCTCCACACAAGTGACTAGGTAAGCTCTTGC R 5′ → 3′: GCAAGAGCTTACCTAGTCACTTGTGTGGAGACTTAAAT</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.981 T &gt; C</bold> (p.P327P)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: ATCCAAACAGATCATTATAAACCCGCAATTTCCCATCGAGATTTAAA R 5′ → 3′: TTTAAATCTCGATGGGAAATTGCGGGTTTATAATGATCTGTTTGGAT</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1021G &gt; A</bold> (p.V341M)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GAGATTTAAACAGCAGAAATGTCCTAATGAAAAATGATGGAACCTG R 5′ → 3′: CAGGTTCCATCATTTTTCATTAGGACATTTCTGCTGTTTAAATCTC</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1400A &gt; G</bold> (p.K467R)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CTTACCAGGCTATTTTCCTTCCAGGCTTCTGGGAA R 5′ → 3′: TTCCCAGAAGCCTGGAAGGAAAATAGCCTGGTAAG</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>c.1467G &gt; A</bold> (p.E489E)</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GTTGGGACCAGGATGCAGAAGCTCGGCTTA R 5′ → 3′: TAAGCCGAGCTTCTGCATCCTGGTCCCAAC</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F: Forward; R: Reverse.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Primer sequences for mutagenesis in 5′UTR region of the <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nucleotide change</th><th>Primers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>c.1-347C &gt; T</bold>
</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: CTGGATATGTTTTCTCCCAGACTTGGATATTTTTTTGATATCGTG</td></tr><tr><td>R 5′ → 3′: CACGATATCAAAAAAATATCCAAGTCTGGGAGAAAACATATCCAG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>c.1-301G &gt; A</bold>
</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: ACGAGGGAAATAATTTGGAGGATTTCTTCTTGGCTCC</td></tr><tr><td>R 5′ → 3′: GGAGCCAAGAAGAAATCCTCCAAATTATTTCCCTCGT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>c.1-279C &gt; A</bold>
</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: TCTTCTTGGCTCCCTGATTTCCCCACAGACATG</td></tr><tr><td>R 5′ → 3′: CATGTCTGTGGGGAAATCAGGGAGCCAAGAAGA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>c.1-186A &gt; T</bold>
</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GGGAGAGAAATGAAGGGTATTTCTGCAGCGGCATG</td></tr><tr><td>R 5′ → 3′: CATGCCGCTGCAGAAATACCCTTCATTTCTCTCCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>c.1-92C &gt; A</bold>
</td><td>F 5′ → 3′: GGGCAGGATCAGTCCAAGGGAGAGAAGACG</td></tr><tr><td>R 5′ → 3′: CGTCTTCTCTCCCTTGGACTGATCCTGCCC</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F: Forward; R: Reverse.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Cell culture and transfections</title>
        <p>We used COS-7 cells for minigene assay, HELA cells for subcellular localization studies and COS-1 cells for luciferase assay. All cell lines were cultured in DMEM (Gibco, Grand Island, USA), supplemented with 10% Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS; Gibco, Grand Island, USA), 1% L-Glutamine (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland) and 1% penicillin/streptomycin (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland), in a humidified atmosphere at 37 °C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. COS-7 cells with 80–90% confluency at passage three were transiently transfected by using 2 µg of pSPL3 construct (wild-type and mutant construct) per well. HELA cells were cultured in six-well plates on glass coverslips. On the other hand, COS-1 cells with 80–90% confluency were transfected by using 2 µg of pGL3-Bassic construct (with 5′UTR region of <italic>BMPR2</italic> gene, wild-type and mutant) per well and pGL3-Promoter vector as negative control. COS-1 cells were co-transfected with 20 ng of pRL-CMV vector (control Renilla plasmid). COS-7 transfection was performed using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA, USA) in a 2:5 ratio of μg of plasmid DNA to μl of Lipofectamine. Hela and COS-1 transfection was performed using Fugene HD (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA), in a 2:5 and 1:3 ratio of μg of plasmid DNA to μl of Fugene HD, respectively, and following the manufacturer’s instructions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Minigene Assay</title>
        <p>COS-7 cells were incubated during 36 h after transfection and all experiments were performed in duplicate. RNA extraction was performed with the Nucleospin RNA II Kit (Macherey-Nagel, Düren, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. RT-PCR was carried out with geneAmp Gold RNA PCR Core Kit (Applied Biosystems, California, USA) and the resulting cDNA was amplified with High Fidelity Phusion polymerase (Finnzymes, Espoo, Finland) with primers 5′-TCTGAGTCACCTGGACAACC-3′ (<italic>forward</italic>) and 5′-ATCTCAGTGGTATTTGTGAGC-3′ (reverse), which anneal with the SD6 and SA2 exons in pSPL3 vector. Amplification conditions were as follows: 98 °C for 30 s, 30 cycles of 98 °C for 10 s, 58 °C for 30 s, 72 °C for 30 s and finally, 72 °C for 7 min. The PCR products were separated by electrophoresis on 2% agarose gel to analyze changes in the transcript pattern, and sequenced with the BigDye Terminator version 3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, California, USA) to identify changes in splicing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>Subcellular Localization Assay</title>
        <p>For subcellular localization studies, HELA cells were fixed 24 h post-transfection in 4% (w/v) paraformaldehyde in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 15 min. After several washes with PBS, samples were mounted in Fluoromount-F (Souther Biotech, Birmingham, AL, USA). Images were visualized using a Leica TCS SP2 confocal system. In order to determine the pattern of localization for each mutant, a blind assessment by two researchers was performed using an average of 40 cells for each construct.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec21">
        <title>Luciferase Assay</title>
        <p>Cells were harvested at 36 h after transfection. Luciferase assays were performed with the Dual Luciferase Assay System (Promega, Madison, Wisconsin, USA) on a 2104 EnVision Luminometer (PerkinElmer, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). Cells were lysed in 500 µL of passive lysis buffer (PLB buffer) at room temperature for 30 min. For dual luciferase assay, 20 µL of lysate was aliquoted into a 96-well plate for measuring firefly luciferase (100 µL of LAR II) and renilla luciferase (100 µL of stop and glow buffer) activity. Firefly values were divided by Renilla values to normalize for fluctuations in plated cells and transfection efficiency. All experiments were repeated twice in triplicate and we analyzed two different constructs for the wild-type and the mutations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec22">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Values are expressed as mean ± SD (standard deviation). Differences between groups were examined for statistical significance using Student’s t-test. Chi-square test was used to compare clinical and hemodynamic variables among genotypes (variables were categorized according to the best cut off point by ROC curve). These correlations were analyzed by the Spearman test. Probability values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS for Windows (v19.0).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We are grateful to the patients who participated in our study; we thank the physicians who participated in the collection of patients and data (Carlos Vilariño Pombo, José Manuel Cifrián, Olalla Castro Añón). We really thank to Dr. Jose María Millán as he kindly provided the exon trapping expression vector pSPL3. We acknowledge the cooperation of Asociación Española de Hipertensión Pulmonar and Programa de Apoyo a las Capacidades Biomédicas (BIOCAPS) FP7-REGPOT316265. This study was supported by the grants IN-202-05 from SOGAPAR, CO-0085-10 from Actelion Pharmaceuticals and INBIOMED 2009-063 from Xunta de Galicia. CE has a “Miguel Servet” contract funded by the Instituto de Salud Carlos III (ISCIII) and the Centro de Investigación Príncipe Felipe (CIPF) [Grant no. CPII14/00002]. SCS and MAS are recipients of FPU fellowships from the Spanish Ministry of Education, Culture and Sports and ASM has a grant funded by the Fundació per amor a l’art”.</p>
    </ack>
    <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
      <title>Author Contributions</title>
      <p>G.P. conceived the study and its design, performed genetic research, functional characterization, data statistical analysis and interpretation, correlation genotype/phenotype and drafted the manuscript. V.L. performed functional characterization, data interpretation and drafted the manuscript. S.C.S. helped in functional characterization, data statistical analysis and draft the manuscript. M.A.S. helped in functional characterization, data interpretation and draft the manuscript. A.S.M. helped in functional characterization and data interpretation. A.B. conceived the study, collected the patients and clinical data, performed statistical analysis and drafted the manuscript. C.E. helped in study design, interpretation and draft the manuscript. D.V. conceived the study and participated in its design and coordination, interpretation the results and draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
    </notes>
    <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
      <sec id="FPar1">
        <title>Competing Interests</title>
        <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
    </notes>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoeper</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Definitions and Diagnosis of Pulmonary Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>25S</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.032</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peacock</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>NF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McMurray</surname>
              <given-names>JJV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caballero</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An epidemiological study of pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>104</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00092306</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17360728?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360728</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D’Alonzo</surname>
              <given-names>GE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Survival in patients with primary pulmonary hypertension. Results from a national prospective registry</article-title>
          <source>Ann Intern Med.</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>343</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-115-5-343</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1863023?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1863023</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics and Genomics of Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
          <fpage>S32</fpage>
          <lpage>S42</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2009.04.015</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19555857?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19555857</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary arterial hypertension in women</article-title>
          <source>Rev Mal Respir.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>e79</fpage>
          <lpage>e87</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmr.2009.12.001</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20965396?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20965396</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simonneau</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Updated clinical classification of pulmonary hypertension</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>25 Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>D34</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.029</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24355639?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355639</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soubrier</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics and Genomics of Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>25 Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>D13</fpage>
          <lpage>21</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2013.10.035</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24355637?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24355637</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Long</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>PN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression of mutant BMPR-II in pulmonary endothelial cells promotes apoptosis and a release of factors that stimulate proliferation of pulmonary arterial smooth muscle cells</article-title>
          <source>Pulm Circ.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2045-8932.78100</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22034596?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22034596</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pfarr</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemodynamic and clinical onset in patients with hereditary pulmonary arterial hypertension and BMPR2 mutations</article-title>
          <source>Respir Res.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-12-99</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21801371?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801371</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pousada</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vilariño</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cifrian</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel mutations in BMPR2, ACVRL1 and KCNA5 genes and hemodynamic parameters in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>e100261</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100261</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24936649?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24936649</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pfarr</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hemodynamic and genetic analysis in children with idiopathic, heritable, and congenital heart disease associated pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Respir Res.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-14-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23298310?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23298310</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ulrich</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence Variants in BMPR2 and Genes Involved in the Serotonin and Nitric Oxide Pathways in Idiopathic Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension and Chronic Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension: Relation to Clinical Parameters and Comparison with Left Heart Disease</article-title>
          <source>Respiration.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>287</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000250322</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19844076?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19844076</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Whole Exome Sequencing to Identify a Novel Gene (Caveolin-1) Associated with Human Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Circ Cardiovasc Genet.</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>336</fpage>
          <lpage>343</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.111.961888</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22474227?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22474227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension: Morphogenetic protein type II receptor</article-title>
          <source>Chest.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>134</volume>
          <fpage>1271</fpage>
          <lpage>1277</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.08-1341</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19059957?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19059957</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of pulmonary arterial hypertension: do the molecular findings have translational value</article-title>
          <source>F1000 Biology Reports.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 20948811?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20948811</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Upton</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The transforming growth factor-β-bone morphogenetic protein type signaling pathway in pulmonary vascular homeostasis and disease</article-title>
          <source>Exp Physiol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1262</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.2012.069104</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23645549?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23645549</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sauna</surname>
              <given-names>ZE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimchi-Sarfaty</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Understanding the contribution of synonymous mutations to human disease</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>683</fpage>
          <lpage>691</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3051</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21878961?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878961</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewandowska</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The missing puzzle piece: splicing mutations</article-title>
          <source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>2675</fpage>
          <lpage>2682</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 24294354?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24294354</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aparisi</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Study of USH1 Splicing Variants through Minigenes and Transcript Analysis from Nasal Epithelial Cells</article-title>
          <source>PLoS ONE.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>e57506</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057506</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23451239?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23451239</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lupo</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Missense mutations in the SH3TC2 protein causing Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4C affect its localization in the plasma membrane and endocytic pathway</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <issue>23</issue>
          <fpage>4603</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddp427</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19744956?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19744956</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel promoter and exon mutations of the BMPR2 gene in Chinese patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Hum Genet.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1063</fpage>
          <lpage>1069</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejhg.2009.3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19223935?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19223935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pousada</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular and clinical analysis of TRPC6 and AGTR1 genes in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Orphaned J Rare Dis.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13023-014-0216-3</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pousada</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fontán</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Núñez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutational and clinical analysis of the ENG gene in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>BMC Genetics.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>72</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12863-016-0384-3</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 27260700?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27260700</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Masica</surname>
              <given-names>DL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karchin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Towards Increasing the Clinical Relevance of In Silico Methods to Predict Pathogenic Missense Variants</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Comput Biol.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>e1004725</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004725</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 27171182?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27171182</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soukarieh</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exonic Splicing Mutations Are More Prevalent than Currently Estimated and Can Be Predicted by Using In Silico Tools</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>e1005756</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1005756</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26761715?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26761715</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pousada</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baloira</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valverde</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Complex inheritance in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension patients with several mutations</article-title>
          <source>Sci Rep.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>33570</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep33570</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 27630060?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27630060</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>ZX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peng</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Su</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A human-specific mutation leads to the origin of a novel splice form of neurosis (KLK8), a gene involved in learning and memory</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>978</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.20547</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17487847?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17487847</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Claverie-Martin</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez-Paredes</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos-Trujillo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Splicing defects caused by exonic mutations in PKD1 as a new mechanism of pathogenesis in autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease</article-title>
          <source>RNA Biol.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>369</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2015.1014291</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25757501?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25757501</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sharma</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Experimental assessment of splicing variants using expression minigenes and comparison with in silico predictions</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>1249</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.22624</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25066652?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25066652</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McIntosh</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keston</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ferguson</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brock</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three novel mutations in the cystic fibrosis gene detected by chemical cleavage: analysis of variant splicing and a nonsense mutation</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/1.1.11</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1284466?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1284466</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burset</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seledtsov</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solovyev</surname>
              <given-names>VV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of canonical and non-canonical splice sites in mammalian genomes</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>21</issue>
          <fpage>4364</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.21.4364</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11058137?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11058137</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brackenridge</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilkie</surname>
              <given-names>AOM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Screaton</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficient use of a ‘dead-end’ GA 5′ splice site in the human fibroblast growth factor receptor genes</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1620</fpage>
          <lpage>1631</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdg163</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12660168?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660168</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roca</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sachidanandam</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krainer</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determinants of the inherent strength of human 5′ splice sites</article-title>
          <source>RNA.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>683</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.2040605</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15840817?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840817</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>IJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A reappraisal of non-consensus mRNA splice sites</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <fpage>3795</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/19.14.3795</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 1713664?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1713664</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richard</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beckmann</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How neutral are synonymous codon mutations?</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0795-259</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 7670461?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7670461</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chaney</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Roles for synonymous codon usage in protein biogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Biophys.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biophys-060414-034333</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Montani</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1172-8-97</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23829793?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23829793</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hamid</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Penetrance of Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension is modulated by the expression of normal BMPR2 allele</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>649</fpage>
          <lpage>654</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.20922</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19206171?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19206171</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Best</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elliott</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of pulmonary hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>520</fpage>
          <lpage>527</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HCO.0000000000000105</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25159282?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25159282</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fessel</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loyd</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genetics of pulmonary arterial hypertension in the post-BMPR2 era</article-title>
          <source>Pulm Circ.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>305</fpage>
          <lpage>319</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2045-8932.87293</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 22140620?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22140620</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Majka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Physiologic and molecular consequences of endothelial BMPR2 mutation</article-title>
          <source>Respir Res.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>84</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-12-84</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21696628?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696628</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ravesh</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Novel C8orf37 mutations cause retinitis pigmentosa in consanguineous families of Pakistani origin</article-title>
          <source>Mol Vis.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>236</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 25802487?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25802487</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genes, mutations, and human inherited disease at the dawn of the age of personalized genomics</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>631</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.21260</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 20506564?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20506564</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baralle</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baralle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Splicing in action. Assessing disease causing sequence changes</article-title>
          <source>J Med Genet.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jmg.2004.029538</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16199547?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199547</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nuzzo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of an apparently synonymous F5 mutation causing aberrant splicing and factor V deficiency</article-title>
          <source>Haemophilia.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>241</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/hae.12554</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25470420?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25470420</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gilboa</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bone morphogenetic protein receptor complexes on the surface of live cells: a new oligomerization mode for serine/threonine kinase receptors</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Cell.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>1023</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.11.3.1023</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10712517?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712517</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Girerd</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of pulmonary arterial hypertension in affected carriers of a mutation located in the cytoplasmic tail of bone morphogenetic protein receptor type 2</article-title>
          <source>Chest.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1385</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.14-0880</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25429696?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429696</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rudarakanchana</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional analysis of bone morphogenetic protein type II receptor mutations underlying primary pulmonary hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>13</issue>
          <fpage>1517</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/11.13.1517</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12045205?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045205</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wertz</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bauer</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Caveolin-1 regulates BMPRII localization and signaling in vascular smooth muscle cells</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>375</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>557</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2008.08.066</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18725205?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18725205</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nishihara</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watabe</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imamura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyazono</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional heterogeneity of bone morphogenetic protein receptor-II mutants found in patients with primary pulmonary hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Cell.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>3055</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E02-02-0063</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 12221115?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12221115</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gallione</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation and expression analysis of the Endoglin Gene in Hereditary Hemorrhagic Telangiectasia reveals null alleles</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>286</fpage>
          <lpage>294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-1004(1998)11:4&lt;286::AID-HUMU6&gt;3.0.CO;2-B</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 9554745?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9554745</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <label>52.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional Changes in Pulmonary Arterial Endothelial Cells Associated with BMPR2 Mutations</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>e106703</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106703</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25187962?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25187962</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <label>53.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>John</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kizhakkedath</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Al-Gazali</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ali</surname>
              <given-names>BR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Defective celular trafficking of the bone morphogenetic protein receptor type II by mutations underlying familial pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Gene.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>561</volume>
          <fpage>148</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2015.02.038</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25688877?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25688877</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <label>54.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Förg</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hafner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lux</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investigation of endoglin wild-type and missense mutant protein heterodimerisation using fluorescence microscopy based IF, BiFC and FRET analyses</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>e102998</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102998</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25080347?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25080347</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR55">
        <label>55.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Razani</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Caveolin-1 regulates transforming growth factor (TGF)-beta/SMAD signaling through an interaction with the TGF-beta type I receptor</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>6727</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M008340200</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 11102446?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11102446</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR56">
        <label>56.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prewitt</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Heterozygous Null Bone Morphogenetic Protein Receptor Type 2 Mutations Promote SRC Kinase-dependent Caveolar Trafficking Defects and Endothelial Dysfunction in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>290</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>960</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.591057</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25411245?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25411245</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR57">
        <label>57.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ramos</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lame</surname>
              <given-names>MW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Segall</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>DW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The BMP type II receptor is located in lipid rafts, including caveolae, of pulmonary endothelium <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>
          <source>Vascul Pharmacol.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vph.2005.09.007</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16271518?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16271518</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR58">
        <label>58.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>García-Cardeña</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stern</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sessa</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endothelial nitric oxide synthase is regulated by tyrosine phosphorylation and interacts with caveolin-1</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>271</volume>
          <issue>44</issue>
          <fpage>27237</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.44.27237</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8910295?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8910295</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR59">
        <label>59.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elliot</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship of BMPR2 mutations to vasoreactivity in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Circulation.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>2509</fpage>
          <lpage>2515</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.105.601930</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717148</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR60">
        <label>60.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amsalem</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential regulation of translation and endocytosis of alternatively spliced forms of the type II bone morphogenetic protein (BMP) receptor</article-title>
          <source>Mol Biol Cell.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>716</fpage>
          <lpage>30</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E15-08-0547</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26739752?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26739752</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR61">
        <label>61.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boogerd</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Msx1 and Msx2 are functional interacting partners of T-box factors in the regulation of Connexin43</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Res.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>485</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/cvn049</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 18285513?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18285513</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR62">
        <label>62.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional genetic variants of TNFSF15 and their association with gastric adenocarcinoma: a case-control study</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>e108321</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108321</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25251497?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25251497</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR63">
        <label>63.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rodríguez-Viales</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutation in BMPR2 Promoter: A ‘Second Hit’ for Manifestation of Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension?</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>e0133042</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133042</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26167679</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR64">
        <label>64.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Early onset severe pulmonary arterial hypertension with ‘two-hit’ digenic mutations in both BMPR2 and KCNA5 genes</article-title>
          <source>Int J Cardiol.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>177</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>e167</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijcard.2014.08.124</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 25189502?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25189502</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR65">
        <label>65.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frump</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowery</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamid</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Caestecker</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abnormal trafficking of endogenously expressed BMPR2 mutant allelic products in patients with heritable pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>PLoS One.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>e80319</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0080319</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24224048?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24224048</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR66">
        <label>66.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bone Morphogenic Protein Type 2 Receptor Mutation-Independent Mechanisms of Disrupted Bone Morphogenetic Protein Signaling in Idiopathic Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>564</fpage>
          <lpage>575</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2015-0402OC</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 27187737?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27187737</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR67">
        <label>67.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonder</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reynolds</surname>
              <given-names>PN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>BMPR2 gene therapy for PAH acts via Smad and non-Smad signaling</article-title>
          <source>Respirology.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>727</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.12729</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26809239?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26809239</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR68">
        <label>68.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doublié</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural biology of poly(A) site definition</article-title>
          <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>732</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wrna.88</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21823232?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21823232</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR69">
        <label>69.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Whitmarsh</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of gene transcription by mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling pathways</article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>1773</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>1285</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2006.11.011</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 17196680?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196680</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR70">
        <label>70.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Olson</surname>
              <given-names>EN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perry</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schulz</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of muscle differentiation by the MEF2 family of MADS box transcription factors</article-title>
          <source>Dev Biol.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>2</fpage>
          <lpage>14</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.1995.0002</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 7589800?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589800</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR71">
        <label>71.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional mutations in 5′UTR of the BMPR2 gene identified in Chinese families with pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Pulm Circ.</source>
          <year>2016</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/685078</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 27162618?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27162618</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR72">
        <label>72.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paixão-Côrtes</surname>
              <given-names>VR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PAX9 and MSX1 transcription factor genes in non-syndromic dental agenesis</article-title>
          <source>Arch Oral Biol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.archoralbio.2010.10.020</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21111400?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21111400</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR73">
        <label>73.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aldred</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>BMPR2 gene rearrangements account for a significant proportion of mutations in familial and idiopathic pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>212</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.9398</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 16429403?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16429403</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR74">
        <label>74.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Machado</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension: A Current Perspective on Established and Emerging Molecular Genetic Defects</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mutat.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>1113</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.22904</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26387786?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26387786</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR75">
        <label>75.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Deng</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Familial primary pulmonary hypertension (gene PPH1) is caused by mutations in the bone morphogenetic protein receptor-II gene</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet.</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          <lpage>44</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/303059</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 10903931?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903931</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR76">
        <label>76.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Drake</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunmore</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McNelly</surname>
              <given-names>LN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrell</surname>
              <given-names>NW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aldred</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Correction of nonsense BMPR2 and SMAD9 mutations by ataluren in pulmonary arterial hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>403</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2013-0100OC</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 23590310?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23590310</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR77">
        <label>77.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yasuda</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tada</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanabe</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tatsumi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rho-kinase inhibition alleviates pulmonary hypertension in transgenic mice expressing a dominant-negative type II bone morphogenetic protein receptor gene</article-title>
          <source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol.</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>301</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>L667</fpage>
          <lpage>74</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplung.00423.2010</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 21856816?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856816</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR78">
        <label>78.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galiè</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ESC/ERS Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of pulmonary hypertension: The Joint Task Force for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Pulmonary Hypertension of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Respiratory Society (ERS): Endorsed by: Association for European Paediatric and Congenital Cardiology (AEPC), International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation (ISHLT)</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J.</source>
          <year>2015</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>903</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.01032-2015</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 26318161?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26318161</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR79">
        <label>79.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adzhubei</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sunyaev</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Predicting functional effect of human missense mutations using PolyPhen-2</article-title>
          <source>Curr Protoc Hum Genet.</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <?supplied-pmid 23315928?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23315928</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR80">
        <label>80.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrer-Costa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orozco</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de la Cruz</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence-based prediction of pathological mutations</article-title>
          <source>Proteins.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>811</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.20252</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 15390262?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15390262</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR81">
        <label>81.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henikoff</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ng</surname>
              <given-names>PC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Predicting the effects of coding nonsynonymous variants on protein function using the SIFT algorithm</article-title>
          <source>Nat Protoc.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1073</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2009.86</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19561590?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19561590</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR82">
        <label>82.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwarz</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schuelke</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seelow</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MutationTaster2: mutation prediction for the deep-sequencing age</article-title>
          <source>Nat Methods.</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>362</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2890</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 24681721?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24681721</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR83">
        <label>83.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reese.</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eeckman</surname>
              <given-names>FH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kulp</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haussler</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Improved splice site detection in Genie</article-title>
          <source>J Comp Biol.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>311</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.1997.4.311</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR84">
        <label>84.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hebsgaard</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Splice site prediction in Arabidopsis thaliana DNA by combining local and global sequence information</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>3439</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/24.17.3439</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 8811101?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8811101</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR85">
        <label>85.</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desmet</surname>
              <given-names>FO</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human Splicing Finder: an online bioinformatics tool to predict splicing signals</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>e67</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp215</pub-id>
          <?supplied-pmid 19339519?>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19339519</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>

</metadata></record></GetRecord></OAI-PMH>